<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:51:31[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<type  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105840188">
<phase  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="115290337">
<header>
<title>Graduate school</title>
<id>346628</id>
<revision>
<id>243242231</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-05T19:30:32Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>LeaveSleaves</username>
<id>3431267</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>Articles with disputed statements from September 2007</category>
<category>Educational stages</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>School types</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

A <b>graduate school</b> or ("grad school") is a school that awards advanced degrees, such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
doctoral degrees</link> with the general requirement that students must have earned a previous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../289/217289.xml">
undergraduate</link> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/188874.xml">
bachelor's</link>) degree. Many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/19725260.xml">
universities</link> award graduate degrees; a graduate school is not necessarily a separate institution. Original research experience is often a significant component of graduate studies, including the writing and defense of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
thesis</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
dissertation</link>.  The term "graduate school" is primarily <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../139/21139.xml">
North America</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
n. Additionally, in North America, the term does not usually refer to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/465584.xml">
medical school</link> (whose students are called "medical students"), and only occasionally refers to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../885/3262885.xml">
law school</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/43355.xml">
business school</link> (the latter types of programs are often collectively termed "professional schools.")<p>

Those attending graduate schools are called <b>graduate students</b>, or in <speech wordnetid="107109196" confidence="0.8">
<dialect wordnetid="107155661" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<non-standard_speech wordnetid="107155081" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../179/4179.xml">
British English</link></non-standard_speech>
</language>
</auditory_communication>
</dialect>
</speech>
 <b>postgraduate students</b>, or, colloquially, <b>postgrads</b>. Degrees awarded by graduate schools include, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
master's degree</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
doctoral degrees</link>, and other postgraduate qualifications such as graduate certificates and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/8810912.xml">
professional degree</link>s.</p>
<p>

Although graduate school programs are distinct experiences from undergraduate degree programs, graduate instruction (in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, and other countries) is often offered by some of the same senior academic staff and departments that teach undergraduate courses. Unlike in undergraduate programs, however, it is rare for graduate students to take <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/441142.xml">
coursework</link> outside their specific field of study at graduate/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/15681563.xml">
Graduate Entry</link> level. At the Ph.D. level, though, it is quite common to take courses from a wider range of study, for which some fixed portion of coursework, sometimes known as a residency, is typically required to be taken from outside the department and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/5689.xml">
college</link> of the degree-seeking candidate, to broaden the research abilities of the student. Some institutions designate separate graduate versus undergraduate staff and denote other divisions (often called School of X, e.g., diplomacy)</p>

<sec>
<st>
Australia</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Admission</st>
<p>

Generally, the Australian higher education system follows that of its British counterpart. Programmes are divided into coursework-based and research-based degrees, and entrance is decided by merit (entrance to coursework-based programmes is usually not as strict); most universities usually require a "Credit" average (equivalent to the British B-) as entry to their taught programmes in a field related to their previous undergraduate. On average, however, a strong "Credit" or "Distinction" average is the norm for accepted students.</p>
<p>

Ph.D. entrance requirements in the higher ranked schools typically require a student to have a master's degree by research, or a master's with a significant research component. Those who hold a first-class four-year honours degree may be considered, but are usually first admitted as probationary Ph.D.-students during the first year, then transfer to permanent candidacy contingent upon successful progress.  The minimum duration of a Ph.D. programme is two years, but completing within this timespan is unusual, with Ph.D.s usually taking an average of three to four years to be completed.</p>
<p>

Most of the confusion with Australian postgraduate programmes occurs with the research-based programmes. Research degrees generally require candidates to have a minimum of a second-class four-year honours undergraduate degree to be considered for admission. There has been some debate over the acceptance of a three-year honours degree (as in the case of graduates from British universities) as equivalent entry requirement to graduate research programmes (M.Phil., Ph.D.) in Australian universities, even though British graduates hold equivalent honours classification (upper-second and above).</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Professional programs</st>

<p>

There are many professional programs such as medical and dental school require a previous bachelors for admission and are considered graduate or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/15681563.xml">
Graduate Entry</link> programs even though they culminate in a bachelors degree.  Example, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/910147.xml">
Bachelor of Medicine (MBBS)</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/8005.xml">
Bachelor of Dentistry (BDent)</link>.</p>
<p>

There has also been some confusion over the conversion of the different marking schemes between British, U.S., and Australian systems for the purpose of assessment for entry to graduate programmes. The Australian grades are divided into four categories: High Distinction, Distinction, Credit, and Pass (though many institutions have idiosyncratic grading systems). Assessment and evaluation based on the Australian system is not equivalent to British or U.S. schemes because of the "low-marking" scheme used by Australian universities. For example, a British student who achieves 70+ will receive an A grade, whereas an Australian student with 70+ will receive a Distinction which is not the highest grade in the marking scheme. Hence, there have been many instances where Australian university admission officers have incorrectly assessed foreign grade marks as equivalent to their own.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

The Australian government usually offer full funding (fees and a monthly stipend) to its citizens and permanent residents who are pursuing research-based higher degrees. There are also highly competitive scholarships for international candidates who intend to pursue research-based programmes. Taught-degree scholarships (certain masters' degrees, Grad. Dip., Grad. Cert., D.Eng., D.B.A.) are almost non-existent for international students, so they are usually required to be self-funded.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Requirements for completion</st>
<p>

Requirements for the successful completion of a taught master's programme are that the student pass all the required modules. Some universities require eight taught modules for a one-year programme, twelve modules for a one-and-a-half-year programme, and twelve taught modules plus a thesis or dissertation for a two-year programme. The academic year for an Australian postgraduate programme is typically two semesters (eight months of study).</p>
<p>

Requirements for research-based programmes vary among universities. Generally, however, a student is not required to take taught modules as part of their candidacy. It is now common that first-year Ph.D. candidates are not regarded as permanent Ph.D. students for fear that they may not be sufficiently prepared to undertake independent research. In such cases, an alternative degree will be awarded for their previous work, usually an M.Phil. or M.Sc. by research.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Canada</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Admission</st>
<p>

Admission to a master's program generally requires a bachelor's degree in a related field, with sufficiently high grades usually ranging from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../946/3475946.xml">
B+</link> and higher (note that different schools have different <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/247805.xml">
letter grade</link> conventions, and this requirement may be significantly higher in some faculties), and recommendations from professors. Some schools require samples of the student's writing as well as a research proposal. At English-speaking universities, applicants from countries where English is not the primary language are required to submit scores from the Test of English as a Foreign Language (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/293114.xml">
TOEFL</link>).</p>
<p>

Admission to a doctoral program typically requires a master's degree in a related field, sufficiently high grades, recommendations, samples of writing, a research proposal, and typically an interview with a prospective supervisor. Requirements are often set higher than those for a master's program. In exceptional cases, a student holding an honours BA with sufficiently high grades and proven writing and research abilities may be admitted directly to a Ph.D. program without the requirement to first complete a master's. Many Canadian graduate programs allow students who start in a master's to "reclassify" into a Ph.D. program after satisfactory performance in the first year, bypassing the master's degree.</p>
<p>

Graduate students must usually declare their research goal or submit a research proposal upon entering grad school; in the case of master's degrees, there will be some flexibility (that is, one is not held to one's research proposal, although major changes, for example from premodern to modern history, are discouraged). In the case of Ph.D.s, the research direction is usually known as it will typically follow the direction of the master's research.</p>
<p>

Master's degrees can typically be completed in one year but normally take at least two; they typically may not exceed five years. Doctoral degrees require a minimum of two years but frequently take much longer, not usually exceeding six years.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

Graduate students may take out <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/10905128.xml">
student loans</link>, but instead they often work as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/1250533.xml">
teaching</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/381892.xml">
research assistant</link>s. Students often agree, as a condition of acceptance to a programme, not to devote more than twelve hours per week to work or outside interests.</p>
<p>

Funding is available to first-year masters students whose transcripts reflect exceptionally high grades; this funding is normally given in the second year.</p>
<p>

Funding for Ph.D. students comes from a variety of sources, and many universities waive tuition fees for doctoral candidates.</p>
<p>

Funding is available in the form of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/180337.xml">
scholarships</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/1915666.xml">
bursaries</link> and other awards, both private and public.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Requirements for completion</st>
<p>

Both master's and doctoral programs may be done by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/441142.xml">
coursework</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/25524.xml">
research</link> or a combination of the two, depending on the subject and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/2616927.xml">
faculty</link>. Most faculties require both, with the emphasis on research, and with coursework being directly related to the field of research.</p>
<p>

Master's candidates undertaking research are typically required to complete a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
thesis</link> comprising some original research and ranging from seventy to two-hundred pages. Some fields may require candidates to study at least one foreign language if they have not already earned sufficient foreign-language credits. Some faculties require candidates to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
defend their thesis</link>, but many do not. Those that do not often have a requirement of taking two additional courses, minimum, in lieu of preparing a thesis.</p>
<p>

Ph.D. candidates undertaking research must typically complete a thesis, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
dissertation</link>, consisting of original research representing a significant contribution to their field, and ranging from two-hundred to five-hundred pages. Most Ph.D. candidates will be required to sit <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/2307679.xml">
comprehensive examination</link>s—examinations testing general knowledge in their field of specialization—in their second or third year as a prerequisite to continuing their studies, and must defend their thesis as a final requirement. Some faculties require candidates to earn sufficient credits in a third or fourth foreign language; for example, most candidates in modern Japanese topics must demonstrate ability in English, <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/15606.xml">
Japanese</link></language>
, and <speech wordnetid="107109196" confidence="0.8">
<dialect wordnetid="107155661" confidence="0.8">
<auditory_communication wordnetid="107109019" confidence="0.8">
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<non-standard_speech wordnetid="107155081" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../657/24657.xml">
Mandarin</link></non-standard_speech>
</language>
</auditory_communication>
</dialect>
</speech>
, while candidates in pre-modern Japanese topics must demonstrate ability in English, Japanese, <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../516/123516.xml">
Classical Chinese</link></language>
, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/1301382.xml">
Classical Japanese</link>.</p>
<p>

At English-speaking Canadian universities, both master's and Ph.D. theses may be presented in English or in the language of the subject (<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/11884.xml">
German</link></language>
 for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/15876505.xml">
German literature</link>, for example), but if this is the case an extensive abstract must be also presented in English. In exceptional circumstances, a thesis may be presented in French.</p>
<p>

French-speaking universities have varying sets of rules; some will accept students with little knowledge of French if they can communicate with their supervisors (usually in English).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
United Kingdom</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Admission</st>

<p>

Admission to undertake a research degree in the UK typically requires a good bachelor's degree (at least <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/460615.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Second-class+honours%22])">
lower second</link>, but usually an upper second or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/460615.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22First-class+honours%22])">
first class</link>). Students may or may not already have a Master's degree. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
Doctoral</link> candidates are initially admitted to a Masters in Research Philosophy (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/2297173.xml">
M.Phil.</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/3954275.xml">
MRes</link>), then later accede to a Ph.D. if they progress well.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

Funding for postgraduate study in the UK is awarded competitively, and usually is disseminated by institution (in the form of a certain allocation of studentships for a given year) rather than directly to individuals. There are a number of scholarships for Master's courses, but these are relatively rare and dependent on the course and class of undergraduate degree obtained (usually requiring at least a lower second). Most Master's students are self-funded.</p>
<p>

Funding is available for some Ph.D. courses. As at the Master's level, there is more funding available to those in the sciences than in other disciplines. Such funding generally comes from <body wordnetid="105216365" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/830538.xml">
Research Council</link></natural_object>
</body>
s such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/2598108.xml">
Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council</link> (EPSRC), <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/2598134.xml">
Arts and Humanities Research Council</link> (AHRC), <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<council wordnetid="108310949" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/636280.xml">
Medical Research Council</link></council>
</administrative_unit>
 (MRC) and others.</p>
<p>

For overseas students, most major funding applications are due as early as twelve months or more before the intended graduate course will begin. This funding is also often highly competitive. The most widely available, and thus important, award for overseas students is the Overseas Research Student Award, which pays the difference in university fees between an overseas student and a British or EU resident. However, a student can only apply for the ORS for one university, often before he or she knows whether they have been accepted.</p>
<p>

Students studying part-time for a Master's degree can apply for income-based <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/771790.xml">
Jobseeker's Allowance</link> provided their timetabled hours are less than 16 hours per week. This also entitles the student to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../279/3187279.xml">
housing benefit</link> provided by their local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/52786.xml">
council</link>. Full-time students (of any type) are not normally eligible for state benefits, including during vacation time.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
United States</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Admission</st>
<p>

Admission to graduate school usually requires a bachelor's degree. High grades in one's field of study are important &mdash; grades outside the field less so. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../971/225971.xml">
Standardized test</link> (e.g., <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/346643.xml">
Graduate Record Examination</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 (GRE), <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/255232.xml">
Graduate Management Admission Test</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 (GMAT), <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../891/241891.xml">
Medical College Admission Test</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 (MCAT), <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/346643.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22GRE+Subject+tests%22])">
Graduate Record Examination (GRE) Subject Test</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
, <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<examination wordnetid="107197021" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/386327.xml">
Law School Admission Test</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</examination>
</process>
 (LSAT)) scores may be required by some institutions <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> and, especially, good letters of recommendation from undergraduate instructors are often essential. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> Strong recommendation letters from mentors or supervisors of undergraduate research experience provide evidence that the applicant can perform research.</p>
<p>

Within the sciences and some social sciences, previous research experience may be important; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> within most humanities disciplines, an example of academic writing normally suffices. Many universities require a personal statement (sometimes called Statement of Purpose or Letter of Intent), which may include indications of the intended area(s) of research; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> how detailed this statement is or whether it is possible to change one's focus of research depends strongly on the discipline and department to which the student is applying.</p>
<p>

In some disciplines or universities, graduate applicants may find it best to have at least one recommendation from research work outside of the college where they earned their Bachelor's degree;  however, as with previous research experience, this may not be very important in most humanities disciplines.</p>
<p>

Some schools set minimum <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/247805.xml">
GPA</link>s and test scores below which they will not accept any applicants; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> this reduces the time spent reviewing applications. On the other hand, many other institutions often explicitly state that they do not use any sort of cut-offs in terms of GPA or the GRE scores. Instead, they claim to consider many factors, including past research achievements, the compatibility between the applicant's research interest and that of the faculty, the statement of purpose and the letters of reference, as stated above. Some programs also require professors to act as sponsors. Finally, applicants from non-English speaking countries must take the Test of English as a Foreign Language (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/293114.xml">
TOEFL</link>). <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>
<p>

At most institutions, decisions regarding admission are not made by the institution itself but the department to which the student is applying. Some departments may require interviews before making the decision to accept an applicant. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Requirements for completion</st>

<p>

Graduate students often declare their intended degree (master's or doctorate) in their applications. In some cases, master's programs allow successful students to continue toward the doctorate degree. Additionally, doctoral students who have advanced to candidacy but not filed a dissertation ("ABD," for "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/13881572.xml">
all but dissertation</link>") often receive master's degrees and an additional master's called a Master of Philosophy, or MPhil, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/1504779.xml">
C.Phil.</link> "Candidate in Philosophy" degree. The master's component of a doctorate program often requires one or two years, and some students, because doctoral programs are better-funded, apply for doctoral programs while only intending to attain a master's degree.  This is generally not accepted and, if a student's advisor learns of the student's plans, can result in early termination.</p>
<p>

Many graduate programs require students to pass one or several examinations in order to demonstrate their competence as scholars. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> In some departments, a comprehensive examination is often required in the first year of doctoral study, and is designed to test a student's background undergraduate-level knowledge. Examinations of this type are more common in the sciences and some social sciences, and relatively unknown in most humanities disciplines.</p>
<p>

Most graduate students perform teaching duties, often serving as graders and tutors. In some departments, they can be promoted to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/366338.xml">
Lecturer</link> status, a position that comes with more responsibility.</p>
<p>

Doctoral students generally spend roughly their first two to three years taking coursework, and begin research by their second year if not before. Many master's and all specialist students will perform research culminating in a paper, presentation, and defense of their research. This is called the master's thesis (or, for Educational Specialist students, the specialist paper). However, many US master's degree programs do not require a master's thesis, focusing instead primarily on course work or on "practicals" or "workshops".  Such "real-world" experience may typically require a candidate work on a project alone or in a team as a consultant, or consultants, for an outside entity approved or selected by the academic institution, and under faculty supervision.</p>
<p>

In the second and third years of study, doctoral programs often require students to pass more examinations. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Programs often require a Qualifying Examination ("Quals"), a PhD Candidacy Examination ("Candidacy"), or a General Examination ("Generals"), designed to students' grasp of a broad sample of their discipline, and/or one or several Special Field Examinations ("Specials"), which test students in their narrower selected areas of specialty within the discipline. If these examinations are held orally, they may be known colloquially as "orals". For some social science and many humanities disciplines, where graduate students may or may not have studied the discipline at the undergraduate level, these exams will be the first set, and be based either on graduate coursework or specific preparatory reading (sometimes up to a year's work in reading). In all cases, comprehensive exams are normally both stressful and time consuming, and must be passed to be allowed to proceed on to the thesis. Passing such examinations allows the student to stay, begin doctoral research, and rise to the status of a doctoral candidate, while failing usually results in the student leaving the program or re-taking the test after some time has passed (usually a semester or a year). Some schools have an intermediate category, passing at the master's level, which allows the student to leave with a master's without having completed a master's thesis.</p>
<p>

For the next several years the doctoral candidate primarily performs his or her research. Usually this lasts three to eight years, though a few finish more quickly and some take substantially longer. In total, the typical doctoral degree takes between 4 and 8 years from entering the program to completion, though this time varies depending upon the department, thesis topic, and many other factors.</p>
<p>

For example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/50650.xml">
astronomy</link> degrees take five to six years on average, but <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../266/507266.xml">
observational astronomy</link> degrees take six to seven due to limiting factors of weather, while <link>
theoretical astronomy</link> degrees take five. Though there is substantial variation among universities, departments, and individuals, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/53132.xml">
humanities</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../781/26781.xml">
social science</link> doctorates on average take somewhat longer to complete than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/38890.xml">
natural science</link> doctorates. These differences are due to the differing nature of research between the humanities and some social sciences and the natural sciences, and to the differing expectations of the discipline in coursework, languages and length of thesis. However, time required to complete a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
doctorate</link> also varies according to the candidate's abilities and choice of research. Some students may also choose to remain in a program if they fail to win an academic position, particularly in disciplines with a tight job market; by remaining a student, they can retain access to libraries and university facilities, while also retaining an academic affiliation, which can be essential for conferences and job-searches.</p>
<p>

Traditionally, doctoral programs were only intended to last three to four years and, in some disciplines (primarily the natural sciences), with a helpful advisor, and a light teaching load, it is possible for the degree to be completed in that amount of time. However, increasingly many disciplines, including most humanities, set their requirements for coursework, languages and the expected extent of thesis research by the assumption that students will take five years minimum or six to seven years on average; competition for jobs within these fields also raises expectations on the length and quality of theses considerably.</p>
<p>

In some disciplines, doctoral programs can average seven to ten years. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../655/18951655.xml">
Archaeology</link>, which requires long periods of research, tends towards the longer end of this spectrum. The increase in length of degree is a matter of great concern for both students and universities, though there is much disagreement on potential solutions to this problem.</p>
<p>

Foreign graduate students outnumber US-born students in some departments, primarily in the natural sciences, and engineering. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

Many departments, especially those in which students have research or teaching responsibilities, offer tuition-forgiveness and a stipend that pays for most expenses. At some elite universities, there may be a minimum stipend established for all Ph.D. students, as well as a tuition waiver. The terms of these stipends vary greatly, and may consist of a scholarship or fellowship, followed by teaching responsibilities. At many elite universities, these stipends have been increasing, in response both to student pressure and especially to competition among the elite universities for graduate students.</p>
<p>

In some fields, research positions are more coveted than teaching positions because student researchers are typically paid to work on the dissertation they are required to complete anyway, while teaching is generally considered a distraction from one's work. Research positions are more typical of science disciplines; they are relatively uncommon in humanities disciplines, and where they exist, rarely allow the student to work on their own research.</p>
<p>

Departments often have funds for limited discretionary funding to supplement minor expenses such as research trips and travel to conferences.</p>
<p>

A few students can attain outside <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/180337.xml">
fellowship</link>s such as the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/157427.xml">
National Science Foundation</link></agency>
 (NSF) and <link>
National Physical Science Consortium</link> (NPSC). The sciences are funded well enough that most students can attain either outside or institutional funding, but in the humanities, not all do. Some humanities students borrow money during their coursework, then take full-time jobs while completing their dissertations. Funding differs greatly by departments and universities; some universities give five years of full funding to all Ph.D. students, though often with a teaching requirement attached; other universities do not. However, because of the teaching requirements, which can be in the research years of the Ph.D., even the most funded of universities often do not have funding for humanities or social science students who need to do research elsewhere, whether in the United States or overseas. </p>
<p>

Foreign students are typically funded the same way as domestic (US) students, although Federally-subsidized student and parent loans and work-study assistance are generally limited to U.S. citizens and nationals, permanent residents, and approved refugees<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>.  Moreover, some funding sources (such as many NSF fellowships) may only be awarded to domestic students. International students often have worse financial difficulties than domestic students.&#91;&#32; &ndash; &#93; Reasons include high costs to visit their families back home, support of a family not allowed to work due to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../312/4599312.xml">
immigration</link> laws, tuition that is steep by world standards, and large fees: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/330265.xml">
visa</link> fees by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/3805309.xml">
U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../231/87231.xml">
surveillance</link> fees (such as Student and Exchange Visitor Information Systems, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/287255.xml">
SEVIS</link><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnn.com/2004/EDUCATION/03/21/international.students.ap/index.html">
http://www.cnn.com/2004/EDUCATION/03/21/international.students.ap/index.html</weblink>) by the <legislature wordnetid="108163273" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/31756.xml">
United States Congress</link></legislature>
 and the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/58236.xml">
United States Department of Homeland Security</link></agency>
.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Graduate employee unions</st>
<p>

At many universities, graduate students are employed by their university to teach classes or do research. While all graduate employees are graduate students, many graduate students are not employees. MBA students, for example, usually pay tuition and do not have paid teaching or research positions. In many countries graduate employees have collectively organized <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/17626.xml">
labor union</link>s in order to bargain a contract with their university. In Canada, for example, almost all graduate employees are members of a <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/863685.xml">
CUPE</link></union>
 local.</p>
<p>

In the United States there are many graduate employee unions at public universities, the <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/3233774.xml">
Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions</link></union>
 lists 25 recognized unions at public universities on its website. Private universities, however, are covered under the <administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/55816.xml">
National Labor Relations Act</link></agency>
</administrative_unit>
 rather than state labor laws and until 2001 there were no recognized unions at private universities.</p>
<p>

Many graduate students see themselves as akin to junior faculty, but with significantly lower pay. Many graduate students feel that teaching takes time that would better be spent on research, and many point out that there is a vicious circle in the academic labor economy. Institutions that rely on cheap graduate student labor have no need to create expensive professorships, so graduate students who have taught extensively in graduate school can find it immensely difficult to get a teaching job when they have obtained their degree. Many institutions depend heavily on graduate student teaching: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.yaleunions.org/geso/reports/BlackboardBlues.pdf">
a 2003 report by agitators for a graduate student union at Yale</weblink>, for instance, claims that "70% of undergraduate teaching contact hours at Yale are performed by transient teachers: graduate teachers, adjunct instructors, and other teachers not on the tenure track." Additionally, graduate employees are currently organizing to have a greater voice in <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cmugsu.com">
CMU graduate school</weblink> decision making.  Michigan leads in terms of progressive policy regarding graduate student unions, and four graduate schools in Michigan currently recognize graduate employee unions: the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, Wayne State University, and Western Michigan University.</p>
<p>

The <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../140/320140.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Academic+Union%22])">
United Auto Workers</link></union>
 (under the slogan "Uniting Academic Workers") and the <union wordnetid="108233056" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../604/591604.xml">
American Federation of Teachers</link></union>
 are two international unions that represent graduate employees. Private universities' administrations often oppose their graduate students when they try to form unions, arguing that students should be exempt from labor laws intended for "employees". In some cases unionization movements have met with enough student opposition to fail. At the schools where graduate employees are unionized, which positions are unionized vary. Sometimes only one set of employees will unionize (e.g. teaching assistants, residential directors); at other times, most or all will. Typically, fellowship recipients, usually not employed by their university, do not participate.</p>
<p>

When negotiations fail, graduate employee unions sometimes go on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../134/155134.xml">
strike</link>. While graduate student unions can use the same types of strikes that other unions do, they have also made use of teach-ins, work-ins, marches, rallies, and <it>grade strikes</it>. In a grade strike, graduate students refuse to grade exams and papers and, if the strike lasts until the end of the academic term, also refuse to turn in final grades. Another form of job action is known as "work-to-rule", in which graduate student instructors work exactly as many hours as they are paid for and no more.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Eligibility guidelines from Jobcentre plus <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jobcentreplus.gov.uk/JCP/Customers/WorkingAgeBenefits/Jobseekerallowance/index.html">
website</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
Dale Bloom, Jonathan Karp, Nicholas Cohen, <it>The Ph.D. Process: A Student's Guide to Graduate School in the Sciences</it>, Oxford University Press, 1998, ISBN 0195119002.</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gradschool.about.com/od/admissionsadvice/a/overview.htm">
Graduate School Admissions 101</weblink>, About.com, accessed September 2, 2007</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gradschool.about.com/od/askingforletters/a/askrec.htm">
Recommendation Letters: Choosing Referees</weblink>, About.com, accessed September 2, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gradschool.about.com/od/admissionsadvice/a/research.htm">
Research Experience for Graduate Admissions</weblink>, About.com, accessed September 2, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://gradschool.about.com/od/admissionsadvice/a/gpa.htm">
GPA and Graduate School Admission</weblink>, About.com, accessed September 2, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ets.org/toefl/">
TOEFL: Test of English as a Foreign Language</weblink>, Educational Testing Service, accessed September 2, 2007.</entry>
<entry id="8">
http://ifap.ed.gov/sfahandbooks/attachments/0708FSAHBKVol1Ch2.pdf</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 William G. Bowen &amp; Neil L. Rudenstine, <it>In Pursuit of the PhD</it> (Princeton UP, 1992; ISBN 0-691-04294-2). A comprehensive report on graduate education in the US from the 1960s to the 1990s, based on surveys of tens of thousands of graduate students.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/15681563.xml">
Graduate Entry</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/167241.xml">
Academic degree</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<phase wordnetid="115290337" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/153981.xml">
Postgraduate education</link></phase>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Professional bodies</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/8810912.xml">
Professional degree</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/6251.xml">
Professional qualification</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/2307679.xml">
Comprehensive examination</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../695/1198695.xml">
EURODOC</link> (European Council of Doctoral Candidates and junior researchers)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../900/2936900.xml">
Piled Higher and Deeper</link> (widely read graduate school oriented comic strip)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
Thesis</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/6240548.xml">
List of postgraduate-only institutions</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../255/10945255.xml">
List of fields of doctoral studies</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.apa.org/monitor/nov00/phd.html">
Growth of the PhD</weblink> - Discusses innovations in doctoral training.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www-psych.stanford.edu/~amiawake/how">
How I Got Into the Stanford Psychology Ph.D. Program</weblink> - One student's experiences when applying to graduate programs in psychology. Includes helpful explanations and tips for all stages of the application process.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~harchol/gradschooltalk.pdf">
Guide to applying to PhD</weblink> - Covers selecting the right program, taking tests, recommendations, and statement of purpose from a professor who has been on the admissions committee for CMU, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/19061.xml">
MIT</link>, Berkeley.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://web.pdx.edu/~obrienk/gradschool%20advice.pdf">
Free Advice On Applying To Graduate School (PDF)</weblink> - Written by a professor of psychology at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/225577.xml">
Portland State University</link></university>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.augustanafaculty.org/career_application.php">
Guide to More Effective Applications</weblink> - A concise list of suggestions for how to make an effective application to a first academic job.  Aimed primarily at applicants to undergraduate institutions, but some good advice across the board.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://services.aamc.org/currdir/start.cfm">
AAMC Curriculum Directory</weblink> - Decription of medical education programs at 125 U.S. and 16 Canadian graduate schools.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://education-portal.com/article_directory/Glossary_of_Master%27s_Degree_Programs.html">
Glossary of Master's Degree Programs</weblink> - Hundreds of unbiased articles offering an overview of various master's degree programs. Includes information on commonly required coursework, as well as occupational outlooks.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</phase>
</type>
</article>
