<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:24:40[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<degree  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="105093890">
<property  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104916342">
<header>
<title>Doctor of Philosophy</title>
<id>8775</id>
<revision>
<id>244639058</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T20:42:15Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Zzuuzz</username>
<id>365454</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles to be expanded since June 2008</category>
<category>All articles to be expanded</category>
<category>Doctoral degrees</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<indent level="1">

<it>"Ph.D." redirects here, for other uses see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/24874.xml">
Ph.D. (disambiguation)</link>.</it>
</indent>

<b>Doctor of Philosophy</b>, abbreviated <b>Ph.D.</b> or <b>PhD</b> for the <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/17730.xml">
Latin</link></language>
 <it>Philosophiæ Doctor</it>, meaning "teacher of philosophy", (or, more rarely, <b>D.Phil.</b>, for the equivalent <it>Doctor Philosophiæ</it>) is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/153981.xml">
advanced</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/167241.xml">
academic degree</link> awarded by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/19725260.xml">
 universities</link>. In many, but not all countries in the English-speaking world, it has become the highest degree one can earn (but see also the <link>
Higher doctorate</link>s awarded by universities in the UK, Ireland and some <organization wordnetid="108008335" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/70385.xml">
 Commonwealth</link></organization>
 countries) and applies to graduates in a wide array of disciplines in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
science</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/53132.xml">
humanities</link>. The Ph.D. has become a  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/3016712.xml">
requirement</link> for a career as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/351220.xml">
university professor or researcher</link> in many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/2616927.xml">
fields</link>. In addition, many Ph.D. graduates go on to careers in government departments, non-governmental organizations (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/3742142.xml">
NGO</link>s), or in the private sector.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

The detailed requirements for award of a Ph.D. vary throughout the world; however, there are a number of common factors.  A candidate must submit a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
thesis or dissertation</link> consisting of a suitable body of original academic research, which is in principle worthy of publication in a peer-refereed context.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> In many countries a candidate must defend this work before a panel of expert examiners appointed by the university; in other countries, the dissertation is examined by a panel of expert examiners who stipulate whether the dissertation is in principle passable and the issues that need to be addressed before the dissertation can be passed. There is usually a prescribed minimum period of study — typically two to three years full time — which must take place before submission of the thesis. This requirement is usually waived for academic staff submitting a portfolio of peer-reviewed published work.</p>
<p>

The candidate may also be required to successfully complete a certain number of additional, advanced courses relevant to his or her area of specialization. In some countries (the US, Canada, Denmark, for example), most universities require coursework for Ph.D. degrees. In many other countries (especially those which have a greater degree of specialization at the undergraduate level, such as the UK) there is no such condition in general. It is not uncommon, however, for individual universities or departments to specify analogous requirements for students not already in possession of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
master's degree</link>.  Universities in the non-<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
-speaking world have begun adopting similar standards to those of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../706/210706.xml">
Anglophone</link> Ph.D. for their research doctorates (see, for example, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/363338.xml">
Bologna Process</link>).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
History of the Ph.D.</st>
<p>

The origins of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
doctorate</link> dates back to the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/8214930.xml">
ijazat</link> attadris wa 'l-iftta</it> ("license to teach and issue legal opinions") in the medieval <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/209717.xml">
Madrasah</link>s from the 9th century, though it was limited to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/28840.xml">
Islamic law</link> at the time, as in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../182/854182.xml">
Doctor of Laws</link> degree.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> The doctorate was later extended to philosophy in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/9239.xml">
Europe</link>an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/19725260.xml">
universities</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/18836.xml">
Middle Ages</link> which generally placed all academic disciplines outside the professional fields of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../503/30503.xml">
theology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medicine</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../668/18949668.xml">
law</link> under the broad heading of "philosophy" (or "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/382251.xml">
natural philosophy</link>" when referring to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../700/26700.xml">
science</link>). The degree of Doctor of Philosophy was a doctorate, generally granted as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/464751.xml">
honorary degree</link>s to select and well-established scholars.</p>
<p>

According to Wellington, Bathmaker, Hung, MucCullough and Sikes (2005), the first Ph.D. was awarded in Paris in 1150, but not until the early nineteenth century did the term "Ph.D." acquire its modern meaning as the highest academic doctoral degree, thanks to university practice in Germany. As Wellington et al. explain, prior to the nineteenth century professional doctoral degrees could only be awarded in theology (Th.D.), law (J.D.), or medicine (M.D.). In 1861, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/34273.xml">
Yale University</link></university>
 adopted the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
German</link></country>
 practice (first introduced in the 19th century at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/308234.xml">
Friedrich Wilhelm University</link></university>
 in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<settlement wordnetid="108672562" confidence="0.8">
<capital wordnetid="108518505" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/3354.xml">
Berlin</link></urban_area>
</district>
</geographical_area>
</seat>
</village>
</area>
</center>
</country>
</city>
</capital>
</settlement>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
) of granting the degree to younger students who had completed a prescribed course of graduate study and successfully defended a thesis/dissertation containing original research in science or in the humanities.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

From the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 the degree spread to <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
 in 1900, and then to the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 in 1917.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> This displaced the existing Doctor of Philosophy degree in some universities; for instance, the <b>D.Phil.</b> (<link>
higher doctorate</link> in the faculty of philosophy) at the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/181348.xml">
University of St Andrews</link></university>
 was discontinued and replaced with the Ph.D. (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
research doctorate</link>). <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/31797.xml">
Oxford</link></university>
 retained the D.Phil. abbreviation for their research degrees. Some newer UK universities, for example <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/680341.xml">
Buckingham</link></university>
 (est. 1976), <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/32045.xml">
Sussex</link></university>
 (est. 1961), and, until a few years ago, <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/155637.xml">
York</link></university>
 (est. 1963), chose to adopt the D.Phil., as did some universities in <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/4913064.xml">
New Zealand</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</colony>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
</autocracy>
.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Doctor of Philosophy degrees across the globe</st>
<p>

Ph.D.s are awarded under different circumstances and with different requirements in many different countries. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
Australia</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Admission</st>
<p>

Admission to a Ph.D. program within Australia and New Zealand requires the prospective student to have completed a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/188874.xml">
Bachelor's Degree</link> with an Honours component or a higher degree, such as a post graduate  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
Master's Degree</link> by research or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
Master's Degree</link> by course work. </p>
<p>

In most disciplines, Honours requires an extra year of study including a large research component in addition to coursework; however, in some disciplines such as engineering, law and pharmacy, Honours is automatically awarded to high achievers of the normal four-year program. To obtain a Ph.D. position, students must usually gain a First Class Honours, but may sometimes be admitted with a high Second Class Honours (known as a 2A, or Second Class Honours Division I). Alternatively, a student who fails to achieve a First or Second Class Honours may apply for a Research Masters course (usually 12–18 months) and upgrade to a Ph.D. after the first year, pending sufficient improvement.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, Ph.D. students are sometimes offered a scholarship to study their Ph.D.  The most common of these is the government-funded Australian Postgraduate Award (APA), which provides a living stipend to students of approximately <currency wordnetid="113385913" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/81215.xml">
AU$</link></currency>
 20,000 a year (tax free). Most universities also offer a similar scholarship that matches the APA amount, but are funded by the university. In recent years, with the tightening of research funding in Australia, these scholarships have become increasingly hard to obtain. Due to a continual increase to living costs, many Ph.D. students are forced to live under the poverty line.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> In addition to the more common APA and University scholarships, Australian students also have other sources of funding in their Ph.D. These could include, but are not limited to, scholarships offered by schools, research centres and commercial enterprise. For the latter, the amount is determined between the university and the organisation, but is quite often set at the APA (Industry) rate, roughly <currency wordnetid="113385913" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/81215.xml">
AU$</link></currency>
7,000 more than the usual APA rate. Australian students are often also able to tutor undergraduate classes and do guest lectures (much like a teaching assistant in the USA) to generate income. An Australian Ph.D. scholarship is paid for a duration of 3 years, while a 6 month extension is usually possible upon citing delays out of the control of the student.</p>
<p>

Australian-citizen and other eligible Ph.D. and Research Masters students in Australia are not charged course fees as these are paid for by the Australian Government under the Research Training Scheme. International students and Coursework Masters students must pay course fees, unless they receive a scholarship to cover them.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Argentina</st>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/392708.xml">
Education in Argentina</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
<ss2>
<st>
Admission</st>
<p>

In the <it><body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/16965626.xml">
Latin American docta</link></group>
</social_group>
</university>
</body>
</it>, the admission to a Ph.D. program at an Argentine University requires the full completion of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
Master's degree</link> or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/977277.xml">
Licentiate</link>'s degree. Non-Argentinian Master's titles are generally accepted into a Ph.D. program when the degree comes from a recognized university.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Funding</st>

<p>

While a significant portion of postgraduate students finance their tuition and living costs with teaching or research work at private and state-run institutions, international institutions, such as the Fullbright Program and the Organization of American States (OAS), have been known to grant full scholarships for tuition with apportions for housing.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Requirements for completion</st>
<p>

Upon completion of at least two years' research and course work as a graduate student, a candidate must demonstrate  truthful and original contributions to his or her specific field of knowledge within a frame of academic excellence.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> The doctoral candidate's work should be presented in a dissertation or thesis prepared under the supervision of a tutor or director, and reviewed by a Doctoral Committee. This Committee should be composed of examiners external to the program, and at least one of them should also be external to the institution. The academic degree of Doctor — abbreviated, "Dr.", with a suffix appropriate to the specific field — is received after a successful defense of the candidate’s dissertation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Canada</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Admission</st>

<p>

Admission to a Ph.D. program at a Canadian university may require completion of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
Master's degree</link> in a related field, with sufficiently high grades and proven research ability. In some cases, a student may progress directly from an Honours <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/188874.xml">
Bachelor's degree</link> to a Ph.D. program. The student usually submits an application package including a research proposal, letters of reference, transcripts, and in some cases, a sample of the student's writing. A common criterion for prospective Ph.D students is the comprehensive or qualifying examination, a process that often commences in the second year of a graduate program. Generally, successful completion of the qualifying exam permits continuance in the graduate program. Formats for this examination include oral examination by the student's faculty committee (or a separate qualifying committee), or written tests designed to demonstrate the student's knowledge in a specialized area (see below).</p>
<p>

At <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
-speaking universities, a student may also be required to demonstrate English language abilities, usually by achieving an acceptable score on a standard examination (e.g., Test of English as a Foreign Language (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/293114.xml">
TOEFL</link>)). Depending on the field, the student may also be required to demonstrate ability in one or more additional languages. A prospective student applying to French-speaking universities may also have to demonstrate some English language ability.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Funding</st>

<p>

While some students work outside the university (or at student jobs within the university), in some programs students are advised (or must agree) not to devote more than ten hours per week to activities (i.e., employment) outside of their studies.   </p>
<p>

At some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canadian</link> universities, most Ph.D. students receive an award equivalent to the tuition amount for the first four years (this is sometimes called a tuition deferral or tuition waiver).  Other sources of funding include <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/1250533.xml">
teaching assistant</link>ships and research assistantships;  experience as a teaching assistant is encouraged but not requisite in many programs. Some programs may require all Ph.D. candidates to teach, which may be done under the supervision of their supervisor or regular faculty. </p>
<p>

Besides these sources of funding, there are also various competitive scholarships, bursaries, and awards available, such as those offered by the federal government via <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../737/599737.xml">
NSERC</link>, <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<division wordnetid="108220714" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_unit wordnetid="108077292" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<department wordnetid="108114861" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../226/2303226.xml">
CIHR</link></department>
</association>
</administrative_unit>
</division>
</institute>
, or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/1205910.xml">
SSHRC</link>.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Requirements for completion</st>

<p>

In general, the first two years of study are devoted to completion of coursework and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/2307679.xml">
comprehensive examination</link>s.  At this stage, the student is known as a "Ph.D. student." It is usually expected that the student will have completed most of his or her required coursework by the end of this stage. Furthermore, it is usually required that by the end of eighteen to thirty-six months after the first registration, the student will have successfully completed the comprehensive exams.  </p>
<p>

Upon successful completion of the comprehensive exams, the student becomes known as a "Ph.D. candidate." From this stage on, the bulk of the student's time will be devoted to his or her own research, culminating in the completion of a Ph.D. thesis or dissertation. The final requirement is an oral defence of the thesis, which is open to the public.</p>
<p>

At most Canadian universities, the time needed to complete a Ph.D. typically ranges from four to six years. It is, however, not uncommon for students to be unable to complete all the requirements within six years, particularly given that funding packages often support students for only two to four years; many departments will allow program extensions at the discretion of the thesis supervisor and/or department chair. Alternate arrangements exist whereby a student is allowed to let their registration in the program lapse at the end of six years and re-register once the thesis is completed in draft form.  The general rule is that graduate students are obligated to pay tuition until the initial thesis submission has been received by the thesis office. In other words, if a Ph.D. student defers or delays the initial submission of their thesis they remain obligated to pay fees until such time that the thesis has been received in good standing.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
France</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Admission</st>
<p>

Due to the differences in French education systems in comparison to anglophone systems, students who want to earn the Ph.D. degree must complete a Master of Science program which lasts for 2 years after graduation with a Bachelor's degree (5 years in total).</p>
<p>

In France, the Masters program is divided into two branches, Master of Engineering which orients the students towards the working world. On the other hand, a Master of Science orients the students towards research.
The Ph.D admission is adopted by a graduate school (in French, "école doctorale"), a Ph.D Student has to follow some courses offered by the graduate school while continuing his/her research at laboratory. His/her research may be carried out in a laboratory, at a university, or in a company. In the last case, the company hires the student as an engineer and the student is supervised by both the company's tutor and a labs' professor. The validation of the Ph.D degree requires generally 3 to 4 years after the Master degree. Consequently, the Ph.D degree is considered in France as a "Bac +8" diploma ."Bac" stands for "Baccalauréat" which is the French High-school diploma.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

The financing of Ph.D studies comes mainly from funds for research of French Ministry of National Education. These grants often depend of the results and the student's file. However, the student can apply for funds from a company who can host him/her at its premise (as in the case where Ph.D students do their researches in a company). Other resources come from some regional/city projects, some associations, etc.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Germany</st>


<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/375698.xml">
Education in Germany</link></it>
</indent>

</p>
<ss2>
<st>
Admission</st>

<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
 a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
Master</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/1978155.xml">
Diplom</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/8185880.xml">
Magister</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/17754248.xml">
Staatsexamen</link> (state examination) degree is usually required to gain admission to a doctoral program. Sometimes good grades or a degree in a related field are additional requirements. The candidate must also find a tenured professor or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/220540.xml">
Privatdozent</link> to serve as the formal advisor on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
Dissertation</link> throughout the doctoral program. This advisor is informally termed <link>
Doktorvater</link>. </p>
<p>

Doctoral programs in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
 generally take three to five years to complete, strongly depending on the subject. Because there usually are no formal classes, but instead independent research is conducted under the tutelage of a single professor, a good deal of doctoral candidates work as teaching or research assistants, and are paid a reasonably competitive salary. This is a considerable difference from the situation in many other countries (such as the U. S.) where doctoral candidates are often referred to as Ph.D. "students"; whereas with German candidates, this rather inaccurate term should be avoided.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
History</st>

<p>

In early university history the Doctorate was awarded as a first degree. It has since evolved into a research degree.</p>
<p>

In <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../884/11884.xml">
German</link></language>
-speaking countries, most Eastern European countries, the former <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/26779.xml">
Soviet Union</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, most parts of <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<center wordnetid="108523483" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<see wordnetid="108586825" confidence="0.8">
<seat wordnetid="108647945" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/5334607.xml">
Africa</link></location>
</seat>
</see>
</area>
</center>
</region>
, <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/689.xml">
Asia</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
, and many <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/26825.xml">
Spanish</link></language>
-speaking countries  the corresponding degree is simply called "Doctor" and is distinguished by subject area with a <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/17730.xml">
Latin</link></language>
 suffix (e.g. "Dr.med." for doctor medicinæ, which is a scientifical title unlike an M.D., "Dr.rer.nat" for doctor rerum naturalium — Doctor of Science, "Dr. phil." for doctor philosophiæ, "Dr. iur." for doctor iuris, which is not equal to a J.D., etc.).</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-notice" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="36px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Doctor_of_Philosophy&amp;action=edit">
improve this section</weblink> by expanding it.</b> Further information might be found on the  or at . 
<it>(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
United Kingdom</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Dphil_gown.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/31797.xml">
University of Oxford</link></university>
 <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/8775.xml">
DPhil</link></property>
</degree>
 in full academic dress.
</caption>
</image>

</p>
<ss2>
<st>
 Admission </st>
<p>

In principle, a university is free to admit anyone to a Ph.D. programme; however, in practice, admission is usually conditional on the prospective student having successfully completed an undergraduate degree with at least upper second-class honours, or a postgraduate master's degree.</p>
<p>

In addition, Ph.D. students from countries outside the EU/EFTA area are required to comply with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/19452330.xml">
Academic Technology Approval Scheme</link> (ATAS), which involves undergoing a security clearance process with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../653/59653.xml">
Foreign Office</link> for certain courses in Medicine, Mathematics and many natural, engineering and material sciences.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> This requirement was introduced in 2007 due to concerns about terrorism and weapons proliferation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

In the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, funding for Ph.D. students is sometimes provided by government-funded <body wordnetid="105216365" confidence="0.8">
<natural_object wordnetid="100019128" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../538/830538.xml">
Research Council</link></natural_object>
</body>
s or the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../384/4060384.xml">
European Social Fund</link>, usually in the form of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/50845.xml">
tax-free</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/1915666.xml">
bursary</link> which consists of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/249320.xml">
tuition fees</link> together with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/1704572.xml">
stipend</link> of around <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../673/270673.xml">
GBP</link> 12,940 per year for three years (rising to £14,940 per year in London)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>, whether or not the degree continues for longer. Research Council funding is sometimes '<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/17649566.xml">
earmark</link>ed' for a particular department or research group, who then allocate it to a chosen student, although in doing so they are generally expected to abide by the usual minimum entry requirements (typically a first degree with upper second class honours, although successful completion of a postgraduate master's degree is usually counted as raising the class of the first degree by one division for these purposes).  However, the availability of funding in many disciplines (especially humanities, social studies, and pure science subjects) means that in practice only those with the best research proposals, references and backgrounds are likely to be awarded a studentship.  The ESRC (Economic and Social Science Research Council) explicitly state that a 2.1 minimum (or 2.2 plus additional masters degree) is required - no additional marks are given for students with a first class honours or a distinction at masters level.</p>
<p>

Since 2002, there has been a move by research councils to fund interdisciplinary doctoral training centres such as MOAC<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref> which concentrate on communication between traditional disciplines and an emphasis on transferable skills in addition to research training.</p>
<p>

Many students who are not in receipt of external funding may choose to undertake the degree part time, thus reducing the tuition fees, as well as creating free time in which to earn money for subsistence.</p>
<p>

Students may also take part in tutoring, work as research assistants, or (occasionally) deliver lectures, at a rate of typically US$25–30 per hour, either to supplement existing low income or as a sole means of funding.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Completion</st>
<p>

Funding typically lasts for three or four years for PhD students and four years for students earning both their Master's degree and PhD; there is a usually first-year assessment to remain in the programme and the thesis is submitted at the end of the 3-4 year program.  These periods are usually extended pro rata for part-time students.  With special dispensation, the final date for the thesis can be extended for up to four additional years, for a total of seven, but it is rare for students to spend more than four years in the programme.  Since the early 1990s, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1048927.xml">
UK</link> funding councils have adopted a policy of penalising departments where large proportions of students fail to submit their theses in four years (or pro rata equivalent) by reducing the number of funded places in subsequent years.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Other doctorates</st>
<p>

In the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 Ph.D.s are distinct from other doctorates, most notably the <link>
higher doctorate</link>s such as <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../728/3237728.xml">
D.Litt.</link></property>
</degree>
 (Doctor of Letters) or <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../822/430822.xml">
D.Sc.</link></property>
</degree>
 (Doctor of Science), which are granted on the recommendation of a committee of examiners on the basis of a substantial portfolio of submitted (and usually published) research.</p>
<p>

Recent years have seen the introduction of professional doctorates, most notably in the fields of engineering (<qualification wordnetid="104717139" confidence="0.8">
<degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<fitness wordnetid="104716864" confidence="0.8">
<suitability wordnetid="104715487" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../336/1978336.xml">
Eng.D.</link></property>
</suitability>
</fitness>
</degree>
</qualification>
), education (Ed.D.), clinical psychology (D.Clin.Psych.), business administration (D.B.A.), and music (<degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../514/400514.xml">
D.M.A.</link></property>
</degree>
). These typically have a more formal taught component consisting of smaller research projects, as well as a 40,000-60,000 word thesis component, which collectively is equivalent to that of a Ph.D.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
United States</st>

<ss2>
<st>
Overview</st>

<p>

In the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, the Ph.D. is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/3016712.xml">
highest academic degree</link> awarded by universities in many fields of study.  American students typically undergo a series of three phases in the course of their doctoral work, after they have obtained a bachelor's degree.  In some cases a master's degree may be required for a Ph.D. program, but in other cases (when a master's is not required) it may not be possible to fully transfer credits from a previously attended master's program to the Ph.D. program.  In some fields, the master's is considered terminal, and a university's Ph.D. program may refuse to accept any graduates from the same school's master's program.  The first phase consists of coursework in the student's field of study and requires one to three years to complete. This often is followed by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/2794761.xml">
preliminary</link> or comprehensive examination and/or a series of cumulative examinations where the emphasis is on breadth rather than depth of knowledge. Some Ph.D. programs require the candidate to complete successfully requirements in pedagogy (taking courses on higher level teaching and teaching undergraduate courses) and/or applied science (e.g., clinical practica and predoctoral clinical internship in Ph.D. programs in clinical or counseling psychology).</p>
<p>

Another two to four years are usually required for the composition of a substantial and original contribution to human knowledge in the form of a written <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
dissertation</link>, which in the social sciences and humanities is typically 50 to 450 pages in length. In many cases, depending on the discipline, a dissertation would consist of (i) a comprehensive literature review, (ii) an outline of methodology, and (iii) several chapters of scientific, social, historical, philosophical, or literary analysis. Typically, upon completion, the candidate undergoes an oral examination, sometimes public, by his or her supervisory committee with expertise in the given discipline.</p>
<p>

As the Ph.D. is often a preliminary step toward a career as a professor, throughout the whole period of study and dissertation research the student may be required or at least offered the opportunity, depending on the university and degree, to teach undergraduate or sometimes graduate courses in relevant subjects.</p>
<p>

The Ph.D. is often misunderstood to be synonymous with the term "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
doctorate</link>". While the Ph.D. is the most common doctorate, the term "doctorate" can refer to any number of doctoral degrees in the United States.  The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/70919.xml">
U.S. Department of Education</link> and the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/157427.xml">
National Science Foundation</link></agency>
 recognize numerous doctoral degrees as "equivalent", and do not discriminate between them. (<it>See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22United+States%22])">
Doctoral Degree in the United States</link></it>).</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Admission</st>
<p>

There are 282 universities in the United States that award the Ph.D., and those universities vary widely in their criteria for admission, as well as the rigor of their academic programs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> Typically, Ph.D. programs require applicants to have a Bachelor's degree in a relevant field, reasonably high grades, several letters of recommendation, relevant academic coursework, a cogent statement of interest in the field of study, and satisfactory performance on a graduate-level exam specified by the respective program (e.g., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../643/346643.xml">
GRE</link>, <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/255232.xml">
GMAT</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>). Specific admissions criteria differ substantially according to university admissions policies and fields of study; some programs in well-regarded research universities (i.e., <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/540954.xml">
Research 1</link> universities) may admit less than 5% of applicants and require an exceptional performance on the GRE along with near-perfect grades, strong support in letters of recommendation, substantial research experience, and academically sophisticated samples of their writing.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Master's degree "in passing"</st>
<p>

As applicants to many Ph.D. programs are not required to have Master's Degrees, many programs award a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/4126896.xml">
Master of Arts</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../722/236722.xml">
Master of Science</link> degree "in passing" or "in course" based on the graduate work done in the course of achieving the Ph.D. Students who receive such Master's Degrees are usually required to complete a certain amount of coursework and a master's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/300215.xml">
thesis</link>. Depending on the specific program, masters-in-passing degrees can be either mandatory or optional. Not all Ph.D. students choose to complete the additional requirements necessary for the M.A. or M.S. if such requirements are not mandated by their programs. Those students will simply obtain the Ph.D. at the end of their graduate study.</p>
<p>

Some programs also include a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/2297173.xml">
Master of Philosophy</link> degree as part of the Ph.D. program.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> The M.Phil., in those universities that offer it, is usually awarded after the appropriate M.A. or M.S. (as above) is awarded, and the degree candidate has completed all further requirements for the Ph.D. (which may include additional language requirements, course credits, teaching experiences, and comprehensive exams) aside from the writing and defense of the dissertation itself. This formalizes the "all but dissertation" (ABD) status used informally by some students, and represents that the student has achieved a higher level of scholarship than the M.A./M.S. would indicate - as such, the M.Phil. is sometimes a helpful credential for those applying for teaching or research posts while completing their dissertation work for the Ph.D. itself. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Time</st>
<p>

Depending on the specific field of study, completion of a Ph.D. program usually takes four to eight years of study after the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/188874.xml">
Bachelor's Degree</link>; those students who begin a Ph.D. program with a Master's Degree may complete their Ph.D. a year or two sooner.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> As Ph.D. programs typically lack the formal structure of undergraduate education, there are significant individual differences in the time taken to complete the degree. Many US universities have set a 10-year limit for students in Ph.D. programs, or refuse to consider graduate credit older than ten years as counting towards a Ph.D.  Similarly, students may be required to re-take the comprehensive exam if they do not defend their dissertations within five years of taking it. Overall, 57% of students who begin a Ph.D. program in the US will complete their degree within 10 years, approximately 30% will drop out or be dismissed, and the remaining 13% of students will continue on past 10 years.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Funding</st>
<p>

Doctoral students are usually discouraged from engaging in external employment during the course of their graduate training. As a result, Ph.D. students at U.S. universities typically receive a tuition waiver and some form of annual stipend. The source and amount of funding varies from field to field and university to university. Many U.S. graduate students work as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../533/1250533.xml">
teaching assistant</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/381892.xml">
research assistant</link>s while they are doctoral students.  Graduate schools increasingly encourage their students to seek outside funding; many are supported by fellowships they obtain for themselves or by their advisors' research grants from government agencies such as the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/157427.xml">
National Science Foundation</link></agency>
 and the <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/46174.xml">
National Institutes of Health</link></association>
</institute>
. Many <conference wordnetid="108308497" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/14975.xml">
Ivy League</link></conference>
 and other well-endowed universities provide funding for the entire duration of the degree program (if it is short) or for most of it.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
Ph.D. candidacy</st>
<p>

Ph.D. Candidate, sometimes called <degree wordnetid="105093890" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="104916342" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/1504779.xml">
Candidate of Philosophy</link></property>
</degree>
, is a stage of university education in North American and some European and Argentine universities. A Ph.D. Candidate is a postgraduate student in the doctoral level who has successfully satisfied the requirements for doctoral studies, minus the thesis or dissertation. As such, a Ph.D. Candidate is sometimes called an ABD (All But Dissertation). The process through which a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
doctoral</link> student becomes a Ph.D. Candidate varies based on the country and even the university. However, it often consists of a series of oral and written examinations, as well as an occasional defense of a dissertation project or topic. Although a minor distinction in postgraduate study, achieving Ph.D Candidacy is not without additional benefit. For example, in many courses of study and universities, promotion to Ph.D. Candidate status coincides with an increase in the student's monthly stipend and may make them eligible for Teaching Assistantships.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Models of supervision</st>
<p>

At some universities, there may be training for those wishing to supervise Ph.D. studies. There is now a lot of literature published for academics who wish to do this, such as Delamont, Atkinson and Parry (1997). Indeed, Dinham and Scott (2001) have argued that the worldwide growth in research students has been matched by increase in a number of what they term "how-to" texts for both students and supervisors, citing examples such as Pugh and Phillips (1987). These authors report empirical data on the benefits that Ph.D. students may gain if they publish their work, and note that Ph.D. students are more likely to do this with adequate encouragement from their supervisors. </p>
<p>

Wisker (2005) has noticed how research into this field has distinguished between two models of supervision:
The technical-rationality model of supervision, emphasising technique;
The negotiated order model, being less mechanistic and emphasising fluid and dynamic change in the Ph.D. process.
These two models were first distinguished by Acker, Hill and Black (1994; cited in Wisker, 2005). 
Considerable literature exists on the expectations that supervisors may have of their students (Phillips &amp; Pugh, 1987) and the expectations that students may have of their supervisors (Phillips &amp;  Pugh, 1987; Wilkinson, 2005) in the course of Ph.D. supervision. Similar expectations are implied by the Quality Assurance Agency's Code for Supervision (Quality Assurance Agency, 1999; cited in Wilkinson, 2005).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<b>International Ph.D. Equivalent Degrees:</b></p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Argentina: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
Doctorado</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
Doctorate</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Belgium: <link>
Doctoraat</link>/<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
Doctorate</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brazil: </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

France: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Country-specific+practice%22])">
Doctorat</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Greece: <link>
Διδακτωρικό</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Italy: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../257/2908257.xml">
dottorato di ricerca</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Poland: Doktor -&amp;gt; <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doktor_(stopie%C5%84_naukowy)">
http://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doktor_(stopie%C5%84_naukowy)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Portugal: <link>
Doutoramento</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Spain: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
Doctorado</link></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<b>Other Degrees:</b>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
Doctorate</link> - A general term describing a set of degrees analogous to the Ph.D.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../712/3016712.xml">
Terminal degree</link> - The highest degree awarded in a field, usually a Ph.D.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/153981.xml">
Graduate student</link> - A student pursuing education past the bachelor's degree, such as Masters Degree or a Ph.D.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/1504779.xml">
C.Phil.</link> (also ABD) - Term, usually used unofficially, for a graduate student who has completed all Ph.D. coursework but has yet to defend his or her dissertation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../671/2739671.xml">
Kandidat</link> - Degree awarded by USSR and post-Soviet states.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/977277.xml">
Licentiate</link> - Degree awarded in various countries, including <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/23033.xml">
Portugal</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/3343.xml">
Belgium</link></country>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/1048927.xml">
UK</link>, <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/18951905.xml">
Argentina</link></country>
</city>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/26748.xml">
Switzerland</link></country>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/5058739.xml">
Sweden</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</autocracy>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/10577.xml">
Finland</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/4913064.xml">
New Zealand</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</colony>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
</autocracy>
, <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3966054.xml">
Mexico</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../936/22936.xml">
Poland</link></country>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Notes </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ous/international/usnei/us/edlite-research-doctorate.html">
Research Doctorate Programmes</weblink>", US Department of Education&#32;(Retrieved 6/18/06).&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Dinham, S.; Scott, C.&#32;(2001).&#32;"The experience of the results of disseminating the results of doctoral research". <it>Journal of Further and Higher Education</it>&#32;<b>25</b>: 45–55. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F03098770020030498">
10.1080/03098770020030498</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
The term "doctor of philosophy" is not generally applied by them to graduates in disciplines other than <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/13692155.xml">
philosophy</link> itself. These doctoral degrees, however, are sometimes colloquially identified in English as Ph.D.'s.</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite id="CITEREFMakdisi" style="font-style:normal">Makdisi, George&#32;(April-June 1989),&#32;"Scholasticism and Humanism in Classical Islam and the Christian West",&#32;<it>Journal of the American Oriental Society</it>&#32;<b>109</b>(2):  175–182 [175–77], <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307%2F604423">
10.2307/604423</weblink></cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
See, for instance,  <cite style="font-style:normal">Rosenberg, Ralph P.&#32;(1962).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/pss/1979947">
Eugene Schuyler's Doctor of Philosophy Degree: A Theory Concerning the Dissertation</weblink>". <it>The Journal of Higher Education</it>&#32;<b>33</b>: 381 &ndash; 386. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307%2F1979947">
10.2307/1979947</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp; (subscription required)</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Simpson, Renate&#32;(1984). How the PhD came to Britain : A Century of Struggle for Postgraduate Education.&#32;Taylor and Francis.</cite>&nbsp; </entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">ABC&#32;(2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/04/30/2231306.htm">
PhD students living below poverty line</weblink>". <it>ABC News</it>&#32;<b>2008</b>: 1–2.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
http://spuweb.siu.edu.ar/studyinargentina/pages/study1203.php Scholarships in Argentina </entry>
<entry id="9">
http://www.gfme.org/global_guide/pdf/13-18%20Argentina.pdf</entry>
<entry id="10">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.coneau.edu.ar/index.php?item=29&amp;apps=16&amp;id=428&amp;act=ver&amp;idioma=en">
CONEAU</weblink></entry>
<entry id="11">
FCO Counter terrorism &amp; weapons proliferation  staff: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/fco-in-action/counter-terrorism/weapons/atas/who-atas/phd-or-other">
Advice for PHD/doctoral level students applying for an ATAS certificate</weblink>. Accessed 16 September 2008</entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/6441263.stm">
Postgrad checks worry scientists</weblink> BBC News, 12 March 2007</entry>
<entry id="13">
http://www.ahrc.ac.uk/images/pg_grants_fees_200809.pdf</entry>
<entry id="14">
http://www.warwick.ac.uk/go/moac</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">M. Bray, P. Kwok&#32;(2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6VB9-48NKMVT-7&amp;_user=10&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=6a633cf7ed81c05dc67fd6275fdd236f">
Demand for private supplementary tutoring: conceptual considerations, and socio-economic patterns in Hong Kong</weblink>". <it>Economics of Education Review</it>&#32;<b>22</b>: 611–620.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/index.asp?key=63&amp;search_flag=true&amp;ref=783&amp;start=783&amp;BASIC2005=15">
Listing of Research I Universities</weblink>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/2038887.xml">
Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching</link> - 282 is the sum of all three categories of doctoral universities.</entry>
<entry id="16">
http://www.esrcsocietytoday.ac.uk/ESRCInfoCentre/Images/res_grant_linked_studentships_tcm6-12550.pdf</entry>
<entry id="19">
http://www2.gsb.columbia.edu/doctoral/admissions/index.html</entry>
<entry id="18">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wharton.upenn.edu/doctoral/admissions/apply/requirements.cfm#scores">
Wharton Doctoral Programs: Application Requirements</weblink></entry>
<entry id="21">
[http://www.yale.edu/bulletin/html2003/grad/policies.html Policies and Regulations</entry>
<entry id="20">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/gsas/rules/chapter-7/pages/deg-req/sec/mphil.html">
Master of Philosophy (M.Phil.)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="22">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://chronicle.com/weekly/v53/i47/47a00101.htm">
In Humanities, 10 Years May Not Be Enough to Get a Ph.D.</weblink>, <b>The Chronicle of Higher Education</b> July 27, 2007</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Delamont, S., Atkinson, P. &amp; Parry, O. (1997). Supervising the Ph.D.: A guide to success. Buckingham: Open University Press. ISBN 0-335-19516-4</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dinham, S. &amp; Scott, C. (2001). The experience of the results of disseminating the results of doctoral research. Journal of Further and Higher Education, 25 (1) 45-55. ISSN: 1469-9486</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

MacGillivray, Alex; Potts, Gareth; Raymond, Polly. <it>Secrets of Their Success</it> (London: New Economics Foundation, 2002).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Phillips, E. &amp; Pugh, D.S. (1987). How to get a PhD : managing the peaks and troughs of research / Estelle M. Phillips and D.S. Pugh. Milton Keynes : Open University Press ISBN 0335155375 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Simpson, Renate. <it>How the PhD came to Britain: A century of struggle for postgraduate education</it>, Society for Research into Higher Education, Guildford (1983).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wellington, J. Bathmaker, A._M., Hunt, C., McCullough, G. &amp; Sikes, P. (2005). Succeeding with your doctorate. London: Sage. ISBN 1-4129-0116-2</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wilkinson, D. (2005) The essential guide to postgraduate study. London : SAGE ISBN 141290062X (hbk.)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.norc.org/NR/rdonlyres/2E87F80C-82F6-4E26-9F78-CA4C6E0B79C6/0/sed2005.pdf">
Doctorate Recipients from United States Universities: Summary Report 2005</weblink> (1.9MiB)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.economics.soton.ac.uk/staff/aldrich/PhD.htm">
The Mathematics PhD in the United Kingdom: Notes on its History</weblink> Contains information/links of more general relevance than mathematics.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://openwetware.org/wiki/LaTeX_template_for_PhD_thesis">
LaTeX template for writing PhD thesis</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../241/167241.xml">
Academic degree</link>s</header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd"><p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/223220.xml">
Associate's degree</link> (<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
U.S.</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/362570.xml">
Foundation degree</link> (<autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
UK</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
 except <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/26994.xml">
Scotland</link></country>
)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/188874.xml">
Bachelor's degree</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/170346.xml">
Master's degree</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/1978155.xml">
Diplom</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../880/8185880.xml">
Magister</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/1240807.xml">
DEA</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../807/1240807.xml">
MAS</link>&nbsp;· </p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../277/977277.xml">
Licentiate</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/1886191.xml">
Specialist degree</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/1260570.xml">
Engineer's degree</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/8810912.xml">
Professional degree</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/428966.xml">
M.D.</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../762/707762.xml">
PharmD</link> &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/188886.xml">
Doctoral degree</link></p>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</property>
</degree>
</article>
