<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 00:37:39[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>D&apos;Arcy McNickle</title>
<id>11041456</id>
<revision>
<id>207188612</id>
<timestamp>2008-04-21T19:42:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Deejayk</username>
<id>1333721</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>(William) D'Arcy McNickle</b> (1904–1977) was a writer, Native American activist and anthropologist.
<ss1>
<st>
 Biography </st>
<p>

D’Arcy McNickle, an enrolled Salish Kootenai on the Flathead Reservation, became one of the most prominent twentieth-century American Indian activists. He was born on January 14, 1904, to an Irish father, William McNickle, and a one-quarter Cree Métis mother, Philomene Parenteau. He grew up on the Flathead Reservation in St. Ignatius, Montana and went to mission and non-reservation boarding schools. In 1925 McNickle sold his land allotment on the Flathead Reservation so that he could raise the money necessary to study abroad at Oxford University. After returning to the United States, McNickle lived in New York City until he was hired by the Bureau of Indian Affairs in 1936. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

<p>

D’Arcy McNickle worked under Commissioner of Indian Affairs John Collier during the 1930s and 1940s. The Bureau of Indian Affairs first hired him as an administrative assistant, but by 1950 he had been appointed chief of the tribal relations branch, and he soon became an expert.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Organizations </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/18017061.xml">
National Congress of American Indians</link> (N.C.A.I)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

American Indian Development (A.I.D)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Literary Contributions </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Surrounded (1936)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wind From an Enemy Sky (1978)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Hawk is Hungry</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Indian Man: A Life of Oliver La Farge (1971)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Indians and Other Americans: Two Ways of Life Meet</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Native American Tribalism: Indian Survivals and Renewals</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Runner in the Sun: a story of Indian Maize</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

They Came Here First : the Epic of the American Indian (1949)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Indian in American Society (for National Congress of American Indians, 1955)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

An Historical Review of Federal-Indian Relationships (American Indian Policy Review Commission, 1975)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 American Indian Chicago Conference </st>
<p>

June 1961
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Declaration of Indian Purpose</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Dorothy R. Parker, Singing an Indian Song: A Biography of D’Arcy McNickle (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1992), 22-27, 68. Dorothy Parker, “D’Arcy McNickle,” in The New Warriors: Native American Leaders since 1900 (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2001), 98-99.</entry>
<entry id="2">
Parker, Singing, 122.</entry>
</reflist>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

“McNickle, D”Arcy.” In American National Biography. New York: Oxford University Press, Volume 15, 1999. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Adams, Bonnie Jean. “Sending an American Indian Voice: D’Arcy McNickle: Educator, Anthropologist, Historian: An Intellectual Biography.” Thesis Dissertation (Ph.D.) Loyola University of Chicago, 1998. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Burlingame, Lori Lynn. “Cultural Survival and the Oral Tradition in the Novels of D’Arcy McNickle and his Successors, Momaday, Silko, and Welch.” Thesis Dissertation (Ph.D.) University of Rochester, Department of English, 1995. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cobb, Daniel M. “Chapter One: Declarations.” In Before Red Power: The Politics of Tribal Self-Determination in Cold War America. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 2008. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cobb, Daniel M. “Indian Politics in Cold War America: Parallel and Contradiction.” Princeton University Library Chronicle LXVII, no. 2 (winter 2006): 392-419. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cobb, Daniel M. “Talking the Language of the Larger World: Politics in Cold War (Native) America.” In Beyond Red Power: New Perspectives on American Indian Politics and Activism. Edited by Daniel M. Cobb and Loretta Fowler. Santa Fe: School of American Research Press, 2007. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Collier, John. “A Perspective on the United States Indian Situation of 1952 in its Hemispheric and Worldwide Bearing.” América Indígena 13, no. 1 (January 1953): 7-13.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cowger, Thomas. The National Congress of American Indians: The Founding Years. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2001. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cracroft, Richard H. Twentieth-century American Western Writers. Detroit: Gale Group, 1999. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Critical Perspectives on Native American Fiction. Edited by Richard F. Fleck. Washington, D.C.: Three Continents Press, 1993. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Handbook of Native American Literature. Edited by Andrew Wiget. New York: Garland, 1996. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hans, Birgit, ed. “The Hawk is Hungry” &amp; Other Stories: An Annotated Anthology of D’Arcy McNickle’s Short Fiction. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1992. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hans, Birgit. “Surrounded: The Fiction of D’Arcy McNickle.” Thesis Dissertation (Ph.D.) University of Arizona, 1988. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Hans, Birgit. The Hawk is Hungry: An Annotated Anthology of D’Arcy McNickle’s Short Fiction. Thesis (M.A.) University of Arizona, 1986. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lagrand, James B. Indian Metropolis: Native Americans in Chicago, 1945-75. Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 2002. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Libby, Orin Grant. The Arikara Narrative of Custer’s Campaign and the Battle of the Little Bighorn. Introduction by D’Arcy McNickle. 1920. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1998. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Lurie, Nancy Oestreich. “Sol Tax and Tribal Sovereignty,” Human Organization: Journal of the Society for Applied Anthropology, Vol. 58 No. 1 (Spring 1999): 108-117.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Miller, Jay. Writings in Indian History, 1985-1990. Compiled by Jay Miller, Colin G. Calloway, and Richard A. Sattler. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1995. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nagel, Joane. American Indian Ethnic Renewal: Red Power and the Resurgence of Identity and Culture. New York: Oxford University Press, 1997.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Native American Literature: An Anthology. Compiled by Lawana Trout. Lincolnwood, Ill.: NTC Pub. Group, 1999. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ortiz, Alfonso. D’Arcy McNickle (1904-1977): Across the River and Up the Hill: A Personal Remembrance. 1980-1989?. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ortiz, Simon J. “Towards a National Indian Literature: Cultural Authenticity in Nationalism.” MELUS 8, no. 2 (summer 1981): 7-12. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Owens, Louis. Other Destinies: Understanding the American Indian Novel. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1992. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Parker, Dorothy R. “Choosing an Indian Identity: A Biography of D’Arcy McNickle.” Thesis Dissertation (Ph. D.) University of New Mexico, 1988. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Parker, Dorothy R. “D’Arcy McNickle: Living a Broker’s Life.” In Between Indian and White Worlds: The Cultural Broker. Edited by Margaret Connell Szasz. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1994. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Parker, Dorothy R. Singing an Indian Song: A Biography of D’Arcy McNickle. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1992.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Parker, Dorothy. “D’Arcy McNickle.” In The New Warriors: Native American Leaders since 1900. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2001. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Parker, Robert Dale. The Invention of Native American Literature. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2003. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Provinse, John Henry, Thomas Segundo, Sol Tax, and D’Arcy McNickle. The American Indian Now: An NBC Radio Discussion. Chicago: University of Chicago Round Table (Radio Program), 1954. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Purdy, John Lloyd. Word Ways: The Novels of D’Arcy McNickle. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1990. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Rains, James W. “Today Speaks in Yesterday’s Voice: Writing American Indians into History in the Fiction of D’Arcy McNickle." Thesis Dissertation (Ph.D.) University of Michigan, 2004. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Roemer, Kenneth M. Native American Writers of the United States. Detroit: Gale Research, 1997. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Rosier, Paul C. “’They Are Ancestral Homelands’: Race, Place, and Politics in Cold War Native America, 1945-1961.” Journal of American History 92, no. 4 (March 2006): 1300-1326. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ruppert, James. D’Arcy McNickle. Boise, Idaho: Boise State University, 1988. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Smoke Rising: The Native American Literary Companion. Edited by Joseph Bruchac, managing editor; Janet Witalec, editor with Sharon Malinowski. Detroit: Visible Ink Press, 1995. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Squires, Nancy Elam. "Back to the Blanket: The Indian Fiction of Oliver La Farge, Joseph Matthews, D’Arcy McNickle, Ruth Underhill and Frank Waters, 1927-1944." Thesis (Ph.D.) Harvard University, 2004.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Stories for a Winter’s Night: Short Fiction by Native Americans. Edited by Maurice Kenny. Buffalo, N.Y.: White Pine Press, 2000. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Straus, Terry, Ron Bowan, and Michael Chapman, “Anthropology, Ethics, and the American Indian Chicago Conference,” American Ethnologist Vol. 13 No. 4 (November 1986): 802-804. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Legacy of D’Arcy McNickle: Writer, Historian, Activist. Edited by John Lloyd Purdy. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1996. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Singing Spirit: Early Short Stories by North American Indians. Edited by Bernd C. Peyer. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, 1989. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Thompson, Joan Elizabeth. “The Control of Water and Land: Dams and Irrigation in Novels by Mary Hallock Foote, Mary Hunter Austin, Frank Waters, and D’Arcy McNickle.” Thesis Dissertation (Ph.D) University of Minnesota, 1994. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Towner, Lawrence William. “D’Arcy McNickle.” In Past Imperfect: Essays on History, Libraries, and the Humanities. Edited by Robert W. Karrow, Jr. and Alfred F. Young, with an introduction by Alfred F. Young. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1993. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Voice of the Turtle: American Indian Literature, 1900-1970. Edited by Paula Gunn Allen. New York: Ballantine Books, 1994. </entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Newberry Library D’Arcy McNickle Center for Native American History,  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Biography of D’Arcy McNickle, The Newberry Library, Chicago, IL,  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

D’Arcy McNickle Library, Salish Kootenai College, Flathead Indian Reservation, Montana, </entry>
</list>
</p>



</ss1>
</bdy>
</article>
