<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 05:11:20[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<game  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100456199">
<header>
<title>King&apos;s Field II</title>
<id>19014712</id>
<revision>
<id>236792153</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-07T04:09:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Kotbot</username>
<id>5277842</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>PlayStation games</category>
<category>Role-playing video games</category>
<category>From Software games</category>
<category> 1996 video games</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox VG</name>
<parameters>

<image width="256px" src="kingsfield2_cover1.jpg">
<caption>

Cover art for the U.S. release of King's Field II.
</caption>
</image>
</parameters>
</template>


<b>King's Field II</b> is the second game in the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/19017416.xml">
King's Field</link></it> <it><genre wordnetid="105845332" confidence="0.8">
<idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<category wordnetid="105838765" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<kind wordnetid="105839024" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/356777.xml">
RPG</link></kind>
</psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</category>
</concept>
</idea>
</genre>
</it> series. Like both its successors and predecessor, the game is played through first person view in a dark and mysterious, medieval fantasy setting.<p>

The game was developed by the Japanese game development company <it><company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/2254865.xml">
From Software</link></company>
</it>, and released July 21st, 1995 in Japan, and December 31, 1995 in the U.S. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Since the first King's Field game was never published outside Japan, King's Field II is commonly known simply as 'King's Field' in the U.S. It has only been released for the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/23964.xml">
Playstation</link> console.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Synopsis</st>
<p>

The game takes place on the island of Melanat. You take the role of Prince Alexander, who has taken it upon himself, as one of the king of Verdite's closest friends, to retrieve the holy sword known as the Moonlight Sword, and return it to King Alfred of the kingdom of Verdite. Alexander is washed up on the coast of Melanat, as the sole survivor after the ship he came with sank into the ocean. To find the Moonlight Sword, Alexander must press ever forward and uncover the secrets the dark island of Melanat holds.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Characters</st>
<p>

Not yet complete.
This information has been taken directly from the game, including any grammatical errors. The information has been gathered through the Truth Mirror item in the game. If any information appears twice(sometimes with slight changes), it means that one NPC might be moving around to different areas.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Base No. 1</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Earnest Clyde - A nobleman in Verdite and King Alfred's right-hand man. Earnest sent his troops to the island, but lost contact with his men. Then he came to the island by himself.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Big Mine</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Cliff Lore - Cliff is obstinate, but he has a gentle heart. His family had been dealing with the royal palace of Granatyki, and he knows the upper class people. While traveling all over the world, Cliff stopped by the island and started to work in a mine.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Dalf Vice - A descendant of King Harvine's brain. Dalf came to the island to hunt for treasures with the "Harvine's Key," which was handed down by his ancestors. Now he is working in a mine because he lost the key.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

David Tabler - David was one of the best knights in Egreck. He quit the knighthood and became a crystal-miner. Now he works hard and has earned a good reputation.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Central Village</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Celffy Foss - A merchant in Dark-Elf who is more than 400 years old. His best customer is Necron. Foss is the only one who supplies the villagers with their daily necessities.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Kehl Hunt - The twin brother of Al Hunt. Kehl used to be a farmer in his country. He came to the island with Al. Even though he doesn't work, he is better off here because it is said that he does business with Dark-Elf.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Krola Amgun - Krola came from a seaside town called Camy with her whole family to hunt for crystals. Her husband was killed in an accident. She now takes care of crystal-miners.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Meryl - A fortune-teller who can see all over the world with her crystal ball. Nothing about herself is known except that she is female.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Radd Bilheim - A crystal-crafter. Radd is making crystal bottles that will fold the magic water which controls the poison. He learned crafting techniques from Leon, but he can not work as well as Leon can.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Sandler Amgun - Sandler is a child who plays around the underworld posing as an explorer. He has found a key on the beach, and he went to a cave to hunt for another treasure.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Coliseum </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Dias Bagil - Attracted by a man in the darkside, this man came to the island. He calls himself "Necron." He is known as the best warrior in the world, and he owns the Coliseum.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Earnest Clyde - A nobleman in Verdite and King Alfred's right-hand man. Earnest sent his troops to the island, but lost contact with his men. Then he came to the island by himself.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Miria - Miria appears before many warriors. She was created to find the chosen one who has the power to use the "Moonlight Sword."</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

East Coast</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Karen Shore - Karen is a descendant of the High-Elf kinsfolk and had lived a quiet life in the depths of the forest. She left her village with her son Leon, who is half-human and half-Elf, and came to the island.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Leon Shore - He came to the island with his mother from the village of the High-Elves. There were many talented craftsmen in High-Elf, but Leon exceeded all of them in talent and ability.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

East Village</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Gigi Budwell - She moved to the island with her father. Gigi is frequently sick so she doesn't go out very often. She hopes to hear from Leon about his adventures.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Teo Budwell - He used to be a warrior in Verdite. Teo came to the island to dig for crystals in order to make money for his sickly daughter Gigi.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Guyra's Dimension</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Guyra - The Black Dragon who is opposed to the White Dragon, "Seath." Guyra broke a black crystal which controls the powers of nature. He created the "Moonlight Sword" to make his chosen warriors fight for his revival.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Harvine's Castle</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The Portrait of a King - </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

High-Elf Shrine</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Dragon Grass - It existed in this land before Guyra and Seath came. It knows the truth about everything.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

The Grave of a Saint - The grave of Olfe, who was the highest ranking priest when High-Elf built the Shrine. His souls still remains, and is trying to tell the truth.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

North Village</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Al Hunt - Al was the chief cook in the castle, but he was expelled for hurting his Lord's feeling. He came to the island to look for a rare type of food.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Nola Bagil - A sister of the famous soldier, Dias. Nola became worried about her brother once she heard that a man named Necron had appeared on the island. Then she came to the island by herself to find Dias.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Poison Cave</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Teo Budwell - He used to be a warrior in Verdite. Teo came to the island to dig for crystals in order to make money for his sickly daughter Gigi.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Royal Treasure House</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Celffy Foss - A merchant in Dark-Elf who is more than 400 years old. His best customer is Necron. Foss is the only one who supplies the villagers with their daily necessities.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Earnest Clyde - A nobleman in Verdite and King Alfred's right-hand man. Earnest sent his troops to the island, but lost contact with his men. Then he came to the island by himself.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Leon Shore - He came to the island with his mother from the village of the High-Elves. There were many talented craftsmen in High-Elf, but Leon exceeded all of them in talent and ability.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Small Mine</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Rand Ferrer - A young woodsman on the edge of Verdite. He was a hard worker, but he started to work in a mine after monsters had appeared in the woods.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

South Village</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Fai Fadlin - Fai has come to the island with his friend, Dias. Ever since Dias' sister Nola came to the island, Fai has been trying to send her back to the continent.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Mark Wozz - He was egged on by the Thief Gill to steal. Mark escaped from his country and came to the island. He has opened a key shop for treasure hunters.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Raffy Foss - A grandson of Celffy. Raffy only deals in goods of little value because he is not trusted.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Termite's Nest</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Sandler Amgun - Sandler is a child who plays around the underworld posing as an explorer. He has found a key on the beach, and he went to a cave to hunt for another treasure.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Cemetery</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Harris Carvitto - The first resident on this island. He was a skilled crystal-miner before he hurt his leg. Now he lives outside the village, keeping his friend's grave.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

West Coast</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Jose Harven - A descendant of the old pirates on this island. He came to the island since he heard from his grandfather that the treasure is still hidden somewhere on the island.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Enemies</st>
<p>

This information has been taken directly from the game, including any grammatical errors. The information has been gathered through the Truth Mirror item in the game. If any information appears twice(sometimes with slight changes), it means that there are more than one type of that enemy in the game, but with the same name or Truth Mirror information on it.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Archers - Former soldiers who were manipulated by Necron. All they can do now is continuously shoot their bows.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Baltail - Insect-type monster that have excellent eyes and ears and attack from above.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Billent - Ornaments which are made by a Mage of Fire, Tsedeck. After losing their power, the ornaments attacked with their fire magic.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bitt - Guyra's final guard. It sucks in all magic.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Copper Knight - This monster was created by the Mage of Fire and the King of Winds to guard the King's Treasure.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Demon Lord - A monster created by a man in the darkside, Necron. This creature has high intelligence and possesses high levels of magics.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dias Bagil - Attracted by a man in the darkside, this man came to the island. He calls himself "Necron." He is known as the best warrior in the world, and he owns the Coliseum.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Earth-Elemental - Uses stone ball magic.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Fire-Elemental - A fire-ball with an element of fire. It floats with intellect.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Flame Spirit - Ornaments which are made by a Mage of Fire, Tsedeck. After losing their power, the ornaments attacked with their fire magic.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Freeze Ball - A form of ice magic that is cast by Tarn, the Mage of Ice.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ghosts - Ghosts that appears in certain areas. If they touch you, you will be paralyzed.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Green Slime - They live in groups and reside in dark and damp places. They have "counteractive water' inside their bodies, so that poison will be recovered whenever someone touches them. They can be damaged by fire magic more than swords.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Guyra - The Black Dragon who is opposed to the White Dragon, "Seath." Guyra broke a black crystal which controls the powers of nature. He created the "Moonlight Sword" to make his chosen warriors fight for his revival.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Head Eater - Attacks with its large mouth, which has poisonous stingers. These are different species from the ones in Verdite, and they are more dangerous.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kald - This monster lives in the mine and attacks suddenly from its dark hiding spot. It can see in the dark.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kraken - The ruler of the north sea. With its giant legs, it drags ships into the water. Before growing up, this monster is small and not very powerful.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Log Stalker - A heinous monster that attacks people. It used to be a dead tree before it was given a soul by Necron.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mage's Candlestcks - Decorated candlesticks that are alive and that were set up by Tsedeck to test visitors in the Magic Palace. These four candlesticks are waiting for the person who can light them.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mecha-Demon Lord - Demon Lord was strengthened and became a mechanical monster. It has weird eyes and uses high-level magics.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mecha-Reiks - Same as above, it has the same characteristics that Reiks do.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mecha-Termite - A mecha-monster created just like the Termites were, and that has the same characteristics as the Termites do.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mogle - An animal which evolved only on the island of Melanat. It attacks its prey with its sharp fangs and strong legs. Sometimes it jumps on its victim and crushes it to death.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Necron's Soldiers - Soldiers who were manipulated by Necron. They have lost their souls and their minds, and they can only attack. There is no way to help them.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Poison Baltail - A variety of Baltail. Their sting is poisonous.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Poison Slime - Same species as Green Slime, but they have poison water in their body.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Psythe - A Death created by the Mage of Fire. He has high intelligence and possesses many kinds of magic. A large psythe can paralyze your body.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Queen Termite - The queen of termites. It doesn't move very much. It attacks those who come close with its big mouth.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Refma - The soul of High-Elf, which is protecting their dark Crystal. It doesn't remember what it once was, and attacks those who come near it.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Refma - The soul of High-Elf, who is protecting the Dark Crystal. It doesn't remember what it once was, and it attacks those who come near it.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Reiks - A flying creature with a hard shell. I is extremely ferocious.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Salamander - Ornaments which are made by a Mage of Fire, Tsedeck. After losing their power, the ornaments attacked with their fire magic.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sigill - After growing up, Sigill start to live in the deep-sea. There they can attack their game much more powerfully.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Sigill - Grotesque and ferocious fish that live in the sea. They attack in packs whenever anyone gets close to them.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Skeleton - Necron granted wicked souls to bodies that were already dead. They can be revived until they are completely destroyed.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Skeleton of One-Eyed Giant - Skeleton of One-Eyed Giant made by the best Mage on the northern continent, Shaddam. Shaddam only could become the Mage who owns the Coliseum because of this Giant.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

S-Knight - A ferocious creature which eats everything. It has a strong defensive ability, and its' shells cannot be damaged.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Tarn - The Mage of Ice, who was transformed by a man in the darkside. This creature used to be an Ice Warrior named Kal Fargus, who owned a Coliseum. Tarn kept all of the equipment that he used before.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Termite - An insect-type monster. There are millions of Termites swarming around each nest.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The Picture of a King - This picture was drawn by the magical powers of King Harvine to protect his treasure. The picture attacks all approachers.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Credits</st>
<p>

Credits acquired from IMDB.com<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> and the original U.S. release game manual.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Executive Producer''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Naotoshi Zin</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Main programmer''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Eiichi Hasegawa</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Programmer''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Toshio Shimada</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Hiroyuki Arai</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Akinori Kaneko</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>CG Animation Supervisor''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Yasuyoshi Karasawa</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>CG Animation Designer''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Mitsuhiro Okamura</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Character Designer''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Sakumi Watanabe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Texture coordinator''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Masahiro Kajita</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Scenario Writer''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Toshiya Kimura</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Shinichiro Nishida</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Music and sound effects''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

SOUND KID'S Corp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Localization''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Minako Goto</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Noriko Ozaki</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Special Thanks''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

Tim Lindquist</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Production Companies''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/2254865.xml">
From Software</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

SOUND KID'S Corp.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Distributors''</it></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/2254865.xml">
From Software</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../129/999129.xml">
ASCII Entertainment</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../174/8760174.xml">
King's Field</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/13699578.xml">
King's Field III</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/19017100.xml">
King's Field IV</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/19017416.xml">
King's Field Series</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/2254865.xml">
From Software</link></company>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/2858573.xml">
Agetec</link></institution>
</company>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.agetec.com/catalog/product_info.php?manufacturers_id=10&amp;products_id=94&amp;osCsid=uueta7b1fr62e3e543u5c3b914">
Agetec 'King's Field (U.S.)' listing</weblink></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/From_Software#Playstation">
From Software - Wikipedia</weblink></entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.agetec.com/catalog/product_info.php?manufacturers_id=10&amp;products_id=94&amp;osCsid=uueta7b1fr62e3e543u5c3b914">
Agetec Product listing</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0373063/">
King's Field II - IMDB.com</weblink></entry>
</reflist>




</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</game>
</article>
