<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:47:23[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<standard  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="107260623">
<header>
<title>Smart card</title>
<id>59957</id>
<revision>
<id>244083338</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T07:29:44Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>B7342</username>
<id>38660</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>ISO standards</category>
<category>Smart cards</category>
<category>Banking technology</category>
<category>Ubiquitous computing</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles to be split from August 2008</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="Carte_vitale_anonyme.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Smart card used for health insurance in France.
</caption>
</image>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Differentsmartcardpadlayouts.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Many different pad layouts can be found on a contact Smart card
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Smartcardchip.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Size comparison of chip
</caption>
</image>

A <b>smart card</b>, <b>chip card</b>, or <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/15150.xml">
integrated circuit</link> card</b> (<b>ICC</b>), is any pocket-sized card with embedded integrated circuits which can process data. This implies that it can receive input which is processed &mdash; by way of the ICC applications &mdash; and delivered as an output.  There are two broad categories of ICCs. <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/212855.xml">
Memory card</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
s contain only non-volatile memory storage components, and perhaps some specific security logic. <link>
Microprocessor card</link>s contain volatile memory and microprocessor components. The card is made of plastic, generally <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/24458.xml">
PVC</link>, but sometimes <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../778/233778.xml">
ABS</link>. The card may embed a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../338/66338.xml">
hologram</link> to avoid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../662/205662.xml">
counterfeit</link>ing. Using smartcards also is a form of strong security authentication for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/927470.xml">
single sign-on</link> within large companies and organizations.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

A "smart card" is also characterized as follows:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Dimensions are normally <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17182301.xml">
credit card</link> size. The ID-1 of <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/187874.xml">
ISO/IEC 7810</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
 standard defines them as 85.60&nbsp;×&nbsp;53.98 mm. Another popular size is ID-000 which is 25&nbsp;×&nbsp;15 mm. Both are 0.76&nbsp;mm thick.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Contains a security system with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/357347.xml">
tamper-resistant</link> properties (e.g. a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/59865.xml">
secure cryptoprocessor</link>, secure file system, human-readable features) and is capable of providing security services (e.g. confidentiality of information in the memory). </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Asset managed by way of a central administration system which interchanges information and configuration settings with the card through the security system. The latter includes card hotlisting, updates for application data. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Card data is transferred to the central administration system through card reading devices, such as ticket readers, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/46628.xml">
ATM</link>s etc.</entry>
</list>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Benefits </st>
<p>

Smart cards provide a means of effecting business transactions in a flexible, secure, standard way with minimal human intervention.</p>
<p>

Smart card can provide strong authentication<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/927470.xml">
single sign-on</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/927470.xml">
enterprise single sign-on</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../457/7878457.xml">
computers</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/198584.xml">
laptops</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/18985040.xml">
data</link> with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../294/10294.xml">
encryption</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../310/9310.xml">
enterprise resource planning</link> platforms such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../769/276769.xml">
SAP</link>, etc.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

The automated chip card was invented by <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
German</link></country>
 rocket scientist <link>
Helmut Gröttrup</link> and his colleague Jürgen Dethloff in 1968; the patent was finally approved in 1982. The first mass use of the cards was for payment in French <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/163387.xml">
pay phones</link>, starting in 1983 (<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/24879.xml">
Télécarte</link></it>).</p>
<p>

<link>
Roland Moreno</link> actually patented his first concept of the memory card in 1974. In 1977, <link>
Michel Ugon</link> from <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../024/945024.xml">
Honeywell Bull</link></institution>
</company>
 invented the first microprocessor smart card. In 1978, Bull patented the SPOM (Self Programmable One-chip Microcomputer) that defines the necessary architecture to auto-program the chip. Three years later, the very first "CP8" based on this patent was produced by Motorola. At that time, Bull had 1200 patents related to smart cards. In 2001, Bull sold its CP8 Division together all its patents to Schlumberger. Schlumberger combined its smart card department and CP8 and created Axalto. In 2006, Axalto and Gemplus, at the time the world's no.2 and no.1 smart card manufacturers, merged and became Gemalto.</p>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="Smartcard3.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A smart card, combining <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/17182301.xml">
credit card</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/9008.xml">
debit card</link> properties. The 3 by 5 mm security chip embedded in the card is shown enlarged in the inset. The contact pads on the card enables electronic access to the chip.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The second use was with the integration of microchips into all French <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/9008.xml">
debit card</link>s (<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../505/2350505.xml">
Carte Bleue</link></it>) completed in 1992. When paying in France with a Carte Bleue, one inserts the card into the merchant's terminal, then types the PIN, before the transaction is accepted. Only very limited transactions (such as paying small <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../245/758245.xml">
autoroute</link> tolls) are accepted without PIN.</p>
<p>

Smart-card-based electronic purse systems (in which value is stored on the card chip, not in an externally recorded account, so that machines accepting the card need no network connectivity) were tried throughout Europe from the mid-1990s, most notably in Germany (Geldkarte), Austria (Quick), Belgium (Proton), France (Moneo), the Netherlands (Chipknip and Chipper), Switzerland ("Cash"), Norway ("Mondex"), Sweden ("Cash"), Finland ("Avant"), UK ("Mondex"), Denmark ("Danmønt") and Portugal ("Porta-moedas Multibanco"). </p>
<p>

The major boom in smart card use came in the 1990s, with the introduction of the smart-card-based <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/197489.xml">
SIM</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 used in GSM mobile phone equipment in Europe. With the ubiquity of mobile phones in Europe, smart cards have become very common.</p>
<p>

The international payment brands MasterCard, Visa, and Europay agreed in 1993 to work together to develop the specifications for the use of smart cards in payment cards used as either a debit or a credit card.  The first version of the <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/458524.xml">
EMV</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 system was released in 1994.  In 1998 a stable release of the specifications was available.  <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emvco.org/">
EMVco</weblink>, the company responsible for the long-term maintenance of the system, upgraded the specification in 2000 and most recently in 2004. The goal of EMVco, is to assure the various financial institutions and retailers that the specifications retain backward compatibility with the 1998 version.  </p>
<p>

With the exception of countries such as the United States of America there has been significant progress in the deployment of EMV-compliant point of sale equipment and the issuance of debit and or credit cards adhering the EMV specifications.  Typically, a country's national payment association, in coordination with <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/378791.xml">
MasterCard</link></company>
 International, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/85244.xml">
Visa</link> International, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/326512.xml">
American Express</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/930353.xml">
JCB</link></institution>
</company>
, develop detailed implementation plans assuring a coordinated effort by the various stakeholders involved. </p>
<p>

The backers of EMV claim it is a paradigm shift in the way one looks at payment systems. In countries where banks do not currently offer a single card capable of supporting multiple account types, there may be merit to this statement. Though some banks in these countries are considering issuing one card that will serve as both a debit card and as a credit card, the business justification for this is still quite elusive.  Within EMV a concept called Application Selection defines how the consumer selects which means of payment to employ for that purchase at the point of sale.</p>
<p>

For the banks interested in introducing smart cards the only quantifiable benefit is the ability to forecast a significant reduction in fraud, in particular counterfeit, lost and stolen. The current level of fraud a country is experiencing, coupled with whether that country's laws assign the risk of fraud to the consumer or the bank, determines if there is a business case for the financial institutions. Some critics claim that the savings are far less than the cost of implementing EMV, and thus many believe that the USA payments industry will opt to wait out the current EMV life cycle in order to implement new, contactless technology. </p>
<p>

Smart cards with contactless interfaces are becoming increasingly popular for payment and ticketing applications such as  mass transit. Visa and MasterCard have agreed to an easy-to-implement version currently being deployed (2004-2006) in the USA.  
Across the globe, contactless fare collection systems are being implemented to drive efficiencies in public transit.  The various standards emerging are local in focus and are not compatible, though the MIFARE Standard card from Philips has a considerable market share in the US and Europe. </p>
<p>

Smart cards are also being introduced in personal identification and entitlement schemes at regional, national, and international levels. Citizen cards, drivers’ licenses, and patient card schemes are becoming more prevalent; For example in Malaysia, the compulsory national ID scheme <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/1832825.xml">
MyKad</link></method>
</know-how>
 includes 8 different applications and is rolled out for 18 million users. Contactless smart cards are being integrated into <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/14985.xml">
ICAO</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/1438860.xml">
biometric passport</link>s to enhance security for international travel.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Contact smart card </st>

<p>

Contact smart cards have a contact area, comprising several gold-plated contact pads, that is about 1cm square.  When inserted into a <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../518/4397518.xml">
reader</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
, the chip makes contact with electrical connectors that can read information from the chip and write information back.</p>
<p>

The <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/59959.xml">
ISO/IEC 7816</link></b> and <b><document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/187874.xml">
ISO/IEC 7810</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
</b> series of standards define:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the physical shape</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the positions and shapes of the electrical connectors</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the electrical characteristics</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../235/83235.xml">
communications protocol</link>s, that includes the format of the commands sent to the card and the responses returned by the card.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 robustness of the card</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 the functionality</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The cards do not contain <substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/19174720.xml">
batteries</link></material>
</part>
</substance>
; energy is supplied by the card reader.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Electrical signals description </st>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="SMARTPINOUT.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A smart card pinout
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

VCC : <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../348/1625348.xml">
Power supply input</link></p>
<p>

RST : Either used itself (reset signal supplied from the interface device) or in combination with an internal reset control circuit (optional use by the card). If internal reset is implemented, the voltage supply on Vcc is mandatory.</p>
<p>

CLK : Clocking or timing signal (optional use by the card).</p>
<p>

GND : <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/41215.xml">
Ground</link> (reference voltage).</p>
<p>

VPP : Programming voltage input (deprecated / optional use by the card).</p>
<p>

I/O : Input or Output for serial data to the integrated circuit inside the card.</p>
<p>

NOTE - The use of the two remaining contacts will be defined in the appropriate application standards. </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Reader </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Card_reader#Smart_card_readers</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</it>
</indent>
</p>
<p>

Contact smart card readers are used as a communications medium between the smart card and a host, e.g. a computer, a point of sale terminal, or a mobile telephone.</p>
<p>

Since the chips in the financial cards are the same as those used for mobile phone <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/197489.xml">
Subscriber Identity Module</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 (SIM) cards, just programmed differently and embedded in a different shaped piece of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../458/24458.xml">
PVC</link>, the chip manufacturers are building to the more demanding GSM/3G standards. So, for instance, although EMV allows a chip card to draw 50&nbsp;mA from its terminal, cards are normally well inside the telephone industry's 6mA limit. This is allowing financial card terminals to become smaller and cheaper, and moves are afoot to equip every home PC with a card reader and software to make internet shopping more secure.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Contactless smart card</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/13725692.xml">
List of smart cards</link></it>
</indent>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Splitsection.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this section be  into a new article. ()</col>
</row>
</table>


A second type is the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/270072.xml">
contactless smart card</link></it>, in which the chip communicates with the card reader through <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/169320.xml">
RFID</link> induction technology (at data rates of 106 to 848 kbit/s).  These cards require only close proximity to an antenna to complete transaction. They are often used when transactions must be processed quickly or hands-free, such as on mass transit systems, where smart cards can be used without even removing them from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/653173.xml">
wallet</link>.</p>
<p>

The standard for contactless smart card communications is <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/187876.xml">
ISO/IEC 14443</link></b>, dated 2001. It defines two types of contactless cards ("A" and "B"), allows for communications at distances up to 10 cm. There had been proposals for ISO 14443 types C, D, E and F that have been rejected by the International Organization for Standardization. An alternative standard for contactless smart cards is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/1468909.xml">
ISO 15693</link>, which allows communications at distances up to 50 cm.</p>
<p>

Example of widely used contactless smart cards are Hong Kong's <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/267624.xml">
Octopus card</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
, and Japan Rail's <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../046/404046.xml">
Suica</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
 Card; which predate the ISO/IEC 14443 standard. The following tables list smart cards used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/23894.xml">
public transportation</link> and other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/66244.xml">
electronic purse</link> applications.</p>
<p>

<image width="150px" src="SingapourMetroCard.jpg">
<caption>

Singapore's MRT <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ezlink.com.sg">
EZlink</weblink>
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="TransportMifareNovosibirskExample.jpg">
<caption>

Novosibirsk (Russia). Transport farecollection terminal <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.socialcard.ru">
CFT</weblink>
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Matkakortti_ja_kortinlukija.jpg">
<caption>

Smartcard used for paying for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/23894.xml">
public transportation</link> in the <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/13696.xml">
Helsinki</link></village>
 area; the card is read remotely.
</caption>
</image>

<image width="150px" src="OctopusFrontNew.jpg">
<caption>

Obverse side of a standard adult <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/267624.xml">
Octopus card</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
, a contactless smart card.
</caption>
</image>
</p>

<p>

A related contactless technology is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/169320.xml">
RFID</link> (radio frequency identification). In certain cases, it can be used for applications similar to those of contactless smart cards, such as for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/370644.xml">
electronic toll collection</link>.  RFID devices usually do not include writeable memory or microcontroller processing capability as contactless smart cards often do.</p>
<p>

There are dual-interface cards that implement contactless and contact interfaces on a single card with some shared storage and processing.  An example is <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../715/100715.xml">
Porto</link></site>
's multi-application transport card, called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/4867808.xml">
Andante</link>, that uses a chip in contact and contactless (ISO 14443B).</p>
<p>

Like smart cards with contacts, contactless cards do not have a battery.  Instead, they use a built-in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../896/14896.xml">
inductor</link> to capture some of the incident radio-frequency interrogation signal, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/60569.xml">
rectify</link> it, and use it to power the card's electronics.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Communication protocols </st>
<p>

<table class="wikitable">
<caption>
Communication protocols</caption>
<header>
Name</header>
<header>
Description</header>
<row>
<col>
T=0</col>
<col>
Byte-level transmission protocol, defined in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/59959.xml">
ISO/IEC 7816-3</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
T=1</col>
<col>
Block-level transmission protocol, defined in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/59959.xml">
ISO/IEC 7816-3</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
ISO/IEC 14443</col>
<col>
APDU transmission via contactless interface, defined in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/187876.xml">
ISO/IEC 14443-4</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Credit card contactless technology</st>

<p>

These are the best known payment cards (classical plastic card):
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Visa: Visa Contactless, Quick VSDC - "qVSDC", Visa Wave, MSD, payWave</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 MasterCard: PayPass Magstripe, PayPass MChip</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 American Express: Express Pay</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Chase: Blink (credit and debit cards)</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Roll-outs started in 2005 in USA (Asia and Europe - 2006). Contactless (non PIN) transactions cover a payment range of ~$5-50. There is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../876/187876.xml">
ISO 14443</link> PayPass implementation. All PayPass implementations may be separated on EMV and non EMV.</p>
<p>

Non-EMV cards work like magnetic stripe cards. This is a typical card technology in the USA (PayPass Magstripe and VISA MSD). The cards do not control amount remaining.  All payment passes without a PIN and usually in off-line mode. The security level of such a transaction is no greater than with classical magnetic stripe card transaction. </p>
<p>

EMV cards have two interfaces (contact and contactless) and they work as a normal EMV card via contact interface. Via contactless interface they work almost like an EMV (card command sequence adopted on contactless features as low power and short transaction time).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Cryptographic smart cards</st>
<p>

Cryptographic smart cards are often used for single sign-on. Most advanced smart cards are equipped with specialized cryptographic hardware that let you use algorithms such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/25385.xml">
RSA</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/59470.xml">
DSA</link> on board. Today's cryptographic smart cards are also able to generate key pairs on board, to avoid the risk of having more than one copy of the key (since by design there usually isn't a way to extract private keys from a smart card).</p>
<p>

Such smart cards are mainly used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../644/59644.xml">
digital signature</link> and secure identification, (see applications section). <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

The most common way to access cryptographic smart card functions on a computer is to use a <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/7620041.xml">
PKCS#11</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
 library provided by the vendor. On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../890/18890.xml">
Microsoft Windows</link> platforms the <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<component wordnetid="105868954" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="105867413" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../110/3168110.xml">
CSP</link></part>
</component>
</concept>
</idea>
 API is also adopted.</p>
<p>

The most widely used cryptographic algorithms in smart cards (excluding the GSM so-called "crypto algorithm") are 3DES (<cipher wordnetid="106254239" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../375/48375.xml">
Triple DES</link></cipher>
) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../385/25385.xml">
RSA</link>. The key set is usually loaded (DES) or generated (RSA) on the card at the personalization stage.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Applications</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Computer security</st>
<p>

The <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.8">
<application wordnetid="106570110" confidence="0.8">
<program wordnetid="106568978" confidence="0.8">
<browser wordnetid="106571301" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106359877" confidence="0.8">
<code wordnetid="106355894" confidence="0.8">
<coding_system wordnetid="106353757" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/210892.xml">
Mozilla Firefox</link></coding_system>
</code>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</browser>
</program>
</application>
</software>
 web browser can use smart cards to store <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/223796.xml">
certificate</link>s for use in secure web browsing<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>.</p>
<p>

Some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/1845155.xml">
disk encryption systems</link>, such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/4954583.xml">
FreeOTFE</link></software>
, can use smart cards to securely hold encryption keys, and also to add another layer of encryption to critical parts of the secured disk<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>.</p>
<p>

Smartcards are also used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/927470.xml">
single sign-on</link> to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../372/9878372.xml">
log on</link> to computers</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Financial</st>
<p>

The applications of smart cards include their use as credit or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/46628.xml">
ATM</link> cards, in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/7986973.xml">
fuel card</link>, <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/197489.xml">
SIM</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
s for mobile phones, authorization cards for pay television, pre-pay utilities in household, high-security identification and access-control cards, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../894/23894.xml">
public transport</link> and public phone payment cards.</p>
<p>

Smart cards may also be used as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../335/5758335.xml">
electronic wallet</link>s. The smart card chip can be loaded with funds which can be spent in parking meters and vending machines or at various merchants. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/591994.xml">
Cryptographic protocol</link>s protect the exchange of money between the smart card and the accepting machine. There is no connection to the issuing bank necessary, so the holder of the card can use it regardless of him being the owner. Examples are <link>
Proton</link>, <link>
Geldkarte</link>, <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<medium_of_exchange wordnetid="113372961" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<currency wordnetid="113385913" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/3785512.xml">
Chipknip</link></currency>
</system_of_measurement>
</medium_of_exchange>
</standard>
 and <link>
Mon€o</link>. The German Geldkarte is also used to validate the customers age at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/266339.xml">
vending machine</link>s for cigarettes.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Identification</st>
<p>

A quickly growing application is in digital identification cards. In this application, the cards are used for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/47967.xml">
authentication</link> of identity. The most common example is in conjunction with a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../112/194112.xml">
PKI</link>. The smart card will store an encrypted digital certificate issued from the PKI along with any other relevant or needed information about the card holder. Examples include the <agency wordnetid="108337324" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/7279897.xml">
U.S. Department of Defense</link></agency>
 (DoD) <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/2460204.xml">
Common Access Card</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
 (CAC), and the use of various smart cards by many governments as identification cards for their citizens. When combined with biometrics, smart cards can provide two- or three-factor authentication. Smart cards are not always a privacy-enhancing technology, for the subject carries possibly incriminating information about him all the time. By employing contactless smart cards, that can be read without having to remove the card from the wallet or even the garment it is in, one can add even more authentication value to the human carrier of the cards.</p>
<p>

The first smart card driver's license system in the world was issued in 1995 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/2508251.xml">
Mendoza</link>, a province of <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/18951905.xml">
Argentina</link></country>
</city>
. Mendoza has a high level of road accidents, driving offenses, and a poor record of recovering outstanding fines. The smart licenses keep an up-to-date record of driving offenses and unpaid fines. They also store personal information, license type and number, and a photograph of the holder. Emergency medical information like blood type, allergies, and biometrics (fingerprints) can be stored on the chip if the cardholder wishes. The Argentina government anticipates that this new system will help to recover more than $10 million per year in fines.</p>
<p>

<legal_power wordnetid="105198427" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/53707.xml">
Gujarat</link></legal_power>
 was the first state in India to introduce the <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.parivahan.nic.in/">
smart card license system</weblink> in 1999. To date the Gujarat Government has issued 5 million smart card driving licenses to its people. This card is basically a plastic card having <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/187874.xml">
ISO/IEC 7810</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
 certification and integrated circuit, capable of storing and verifying information according to its programming.</p>
<p>

Smart cards have been advertised as suitable for personal identification tasks, because they are engineered to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../347/357347.xml">
tamper resistant</link>. The embedded chip of a smart card usually implements some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/18934432.xml">
cryptographic algorithm</link>. Information about the inner workings of this algorithm can be obtained if the precise time and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/6207.xml">
electrical current</link> required for certain encryption or decryption operations is measured. A number of research projects have now demonstrated the feasibility of this line of attack. Countermeasures have been proposed.</p>
<p>

By the start of 2009 the entire population of <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/3343.xml">
Belgium</link></country>
 will have an eID card, that is issued by the Spanish and Belgian Governments and that is used to identify an individual. These cards contain 2 certificates: one for authentication and one for signature. This signature is legally adopted. More and more services in these countries are using the eID card as an authorization token. More information on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dnielectronico.es/">
http://www.dnielectronico.es/</weblink>and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eid.belgium.be/">
http://eid.belgium.be/</weblink></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other</st>
<p>

Smart cards are widely used to protect digital television streams. See <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/2073628.xml">
television encryption</link> for an overview, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../933/1523933.xml">
VideoGuard</link> for a specific example of how smart card security worked (and was cracked).</p>
<p>

The Malaysian government uses smart card technology in identity cards carried by all Malaysian citizens and resident non-citizens. The personal information inside the smart card (called MYKAD) can be read using special APDU commands.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mykadpro.net/">
MYKAD SDK</weblink></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Problems</st>
<p>

Another problem of smart cards may be the failure rate. The plastic card in which the chip is embedded is fairly flexible, and the larger the chip, the higher the probability of breaking. Smart cards are often carried in wallets or pockets &mdash; a fairly harsh environment for a chip. However, for large banking systems, the failure-management cost can be more than offset by the fraud reduction. A <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/7749545.xml">
card enclosure</link> might be a good idea.</p>
<p>

Using a smart card for mass transit presents a risk for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/25009.xml">
privacy</link>, because such a system enables the mass transit operator (and the authorities) to track the movement of individuals. In Finland, the Data Protection <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/202583.xml">
Ombudsman</link> prohibited the transport operator <politics wordnetid="113840719" confidence="0.8">
<social_relation wordnetid="100032823" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/206554.xml">
YTV</link></social_relation>
</politics>
 from collecting such information, in spite of YTV's argument that the owner of the card has the right to get a list of journeys paid with the card. Prior to this, such information was used in the investigation of the <terrorist_attack wordnetid="101246697" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../343/105343.xml">
Myyrmanni bombing</link></terrorist_attack>
.</p>

<p>

Smart cards used for client-side identification and authentication are the most secure way for eg. internet banking applications, but the security is never 100% sure. In the example of internet banking, if the PC is infected with any kind of malware, the security model is broken. A malware can override the communication (both input via keyboard and output via application screen) between the user and the internet banking application (eg. browser). This would result in modifying transactions by the malware and unnoticed by the user. There are malwares in the wild with this capability (eg. Trojan. Silentbanker). Banks like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../073/1253073.xml">
Fortis</link> and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/3032511.xml">
Dexia</link></company>
 in Belgium combine a Smart card with an unconnected card reader to avoid this problem. The customer enters a challenge received from the bank's website, his PIN and the transaction amount into the card reader, the card reader returns an 8 digits signature. This signature is manually copied to the PC and verified by the bank. This method prevents a malware to change the transaction amount.</p>
<p>

In addition to technical hurdles is the lack of standards for smart card functionality and security.  To address this problem, the ERIDANE Project was launched by <link>
The Berlin Group</link> to develop a proposal for "a new functional and security framework for smart-card based Point of Interaction (POI) equipment", equipment that would be used, for instance, in retail environments.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/9267751.xml">
Access badge</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../684/40684.xml">
Access control</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link>
Keycard</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/8399968.xml">
Disk encryption</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/58725.xml">
Physical security</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/6723240.xml">
BasicCard</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../622/290622.xml">
Biometrics</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/2460204.xml">
Common Access Card</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/2158184.xml">
Credential</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<protocol wordnetid="106665108" confidence="0.8">
<standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<medium_of_exchange wordnetid="113372961" confidence="0.8">
<direction wordnetid="106786629" confidence="0.8">
<rule wordnetid="106652242" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<currency wordnetid="113385913" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../244/66244.xml">
Electronic money</link></currency>
</system_of_measurement>
</rule>
</direction>
</medium_of_exchange>
</standard>
</protocol>
</message>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/1438860.xml">
Electronic passport</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/458524.xml">
EMV credit cards</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/13744254.xml">
GlobalPlatform standard</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/364578.xml">
ID card</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/2070564.xml">
Java Card</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/207379.xml">
Magnetic stripe card</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</document>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../793/6368793.xml">
MULTOS</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/8551616.xml">
PCI DSS</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/270072.xml">
Proximity card</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/169320.xml">
RFID</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../730/28730.xml">
Security engineering</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <system wordnetid="104377057" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/927470.xml">
Single sign-on</link></instrumentality>
</artifact>
</system>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../156/2114156.xml">
Snapi</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <standard wordnetid="107260623" confidence="0.8">
<system_of_measurement wordnetid="113577171" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/197489.xml">
SIM</link></system_of_measurement>
</standard>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../379/207379.xml">
Swipe card</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/24879.xml">
Telephone card</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Terminology </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

ATR:Answer to Reset</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

BCD:<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../821/3821.xml">
Binary-coded decimal</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

CHV:Card Holder Verification</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

COS:Card operating system</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

DF:Dedicated File</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

IC:Integrated circuit</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/1929041.xml">
PC/SC</link>:Personal computer / smart card</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

MF:Master File</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

PPS:Protocol and Parameter Select</entry>
<entry level="1" type="definition">

RFU:Reserved for Future Use</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://secude.com/htm/811/en/White_Paper%3A_Enterprise_SSO.htm">
Intelligent Enterprise Single sign-on</weblink>".&#32;  SECUDE International.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://secude.com/htm/806/en/White_Paper_Section%3A_Single_Sign-On.htm">
White Papers on Using Smartcards for Digital Signatures and Single Sign-on</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/security/pki/pkcs11/">
Mozilla certificate store</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.freeotfe.org/docs/pkcs11_support.htm">
Security Token/Smartcard Support</weblink> used by FreeOTFE</entry>
<entry id="5">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.berlin-group.org/related-eridane.html">
Related Initiatives</weblink>".&#32;<it>Home web for The Berlin Group</it>.&#32;  <link>
The Berlin Group</link>&#32;(2005-08-01).&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2007-12-20</link>.&nbsp;"The aim of ERIDANE is therefore to propose a new functional and security framework for smart-card based Point of Interaction (POI) equipment to be used in a wide variety of retail environment : Point Of Sales (POS) devices in small shops, POS equipment integrated in supermarkets and department stores, card readers to be used on the move (e.g. taxis, etc.), vending machines and other unattended related terminals."</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Books </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Rankl-1997" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Rankl, W.;&#32;W. Effing&#32;(1997). Smart Card Handbook.&#32;John Wiley &amp; Sons. ISBN 0-471-96720-3.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

  <cite id="Reference-Guthery-1998" style="font-style:normal" class="book">Guthery, Scott B.;&#32;Timothy M. Jurgensen&#32;(1998). SmartCard Developer's Kit.&#32;Macmillan Technical Publishing. ISBN 1-57870-027-2.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dmoz.org/Computers/Hardware/Systems/Smartcards//">
Smart card</weblink> at the <work wordnetid="100575741" confidence="0.8">
<possession wordnetid="100032613" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<undertaking wordnetid="100795720" confidence="0.8">
<property wordnetid="113244109" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<subsidiary_company wordnetid="108003935" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../501/18949501.xml">
Open Directory Project</link></institution>
</subsidiary_company>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</property>
</undertaking>
</company>
</event>
</possession>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.smartcardalliance.org/">
Smart Card Alliance</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.opensc-project.org/">
OpenSC (open source smart card framework)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://techwatch.reviewk.com/2008/06/open-source-smart-card-project-launched/">
Open Source Smart Card Project</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openscdp.org/">
Open Smart Card Development Platform</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://secude.com/htm/806/en/White_Paper_Section%3A_Single_Sign-On.htm">
Using Smartcards for Digital Signatures</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mykadpro.net">
Malaysia MYKAD SDK</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wrankl.de/JavaPC/JavaPC.html">
Smartcard simulator</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</standard>
</article>
