<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE inex-snippet-submission SYSTEM "inex-snippet-submission.dtd">
<inex-snippet-submission participant-id="247" run-id="TheCNGL_DCU_SnippetTrack_2012_SRun03">
	<description>Bias factorto score sentences containing query terms more highly.sentence score = (number of query terms in the sentence)^2/number of terms in query.Summary of text is some the highest score sentences.</description>
	<topic topic-id="2012001">
		<snippet doc-id="3457121" rsv="1972.00">In 2000, the John Lennon Museum was opened at the Saitama Super Arena in Saitama, Saitama, Japan, and two years later, Liverpool renamed its airport to Liverpool John Lennon Airpor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5231203" rsv="1930.00">George Toogood Smith (1903–5 June 1955) was the maternal uncle, through marriage, of John Lennon. Lennon lived with Smith and his wife for the majority of his childhood, and Smith </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15852" rsv="1919.00">John Winston Ono Lennon, MBE (born John Winston Lennon; 9 October 1940 – 8 December 1980) was an English rock musician, singer, writer, songwriter, artist, actor and peace activist</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14851312" rsv="1892.00">Baird had an older half-brother, John Lennon (9 October 1940 – 8 December 1980) who was born during her mother's marriage to Alfred Lennon, and an older half-sister, Ingrid Pederso</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7553287" rsv="1891.00">Rosaura Lopez Lorenzo (16 March 1932, Pontevedra, Spain – 19 September 2005, Pontevedra, Spain) was a maid of John Lennon and Yoko Ono in the Dakota apartment between 1976 and 1980</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5231097" rsv="1891.00">Mary Elizabeth "Mimi" Smith (née Stanley) (1903 – 6 December 1992) is best known as the maternal aunt and parental guardian of the English musician John Lennon. After Julia separat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2023257" rsv="1890.00">The Lives of John Lennon is a 1988 biography of musician John Lennon by Americanauthor Albert Goldman. Concerning the author's account of Lennon's consumption of LSD, the New York </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1924705" rsv="1887.00">Milk and Honey is an album of music by John Lennon and Yoko Ono released in 1984. Jack Douglas, who had co-produced Double Fantasy with Lennon and Ono, also had input into the init</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13202488" rsv="1875.00">For information on the surname and given name "Lennon", see Lennon (name). Lennon may refer to: Geography: </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1149616" rsv="1872.00">Cynthia Lennon (née Powell) (born 10 September 1939 in Blackpool, Lancashire, England) is the former wife of John Lennon. Lennon and Cynthia had one last short meeting at Kenwood (</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5733759" rsv="1871.00">For the soundtrack to the film, see The U.S. vs. John Lennon (soundtrack). The U.S. vs. John Lennon is a 2006 documentary film about British musician John Lennon's transformation f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="614773" rsv="1863.00">Double Fantasy is the comeback album by John Lennon and Yoko Ono, released in 1980 initially on the newly-formed Geffen Records, and then from 1989 onwards through EMI. It is notab</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1740047" rsv="1859.00">Menlove Ave. is a John Lennon album, posthumously released in 1986 under the supervision of Yoko Ono, Lennon's widow. All songs by John Lennon, except where noted. Produced by John</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5721446" rsv="1853.00">"Love" is a ballad by John Lennon, originally released in 1970 on his John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band album. The song first came out on Lennon's 1970 album John Lennon/Plastic Ono Ban</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="875989" rsv="1852.00">Unfinished Music No.2: Life with the Lions is an album of experimental music released by John Lennon and Yoko Ono in 1969, and the successor to 1968's highly controversial . Saxoph</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1770362" rsv="1851.00">The John Lennon Collection is a retrospective compilation album of John Lennon's solo music, released in 1982 (see 1982 in music) by Parlophone Records, through EMI and by Geffen R</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5987959" rsv="1850.00">Julia Stanley Lennon (née Stanley) (12 March 1914 – 15 July 1958) was the mother of John Lennon. Lennon chose Alf (twice) and then Julia walked away, but in the end Lennon (crying)</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18960141" rsv="1848.00">"Imagine" is a song by John Lennon, which appears on his 1971 album, Imagine. In the book Lennon in America, written by Geoffrey Giuliano, Lennon commented that the song was "an an</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81562" rsv="1845.00">John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band is the début solo album by English rock musician John Lennon. John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band is generally considered one of Lennon's finest solo albums a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="614795" rsv="1845.00">Walls and Bridges is an album by John Lennon, released in October 1974. During one of his sporadic visits from England to see his father, eleven-year-old Julian Lennon helped recor</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012002">
		<snippet doc-id="9138522" rsv="3390.00">MEGA Brands, Incorporated TSX: MB (Formerly MEGA Bloks, Incorporated) is a publicly traded children's toy company based in Montreal, Canada. Mega Bloks is the name of their most po</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2438332" rsv="3127.00">This is an alphabetical list of video games. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2006923" rsv="2913.00">Servbot (Kobun in Japan, which roughly means "little follower") are a series of characters from the Mega Man Legends'' series. However, by Mega Man Legends 2, the Servbots begin to</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12715707" rsv="2695.00">Block-style figures are a type of collectible toy action figures marked by a generally simplistic representation of the human form, usually comprised of block-shaped apendages and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="146560" rsv="2506.00">A brickfilm is any film made using LEGO, Mega Bloks, or other similar plastic construction block toys. They are most often created with stop motion, though many CGI, 2D animation, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="149671" rsv="2504.00">This is a list of games for the Game Boy Advance handheld game system, organized alphabetically by name. This includes games released in the US, Japan, and Europe for the system. T</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2159245" rsv="2451.00">Each park features large-scale LEGO models of famous landmarks and miniature LEGO models of famous cities, along with LEGO-themed rides. See also: History of LEGO and LEGO timeline</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="708262" rsv="2423.00">This is the official list of games for the Game Boy Color. All games are released in Europe and the USA. organized alphabetically by name, followed by catalog number where known. S</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5994421" rsv="2331.00">Lego Mindstorms NXT is a programmable robotics kit released by Lego in late July 2006. It replaces the first-generation Lego Mindstorms kit, which was called the Robotics Invention</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3478140" rsv="2315.00">The first Lego Space sets were a leap forward in Lego design. Perfectly suited for utilitarian Lego Space, gray had finally become a major color for a Lego theme, especially as mor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4957820" rsv="2257.00">This is not intended to be a complete list. For a list of all toys on which there are currently articles, see Toys. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6707496" rsv="2250.00">Pac-Mania is an arcade video game in the Pac-Man series, released in 1987 by Namco and distributed by Atari Games in the United States and Europe. It is a pseudo-3D interpretation </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1390380" rsv="2217.00">This article lists notable events and releases in the timeline of the Lego Group. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2202938" rsv="2199.00">Minifigures are small, plastic figural toys produced by Danish toy manufacturer Lego, which are customarily sold with Lego sets, as characters intended to populate modular Lego env</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1318591" rsv="2155.00">Lego Baby is a line of blocks by the Lego Group for very young children. In the past it was sold first as Duplo Primo (1995 - 1996) then as Lego Primo (1997 - 1999) and became Lego</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="631107" rsv="2150.00">For other uses of this term, see city block (disambiguation). In an overcrowded city like Mega-City One, tensions and rivalry between neighbouring city blocks are inevitable and, v</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10395475" rsv="2148.00">This list encompasses fictional characters with the paranormal or superhuman ability to generate and manipulate various forms of "earth", including, but not limited to, soil, stone</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4623220" rsv="2134.00">Lego pneumatics is a variety of Lego bricks which utilise air pressure and specialised components to perform various actions utilising the principles of pneumatics. The LEGO pneuma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5965052" rsv="2128.00">Clone Bricks are imitation LEGO Bricks, such as Mega Bloks, Tyco bricks, and others. They are generally considered to be of lower quality and cheaper than LEGO brand bricks, though</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="198856" rsv="2120.00">LEGO Mindstorms is a line of Lego sets combining programmable bricks with electric motors, sensors, Lego bricks, and Lego Technic pieces (such as gears, axles, and beams). Little i</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012003">
		<snippet doc-id="9013183" rsv="2077.00">This article is a list of diseases of bananas and plantains (Musa spp.). </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="38940" rsv="1894.00">Banana chips are a snack produced from dehydrated or fried banana or plantain slices, which have a dark brown color and an intense banana taste. Main article: Banana paperBanana fi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="769420" rsv="1787.00">Black Sigatoka is a leaf spot disease of banana plants caused by ascomycete fungusMycosphaerella fijiensis Morelet. Plants with leaves damaged by the disease may have up to 50% low</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="312937" rsv="1755.00">Fusarium oxysporum, also referred to as Panama disease or Agent Green, is a fungus that causes Fusarium wilt disease in more than a hundred species of plants. This cultivar was wip</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16465743" rsv="1755.00">The Banana industry in the Caribbean is widely spread to each island. In st.Vincent, there are about 5,000 banana growers. 3. Diseases </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12264177" rsv="1651.00">Banana bract mosaic virus (BBrMV) is a plant pathogenic virus of the family Potyviridae. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12264317" rsv="1629.00">Banana streak virus (BSV) is a plant pathogenic virus of the family Caulimoviridae. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12264210" rsv="1628.00">Banana bunchy top virus (BBTV) is a plant pathogenic virus of the family Nanoviridae. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9012366" rsv="1627.00">Lists of plant diseases are presented in the following table. Common Names of Diseases, The American Phytopathological Society </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19106136" rsv="1617.00">The Honduran banana industry employed a significant Garifuna workforce from the Bay Islands off Trujillo and in 1901 the government gave concessions for them to use over 7,000 hect</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11818087" rsv="1615.00">Cylindrocarpon musae is a fungal plant pathogen that causes root rot in banana. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11817197" rsv="1615.00">Cordana johnstonii is a plant pathogen. It produces cordana leaf spot on bananas. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11817228" rsv="1611.00">Cordana musae is a plant pathogen. It produces cordana leaf spot on bananas. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="622746" rsv="1574.00">This led, in part, to the devastating effects of Old World diseases on Native American populations. In addition to the diseases mentioned above, many species of organisms were intr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4302211" rsv="1499.00">The resulting banana trade proved extremely lucrative. Keith then established banana plantations in Panama and in the Colombian Magdalena Department. He eventually came to dominate</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11817399" rsv="1440.00">Guignardia musae is a plant pathogen that causes Freckle of banana a disease that forms water soaked lesions of banana fruit and is spread by rain splash. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16495842" rsv="1434.00">The Citrus industry in the Caribbean is a major one in the Caribbean. Citrus fruits consists of oranges, pineapples, grapefruit, tangerines, limes, &amp;amp; lemons. The Caribbean coun</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2146221" rsv="1427.00">Burrowing nematode or Banana-root nematode (Radopholus similis) is an important parasite of fruit, vegetable, and other crops. It is an especially important pest of bananas and cit</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11818219" rsv="1415.00">Mycosphaerella musicola is a fungal plant pathogen, which is the causal agent of Yellow Sigatoka leaf spot disease on banana plants. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="251116" rsv="1413.00">One of the most well-known products of the province is banana. Banana festivals take place in the province every year, to thank the gods for the harvest. Kluai Khai (mini banana) i</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012004">
		<snippet doc-id="8669149" rsv="2142.00">Criticism of sport utility vehicles is the expression (made by various groups, organizations or individuals) of disapproval of sport utility vehicles (SUVs). SUV safety concerns ar</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="535476" rsv="1970.00">For example, some SUVs and pickup trucks ride higher than cars and lack crumple zones to absorb impact energy. The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration have done studies </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2450538" rsv="1923.00">In China the SUV is sold under the name of Baowei, and it is also available as a pickup truck called the Baodian. The Landwind has attracted a controversy after a series of safety </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="700494" rsv="1918.00">The GLK-Class was launched in 2008 and is built in Bremen (Germany), the first Mercedes SUV to be built there, however after 2008 most will be built in Mexico and Brazil. On 2008-0</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="956354" rsv="1913.00">The BMW X5 is a mid-size crossover SUV sold by BMW since 1999. BMW described it as a SAV (Sport Activity Vehicle) rather than an SUV (Sport Utility Vehicle), to emphasize its on-ro</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6385842" rsv="1909.00">The Hyundai Veracruz is a mid-size crossover SUV sold by Hyundai in the countries of United States, Canada, South Korea, China, and the Middle East. The Veracruz went on sale in Ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1826282" rsv="1904.00">The Daewoo Winstorm is a crossover SUV developed by General Motors's GM Daewoo design center in Bupyeong, South Korea. In crash safety tests conducted by Euro NCAP, the Winstorm wa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1092286" rsv="1899.00">Geo/Chevrolet Tracker is a mini SUV produced by Chevrolet and Geo The Geo Tracker was a mini SUV introduced in late 1988 as a 1989 model. According to a report by the Insurance Ins</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="802817" rsv="1894.00">It was slotted below the larger truck based Explorer in Ford's lineup, but was larger than the small SUV offerings from Honda and Toyota. At the time, most sport utility vehicles u</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="47696" rsv="1890.00">A sport utility vehicle (SUV) is a generic marketing description for a rugged automotive vehicle similar to a station wagon but built on a light-truck chassis. Compact SUVs and min</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="989530" rsv="1886.00">In 1966, Congress held a series of highly publicized hearings regarding highway safety, and passed legislation to make installation of seat belts mandatory, and created several pre</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3014744" rsv="1880.00">As a crossover vehicle, the Edge bridges the gap between minivans like the now discontinued Freestar, and truck-based sport utility vehicles such as the Explorer. The Edge official</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="440246" rsv="1879.00">Historically, higher fuel efficiency was associated with lower traffic safety, intertwining the issues of fuel economy, road-traffic safety, air pollution, climate change, although</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1887376" rsv="1859.00">The Hyundai Santa Fe is a compact/mid-size crossover SUV based on the Hyundai Sonata platform. It was introduced for the 2001 model year as Hyundai's first SUV, released at the sam</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1822962" rsv="1845.00">The project began with a comparative study of competing models from 20 different manufacturers, with Toyota Tercel, Opel Astra and Volkswagen Golf identified as most competitive. S</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5979772" rsv="1837.00">High and Mighty: SUVs - The World's Most Dangerous vehicles and how they got that way (ISBN 1-58648-123-1) is a book by Keith Bradsher which details the tax breaks, protectionism a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2372552" rsv="1833.00">The Saturn Outlook is a premium full-size crossover SUV which debuted at the New York International Auto Show. National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA) The Insurance </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1097589" rsv="1831.00">The Mazda Navajo was a 2-door SUV introduced in 1991, and Mazda's very first off-roader. A rear-wheel drive Navajo was available for 1992, geared towards people who liked the sport</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1278102" rsv="1825.00">The Nissan Murano is a mid-size crossover SUV first manufactured by Nissan in December 2002 and sold as a 2003 model. Nissan introduced the Murano as its first crossover SUV for th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1014707" rsv="1822.00">The Audi Q7 is a full-size luxury sport utility vehicle (SUV) produced by German automaker Audi since its unveiling at the Los Angeles Auto Show in January 2006. quattro GmbH is cu</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012005">
		<snippet doc-id="887" rsv="1720.00">The Apple Newton, or simply Newton, is the iPhone's predecessor and was an early line of personal digital assistants developed and marketed by Apple Computer (now Apple Inc.) from </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1439045" rsv="1703.00">Apple unidentified -- SGX520 + VXD380 Apple unidentified -- SGX531 + VXD380 Apple unidentified -- SGX540 + VXD380 </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19611129" rsv="1692.00">Sleepy People (later renamed Blue Apple Boy) were/are a British psychedelic rock band known for their eccentric and energetic songs and live act, and for incubating three of the fi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9593665" rsv="1678.00">It was sold to and incorporated into an Apple magazine where, of course, all non-Apple content was immediately dropped. There were some regular columns such as Pets Corner (for the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17527833" rsv="1672.00">The word sagardotegi is composed of three elements: sagar "apple" and ardo "wine", yielding sagardo or "cider" and the suffix -tegi which denotes a building where an activity takes</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="264575" rsv="1647.00">This is a list of home and office computers by category where the main category is the home computer's CPU wordlength (8/16/32/64 bits) and the subcategory is the specific CPU used</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="264569" rsv="1625.00">This is a list of home computers, sorted alphanumerically by manufacturer's name and chronologically by computer model. Note: in cases of manufacturers who have made both home and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6870355" rsv="1623.00">ChipWits is a 1984 game for the Apple Macintosh, programmed by Doug Sharp and Mike Johnston, and published by BrainPower software. The game was developed in MacFORTH, and later por</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7754761" rsv="1604.00">Sharp Daily ( Chinese:爽報 Pinyin: Shuǎng Bào) is a free Chinese-language tabloid newspaper, published in Taipei, Taiwan by Next Media. Launched on October 24, 2006 as a rival to Col</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1979166" rsv="1583.00">The King of Chicago is a 1986 action adventure strategy computer game by Doug Sharp. This game was first developed by Doug Sharp on the Mac, then limited to a monochrome display, u</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1688626" rsv="1537.00">"Homer's Barbershop Quartet" is the first episode of The Simpsons' fifth season. It features the Be-Sharps, a fictional barbershop quartet founded by Homer, whose story roughly par</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9081996" rsv="1526.00">Flappy first appeared on the Sharp X1 home computer in 1983. Two officially-unreleased variants of Flappy, Floppy and Beyond Floppy, were programmed by Greg Hale and Ted Cohn for t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="269240" rsv="1505.00">Apple Daily was the first newspaper to use the massive graphics, bold headlines and full colour pages now common to all best-selling papers in Hong Kong and Taiwan. Apple Daily and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="703681" rsv="1498.00">For other uses, see Sharp. Sharp Corporation (シャープ株式会社, Shāpu Kabushiki-gaisha) (TYO: 6753 , LuxSE: SRP) is a Japanese electronics manufacturer, founded in 1912. One of his first i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8953588" rsv="1492.00">This list is ; you can help by expanding it. The following is a list of notable computer system manufacturers. Please do not add entries without proper sources to indicate notabili</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="548115" rsv="1483.00">The Macintosh is the original Apple Macintosh personal computer. As with the Apple II and the Apple Lisa before it, the mouse has only a single button. Apple also offered their 300</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1280893" rsv="1469.00">A cooking apple is an apple that is used primarily for cooking rather than eating fresh. Other variety such as Bramley or Golden Noble are cut into small segments for pies, tarts e</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11931183" rsv="1448.00">Ashmead's Kernel is a diploid cultivar of apple. This desert apple is of medium size, between 65:70mm diameter and has a flat round shape. Ashmead's Kernel makes a good apple juice</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="356878" rsv="1443.00">Xcode is a suite of tools for developing software on Mac OS X, developed by Apple. Version 3.0 is not supported on older Mac OS versions, for which Xcode is also available for free</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2094876" rsv="1425.00">Solanum aculeastrum is commonly known as Soda Apple, Sodaapple Nightshade, Goat Apple, Poison Apple, or more ambiguously as "bitter-apple". The term "soda apple" probably derives f</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012006">
		<snippet doc-id="24032" rsv="2273.00">PET scans are increasingly read alongside CT or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans, the combination ("co-registration") giving both anatomic and metabolic information (i.e., wh</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3557219" rsv="2175.00">More or less concurrently, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI or MR scanning) was developed by researchers including Peter Mansfield and Paul Lauterbur, who were awarded the Nobel Pri</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3457142" rsv="2078.00">MRI does have several disadvantages though. First, MRI has a sensitivity of around 10-3 mol/L  to 10-5 mol/L which compared to other types of imaging can be very limiting. One of t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17890739" rsv="1916.00">The Modular Neutron Array (MoNA) is a large-area, high efficiency neutron detector that is used in basic research of rare isotopes at Michigan State University's National Supercond</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16434531" rsv="1910.00">More recent developments in CT and MRI has meant clearer images and solid data such graphs depicting blood flow and blood volume charted over a fixed period of time. There are diff</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="907554" rsv="1813.00">Learning from MRI, PET and SPECT scanning, scientists were able to develop functional MRI (fMRI) with abilities that opened the door to direct observation of cognitive activities. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2285280" rsv="1785.00">This program is charged with developing and exploiting the unique capabilities of FT-ICR (Fourier Transform Ion Cyclotron Resonance) mass spectrometry. The University of Florida is</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="44585" rsv="1724.00">For other uses, see Cyclotron (disambiguation). A cyclotron is a type of particle accelerator. An alternative to the synchrocyclotron is the isochronous cyclotron, which has a magn</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1228679" rsv="1711.00">In physics, the gyromagnetic ratio (also sometimes known as the magnetogyric ratio in other disciplines) of a particle or system is the ratio of its magnetic dipole moment to its a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="347838" rsv="1689.00">Nuclear medicine is a branch of medicine and medical imaging that uses the nuclear properties of matter in diagnosis and therapy. More specifically, nuclear medicine is a part of m</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2424135" rsv="1686.00">Dr Alan Jeavons, formerly a Senior Physicist at CERN, Switzerland, founded Oxford Positron Systems in 1985. A second-generation prototype two-detector HIDAC-PET camera was assessed</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="170757" rsv="1684.00">The planet Jupiter in particular is a large source of cyclotron radiation. Cyclotron radiation would likely be produced in a high altitude nuclear explosion. Radiation reaction act</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1917699" rsv="1678.00">List of materials analysis methods: </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="439202" rsv="1668.00">In addition to heating, electron cyclotron waves can be used to drive current. Many diverse activities depend on electron cyclotron resonance technology, including The ECR ion sour</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2182716" rsv="1666.00">The physics of FTICR is similar to that of a cyclotron at least in the first approximation. The cyclotron motion is still the frequency being used but the relationship above is not</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7405641" rsv="1665.00">Cyclotron is the name of two incarnations of the same fictional DC Comics character, Terry Curtis. Roy Thomas reinvented the character as Cyclotron, a reluctant supervillain, in Al</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1053016" rsv="1647.00">The Ring Cyclotron is a separated sector cyclotron with a fixed beam energy of 590 MeV, built by PSI and commissioned in 1974. The 72 MeV beam from either one of two injector cyclo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5320931" rsv="1637.00">Cyclotron may refer to: Cyclotron, the particle accelerator. Cyclotron (band), the metal rock band. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11311306" rsv="1623.00">The 1930s were years of intense cyclotron development at Berkeley under Lawrence's leadership and Thornton became a prominent member of his team. In 1945 Thornton returned to Berke</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5320929" rsv="1620.00">For other uses, see Cyclotron (disambiguation). Cyclotron is an Industrial metal duo from Tucson, Arizona. It was formed in 1996 by Brad Lewellyn and Craig Leach but has since been</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012007">
		<snippet doc-id="81837" rsv="2319.00">The name Crystal Palace (coined by the satirical magazine Punch'') was later used to denote this area of south London and the park that surrounds the site, home of the Crystal Pala</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7630449" rsv="2167.00">For the open Low Level station, see Crystal Palace railway station. Crystal Palace (High Level) railway station was a station in the London Borough of Southwark in south London. Th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8000800" rsv="2145.00">New York Crystal Palace was an exhibition building constructed for the Exhibition of the Industry of All Nations in New York City in 1853. The New York Crystal Palace was crowned b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="538328" rsv="2118.00">Crystal Palace may refer to: </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10852310" rsv="2094.00">Idris "Alex" Ughiovhe (born 27 January, 1983 in Washington DC) is an American footballer currently playing for Crystal Palace Baltimore. He can play at right back, central defence </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13341799" rsv="2078.00">The Crystal Palace was an exhibition hall built for the Montreal Industrial Exhibition of 1860, originally located at the foot of Victoria Street between St. Catherine and Cathcart</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="93961" rsv="2076.00">Crystal Palace is a residential area in South London, England named from the erstwhile local landmark, The Crystal Palace, which occupied the area from 1854 to 1936. The palace was</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6883712" rsv="2058.00">The Crystal Palace and South London Junction Railway was built by the London, Chatham and Dover Railway to serve the Crystal Palace after it was moved to Crystal Palace from its or</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7900534" rsv="2053.00">The Glaspalast (Glass Palace) was a glass and iron exhibition building in Munich modeled after The Crystal Palace in London. The Erste Allgemeine Deutsche Industrieausstellung was </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="319983" rsv="1974.00">The former branch line terminus at Crystal Palace High Level railway station closed in 1954, and the remaining Crystal Palace railway station is situated some distance below Upper </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="103293" rsv="1944.00">The Great Exhibition, also known as Crystal Palace, was an international exhibition that was held in Hyde Park, London, England, from 1 May to 15 October 1851 and the first in a se</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7696093" rsv="1942.00">As of August 2007, Woozley worked in the Fire Service. Woozley was born in Berkshire and began his career as a trainee with Crystal Palace, turning professional in August 1997. He </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8680137" rsv="1927.00">Coordinates: 51°25′3″N 0°4′2″W﻿ / ﻿51.4175, -0.06722The Crystal Palace Dinosaurs, also known as Dinosaur Court,  are a series of sculptures of dinosaurs and extinct mammals located</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="94222" rsv="1825.00">In the Victorian era Penge developed into a fashionable suburb because of its proximity to the relocated Crystal Palace. By 1862 Stanford's map of Londonhttp://www.mappalondon.com/</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="95333" rsv="1822.00">Bromley is one of only five London Boroughs not to have at least one London Underground station within its boundaries, however this will change when the East London Line is extende</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19014712" rsv="1816.00">King's Field II is the second game in the King's Field RPG series. Like both its successors and predecessor, the game is played through first person view in a dark and mysterious, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15577871" rsv="1786.00">Main article: History of Crystal Palace F.C.Preceding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2006-07Succeeding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2008-09---- The 2007-08 season was C</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="816581" rsv="1785.00">The line was opened as a double-track branch of the West End of London and Crystal Palace Railway in 1858, but was closed from 1915 until reopened on March 2 1930 as part of the So</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1091585" rsv="1773.00">Fuller was born  in Kingston, Jamaica and began his career with Tivoli Gardens before moving to English club Crystal Palace in February 2001 for £1million, after impressing on tria</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18243235" rsv="1772.00">Main article: History of Crystal Palace F.C.Preceding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2007-08Succeeding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2009-10---- The 2008-09 season will </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012008">
		<snippet doc-id="4191796" rsv="1889.00">It lies within the city limits of Dunedin. Nearby are important breeding habitats of the threatened yellow-eyed penguin. Pilots Beach is managed as a Recreation reserve by the Dune</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="62049" rsv="1842.00">The Main North Line from Picton to Christchurch and the Main South Line from Lyttelton to Invercargill via Dunedin together comprise the South Island Main Trunk Railway. Commuter t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="567412" rsv="1832.00">The Yellow-eyed Penguin (Megadyptes antipodes) or HoiHo is a penguin native to New Zealand. Previously thought closely related to the Little Penguin (Eudyptula minor), molecular re</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="628345" rsv="1821.00">For other uses, see Dunedin (disambiguation). Between 1881 and 1957, Dunedin was home to cable trams, being both one of the first and last such systems in the world. To the east, D</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="106354" rsv="1799.00">A colony of little blue penguins lives on the harbour, and a colony of yellow-eyed penguins just south of the town attracts ecotourists. Penguins sometimes live under buildings clo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7539625" rsv="1771.00">Waitati is a small seaside settlement in Otago, New Zealand, within the city limits of Dunedin. It is located close to the tidal mudflats of Blueskin Bay, 19 kilometres north of th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7449877" rsv="1761.00">Born at Marton, New Zealand and educated at Wanganui, he became a teacher based in Dunedin after obtaining a diploma in 1922 from Hawkesbury Agricultural College near Sydney, Austr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8103636" rsv="1761.00">Squirt is a New Zealand children's television show, produced in Dunedin. It had been aired since 1996 and on two different TV networks, coming to a close on the 25 November, 2006. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7851400" rsv="1740.00">The arrived at the new settlement of Dunedin on 15 April 1848. He presided over the setting up of the Synod of Otago and Southland in 1866, and established the presbyteries of Dune</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19197944" rsv="1731.00">In recent years the dunes have been subject to severe erosion, and measures have been taken by the Dunedin City Council to reinforce them. This is not the first time that erosion h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1078914" rsv="1717.00">The settlement of Otakou lies within the boundaries of the city of Dunedin, New Zealand. It is located 25 kilometres from the city centre at the eastern end of Otago Peninsula, clo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="548507" rsv="1709.00">A significant area at the head of the harbour has been reclaimed since the founding of Dunedin, primarily for industrial use. The existence of the harbour was guessed by Captain Co</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5878270" rsv="1705.00">Central Dunedin was still occupied about 1785 but was abandoned before 1826. In the 1980s, these trends were paralleled by a burgeoning popular music scene which made Dunedin and i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17155154" rsv="1691.00">Dunedin Public Libraries is a network of five libraries and two bookbuses in Dunedin, New Zealand, owned and operated by the Dunedin City Council. With local authority amalgamation</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7688435" rsv="1686.00">A series of four 15minute programmes called Hidden Places and which featured various New Zealand habitats, notably Okarito, White Island and near-to Dunedin – Sinclair Wetlands, fi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1012608" rsv="1667.00">Hone Tuwhare (21 October 1922 – 16 January 2008) was a noted New Zealand poet of Māori ancestry. He is closely associated with The Catlins in the Otago region of New Zealand, where</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5884581" rsv="1656.00">Marples' Penguin (Palaeeudyptes marplesi) was a large species of the extinct penguin genus Palaeeudyptes. It stood between 105 and 145 cm high in life, larger than the present Empe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5852167" rsv="1638.00">They were probably larger than almost all living penguins, with the smaller species being about the size of an Emperor Penguin and the largest ones having stood about 1.5 meters ta</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13836594" rsv="1633.00">Coordinates: 45°53′45.71″S 170°38′50.33″E﻿ / ﻿-45.8960306, 170.6473139 Sandfly Bay is a sandy bay with large dunes, located on the eastern side of the Otago Peninsula, New Zealand,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="168194" rsv="1632.00">In 1943 Frame began training as a teacher at the Dunedin College of Education, while at the same time auditing courses in English, French and psychology at the adjacent University </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012009">
		<snippet doc-id="13160" rsv="2893.00">The gelatin obtained from acid treated raw material has been called type-A gelatin, and the gelatin obtained from alkali treated raw material is referred to as type-B gelatin. No B</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="320594" rsv="2639.00">There are some Gummi Bears made with pectin or starch instead of gelatin, making them suitable for vegans. Prions are misshapen proteins that cause BSE / Mad Cow Disease in cattle </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18835733" rsv="2364.00">On July 5, 1999 David Osborne Hagger appeared by Statement 476 before the BSE Inquiry. On July 5, 1999 David Hagger appeared by Statement 476 before the inquiry into Bovine spongif</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19344418" rsv="2124.00">BSE is a type of transmissible spongiform encephalopathy (TSE). The finding of a second strain of BSE prion raises the possibility that transmission of BSE to humans has been under</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6058" rsv="1948.00">If collagen is partially hydrolyzed, the three tropocollagen strands separate into globular, random coils, producing gelatin, which is used in many foods, including flavoured gelat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8612989" rsv="1798.00">Nectar Lifesciences Limited is an integrated pharmaceutical company in India that manufactures generic products. The company was promoted by Sanjiv Goyal and incorporated in June 1</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16273260" rsv="1716.00">This is a list of companies listed on the Barbados Stock Exchange. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="491715" rsv="1663.00">The BSE SENSEX (SENSitive indEX), also called the "BSE 30", is a widely used market index in India and Asia. Main article: BSE SensexThe BSE SENSEX (also known as the BSE 30 index)</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13162" rsv="1660.00">The most common culinary use for gelatin is as a main ingredient in varieties of gelatin desserts. Agar, a vegetable product made from seaweed, is used especially in quick jelly po</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="586066" rsv="1656.00">Ballistic gelatin is a solution of gelatin powder in water. Ballistic gelatin is used rather than actual muscle tissue due to the ability to carefully control the properties of the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17482804" rsv="1648.00">BSE Pro (Formerly Blood Sweat and Ears) (or BSE Wrestling) is a Canadian independent professional wrestling organization, founded in 2005. BSE event results and rankings can be fou</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9848049" rsv="1645.00">The Beirut Stock Exchange (or BSE) is the principal stock exchange of Lebanon. The BSE authorizes Brokerage firms the operation and trade in securities listed on the BSE according </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2114707" rsv="1632.00">The Budapest Stock Exchange (BSE) was re-opened in 1990 with headquarters in Budapest, Hungary. The derivatives market of the BSE in futures and options contracts has been availabl</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="441549" rsv="1614.00">A similar method of self-examination is known as the Seven P's of BSE: Older, menopausal women should do BSE once a month, perhaps on the first or last day of every month. About ei</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6946102" rsv="1614.00">Animal based ingredients (other than milk and honey) such as lard, gelatin and meat stock are not used in the traditional cuisine. The definition of vegetarianism throughout Europe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12195660" rsv="1614.00">John Mark Purdey (December 25 1953 – November 12 2006) was a British organic farmer who came to public attention in the 1980s, when he began to investigate the causes of bovine spo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="169365" rsv="1588.00">Commonly used stock market indices include: Large companies not ordered by any nation or type of business (in alphabetical order). Regional indexes covering Europe </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11184911" rsv="1582.00">In Silver-gelatin photography, the emulsion consists of silver halide crystals suspended in gelatin, and the substrate may be glass, plastic film, paper or fabric. Other polymer ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16585" rsv="1578.00">The brand's popularity has led to its becoming a generic term for gelatin dessert across the US and Canada. The powder contains powdered gelatin and flavorings including sugar or a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="971278" rsv="1570.00">Aspic is a dish in which ingredients are set into a gelatine made from  a meat stock or consommé. When cooled, stock made from meat congeals because of the natural gelatin found in</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012010">
		<snippet doc-id="300215" rsv="2228.00">A thesis or dissertation committee is a committee that supervises a student's dissertation. In France, the academic dissertation or thesis is called a thèse while the word disserta</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8775" rsv="1971.00">In many countries a candidate must defend this work before a panel of expert examiners appointed by the university; in other countries, the dissertation is examined by a panel of e</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11041456" rsv="1943.00">(William) D'Arcy McNickle (1904–1977) was a writer, Native American activist and anthropologist. D’Arcy McNickle, an enrolled Salish Kootenai on the Flathead Reservation, became on</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6274827" rsv="1927.00">Einstein also showed Kleiner his first PhD thesis dissertation in November 1901. However, Einstein withdrew his dissertation in February 1902. Indeed, a letter to Besso contains so</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14274604" rsv="1920.00">Naval Air Station (NAS) Banana River was a United States Naval Base in Satellite Beach, Florida. NAS Banana River was transferred to the United States Air Force on September 1, 194</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2449405" rsv="1874.00">Thesis can mean: A formal academic work, also known as a dissertation. The thesis statement (central argument) of a dissertation, essay, or other argumentative work. Lancia Thesis,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18813064" rsv="1863.00">Herma (Greek for bond or foundation, and germ or embryo) is a piece for solo piano composed by Iannis Xenakis in 1961. It is based on a formulation of the algebraic equations of Bo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2297173" rsv="1838.00">The M.Phil. is considered more difficult and prestigious, as it requires both a lengthy thesis as well as more examinations. Even when the student and supervisor agree that a stude</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="859106" rsv="1792.00">Mauro Giuseppe Sergio Pantaleo Giuliani (July 27, 1781 – May 8, 1829) was an Italian guitarist and composer, and is considered by many to be one of the leading guitar virtuosos of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4263768" rsv="1790.00">Zapotec language(s) describes a group of closely-related indigenous Mesoamerican languages spoken by the Zapotec people from Mexico's southwestern-central highlands region. Present</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="346628" rsv="1763.00">Original research experience is often a significant component of graduate studies, including the writing and defense of a thesis or dissertation. Ph.D. candidates undertaking resea</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="977277" rsv="1747.00">In Argentina, the Licentiate degree (Castilian: Licenciatura) is a 4-5 year degree (6 years in some cases under the accomplishment of the licentia doctorandi thesis dissertation), </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1707089" rsv="1704.00">Kate L. Turabian (February 26, 1893–October 25, 1987) is best known for her book A Manual for Writers of Research Papers, Theses, and Dissertations, now in its seventh edition. Tur</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="519705" rsv="1702.00">His thesis "Bahn des Cometen 1880 III" was published in Astronomische Nachrichten No. 2510. The obtained results he submitted to the Faculty of Physics and Mathematics of the Unive</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13165225" rsv="1691.00">Kimberly K. Little is an American historian. She is marriad to the historian Scott Beekman. Scott Beekman </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="400504" rsv="1686.00">A typical 3-year (Full Time) PhD in the United Kingdom usually requires the submission of a maximum 80,000 word thesis; the entire study period would be spent researching the topic</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="188886" rsv="1671.00">Research doctorates are awarded in recognition of both mastery of research methods (as evidenced in class grades and a comprehensive examination) and academic research that is idea</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11832225" rsv="1668.00">Hayward's M.A. thesis was opposed even before it was completed. Dr. Orange, who both supervised and assessed the dissertation, summarised its conclusion in the words "Hayward’s the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1780292" rsv="1662.00">Hovind's use of the title "Doctor" in particular has provoked extensive scrutiny of his education credentials and his dissertation. However, Patriot will not supply copies of Hovin</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9596400" rsv="1643.00">For the scientific document, see dissertation. The Dissertation http://www.amazon.com/dp/0393306488 is a novel by R.M. Koster, part of the Tinieblas trilogy. The book is a mock-PhD</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012011">
		<snippet doc-id="878533" rsv="2584.00">Text can be searched using regular expressions to match subpatterns and recombine the matched substrings in any order, such as reversing dates "May nn" as ("nn May"). The search an</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14885631" rsv="2492.00">The following is a list of software applications that use regular expressions. In some cases, only later versions of the applications use regular expressions. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="25717" rsv="2485.00">Regular expressions (abbreviated as regex or regexp, with plural forms regexes, regexps, or regexen) are written in a formal language that can be interpreted by a regular expressio</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="261964" rsv="2470.00">The command interpreter may be independently run in a text-only mode similarly to ed, from a command line terminal; however, running samterm allows use of a Graphical User Interfac</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="46642" rsv="2311.00">Although grep is not strictly an acronym, the letters are taken from global / regular expression / print, a series of instructions for the ed text editor. For simplicity, these exa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16308759" rsv="2293.00">Consequently, UNA supports all the standard features of programmer editors, including syntax highlighting, regular expression search and replace, file templates, source snippets, a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="24521" rsv="2281.00">Pico is a text editor for Unix and Unix-based computer systems. From the Pine FAQ: "Pine's message composition editor is also available as a separate stand-alone program, called PI</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16260046" rsv="2265.00">ne (for "nice editor") is a console text editor for POSIX computer operating systems such as Linux or Mac OS X. It uses termcap library, or a library such as ncurses which provides</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8233895" rsv="2223.00">TSE features a very capable macro language (SemWare ApplicationLanguage or SAL), regular expression search and replace, keystroke recording and playback, full Undo/Redo, shortcut k</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1038167" rsv="2196.00">vile is a text editor that attempts to combine the best aspects of the popular Emacs and vi editors. These editors are traditionally located on opposing sides of the editor wars, a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9771" rsv="2170.00">ed is the standard text editor on the Unix operating system.  ed was originally written by Ken Thompson and contains one of the first implementations of regular expressions. Prior </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1329953" rsv="2142.00">Notepad++ is a free source code editor for Windows. This project, based on the Scintilla editor component, is written in C++ with pure Win32 API calls and uses STL. The aim of Note</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10817747" rsv="2102.00">Thompson had developed the CTSS version of the editor QED, which included regular expressions for searching text. QED and Thompson's later editor ed (the default editor on Unix) co</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="279688" rsv="2099.00">Sequence (or specifically text string) patterns are often described using regular expressions (i.e. backtracking) and matched using respective algorithms. For simplicity and effici</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="27163" rsv="2098.00">For other uses, see Sed (disambiguation). sed  (Stream EDitor) refers to a Unix utility which (a) parses text files and (b) implements a programming language which can apply textua</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1524877" rsv="2039.00">This article provides a basic feature comparison for several text editors. Additional feature details are available from the Text editor features|Category of text editor features a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="32494" rsv="2026.00">vi is a screen-oriented text editor written by Bill Joy in 1976 for an early BSD release. Any text typed thence gets added to the document, until the escape key is pressed, at whic</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="929837" rsv="2025.00">UltraEdit is a commercial text editor for Microsoft Windows created in 1994 by Ian D. Mead. The editor contains tools for programmers, including macros, configurable syntax highlig</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3750893" rsv="2023.00">For the role in the Christian Church, see Deacon. Diakonos is a customizable, usable curses-based (console-based, or text-based) text editor. It was developed with the intention of</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1635937" rsv="2017.00">TextWrangler is a popular text editor for Mac OS X from Bare Bones Software. It was originally a commercial product, but (beginning with version 2.0) has become the freeware altern</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012012">
		<snippet doc-id="2047900" rsv="2595.00">This article is about the Seinfeld episode. When David came up with using the idea for an episode of Seinfeld, he did not talk about it with Seinfeld for a considerable time, becau</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5186697" rsv="2450.00">"The Masseuse" is the seventy-third episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. This was the 9th episode for the 5th season. It aired on November 18, 1993. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5186845" rsv="2272.00">"The Beard" is the 102nd episode of the hit NBC situation comedy Seinfeld. This was the 16th episode for the 6th season. Jerry takes the lie detector test, but quickly cracks under</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="28606" rsv="2248.00">The show within the show, titled Jerry  was much like Seinfeld, in which Seinfeld played himself, and that the show was "about nothing". Main article: The Finale (Seinfeld episode)</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5270278" rsv="2143.00">"Male Unbonding" is the second episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld to be produced, and aired on June 14, 1990 as the fourth episode of the first season. This is the only Seinfeld ep</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3535188" rsv="2133.00">"The Stake Out" is the second episode of the first season of the NBC comedy Seinfeld. Although it was the third episode to be filmed (after "The Seinfeld Chronicles" and "Male Unbo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1924820" rsv="2123.00">"The Seinfeld Chronicles" (also known as "Good News, Bad News" for syndication) is the pilot episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. The pilot, the first of the 180 Seinfeld episodes, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2104807" rsv="2111.00">"The Robbery" is the third episode of the first season of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. It was written by Matt Goldman, therefore making this the first Seinfeld episode not written by t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15507805" rsv="2109.00">"SeinfeldVision" is the first episode of the second season of 30 Rock and the twenty-second episode of the series. Seinfeld wore a wig in the episode to make him look more like the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1765947" rsv="2104.00">"The Bart Wants What it Wants" is the eleventh episode of The Simpsons' thirteenth season. The episode aired on February 17, 2002. The episode opens with a car/helicopter chase. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7728211" rsv="2082.00">All seasons of Seinfeld have been released on DVD by Sony Pictures Home Entertainment. Unlike some other 1990s sitcom DVD releases, they contain quite comprehensive extras, includi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072787" rsv="2074.00">"The Stock Tip" is the fifth episode of the first season of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. This episode contains the first Seinfeld reference to Superman, which would be a recurring feat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7880167" rsv="2070.00">Season one of Seinfeld, an American television series created by Jerry Seinfeld and Larry David, originally aired  its pilot episode on July 5, 1989 as The Seinfeld Chronicles on N</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5186927" rsv="2066.00">"The Soup Nazi" is the title of the 116th episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld, which was the 6th episode of the 7th season. The first reference to the character (though not by name)</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072861" rsv="2057.00">For the Virgin Comics series now becoming a Sci-Fi Channel pilot, see The Stranded (comic)."The Stranded" is the twenty-seventh episode of the hit sitcom Seinfeld. The episode was </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072895" rsv="2055.00">"The Boyfriend" is a two part episode of the sitcom Seinfeld. The episode was the 35th and 36th episode for the show, and 18th and 19th episode for the show's third season. It aire</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="104492" rsv="2052.00">About his influences, Seinfeld, in his commentary for "The Gymnast" episode on "Seinfeld, Season 6," said, "He really formed my entire comedic sensibility--I learned how to do come</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072796" rsv="2047.00">"The Pony Remark" is the seventh episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. The episode was the second episode for the show's second season. It aired on January 30, 1991. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072792" rsv="2044.00">"The Ex-Girlfriend" is the sixth episode of Seinfeld. The episode was the first episode for the show's second season. The famed premise of Seinfeld is, of course, a "show about not</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072820" rsv="2044.00">"The Baby Shower" is the fifteenth episode of Seinfeld. The episode was the tenth episode for the show's second season. The episode was the first episode written by Larry Charles, </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012013">
		<snippet doc-id="8707733" rsv="2095.00">The following list of biogeographic provinces was developed by Miklos Udvardy in 1975. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8628301" rsv="1919.00">This is the 2006 archive of Geography portal selected pictures. ----__NOTOC__ ---- </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1003579" rsv="1916.00">The continent of Africa can be conceptually subdivided into a number of regions or subregions. One common approach categorises Africa directionally, e.g., by cardinal direction (co</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4558169" rsv="1871.00">Horrible Geography is a series of books which is a spin-off of the Horrible Histories series written by Anita Ganeri, illustrated by Mike Phillips, and published in the UK by Schol</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12914725" rsv="1820.00">A considerable area of Colombia is mountainous, mainly crossed by the Andes mountain range from south to north. In the case of the Guajira Peninsula plains, the trade winds are una</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="66577" rsv="1770.00">There are also places in the tropics which are desert, with extreme heat, such as the Sahara Desert and Australian Outback. Tropical ecosystems may consist of rainforests, dry deci</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="142824" rsv="1741.00">Main article: Indigenous AustraliansThis List of Indigenous Australian group names contains names and collective designations which have been applied, either formerly or in the pas</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="23237" rsv="1737.00">The vastness of the country and the barrenness of the western hinterland have important implications for defense strategy. Inland drainage involving a number of upland basins in th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5244370" rsv="1729.00">East of the Andes in Peru is what is regarded as the most important biodiversity hotspot in the world with its unique forests that form the western edge of the world's largest rain</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="203115" rsv="1711.00">Tropical and subtropical moist broadleaf forests (TSMF), also known as tropical moist forests, are a tropical and subtropical forest biome. Tropical and subtropical forest regions </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1707053" rsv="1696.00">Institutional and policy factors included formal pro-deforestation policies on land development (40%), economic growth including colonization and infrastructure improvement (34%), </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9336" rsv="1685.00">Ecuador is a country in western South America, bordering the Pacific Ocean at the Equator, for which the country is named.Ecuador encompasses a wide range of natural formations and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="636058" rsv="1659.00">It features the largest cat complex in North America; "Kingdoms of the Night" is the world's largest nocturnal exhibit and indoor swamp; the Lied Jungle is the world's largest indo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1268246" rsv="1656.00">AtlanticOceanPacificOceanNorth RegionNortheast RegionCentral-West RegionSoutheast RegionSouth RegionAcreAmazonasParáRoraimaAmapáRondôniaTocantinsMaranhãoBahiaPiauíCearáRio Grandedo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18759220" rsv="1653.00">Population: 13,927,650 Land Area: 283,560 km2Capital: QuitoCurrency: US dollar (USD)Latitude / Longitude: 2 00 77 30 WGDP (PPP) per capita: $ 17,200 Founded:     26 th July 1979 Ar</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8174361" rsv="1651.00">Phelsuma malamakibo is a terrestrial species that inhabits the evergreen rainforests, montane grassland, and heathland of Southern Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/sys</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="45394" rsv="1648.00">It is sometimes used as a synonym for the tropical area of South America, although the ecozone also includes temperate southern South America. The Neotropic includes more tropical </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="903" rsv="1641.00">In geography, arable land (from Latin arare, to plough) is an agricultural term, meaning land that can be used for growing crops. Even if the land is over-farmed and all the nutrie</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="48139" rsv="1640.00">The area, also known as Amazonia, the Amazon jungle, or the Amazon Basin, encompasses seven million square kilometers (1.7 billion acres), though the forest itself occupies some 5.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18725460" rsv="1630.00">The percentages of foreign tourists arrivals by land, air and sea were, respectively, 55.3%, 40.5% and 4.2% for that year. On the top of that is the magical Easter Island. Inland f</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012014">
		<snippet doc-id="939380" rsv="3782.00">Main article: LuigiLuigi (ルイージ, Ruīji?) is a video game character created by Nintendo game designer Shigeru Miyamoto. In most games of the main series, Luigi is playable, occasiona</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="399418" rsv="3660.00">Mario &amp;amp; Luigi: Superstar Saga, known in Japan as Mario &amp;amp; Luigi RPG (マリオ＆ルイージRPG, Mario ando Ruīji Ārupījī), is a role-playing game developed by AlphaDream and published by </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81345" rsv="3643.00">Miyamoto had been inspired by the game Joust to create a game with a simultaneous two-player mode, which lead to his development of the game Mario Bros. in 1983 with the inclusion </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="153434" rsv="3438.00">Mario Golf is a sports video game series that was developed by Camelot Software Planning and published by Nintendo. It began on the Nintendo 64 with two games, one for the N64 and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2257659" rsv="3427.00">This is a list of games that Mario has appeared in, or games with other Mario characters, organized by system. Over the years, Mario and his brother Luigi have appeared in several </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81341" rsv="3423.00">Toad plays a rather minimal role in the original Super Mario Bros. He appears at the end of every fourth stage after Mario or Luigi defeats Bowser. But our princess is in a another</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="100061" rsv="3382.00">In , which was the first game in the Wario series for the Nintendo DS, Wario is walking down the street after having stolen a Game Boy Advance and Game Boy Advance SP, but trips an</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3624315" rsv="3295.00">Mario Golf (マリオゴルフ64, Mario Gorufu 64, Mario Golf 64) is a sports game developed by Camelot Software Planning and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo 64 in 1999. Additionally, d</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81118" rsv="3295.00">Luigi's Mansion (ルイージマンション, Ruīji Manshon) is an action-adventure game developed by Nintendo Entertainment Analysis and Development and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo GameC</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="88528" rsv="3285.00">The game was initially called Super Mario RPG 2, and was first revealed at Nintendo Space World '97, a video game trade show hosted by Nintendo. The game has often been compared to</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="100062" rsv="3269.00">Super Mario 64 (スーパーマリオ64, Sūpā Mario Rokujūyon) is a platform game developed by Nintendo Entertainment Analysis and Development and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo 64. Info</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2323682" rsv="3260.00">Other types of Goombas have appeared throughout the Mario series, although these largely vary from game to game. Goombas made their first playable appearance in Mario Superstar Bas</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="389840" rsv="3240.00">Mario Kart: Double Dash!! is a racing game developed by Nintendo Entertainment Analysis and Development and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo GameCube. Nintendo Power gave the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5249586" rsv="3212.00">Since then, five role-playing games have followed: Paper Mario for the Nintendo 64,  for the Game Boy Advance,  for the Nintendo GameCube,  for the Nintendo DS, and Super Paper Mar</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1902485" rsv="3208.00">Mario &amp;amp; Luigi: Partners in Time, known in Japan as Mario &amp;amp; Luigi RPG 2 (マリオ&amp;amp;ルイージRPG2, Mario ando Ruīji Ārupījī Tsū), is a console role-playing game developed by AlphaDr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1933408" rsv="3192.00">This article is a chronological list of Mario games. :Further information: List of Mario games by system and List of Mario games by genre Iconic Nintendo character Mario has appear</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81361" rsv="3178.00">Mario later appeared with his brother Luigi in another arcade game titled Mario Bros. When the Nintendo Entertainment System was released, Super Mario Bros. was the launch title fo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81435" rsv="3171.00">Super Princess Peach marked the second time that Princess Peach was cast as the main hero in a video game, as Princess Peach had to save Mario and Luigi from King Bowser. Finally, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1394585" rsv="3155.00">He also voices Luigi, Wario, Waluigi, Toadsworth, and a select few other characters, all from the same series. Working for Nintendo since 1987, Martinet started voicing Mario at vi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1577869" rsv="3142.00">Adventure mode has platforming segments similar to the original's "Race to the Finish" mini-game, and All-Star is a fight against every playable character in the game, allows the p</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012015">
		<snippet doc-id="13725692" rsv="2809.00">Example of widely used contactless smart cards are Hong Kong's Octopus card, Paris' Calypso_%28RFID%29/Navigo  and Lisbon' LisboaViva card, which predate the ISO/IEC 14443 standard</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1416441" rsv="2747.00">Tcard (formally Integrated ticketing system) is the name of the contactless smartcard ticketing system that is planned to be introduced on public transport in Sydney, New South Wal</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11582958" rsv="2708.00">Hong Kong was completed in September 1997 and remains the largest transit smart card project in the world with over over 14 million transactions per day. Stockholm - In April 2003,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="59957" rsv="2560.00">A smart card, chip card, or integrated circuit card (ICC), is any pocket-sized card with embedded integrated circuits which can process data. Contact smart card readers are used as</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17171065" rsv="2548.00">OPUS is the name of a rechargeable contactless stored value smart card which is being gradually introduced in most of the  public transit systems in the Canadian province of Quebec</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10088295" rsv="2501.00">LuLuCa (ルルカ, LuLuCa) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Shizuoka, Japan, introduced by Shizuoka Railway (Shizutetsu) group, from Marc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="397763" rsv="2466.00">The technology is a simple extension of the ISO 14443 proximity-card standard (contactless card, RFID) that combines the interface of a smartcard and a reader into a single device.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2774698" rsv="2448.00">See Gemalto for current company information.Axalto was a smart card manufacturer with over 4,500 employees in 60 countries, one of the world's leading providers of microprocessor c</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="966955" rsv="2431.00">The EZ-Link card is a contactless smartcard based on Sony's FeliCa smartcard technology, used for payments in Singapore especially for transportation in Singapore . The card is com</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5730712" rsv="2413.00">PiTaPa (ピタパ, Pitapa) is a contactless smart card ticketing and electronic money system used in the Kansai region (and may also be used in some areas of Okayama Prefecture, Hiroshim</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="267624" rsv="2410.00">The Octopus card is a rechargeable contactless stored value smart card used to transfer electronic payments in online or offline systems in Hong Kong. Launched in September 1997 to</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6880789" rsv="2407.00">myki (pronounced IPA: ) is the name of the contactless smartcard ticketing system to be introduced on public transport in Victoria, Australia. myki is designed to replace a number </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16886727" rsv="2362.00">Hayakaken (はやかけん, Hayakaken) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Fukuoka, Fukuoka Prefecture, Japan. Fukuoka City Transportation Burea</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16742549" rsv="2324.00">SAPICA (サピカ, Sapika) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Sapporo, Japan. The integrated service with Kitaca, a smart card system to be</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13983074" rsv="2306.00">SUGOCA (スゴカ, Sugoka) is a Japanese rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Fukuoka Prefecture and the surrounding areas. The name is an acronym</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10088292" rsv="2296.00">RapiCa (ラピカ, Rapika) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Kagoshima, Japan, introduced by Kagoshima City Transportation Bureau, Nangoku</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5027747" rsv="2295.00">This article is about the smart card ticket system. Pasmo (パスモ, Pasumo) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport introduced in Tokyo, Japan fr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12501708" rsv="2283.00">nimoca (ニモカ, Nimoka) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Fukuoka Prefecture, Japan. Its name is an acronym of "nice money card", while</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2157976" rsv="2280.00">T-money is a rechargeable series of cards and other "smart" devices used for paying transportation fares in and around Seoul and other areas of South Korea. Similar to its predeces</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12501709" rsv="2277.00">Kitaca (キタカ, Kitaka) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Sapporo, Japan. Its name means "the card of north (北, kita)", while 北 is also</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012016">
		<snippet doc-id="6141751" rsv="3156.00">The Princess and the Frog will be a 2009 upcoming American musical feature film produced by Walt Disney Animation Studios and based upon the classic fairy tale The Frog Prince. Whe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="357220" rsv="3031.00">This is a list of theatrical animated feature films produced and/or released by Walt Disney Productions/The Walt Disney Company: The canon includes animated features that were or a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5138153" rsv="2973.00">Enchanted is a 2007 musical film, directed by Kevin Lima and produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation and released by Walt Disney Pictures. Similarly, film critics Richard Roeper </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2287636" rsv="2967.00">Sleeping Beauty is a 1959 animated feature produced by Walt Disney and originally released to theatres on January 29, 1959, by Buena Vista Distribution. The sixteenth animated feat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2690296" rsv="2940.00">Princess Jasmine (Arabic: الأميرة ياسمين) is a fictional Arabian princess who originally appeared in the 1992 Disney film, Aladdin, followed with its two direct-to-video sequels, T</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="76361" rsv="2925.00">It was the first full length animated feature to be produced by Walt Disney, and the first American animated feature film in movie history. The New York Times said "Thank you very </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="805496" rsv="2909.00">It was produced by Walt Disney Productions, and originally released to theatres on July 24, 1985 by Walt Disney Pictures and Buena Vista Distribution. Some CGI includes the realist</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="301574" rsv="2814.00">The Little Mermaid is a 1989 animated feature produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation with a pencil test beginning on September 23, 1988 and a first release on November 17, 1989 </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="492158" rsv="2801.00">Home on the Range is the 44th animated feature produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation and released by Walt Disney Pictures on April 2, 2004. The film is the forty-fifth animated</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="73170" rsv="2795.00">Aladdin is a 1992 animated feature produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, and released by Walt Disney Pictures on November 25, 1992. The thirty-first animated feature in the Di</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4744677" rsv="2791.00">Princess Ariel is a fictional character, a mermaid and the protagonist of Disney's 1989 animated film The Little Mermaid. Until Giselle of Disney's 2007 film Enchanted, she was the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4680612" rsv="2764.00">Mulan II is a Disney direct-to-video animated feature released in 2004 and a sequel to the 1998 animated film Mulan. The film deals with arranged marriages, loyalty, relationships,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7942401" rsv="2740.00">The Annie Award for Best Animated Feature is an Annie Award, awarded annually to the best animated feature film and introduced in 1992. In 1998 the award was renamed Outstanding Ac</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="133462" rsv="2724.00">It is the thirtieth animated feature produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation. It is the first and only full-length animated feature film to ever be nominated for an Academy Award</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1970335" rsv="2719.00">This is a list of notable theatrical feature films produced by Walt Disney Productions and its successor label, Walt Disney Pictures. If Walt Disney Productions did not produce the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="358684" rsv="2713.00">The Return of Jafar is a 1994 animated direct-to-video sequel to the 1992's Aladdin, produced by The Walt Disney Company. The movie was released on May 20, 1994 and serves as the o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="55720" rsv="2709.00">Mulan is a 1998 animated feature film produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, and released by Walt Disney Pictures on June 19, 1998. The thirty-sixth animated feature in the Dis</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3395527" rsv="2703.00">Mickey's Magical Christmas: Snowed in at the House of Mouse is the first direct-to-video movie spin off from the Disney Channel animated television series House of Mouse. A snowsto</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11353299" rsv="2701.00">Disney Princess Enchanted Tales: Follow Your Dreams is a direct-to-video animated feature produced by DisneyToon Studios. It is the first film in the new Disney Princess Enchanted </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="399402" rsv="2684.00">The twelfth animated feature in the Disney animated features canon, the film was directed by Clyde Geronimi, Hamilton Luske and Wilfred Jackson, based the fairy tale "Cinderella" b</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012017">
		<snippet doc-id="7620833" rsv="3811.00">The Optimal Diet (or Optimal Nutrition) is a high fat, low carbohydrate diet developed by Polish doctor Jan Kwasniewski. He believes that a high carbohydrate/low fat diet, such as </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="791546" rsv="3753.00">The "classic" ketogenic diet contains a 4:1 ratio by weight of fat to combined protein and carbohydrate. Wilder's colleague, paediatrician Mynie Peterman, later formulated the "cla</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="437978" rsv="3706.00">It advocates consuming calories from carbohydrates, protein and fat in a ratio of 40%/30%/30%. Sears emphasizes a hormonal paradox contrary to the "low-fat" rationale, namely that </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4330820" rsv="3421.00">The Gross Energy of a food, as measured by bomb calorimetry is equal to the sum of the heats of combustion of the components - protein (GEp), fat (GEf) and carbohydrate (GEcho) (by</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4297420" rsv="3339.00">The range of respiratory coefficients for organisms in metabolic balance usually ranges from 1.0 (representing the value expected for pure carbohydrate oxidation) to ~0.7 (the valu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="459560" rsv="3245.00">For example, contrary to popular belief that low-carbohydrate diets damage the heart, one study found that women eating low-carbohydrate, high-fat/protein diets had the same or sli</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8095528" rsv="3215.00">However, some protein and fat-rich foods (eggs, beef, fish, lentils, cheese, cake, and doughnuts) induced as much insulin secretion as did some carbohydrate-rich foods (eg, beef wa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="264746" rsv="3146.00">Saturated fat is fat that consists of triglycerides containing only saturated fatty acids. There are several kinds of naturally occurring saturated fatty acids, their only differen</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="215509" rsv="3117.00">They recommend a diet high in protein (19–35% energy) and relatively low in carbohydrates (22–40% energy), with a fat intake (28–58% energy) similar to or higher than that found in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="562788" rsv="3086.00">Studies also showed that by eliminating the sex differences that occur with the accumulation of adipose tissue by expressing metabolic rate per unit of "fat-free" or lean body weig</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8460" rsv="3071.00">In this process, fats, obtained from adipose tissue, or fat cells, are broken down into glycerol and fatty acids, which can be used to make energy. The Nurses' Health Study, an obs</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="263487" rsv="3024.00">Trans fat is the common name for a type of unsaturated fat with trans-isomer fatty acid(s). The term trans fat generally refers to a fat that contains one or more trans fatty acid </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7371778" rsv="2993.00">For a more comprehensive list, see the List of nutrition topics. Nutrition or nutrition science studies the relationship between diet and states of health and disease. Main article</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5932" rsv="2985.00">If the carbonyl group is an aldehyde, the monosaccharide is an aldose; if the carbonyl group is a ketone, the monosaccharide is a ketose. The assignment of D or L is made according</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="84121" rsv="2982.00">Net carbohydrates can be calculated from a food source by subtracting fiber and sugar alcohols (which are shown to have a negligible effect on blood sugar levels) from total carboh</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12534814" rsv="2932.00">A no-carbohydrate diet (no-carb diet) is described as human carnivorism. It excludes dietary consumption of all carbohydrates and suggests fat as the main source of energy with suf</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="613420" rsv="2927.00">Microwaveable pork rinds are lower in fat than the deep-fried variety, with only 2 g of fat per 14 g serving and no saturated fat, although the sodium level may be as high as 350 m</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="66575" rsv="2902.00">A nutrient is food or chemicals that an organism needs to live and grow or a substance used in an organism's metabolism which must be taken in from its environment. Fat has an ener</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9503943" rsv="2885.00">Fat has 9 megacalories (38 MJ) per kilogram of energy, which is 2.25 times that of any carbohydrate source. Most adult horses only require 8 to 10% protein in their diet; however, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="305679" rsv="2875.00">Blood contains 95% water, body fat contains 14% water and bone has 22% water.The human body is about 60% in adult males and 55% in adult females. In individuals of normal weight, w</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012018">
		<snippet doc-id="286368" rsv="2094.00">For the Police Interceptor version used by law enforcement, see Ford Crown Victoria Police Interceptor. But while newer front-wheel drive platforms may have been popular among cons</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="523329" rsv="2060.00">These were followed in June 1958 by the company's first police vehicle; a Riley Pathfinder patrol car (209), finished in black and with a die cast police sign fitted to the roof co</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3399893" rsv="2037.00">A typical cruiser would be a young man who drives a modified car. Modifications can take many forms including bodykits and In Car Entertainment (ICE) as represented by the likes of</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="321651" rsv="2017.00">__TOC__Boy racer is now a New Zealand, British and Irish colloquial term for a person, usually a male in his late teens or early twenties, who drives his car in an intimidating or </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9092216" rsv="2004.00">Full-size Ford is the popular term for a long-running line of Ford vehicles which have been produced in North America with a large degree of similarity since the Model T in 1908, u</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1321710" rsv="1997.00">The phrase panda car refers to a small or medium-sized police car operated by British police forces. The boot lids, bonnets and doors were then swapped to create a panda car style </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="331097" rsv="1991.00">The Saab 9-5 is an executive car produced by the Swedish automobile maker Saab. The 9-5 replaced the 9000 in the spring of 1997 for the 1998 model year. By 2008 this engine was pro</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="897080" rsv="1985.00">According to Collectible Auto magazine, the car was described in Car Life’s review as "a big car in miniature" that was "fun to drive" and "ideal for a second car in the family," w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5037907" rsv="1952.00">From 1993–1998, the police car models of Crown Victorias were officially known as Crown Victoria P71s. The current major facelift of the car was introduced in 1998. As one of the f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3612161" rsv="1946.00">Since the termination of the Chevrolet Caprice product, most police departments currently use the Ford Crown Victoria Police Interceptor as the standard patrol car. There are many </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1297380" rsv="1946.00">A police car is the description for a vehicle used by police, to assist with their duties in patrolling and responding to incidents. Typical uses of a police car include transporta</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="644652" rsv="1945.00">"Headlines" is a segment on The Tonight Show with Jay Leno airing weekly. The segment usually airs on Monday, though at times it airs on Tuesday. It was first seen in 1987, when Ja</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="623020" rsv="1938.00">For the 2008 model year, an onboard computer, iPod connectivity with USB, heated mirrors, Q-citura stitching that originally could only be found on the Nera model, and a beige soft</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="996951" rsv="1923.00">Ford Fairlane briefly driven by Bond during his visit to Cuba in Die Another Day. As a punishment for failing to dispose of Bond, Lippe is killed in his Fairlane, which is blown up</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1475902" rsv="1918.00">The story deals with two would-be NASCAR hopefuls; the driver, Larry (Peter Fonda), and his mechanic, Deke (Adam Roarke), who successfully execute a supermarket heist to finance th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="725503" rsv="1910.00">Virgil Exner, Chrysler's chief stylist, designed a car that was smaller and lighter than a full-size car without sacrificing passenger and luggage space. The citation lauded Exner'</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2186972" rsv="1909.00">The Toronto Police is one of the English-speaking world’s oldest modern municipal police departments; older than, for example, the legendary New York City Police Department which w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11693386" rsv="1903.00">It replaced the Dynasty and Monaco as Dodge's largest car. In 2001, the Intrepid made its debut on the NASCAR circuit, signifying the return of Chrysler to NASCAR competition after</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18101227" rsv="1900.00">The Second-generation Ford Taurus is an automobile produced by the Ford Motor Company from 1992 to 1995, which served as the second out of six generations of the Ford Taurus. Main </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6179218" rsv="1897.00">Most popular in this category are 1:18 scale diecast automobile replicas. Typically, companies that produce model cars will have licensing arrangements with real car manufacturers </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012019">
		<snippet doc-id="66400" rsv="2530.00">The names for the chemical elements 104 to 109 were the subject of a major controversy  starting in the 1960s which was finally resolved in 1997. The controversy arose when multipl</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="311180" rsv="2345.00">Prout's hypothesis was an early 19th century attempt to explain the existence of the various chemical elements through a hypothesis regarding the internal structure of the atom. He</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="164644" rsv="2183.00">Albert Ghiorso (born 15 July 1915) is an American nuclear scientist who helped discover numerous chemical elements on the periodic table. He was born in Vallejo, California and gre</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8174364" rsv="2143.00">For Carbon-14 discoverer, see Sam Ruben. Ruben worked as a researcher from 1918-1921 for the Electrochemical Products Company. Samuel Ruben published multiple books, including a un</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5659" rsv="2139.00">The first modern list of chemical elements was given in Antoine Lavoisier's 1789 Elements of Chemistry, which contained thirty-three elements, including light and caloric. Put anot</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="104395" rsv="2121.00">He was taught chemistry by Anders Gustaf Ekeberg, the discoverer of tantalum. In order to aid his experiments, he developed a system of chemical notation in which the elements were</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1073114" rsv="2100.00">Gadolin discovered the chemical element yttrium. This thermochemical work was very precise. One of his latest studies was the chemical analysis of the Chinese alloy pak tong (alpac</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8200" rsv="2086.00">The discovery of the elements known to exist today is presented here in chronological order. The elements are listed generally in the order in which each was first defined as the p</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10777" rsv="2077.00">Friedrich Wöhler (31 July 1800 - 23 September 1882) was a German chemist, best-known for his synthesis of urea, but also the first to isolate several of the elements. Wöhler was al</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="191850" rsv="2073.00">Louis Nicolas Vauquelin (May 16, 1763 - November 14, 1829), was a French pharmacist and chemist. In 1791 he was made a member of the Academy of Sciences and from that time he helpe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1267459" rsv="2060.00">The institution was initially headed by Fausto Elhúyar (1755-1833), the discoverer of tungsten. Later the U.S. geologist George William Featherstonhaugh proposed without success th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="153260" rsv="2047.00">Friedrich Ernst Dorn (27 July 1848 – 16 December 1916) was a German physicist who was the first to discover that a radioactive substance, later named radon, is emitted from radium.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="191838" rsv="2045.00">Antoine Jérôme Balard (30 September 1802 - 30 April 1876) was a French chemist and the discoverer of bromine. Born at Montpellier, he started as an apothecary, but taking up teachi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="150986" rsv="2023.00">Charles Hatchett (2 January 1765 - 10 March 1847) was an English chemist who discovered the element niobium. Hatchett was born, raised, and lived in London. On 24 March 1787, he ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13120" rsv="2015.00">Seaborg developed the chemical elements americium and curium while in Chicago. He held more than 40 patents — among them the only patents ever issued for chemical elements, americi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="59483" rsv="2015.00">He was the discoverer of many chemical substances, most notably discovering oxygen (although Joseph Priestley published his findings first), molybdenum and chlorine before Humphry </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7562549" rsv="2013.00">The ACS National Historic Chemical Landmarks Program was launched by the American Chemical Society in 1992 and has recognized 60 landmarks to date. The project is part of the ACS D</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="62200" rsv="2008.00">On the periodic table of the elements, it is a p-block element and the last one of the 7th period. For example, although ununoctium is a member of the noble gas group, it could hav</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="21278" rsv="2008.00">+ 6 \,^{1}_{0}\mathrm{n}In 1969, the Dubna team carried out chemical experiments on element 102 and concluded that it behaved as the heavier homologue of Ytterbium. This is most de</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="352146" rsv="2006.00">He discovered the phenomenon of the electrochemical branching of the radioactive rows. Afterwards Fajans was working on the electrochemical properties of elements as a result of th</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012020">
		<snippet doc-id="16621051" rsv="2070.00">The NT$2,000 was initially the only banknote to feature a holographic strip, being the highest denomination banknote in public circulation. First introduced in 15 December 2000 for</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15313075" rsv="1981.00">The Estonian 100 Krooni bill (100 EEK) is a denomination of the Estonian currency. Lydia Koidula, who was an Estonian poetess and playwrigh (1843-1886), is featured on the front si</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12572331" rsv="1975.00">The face of the banknote has a portrait of writer Karen Blixen (17 April 1885 to 7 September 1962). The face of the banknote is also decorated with flowers, of which Karen Blixen w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15312026" rsv="1936.00">The Estonian 500 Krooni bill (500 EEK) is a denomination of the Estonian currency . Carl Robert Jakobson, who was an Estonian politician, publisher, writer and promoter of agricult</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1710548" rsv="1929.00">A more standardized approach is adopted across all banknote denominations, with features noticeably differing from all previous series. The note printing company no longer appears </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9738183" rsv="1888.00">In later years, the banknote received unexpected media attention when gay community started to send this banknote as a souvenir to foreign friends. It makes this banknote the only </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="208286" rsv="1863.00">A banknote (often known as a bill, paper money or simply a note) is a kind of negotiable instrument, a promissory note made by a bank payable to the bearer on demand, used as money</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="615913" rsv="1840.00">The EURion constellation is a pattern of symbols found on a number of banknote designs since about 1996. It is added to help software detect the presence of a banknote in a digital</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3671365" rsv="1780.00">A £5 note featuring Dunluce Castle on the obverse and a £1 note also featuring the Girona were issued by the Provincial Bank of Ireland and by AIB, but have not been issued by Firs</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="334169" rsv="1746.00">"From the sovereign of the land of the rising sun (nihon/hi izuru) to the sovereign of the land of the setting sun."There are historians who have concluded that Prince Shōtoku was </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15313964" rsv="1743.00">The Estonian 25 Krooni bill (25 EEK) is a denomination of the Estonian currency . Anton Hansen Tammsaare, who was a famous Estonian writer of classical literature (1870-1940), is f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="54072" rsv="1730.00">The euro banknote designs were chosen from 44 proposals in a design competition, launched by The Council of the European Monetary Institute (EMI) on 12 February 1996. Finally, the </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="596249" rsv="1692.00">The 10-peso banknote was issued months after the 5-piso banknote was issued. The 100-piso banknote is the smallest-valued banknote to have the new security features implemented in </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="477336" rsv="1668.00">U.S. President Andrew Jackson is currently featured on the front side of the bill, which is why the twenty-dollar bill is often called a "Jackson," while the White House is feature</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11933037" rsv="1668.00">For stamp collecting, see Philately. For coin collecting, see Numismatic terminology. This page is a glossary of notaphily. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1993277" rsv="1663.00">Saint Agnes of Bohemia (Czech: Svatá Anežka Česká), or Agnes of Prague (1211-March 6, 1282), was a medieval Bohemian princess who opted for a life of charity and piety over a life </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13261356" rsv="1661.00">Banknotes were issued in 1943 by the British Army for circulation in Tripolitania. The main feature of the notes is depiction of a lion standing on the King's Crown. The notes are </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2341370" rsv="1661.00">This is a list of current motifs on the banknotes of different countries. The customary design of banknotes in most countries is a portrait of a notable citizen on the front (or ob</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="383936" rsv="1645.00">The bolívar fuerte (plural: bolívares fuertes, ISO 4217 code: VEF; locally abbreviated as Bs. F) is the new currency of Venezuela since January 1, 2008. It is subdivided into 100 c</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1403932" rsv="1642.00">Trading as Securency, the RBA together with Innovia Films, market BOPP as 'Guardian' for countries with their own banknote printing facilities. An alternative polymer of polyethyle</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012021">
		<snippet doc-id="12196101" rsv="3555.00">Beyond Vaudeville was a public access television show on Time Warner Cable in New York City that ran from 1986 to 1996. The show eventually made the move to network TV as Oddville,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7195382" rsv="3323.00">Susan Griffiths is a TV actress and popular Marilyn Monroe look-alike. She has been a Marilyn Monroe impersonator in "Legends in Concert" (1991). Since introducing her talents Susa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9055591" rsv="3285.00">As one of the most iconic actresses of the 20th century, Marilyn Monroe is frequently depicted and referenced in popular culture. Artists who have used Monroe as a basis of their w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19318" rsv="2977.00">Main article: Childhood of Marilyn Monroe Monroe was born in the Los Angeles County Hospital,  the third child born to Gladys Pearl Monroe (1902-1984). Marilyn Monroe has finally p</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8731260" rsv="2853.00">Mark Bellinghaus (born July 20, 1963), is a Marilyn Monroe activist and a collector of Monroe memorabilia. In 1995 Bellinghaus emigrated to the United States to study acting at the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4608195" rsv="2823.00">Mixing slapstick, soul music and tearjerking elements, the plot involves a kidnapped James Brown impersonator, a plot to discredit the Japanese Prime Minister, an adulterous hotel </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18062558" rsv="2743.00">Strawhead is a 1982 play by American writer Norman Mailer and Richard G. Hannum about Hollywood icon Marilyn Monroe. In response to former Marilyn Monroe roommate and Academy Award</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="180417" rsv="2729.00">The Pierce Brothers Westwood Village Memorial Park Cemetery is located at 1218 Glendon Avenue in the Westwood Village area of Los Angeles, California. Indeed, when it was announced</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10018022" rsv="2661.00">The Next Best Thing: Who Is the Greatest Celebrity Impersonator? was an American reality TV series competition of celebrity impersonators with a grand prize of $100,000. The eight-</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="848349" rsv="2599.00">In one audition, she performed a rendition of Marilyn Monroe's famous "Happy Birthday, Mr. President", working on her previous experience as a Monroe impersonator at Warner Bros. M</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1957472" rsv="2580.00">The film featured Ashley Judd as Norma Jean Dougherty and Mira Sorvino as Marilyn Monroe. It was partially-based on "Norma Jean: My Secret Life With Marilyn Monroe" by actor Ted Jo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1228430" rsv="2541.00">In 1961, Dr. Ralph Greenson advised Marilyn Monroe, then living in an apartment on North Doheny Drive in Beverly Hills, to recruit Murray as a housekeeper/companion. Many days late</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4292152" rsv="2540.00">Marilyn Monroe was found dead in the bedroom of her Brentwood, California home by her live-in housekeeper Eunice Murray on August 5, 1962. The death of Marilyn Monroe is one of the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="554052" rsv="2534.00">Con O'Neill, who played Mickey, won the Laurence Olivier Award for Best Actor in 1989 (1988 season) his performance. The mother, Mrs. Johnstone pleads, "Tell me it's not true, say </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2181741" rsv="2534.00">The following year, she won the lead role in How to Be Very, Very Popular, a role that was initially rejected by Marilyn Monroe. Media attention over the choice of North in the rol</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="179091" rsv="2515.00">Despite its reputation as a masculine group, the Rat Pack did have female participants, including movie icons Shirley MacLaine, Lauren Bacall, Angie Dickinson, Marilyn Monroe, and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10553349" rsv="2512.00">Mister Lonely is a 2007 film directed by Harmony Korine, and co-written with his brother Avi Korine. During a show in an old people's home Michael Jackson meets Marilyn Monroe. Mor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14286866" rsv="2498.00">The first actual human beings to be digitally duplicated were Marilyn Monroe and Humphrey Bogart in a March 1987 film created by Daniel Thalmann and Nadia Magnenat-Thalmann for the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="76366" rsv="2479.00">Some Like It Hot is a 1959 comedy film directed by Billy Wilder and starring Marilyn Monroe, Tony Curtis, and Jack Lemmon. Joe and Jerry both fall for "Sugar Kane" (Monroe), the ba</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="468301" rsv="2462.00">Morton was born in Clifton Nottingham, England, the daughter of Pamela Freebury, a factory worker, and Peter Morton. Morton has a daughter, Esme (born in 2000), with actor Charlie </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012022">
		<snippet doc-id="618884" rsv="2672.00">Thermes de Cluny are an ancient Gallo-Roman ruin lying in the heart of Paris' 5th arrondissement and which are partly subsumed into the Musée de Moyen Age- Hôtel de Cluny. The best</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14358690" rsv="2492.00">In 123 B.C. the Romans founded Aix-en-Provence, and two years later began a new town at Nemausa (today Nimes.)  The Roman colony known as Provincia was organized in about 120 B.C. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2068003" rsv="2485.00">For Gaul before the Roman conquest, see Gaul.Roman Gaul consisted of an area of provincial rule in the Roman Empire, in modern day France, Belgium, Luxembourg, and western Germany.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2067852" rsv="2468.00">Dating to the first quarter of the first century AD, it originally stood in a temple in the Gallo-Roman civitas of Lutetia (modern Paris, France) and is one of the earliest pieces </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="618873" rsv="2400.00">Gallo-Roman language persisted in the northeast into the Silva Carbonaria that formed an effective cultural barrier with the Franks to the north and east, and in the northwest to t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2929895" rsv="2362.00">Gallo-Roman religion was a fusion of Roman religious forms and modes of worship with Gaulish deities from . In some cases, Gaulish deity names were used as epithets for Roman deiti</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2462183" rsv="2334.00">Around 250, one group of Franks, taking advantage of a weakened Roman Empire, penetrated as far as Tarragona in present-day Spain, plaguing this region for about a decade before Ro</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2691084" rsv="2320.00">The Arènes de Lutèce are among the most important remains from the Gallo-Roman era in Paris (formerly known as Lutèce in French or Lutetia in Latin), together with the Thermes de C</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1846758" rsv="2196.00">The most beautiful building in Verona and one of the most perfect in all Europe, the Palazzo del Consiglio, famous for the decorations of its loggia, was designed by Giocondo at th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2698471" rsv="2151.00">La Graufesenque is an archaeological site 2km from Millau, Aveyron, France at the junction of the Tarn and Dourbie rivers. As Condatomagus (market of the confluent) it was famous i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="203582" rsv="2125.00">Syagrius governed this Gallo-Roman enclave from the death of his father in 464 until 486, when whatever remained of Roman Gaul was overrun by the territorial expansion of the Frank</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2815281" rsv="2112.00">The antrustion was always of Frankish descent, and only in certain exceptional cases were Gallo-Romans admitted into the king's bodyguard. These Gallo-Romans then took the name of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="473019" rsv="2104.00">See also: History of ParisLutetia (sometimes Lutetia Parisiorum or Lucotecia, in French Lutèce) was a town in pre-Roman and Roman Gaul. The Gallo-Roman city was a forerunner of the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="36545" rsv="2099.00">Main articles: Roman Gaul and Gallo-Roman cultureThe Gaulish culture then was massively submerged by Roman culture, Latin was adopted by the Gauls, Gaul was absorbed into the Roman</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="353326" rsv="2081.00">The Musée de Cluny, officially known as Musée National du Moyen Âge, is a museum in Paris, France. The structure  is perhaps the most outstanding example still extant of civic arch</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="21724" rsv="2079.00">Classicists have knowledge of many Gallo-Roman villas in Normandy. Domestic architecture in upper Normandy is typified by half-timbered buildings that also recall vernacular Englis</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2508454" rsv="2069.00">In Ancient Roman architecture a cryptoporticus (from Latin crypta and porticus) is a covered corridor or passageway. The cryptoporticus of Reims, formerly enclosing three sides of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="263867" rsv="2048.00">It lies about 90 km north of Paris. Beauvais was known to the Romans as Bratuspantium (gaulish name) Caesaromagus (gallo-roman name)(though the post-Renaissance Latin rendering is </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1126654" rsv="1997.00">Many items of the Gallo-Roman period have been found locally, particularly coins (including 2 gold Gallic coins found in 1839). The archaeological diggings around the Ducal palace(</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="86038" rsv="1981.00">This article is about the goddess. She was later assimilated into the Gallo-Roman mythology of goddess Diana. However, Deyts notes that the bronze Gallo-Roman statue of a woman in </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012023">
		<snippet doc-id="2772917" rsv="2857.00">Flute repertory is the general term for pieces composed for flute (particularly Western concert flute) and often played by flutists (or flautists). The lists also do not generally </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2447312" rsv="2788.00">James Galway, the famous flute virtuoso, introduced him as being one of the best flutists of his respective generation. Evcil won many prizes and awards in various competitions, am</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18733165" rsv="2759.00">2005 "Crystal"for symphony orchestra :9` 2003\04 "Incoming" for symphony orchestra : 9` 1989 Concerto for solo trombone and symphony orchestra 17' </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="617767" rsv="2752.00">It was first performed in Moscow on 8 January 1972 by the All-Union Radio and Television Symphony Orchestra under Maxim Shostakovich. The movement opens with two chimes on the gloc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9773093" rsv="2682.00">Benjamin-Gunnar Cohrs gave his early conducting debut 1984 with the orchestra of the Youth Music School in Hameln, where he received his early musical education since 1972 (Flute, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8515261" rsv="2673.00">At 13 years old, he has written over 80 pieces of music, including piano solos and sonatas, piano concerto, string trios and quartets, music for Jazz band, concert band and full or</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15456860" rsv="2645.00">Miletić performed as a soloist with Leningrad Philharmonic Orchestra, Slovenian Philharmonic Orchestra, Radio Bratislava Symphonic Orchestra, and since 1946 he was an active violis</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="620890" rsv="2633.00">While his early work is strongly influenced by impressionism, he eventually found a personal style which was more formal in design, with a strong rhythmic drive, and with a more di</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4451623" rsv="2621.00">Thomas Oboe Lee was born in Beijing, China, in 1945. He performed as a jazz flutist with many illustrious Brazilian musicians, including the singer/song-writer Chico Buarque de Hol</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1872612" rsv="2615.00">Toshi Ichiyanagi (一柳 慧, Ichiyanagi Toshi,  born 4 February 1933, Kobe, Japan) is a Japanese composer of avant-garde music. One of his most notable works is the 1960 composition, Ka</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19193763" rsv="2610.00">The following is an incomplete listof works by the polish composer Krzysztof Penderecki. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="596925" rsv="2590.00">Ernst Toch (pronounced [toʜ]) (7 December 1887 - 1 October 1964) was a composer of classical music and film scores. In 1909, his chamber symphony in F major (written 1906) won the </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1816680" rsv="2573.00">His compositions include the four symphonic poems and three orchestral songs making up Livre de la jungle after Rudyard Kipling; many other symphonic poems including Le Buisson Ard</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1056463" rsv="2572.00">Eugène Joseph Bozza (April 4 1905 – September 28 1991) was a French composer. He is particularly noted for his wind writing, having composed pieces for nearly all of the winds and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16410974" rsv="2566.00">In 1952, Kalabis married Zuzana Růžičková, who became a famous harpsichord player. Symphonic music Flute </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7652632" rsv="2556.00">By age thirteen, he performed the Anton Rubinstein Piano Concerto No. 4 with the Oklahoma Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Sir Guy Fraser Harrison. In 1999 he was commissioned by J</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3896810" rsv="2547.00">This is a list of Mieczysław Weinberg's compositions by opus number. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1625597" rsv="2543.00">Dorff is currently composer-in-residence for the Haddonfield Symphony. His works have been commissioned by such ensembles as the Philadelphia Orchestra and the Minnesota Orchestra,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="141849" rsv="2540.00">Widor's best-known single piece for the organ is the final movement, Toccata, from his Symphony for Organ No. 5, which is often played as a recessional at wedding ceremonies and ev</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8146502" rsv="2533.00">He has performed and/or recorded as a featured soloist with the Orchestra dell'Accademia Nazionale di Santa Cecilia, L'Orchestre Symphonique Du Bal de Vienne, Orquesta Sinfónica Si</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012024">
		<snippet doc-id="294843" rsv="1524.00">The first description of a Bond Girl, Casino Royale's Vesper Lynd, is almost a template for the typical dress as well as the general appearance of later Bond Girls; she sports near</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7708702" rsv="1445.00">Irma Bunt is the main henchwoman in the James Bond novel and film On Her Majesty's Secret Service. Unusual for a Bond film villain, Bunt seems to have escaped punishment and retrib</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7708957" rsv="1444.00">A list of henchmen from the 1999 James Bond film The World Is Not Enough from the List of James Bond henchmen Giulietta da Vinci or the Cigar Girl is a fictional character from the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10378603" rsv="1436.00">Bond Girls Are Forever is a 2002 James Bond documentary film hosted by actress Maryam d'Abo, who had played the role of Kara Milovy in the 15th James Bond film The Living Daylights</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2591028" rsv="1424.00">In 1990, he illustrated (and co-created) the Garth Ennis-scripted comedy series Time Flies for the leading British science-fiction comic, 2000 AD. In 1995, Bond was involved in the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19398853" rsv="1417.00">James Bond (also known as I Wish I Was James Bond) will be the sixth and final single from Scouting for Girls' debut album, Scouting for Girls. The song is about the spy James Bond</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2730931" rsv="1400.00">Dr. Christmas Jones is a fictional character from the James Bond movie The World Is Not Enough. The character's name follows in the tradition of other Bond girls names that are dou</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1484173" rsv="1400.00">Blackman, aged 37 at filming, is the oldest actress to take the role of a Bond girl in the series of Bond films from EON Productions. Blackman and Diana Rigg are furthermore the on</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12641342" rsv="1394.00">Construction of the East Campus of Rich Township High School, financed by a $1,600,000 bond issue, began in September, 1952. In 1955, a $450,000 bond issue financed the addition of</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1492745" rsv="1390.00">She has not appeared as a character in a James Bond film, and never will as Danjaq, the copyright holder to the characters, elements, and other material related to James Bond on sc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7737220" rsv="1389.00">Kerim Bey is a Bond ally from the James Bond film From Russia with Love. Vavra, the Gypsy leader, is a Bond ally from the James Bond novel From Russia with Love. Bond only requests</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10481254" rsv="1387.00">Practically alone of all major Bond Girls of the Fleming canon, Gala Brand has not appeared as a character in a James Bond film, the movie version of the novel being an almost tota</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1891478" rsv="1377.00">Honeychile Rider is a fictional character in Ian Fleming's James Bond novel Dr. No. In the 1962 Bond film of the same name, her name was shortened and changed to Honey Ryder. In th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13387115" rsv="1362.00">Sue Bond is a blonde British actress, cabaret singer, and comedienne best remembered for her appearances on The Benny Hill Show in the early 1970s. Alongside of her acting Sue also</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2235752" rsv="1359.00">}"Die Another Day" is the theme to the James Bond film of the same name recorded by Madonna. In an official MORI poll in the UK for the Channel 4 program James Bond's Greatest Hits</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12149652" rsv="1352.00">Teresa "Tracy" Bond (born Teresa "Tracy" Draco, and also known as the Contessa Teresa di Vicenzo) is a fictional character in the James Bond film and novel On Her Majesty's Secret </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18597979" rsv="1348.00">Under Construction Cellophane is the third album by the English rock band The Troggs, released in 1967. The album was re-released in 2003 with twelve bonus tracks by Repertoire Rec</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14701897" rsv="1348.00">After attending Gravesend Grammar School for Girls on Pelham Road in Gravesend attending a performance arts course, she trained at the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art on a full grant</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16058740" rsv="1344.00">The following is a list of cast members who have portrayed characters appearing in the James Bond film series. The list is sorted by film and character, because of multiple actors </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9593869" rsv="1339.00">The James Bond film series are spy films inspired by Ian Fleming's novels about the fictional MI6 agent Commander James Bond (codename 007). For the lead Bond girl “Domino”, a slew</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012025">
		<snippet doc-id="142331" rsv="4421.00">The Second Kashmir War began with Pakistan infiltrating into and starting a rebellion in Jammu and Kashmir. (See Operation Gibraltar) The plan was a non-starter and India retaliate</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4500730" rsv="4005.00">Indo-Pakistani relations are grounded in the politcal, geographic and economic links between the Republic of India and the Islamic Republic of Pakistan, two of the largest and fast</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="429559" rsv="3989.00">In September of 1965 before the two had engaged in the short run Indo-Pakistani War of 1965. In Pakistan many civilians felt that they had won the war - though Pakistan had suffere</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16657283" rsv="3974.00">He was responsible for conducting paramilitary operations and infiltrating Kashmiri militants on the Indian side of the Line of Control, which subsequently led to the Kargil War. H</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3665169" rsv="3942.00">The Lahore Declaration was a bilateral agreement between India and Pakistan signed on February 21, 1999 by the then-Prime Minister of India Atal Bihari Vajpayee and the then-Prime </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18023108" rsv="3919.00">The Kargil War of 1999 broke out when Indian force sought to repel militants and Pakistani soldiers who had infiltrated across the LoC. While the bus service had continued to run d</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="803754" rsv="3870.00">The Kargil War, also known as the Kargil conflict,(I) was an armed conflict between India and Pakistan that took place between May and July 1999 in the Kargil district of Kashmir. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="696760" rsv="3857.00">As a gesture of goodwill India decided not to try 93,000 (80,000 military, paramilitary and police forces, and 13,000 civilians) Pakistan prisoners of war for war crimes and releas</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5015591" rsv="3851.00">Handicapped by the altitude and the limited time, Pakistan could only manage to control the Saltoro Ridge's western slopes and foothills despite the fact that Pakistan possessed mo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14294333" rsv="3800.00">Lieutenant General Muhammad Masood Aslam SJ (born September 1, 1952) is the principal commander of Pakistan Army fighting the pro-Taliban forces in the Waziristan theater, part of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8313471" rsv="3771.00">The Siachen Conflict, sometimes referred to as The Siachen War was a military conflict between India and Pakistan over the disputed Siachen Glacier region in Kashmir. One of the fa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2034675" rsv="3762.00">The Battle of Tololing was one of the pivotal battles in the Kargil War between India's armed forces and troops from the Northern Light Infantry who were aided by other Pakistan ba</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15734948" rsv="3757.00">The 7th Infantry Division, also known as the Golden Arrow (after its formation sign) and Peshawar Division, (after its garrison city) is the Pakistan Armys oldest and most battle-h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17981867" rsv="3746.00">Since the First Kashmir War (1947–48), travel and communication between what became Pakistan-administered Kashmir and Indian-administered Kashmir were indefinitely suspended. The K</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5740934" rsv="3732.00">General Aziz Khan was commissioned in the Pakistan Army in 1966 in the Infantry's Punjab Regiment. He was then posted as the Commander Force Command Northern Areas (FCNA), Gilgit w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16945685" rsv="3705.00">Officially launching its services on March 16, the bus service was not halted even after the outbreak of the Kargil War. While the bus service had continued to run during the Kargi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5174257" rsv="3692.00">The 2001-2002 India-Pakistan standoff was a military standoff between India and Pakistan that resulted in the amassing of troops on either side of the International Border (IB) and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3872983" rsv="3639.00">It was the first large scale use of air power in the Kashmir region since the Indo-Pakistani War of 1971. Main article: Kargil WarInitial infiltrations were noticed in Kargil in ea</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="506952" rsv="3637.00">The Indo-Pakistani War of 1947, sometimes known as the First Kashmir War, was fought between India and Pakistan over the region of Kashmir from 1947 to 1948. The result of the war </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3030955" rsv="3596.00">Main article: Indo-Pakistani War of 1965Main article: Indo-Pakistani War of 1971In 1965 and 1971, heavy fighting again broke out between India and Pakistan. The Indo-Pakistani War </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012026">
		<snippet doc-id="18948043" rsv="3040.00">Main articles: Short-term effects of alcohol, Long-term effects of alcohol, Alcohol and cancer, Alcohol and cardiovascular disease, and Recommended maximum intake of alcoholic beve</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="404063" rsv="2918.00">Persons who believe themselves immune to the effects of alcohol may often be the most at risk for health concerns and the most dangerous of all operating a vehicle. "Chronic heavy </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5600440" rsv="2867.00">Main articles: Fetal alcohol syndrome and Fetal Alcohol Spectrum DisorderDrinking in pregnancy is the cause of Fetal alcohol syndrome (BE: foetal alcohol syndrome), especially in t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="337566" rsv="2855.00">A few researchers have questioned the extent of positive effects as most studies compare moderate drinkers' health to non-drinkers, but fail to take into account the number of peop</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5770231" rsv="2781.00">The relationship between alcohol consumption and health has been the subject of formal scientific research since at least 1926, when Dr. Raymond Pearl published his book, Alcohol a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7697517" rsv="2745.00">College health professionals include physicians, physician assistants, administrators, nurses, nurse practitioners, mental health professionals, health educators, dietitians and nu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2797132" rsv="2724.00">A logical possibility is that some of the alcohol abstainers in research studies previously drank excessively and had undermined their health, thus explaining their high levels of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="295446" rsv="2695.00">Because mare's milk contains more sugars than the cow's or goat's milk fermented into kefir, kumis has a higher, though still mild, alcohol content. Kumis itself has a very low lev</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2701591" rsv="2671.00">Patrick (1952) states that the discovery of late Stone Age beer jugs has established the fact that purposely fermented beverages existed at least as early as c. 10,000 BC. It has b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3363" rsv="2671.00">Some of mankind's earliest known writings refer to the production and distribution of beer: the Code of Hammurabi included laws regulating beer and beer parlours, and The Hymn to N</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2322041" rsv="2668.00">Alcohol advertising is the promotion of alcoholic beverages by alcohol producers through a variety of media. Scientific research around the world conducted by governments, health a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1637334" rsv="2665.00">When the alcohol reaches 40% the Armagnac can be transferred to large glass bottles called "Dame Jeanne" for storage. As with any "eau de vie", Armagnac should be stored vertically</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1946" rsv="2663.00">In Britain a unit of alcohol is defined as 10 millilitres (or approximately 8 grams) of ethanol (ethyl alcohol). The number of units of alcohol in a drink can be determined by mult</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2842910" rsv="2660.00">The U.S. National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA) reports that  "Although there is no evidence that alcohol itself is a carcinogen, alcohol may act as a cocarcino</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18617528" rsv="2637.00">Prohibition of alcohol can also refer to the antecedent religious and political temperance movements calling for sumptuary laws to end or encumber alcohol use. On March 23, 1933, P</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="319138" rsv="2591.00">When a description of this paradox was aired in the United States on 60 Minutes in 1991 with the proposal that red wine, or alcohol, decreases the incidence of cardiac diseases, th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11651736" rsv="2564.00">Alcohol powder is a powder that will produce an alcoholic drink when mixed with water. In the United States, according to the Alcohol and Tobacco Tax and Trade Bureau (TTB), alcoho</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19329865" rsv="2558.00">Alcohol has a biphasic effect on the body, which is to say that its effects change over time. Cell membranes are highly permeable to alcohol, so once alcohol is in the bloodstream </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18450716" rsv="2506.00">Moderate alcohol consumption 30-60 minutes before bedtime catalyzes disruptions in sleep maintenance and sleep architecture that are mediated by blood alcohol levels [2]. Under con</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="32961" rsv="2494.00">Wine became so revered and its effect so feared that elaborate theories were developed about which gemstones would best counteract its negative side effects. See also: Long-term ef</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012027">
		<snippet doc-id="7701" rsv="2722.00">For over a thousand years South American indigenous peoples have chewed the coca leaf (Erythroxylon coca), a plant that contains vital nutrients as well as numerous alkaloids, incl</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="53292" rsv="2546.00">The rationale for including the coca leaf in the 1961 Single Convention is mainly rooted in a report requested of the United Nations by the permanent representative of Peru that wa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4419141" rsv="2384.00">The production, the distribution and the sale of cocaine products is restricted (and illegal in most contexts) in most countries. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6690" rsv="2307.00">The cocaine was derived from the coca leaf and the caffeine from kola nuts - Coca-Cola (the 'K' in Kola was replaced with a C for marketing purposes). To this day, Coca Cola uses a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="581712" rsv="2280.00">Diet sodas (also diet pop, diet, sugar-free, or light soft drinks, refreshments, or carbonated beverages) are sugar-free, artificially sweetened, non-alcoholic carbonated beverages</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="284163" rsv="2265.00">In September 2006, he spoke at the United Nations General Assembly, holding a coca leaf, saying ‘I should like to take this opportunity to speak of another historical injustice: th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="29972" rsv="2240.00">An herbal tea, tisane, or ptisan is an herbal infusion made from anything other than the leaves of the tea bush (Camellia sinensis). The English word "tisane" originated from the G</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="256077" rsv="2223.00">Coca eradication is a controversial strategy strongly promoted by the United States government as part of its "War on Drugs" to eliminate the cultivation of coca, a plant whose lea</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="63576" rsv="2161.00">Pemberton used an old family recipe from his African American maid's family for the original Coca Cola formula, as a nonalcoholic alternative to his French Wine Coca in the event t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="28152" rsv="2149.00">The species Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni, commonly known as sweetleaf, sweet leaf, sugarleaf, or simply stevia, is widely grown for its sweet leaves. However, health and political con</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1723479" rsv="2147.00">New Zealand's Misuse of Drugs Act is a national drug control law that classifies drugs into three classes, or Schedules, based on their risk of harm: CANNABIS FRUIT. COCA LEAF—That</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6516741" rsv="2126.00">It is backed by over 100 multinational companies, including BP, Volkswagen, The Coca-Cola Company and Vodafone. E. Neville Isdell, Chairman and CEO, The Coca-Cola Company:“We have </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="93831" rsv="2084.00">A 2000 review of the available literature concluded that "under present and expected conditions of new use, there is no potential for Roundup herbicide to pose a health risk to hum</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3901072" rsv="2076.00">Coca tea, also called mate de coca, is a tisane (herbal tea) made using the leaves of the coca plant. Coca tea comes from the coca plant, which has the biological name Erythroxylum</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15966318" rsv="2046.00">USAID's programs in Bolivia strengthen democratic institutions; provide economic opportunities for disadvantaged populations through business development and trade; improve family </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4697289" rsv="2043.00">This contamination is a public health concern and has caused significant outcry among environmental and health advocates. The EPA and California have set public health goals for be</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6811" rsv="2035.00">It works to protect public health and safety by providing information to enhance health decisions, and it promotes health through partnerships with state health departments and oth</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="38323" rsv="2018.00">For example, the Public Health Cigarette Smoking Act of 1970 exempted cigars from its advertising ban, and cigar ads, unlike cigarette ads, need not mention health risks. Further i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="225870" rsv="2010.00">The Coca-Cola formula is The Coca-Cola Company's secret recipe for Coca-Cola. To this day, Coca-Cola uses as an ingredient from coca leaf extract prepared by a Stepan Company plant</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9616807" rsv="1969.00">"Ypadú would not be more than an element in Amazonian botanical and ethnographic folklore were it not for its use, which enshrines it as a precursor in the current trend in favour </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012028">
		<snippet doc-id="16652593" rsv="3259.00">On December 15, 1989 KLM Flight 867 from Amsterdam was descending into Anchorage International Airport when the Boeing 747-400 flew though a thick cloud of volcanic ash from Mount </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2528948" rsv="3201.00">On 24 June, 1982, the route was flown by City of Edinburgh, a 747-236B registered G-BDXH. The aircraft flew into a cloud of volcanic ash thrown up by the eruption of Mount Galunggu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="162404" rsv="3048.00">Slightly cooler than usual temperatures recorded worldwide and the brilliant sunsets and sunrises have been attributed to this eruption that sent fine ash and gases high into the s</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1459249" rsv="2927.00">The deposit of that landslide revealed the origin of coarse diamicts with hummocky topography at other strato volcanic cones. The eruptions produced a light cloud, sending a plume </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1533051" rsv="2858.00">An eruption column consists of hot volcanic ash emitted during an explosive volcanic eruption. Eruption columns form in explosive volcanic activity, when the high concentration of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="690526" rsv="2838.00">Laki or Lakagígar (Craters of Laki) is a volcanic fissure situated in the south of Iceland, not far from the canyon of Eldgjá and the small town Kirkjubæjarklaustur, in Skaftafell </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="198811" rsv="2793.00">Volcanic ash consists of small tephra, which are bits of pulverized rock and glass created by volcanic eruptions, less than 2 millimetres (0.079 in) in diameter. Unlike the ash tha</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="254954" rsv="2753.00">It is among the deadliest stratovolcanos on Earth; its volcanic cone composed of layers of volcanic ash and hardened lava. On April 26, the area was dusted by volcanic ash from a n</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15634312" rsv="2727.00">The Puff model is a volcanic ash tracking model developed at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. Puff was initially conceived and developed by Prof. H. Tanaka as a novel method for</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8921015" rsv="2709.00">They are characterised by a dense cloud of ash-laden gas exploding from the crater and rising high above the peak. Steaming ash forms a whitish cloud near the upper level of the co</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="991545" rsv="2693.00">A pyrocumulus or fire cloud is a dense cumuliform cloud associated with fire or volcanic activity. Phenomena such as  volcanic eruptions, forest fires, and occasionally industrial </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="465179" rsv="2661.00">A pyroclastic particle greater than 64 mm in diameter is correctly known as a volcanic bomb when molten, or a volcanic block when solid. Pyroclastic material with particles less th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="904516" rsv="2644.00">Although airport ground crews regularly clean up runways, the crash of Air France Flight 4590 demonstrated that accidents can still occur: in that case, the crash was caused by deb</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="312891" rsv="2606.00">Main article: British Airways Flight 9The last major eruption on Galunggung was in 1982, which had a Volcanic Explosivity Index of 4 and killed 68 people. This eruption also brough</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1451152" rsv="2590.00">The volcano is currently rated by the Alaska Volcano Observatory as Aviation Alert Level Red and Volcanic-alert Level WARNING. On Saturday, July 12, 2008, Okmok Caldera exploded wi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4217801" rsv="2586.00">The Minoan eruption of Thera, also referred to as the Thera eruption or Santorini eruption,  was a major catastrophic volcanic eruption (VEI = 6, DRE = 60 km3) which is estimated t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="673671" rsv="2561.00">A volcanic ash column rose high into the atmosphere and deposited ash in 11 U.S. states. As the water moved back into its basin, it pulled with it thousands of trees felled by a su</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1159922" rsv="2525.00">Plinian eruptions are volcanic eruptions marked by their similarity to the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in AD 79 (as described in a letter written by Pliny the Younger) that killed Pli</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="417762" rsv="2484.00">Commonly associated with explosive volcanic activity - such as Plinian or krakatoan eruption styles, or phreatomagmatic eruptions - pyroclastic deposits are commonly formed from ai</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="32571" rsv="2450.00">A volcano is an opening, or rupture, in a planet's surface or crust, which allows hot, molten rock, ash, and gases to escape from below the surface. Vents that issue volcanic mater</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012029">
		<snippet doc-id="2990519" rsv="4735.00">Proeski, was born in Prilep, Republic of Macedonia, to Dominika and Nikola Proeski from Kruševo, his hometown, where he spent most of his childhood. His fanbase quickly grew and he</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11959661" rsv="3557.00">The former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia (FYR Macedonia) was represented by Tose Proeski and the song "Life". Tose Proeski sang all the songs and the winner was chosen by televoti</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19624965" rsv="3434.00">On the 5th of October the Macedonian POP singer Tose Proeski held his last concert. All of the songs that Tose Proeski has ever written and sang were sang by the singers in attenda</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17873440" rsv="3382.00">For the song by 98 Degrees, see The Hardest Thing. "The Hardest Thing" is the first posthumous single released by Macedonian pop musician, Toše Proeski, from his upcoming English-l</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7866955" rsv="3311.00">"Life" was the FYR Macedonia's entry in the Eurovision Song Contest 2004, performed in English (the first time the Macedonian entry had not featured at least some of the country's </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3402030" rsv="3250.00">Grigor Koprov (Macedonian: Григор Копров) (born September 30, 1943 in Ohrid, now Republic of Macedonia) is arguably one of the most famous pop music composers in the Republic of Ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8344420" rsv="3125.00">Skopje Fest (Macedonian: Скопје Фест) or Festival na zabavni melodii Skopje (Фестивал на забавни мелодии Скопје) is one of the main musical events in the Republic of Macedonia. Sko</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14356965" rsv="3082.00">The 2008 Beovizija semi-finals interval act included singers Stefan Filipović representing Montenegro, Rebeka Dremelj representing Slovenia, Kraljevi Ulice and 75 cents representin</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5005968" rsv="3069.00">The Music School of Bitola or Muzicko Uciliste Bitola is a state school that is located in Bitola, Republic of Macedonia. It provides a full education which includes solfege, music</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4195663" rsv="3031.00">He represented FYR Macedonia  at the 2005 Eurovision Song Contest in Kiev, finishing 17th with the song "Make My Day". He was voted as the 'Discovery of the Year 2002' in the count</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6240669" rsv="2928.00">Esma Redžepova (Macedonian: Есма Реџепова) is a Romani Macedonian vocalist, songwriter, and humanitarian born in Skopje, Socialist Republic of Macedonia, then Yugoslavia. During he</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5244075" rsv="2897.00">Tose can refer to: Leonard Tose - businessman To�e Proeski - a Macedonian singer TOSE Software Company This  page lists articles associated with the same title. If an internal link</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1924921" rsv="2824.00">Tony Cetinski (born May 31, 1969 in Pula, Croatia is a famous Croatian pop singer. Born into a family of musicians, he began singing when he was 15 years old with various local gro</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7850656" rsv="2766.00">"Od nas zavisi" (Macedonian Cyrillic: Од нас зависи, English translation: "It Depends On Us") was FYR Macedonia's entry at the Eurovision Song Contest 2002, performed in the Macedo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10045170" rsv="2711.00">It is structured in a form of a dialogue. Pop, Rock, Jazz, and even Classical cover versions also exist (incl. versions by Esma Redzepova, Goran Bregovic, Toše Proeski, Azra, Laza </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="330226" rsv="2674.00">Karolina Gočeva got her first break at the age of 10 when she performed at the children's festival "Si-Do" in Bitola and the annual festival "Makfest 91" in Štip with the song "Mam</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13910228" rsv="2631.00">Photo credit: Canan KalkanTodor "Toše" Proeski (Macedonian: Тодор „Тоше" Проески) (January 25, 1981–October 16, 2007) was a famous Macedonian singer who was popular across the enti</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11694533" rsv="2631.00">Photo credit: Canan KalkanTodor "Toše" Proeski (Macedonian: Тодор „Тоше" Проески) (January 25, 1981–October 16, 2007) was a famous Macedonian singer who was popular across the enti</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13134953" rsv="2614.00">Zajdi, zajdi, jasno sonce (O Set, O Set, Clear Sun; Macedonian: Зајди, зајди, јасно сонце; Bulgarian: Зайди, зайди, ясно слънце) is a popular Macedonian and  Bulgarian song which h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19496665" rsv="2582.00">Bobi Andonov (Macedonian: Боби Андонов) (born August 18, 1994 in Melbourne, Australia) is a Macedonian Australian singer who will represent Republic of Macedonia at the Junior Euro</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012030">
		<snippet doc-id="83907" rsv="2172.00">SRY (Sex-determining Region Y) is a sex-determining gene on the Y chromosome in the therians (placental mammals and marsupials). This intronless gene encodes a transcription factor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6988346" rsv="2141.00">Anthropometric history is a term coined in 1989 by John Komlos to refer to the study of the history of human height, focusing on explaining secular trends, cycles of various length</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7455643" rsv="2098.00">Human thermal comfort is defined by ASHRAE as the state of mind that expresses satisfaction with the surrounding environment (ASHRAE Standard 55). Thermal comfort is maintained whe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14818586" rsv="2029.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 18, also known as SOX18, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14819212" rsv="2024.00">Zinc finger protein, Y-linked, also known as ZFY, is a human gene. This gene encodes a zinc finger-containing protein that may function as a transcription factor. This gene was onc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="905957" rsv="2020.00">The particular human genome that and individual inherits is a large part of the first variable (nature) and a combination of health and environmental factors present before adultho</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14795865" rsv="2014.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 3, also known as SOX3, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="374298" rsv="2014.00">For the magnetism-related g-factor, see gyromagnetic ratio. Charles Spearman,  early psychometrician, found that schoolchildren's grades across seemingly unrelated subjects were po</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15354559" rsv="2011.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 12, also known as SOX12, is a human gene. Members of the SOX family of transcription factors are characterized by the presence of a DNA-binding h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14814646" rsv="2010.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 6, also known as SOX6, is a human gene. The SOX gene family encodes a group of transcription factors defined by the conserved high mobility group</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16859948" rsv="1998.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 21, also known as SOX21, is a human gene. SRY-related HMG-box (SOX) genes encode a family of DNA-binding proteins containing a 79-amino acid HMG </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14763517" rsv="1993.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 4, also known as SOX4, is a human gene. This intronless gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14879794" rsv="1991.00">Doublesex and mab-3 related transcription factor 1, also known as DMRT1, is a human gene. This gene is found in a cluster with two other members of the gene family, having in commo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14797738" rsv="1989.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 5, also known as SOX5, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14723387" rsv="1981.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 9 (campomelic dysplasia, autosomal sex-reversal), also known as SOX9, is a human gene. The protein encoded by this gene recognizes the sequence C</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14800299" rsv="1960.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 13, also known as SOX13, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7860110" rsv="1951.00">Human sex determination refers to the processes by which an individual becomes either a male or female during development. During the late 1980s and early 1990s, coinciding with th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15075136" rsv="1939.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 15, also known as SOX15, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15417284" rsv="1937.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 14, also known as SOX14, is a human gene. This intronless gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1475503" rsv="1921.00">Testis-determining factor (TDF) is a general term for the gene (or product thereof) that results in maleness in humans and some other species. Embryos are gonadally identical, rega</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012031">
		<snippet doc-id="17524651" rsv="2124.00">The Eurovision Song Contest 2009 will be the 54th Eurovision Song Contest, scheduled to take place between the 12 May and 16 May 2009. Changes in the voting procedure will occur wi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13954204" rsv="2100.00">Dansk Melodi Grand Prix 2008 was the selection for the song to represent Denmark at the Eurovision Song Contest 2008. Two semi-finals and two wildcard selections took place to sele</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9954" rsv="2092.00">Further information: Voting at the Eurovision Song ContestThe voting systems used in the Contest have changed throughout the years. Nowadays members of the public may also vote by </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7901609" rsv="2092.00">Euroviisut 2007 was the show in which Finland chose its entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007. Finland hosted the Eurovision Song Contest for the first time, after Lordi won i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7442310" rsv="2089.00">Dansk Melodi Grand Prix 2007 was the selection for the song to represent Denmark at the Eurovision Song Contest 2007. Two semi-finals and two wildcard selections took place to sele</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15964926" rsv="2079.00">The winner was again chosen by postcard voting, however, this time, only the top four entries were announced. It would be the clearest victory ever in this voting system as they go</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19638614" rsv="2070.00">Euroviisut 2008 was the Finnish national selection for the Finnish entry to the Eurovision Song Contest 2008, held in Belgrade, Serbia. Televoting selected the qualifiers for the f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8366531" rsv="2055.00">Söngvakeppni Sjónvarpsins 2007 was the show in which Iceland selected its entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007, held in Helsinki, Finland. Televoting decided the winner, with</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12291379" rsv="2051.00">The Andorran National Final was held on March 15, 2004, hosted by Pati Molné and Xavier Graset with the winner being chosen by a mixture of an "expert" jury (5/7), SMS voting in An</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3606916" rsv="2046.00">Congratulations: 50 Years of the Eurovision Song Contest was a television programme organised by the European Broadcasting Union (EBU) to commemorate the Eurovision Song Contest's </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11435813" rsv="2045.00">The introduction of the voting system adopted by Eurovision in 1975 was the only major change. The song went on to win the 1999 Eurovision in Jerusalem (the most recent of Sweden's</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7438722" rsv="2040.00">Melodi Grand Prix 2007 (shortened MGP 2007) was the television show in which the Norwegian entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007 was chosen. Just like in 2006, there was be 3 </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3867528" rsv="2029.00">Greece has been participating in the Eurovision Song Contest since 1974, with the exception of 1975, 1982, 1984, 1986, 1999 and 2000. In 2005, Eurovision held a commemorative progr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16353941" rsv="2020.00">Greece and Ellinikí Radiofonía Tileórasi (ERT) chose to host a National Selection with the winner being chosen by  SMS voting (30%), televoting (30%) and an "expert" jury (40%). Ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15426108" rsv="2019.00">Melodi Grand Prix 2008 (shortened MGP 2008) is the television show in which the Norwegian entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2008 is chosen. There were 3 semi finals held, where</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8402277" rsv="2003.00">EMA 2007 was the television show in which Slovenia selected its entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007. Unlike in 2006, the winner was selected through televoting only. Sloveni</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="331425" rsv="2001.00">Sweden was absent at Eurovision for a second time in 1970 because of a Nordic boycott of the voting system, which had led to a four-way tie for first place at the 1969 contest. Mai</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4408017" rsv="1999.00">Televoting or televote is also the term used to describe the telephone voting in the Eurovision Song Contest, as well as for World Idol, American Idol and similar contests. Televot</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4461881" rsv="1995.00">The Eurovision Song Contest 2007 was the 52nd edition of the Eurovision Song Contest. The voting process was the same as 2006 except there was fifteen minutes to vote, an increase </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1998116" rsv="1991.00">Serbia and Montenegro participated in the Eurovision Song Contest twice, from 2004 (see Eurovision 2004). No Name were close to becoming the national entry once more, for the 2006 </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012032">
		<snippet doc-id="623280" rsv="2264.00">In Alien vs. Predator (2004), which serves as a prequel to the Alien series, Henriksen plays Weyland Industries chief executive officer Charles Bishop Weyland. In the previous film</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="713" rsv="2123.00">This Einstein android, also called "Albert Hubo", thus represents the first full-body walking android in history (see video at ). The character Ash in the movie Alien, another arti</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14075240" rsv="2063.00">Evilhawk is a reptilian alien from the planet Luq with an android body. Dargin Bokk is an alien who was born on the planet Luq. Like Darkhawk, Evilhawk's body is an android body po</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10203926" rsv="2049.00">Making it back inside, human android Synthetics attack. Soon, the players are forced to attack a robot-like power-loader piloted by an android. Before long, they face an Alien Drag</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19423847" rsv="2047.00">The first villain of the series, Cool Alien collects human specimens using a vaporizing / teleportation ray from his invisible spaceships. An alien plant covered with countless tho</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17339036" rsv="2039.00">However, the inmate they meet is not Strange himself but an alien robot duplicate. Batman and Robin fight with the alien, but they chase it into the superpower transfer room, and s</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8861419" rsv="2032.00">This article provides a list of episodes of the television series Lost in Space. Complete box sets of all 3 seasons (and the original pilot film) of the original TV series have bee</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9669953" rsv="2001.00">But this arouses the suspicion of the alien leader (Claudio Undali); he has Hall arrested for snooping into matters of national security and Charlie kidnapped. Hall and his helpers</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1619971" rsv="1981.00">Lan becomes devoted to Galactus, and on one journey to seek a planet for sustenance for Galactus, battles the alien race the Ovoids. The Ovoids manage to kill Lan, but not before G</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="602483" rsv="1953.00">Weyland-Yutani is a fictional corporation in the motion picture Alien and its sequels, often referred to simply as "The Company". He is played by Lance Henriksen, the actor that pl</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8995799" rsv="1918.00">The only actor from the Alien films to appear in one of the prequels was Lance Henriksen, who had played the android Bishop in Aliens and a man claiming to be the android's creator</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4930032" rsv="1904.00">The Growing Man is an android and was created for the supervillain, Kang the Conqueror. Knowing that the android would be used as a weapon in the past, the scientists of Kosmos bui</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="213251" rsv="1870.00">For the video games of the same name, see Alien 3 (video game), Alien 3 (1993 game) and Alien 3 (Game Boy). As the third installment in the Alien franchise, it is preceded by Ridle</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="26110" rsv="1869.00">This list of fictional robots and androids is a chronological list, categorised by medium. It includes all depictions of robots, androids and gynoids in literature, television, and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1800005" rsv="1866.00">The Android Invasion is a serial in the British science fiction television series Doctor Who, which was first broadcast in four weekly parts from November 22 to December 13, 1975 S</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9017986" rsv="1852.00">The Android would introduce each challenge by stating its aim, value and special difficulties. Commander: Android, we're in Airlock and the doors are closing. ::Android: Scavengers</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1505455" rsv="1824.00">The tower construction is directed by Krug's most faithful android, Alpha Thor Watchman. Thor's dream is to convince him through indirect means, including the manipulation of his w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6245494" rsv="1800.00">Upon investigation of the transmission source, a derelict alien ship, Executive Officer Kane becomes infected with an alien parasite. On orders of Captain Dallas, Kane is brought b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7872488" rsv="1777.00">It was written by Costa Panayi who also coded Android, Android 2, TLL, Cyclone and Revolution. Highway Encounter is a strategy/action game played from a 3D isometric perspective in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4027932" rsv="1770.00">Eloise is a vat grown prototype Alien/humanoid android hybrid created using Queen DNA. She escapes captivity with a band of Alien warriors, with whom she settles on the planet LK17</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012033">
		<snippet doc-id="3973131" rsv="2765.00">For some women with hypermobility pregnacy related pelvic girdle pain can be debilitating. Symptoms of hypermobility include a dull but intense pain around the knee and ankle joint</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8173442" rsv="2412.00">Xwrits periodically locks the X Window System while a brightly-colored hand, alternately clenching and stretching as if in pain, is displayed to remind the user to take a break. It</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3011904" rsv="2361.00">Blackberry thumb is a form of repetitive strain injury caused by the frequent use of the thumb(s) to press buttons on PDAs, smart phones, or other mobile devices. It is caused by t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7474213" rsv="2321.00">The DataHand keyboard was introduced in 1995 by DataHand Systems, Inc.  Before that it was produced by Industrial Innovations as early as 1992. After the initial prototype was rele</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="25756" rsv="2222.00">A repetitive strain injury (RSI), also called cumulative trauma disorder (CTD), occupational overuse syndrome, or work related upper limb disorder (WRULD), is any of a loose group </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1053949" rsv="2169.00">Traumatic spinal cord injury is classified into five types by the American Spinal Injury Association and the International Spinal Cord Injury Classification System. The exact effec</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18842281" rsv="2144.00">The large number of combinations available from a small number of keys allows text or commands to be entered with one hand, leaving the other hand free to do something else. Keyboa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="56462" rsv="2100.00">Often people suffering from carpal tunnel syndrome can have multiple contributing factors which are aggravated by vigorous hand activities and repetitive stress trauma to the hand.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1272984" rsv="2089.00">The most common cause of this type of fracture is a fall on an outstretched hand(acronym: FOOSH). Patients usually present with a history of an injury and localized pain. Therefore</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13915654" rsv="2026.00">The "goring ox" with its derivatives is put aside, because full compensation for its acts can be demanded only when the master has been forewarned, and the treatise opens with the </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="56283" rsv="1940.00">Type I CRPS develops following an initiating noxious event that may or may not have been traumatic, while type II CRPS develops after a nerve injury. CRPS has characteristics simil</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14243136" rsv="1913.00">Medical Massage Is outcome based massage it is primarily the application of specific treatment protocols targeted to the specific problem(s) the patient presents with physician's d</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1918041" rsv="1908.00">Phantom limb pain is the feeling of pain in an absent limb or a portion of a limb. The pain sensation varies from individual to individual. However, in 1551, French military surgeo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1944613" rsv="1906.00">Chondromalacia Patella (also known as CMP, Patello-femoral Pain Syndrome, or Runner's Knee) is a term for a large and disparate group of medical conditions that can cause pain at t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="272541" rsv="1906.00">Symptoms of tenosynovitis include pain, swelling, and difficulty moving the particular joint where the inflammation occurs. Possible treatments for tenosynovitis include cortisone </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="504841" rsv="1905.00">Osteoarthritis (OA, also known as degenerative arthritis, degenerative joint disease), is a clinical syndrome in which low-grade inflammation results in pain in the joints, caused </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2493928" rsv="1901.00">The first and most obvious symptom is what feels like a sharp stone, although this does not hurt, the pain occurs about 2-3 minutes after being stung.The pain from weever stings ha</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="490901" rsv="1897.00">This fulfills the criteria for animal pain."  However, others argue this may demonstrate a chemical sensitivity rather than pain; notably, no similar result has been obtained with </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="307837" rsv="1891.00">Most often the injury is caused by a blow to the shoulder or by falling on an outstretched hand. Early on arthritis of the shoulder can be managed with mild analgesics and gentle e</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="29666" rsv="1881.00">If not treated surgically, syringomyelia often leads to progressive weakness in the arms and legs, loss of hand sensation, and chronic, severe pain. Symptoms may appear months or e</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012034">
		<snippet doc-id="246574" rsv="3682.00">Demonic possession is often the term used to describe the control over a human form by Satan himself or one of his assigned advocates. Demonic possession is mentioned at length in </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3700127" rsv="3471.00">Because of this precedent, demonic possession was part of the belief system of Christianity since its beginning, and exorcism is still a recognized practice of Catholicism, Eastern</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5033818" rsv="3465.00">The confessions of these nuns were accompanied by what investigators believed were classic signs of demonic possession: contortions, unnatural body movements, speaking in tongues (</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2458960" rsv="3268.00">Anneliese Michel (September 21, 1952 – July 1, 1976) was a German  Catholic woman who was said to be possessed by demons and subsequently underwent an exorcism. Having centered her</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="309564" rsv="3249.00">Biblical passages that highlight the demonic are principally found in the gospels of Matthew, Mark and Luke, and the Acts of the Apostles. In the early church the rite of exorcism </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="174601" rsv="3138.00">Demonologists also often make a distinction between "demonic" and "diabolical," with devils perceived as being much more dangerous -- the "officers," perhaps, while demons would be</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2571604" rsv="3103.00">The Exorcism of Emily Rose is a 2005 horror/thriller film directed by Scott Derrickson. The film is based on the true story of Anneliese Michel, a young Catholic woman from Germany</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5036540" rsv="3041.00">The 1634 case of demonic possession in Loudun, France, is arguably the most famous case of multiple or mass possession in history. No evidences of true possession were found, and t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1623431" rsv="2982.00">Of Exorcisms and Certain Supplications (Latin: De Exorcismis et Supplicationibus Quibusdam) is an 84-page document of the Roman Catholic church describing the rite of exorcism. It </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11441994" rsv="2979.00">This reached such a point that exorcism rituals were organized by the local clergy. It was during these rites that the nuns accused Grandier of being in league with the devil and i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="475322" rsv="2968.00">This article is about exorcism. "Exorcism" in Islam signifies ridding the human body of jinn possession (Christians would be familiar with the term demonic possession) by means of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="86351" rsv="2942.00">It is based on a 1949 exorcism Blatty heard about while he was a student in the class of 1950 at Georgetown University, a Jesuit and Catholic school. Father Damien Karras, who is c</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14914335" rsv="2890.00">José Antonio Fortea Cucurull (born in Barbastro, Spain, 1968), priest and specialized theologian in Demonology. In 1998 he defended his thesis (tesina) entitled Exorcism in the Pre</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="858169" rsv="2863.00">It was while studying at St. Louis University, in 1949, that he would be asked by Father William S. Bowdern to assist in the exorcism rite on a case, which would become famous, con</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18904468" rsv="2840.00">The Demon Murder Trial is the first known case in the United States of a lawyer claiming his client was innocent due to demonic possession. Minella traveled to England to meet with</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="274932" rsv="2822.00">One relatively recent example of Christian demonology is the book War On The Saints, by Jessie Penn-Lewis, which purports to reveal what demons are, how they work at gaining posses</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5271472" rsv="2814.00">It is a factual retelling of the true story of a teenage boy from Mt. Rainier Maryland who went through the rite of exorcism in 1943. Allen tracked down the sole survivor of the te</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7499196" rsv="2749.00">Meg Masters is a fictional character on The CW Television Network's Supernatural'' portrayed by Nicki Aycox and serves as the host body to the demonic daughter of Azazel. In the se</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="412826" rsv="2737.00">In charismatic Christianity, deliverance ministries are activities carried out by individuals or groups aimed at solving problems related to demons and spirits, especially possessi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10612300" rsv="2735.00">Graham H. Twelftree, Ph.D (born 8 July 1950) is an Australian born biblical scholar who currently serves as Distinguished Professor of New Testament at Regent University's School o</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012035">
		<snippet doc-id="13485592" rsv="1757.00">In Australia, there is a growing trend for MPs to become directly involved in the corporate fundraising efforts of their parties. The Australian Labor Party is the main beneficiary</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15756092" rsv="1572.00">The Philippine Children's Fund of America is a non-profit organization registered under the state of California and is duly recognized by the United States Federal Government. It i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="190458" rsv="1546.00">Acids can catalyse the reaction by donating a proton to the carbonyl group, thus making it more reactive, while bases can catalyse the reaction by removing a proton from the alcoho</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3628051" rsv="1526.00">Here follows a list of notable researchers and writers in the field of cryptozoology: Also see: Cryptozoology, Cryptids|Cryptids, zoology. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15298246" rsv="1518.00">Samuel H. Wood is a scientist noted for donating DNA that was used in somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT) to produce mature human embryos that were clones of Dr Wood. Dr. Wood and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17462994" rsv="1501.00">Mobile donating refers to donating to an organization through a mobile device. The primary means for mobile donating is through  SMS.  Mobile donating can also refer to consumers d</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14040996" rsv="1492.00">Additionally, Vijay Singh, who serves as the Eagles for St. Jude Ambassador, is personally donating $5,000 for every eagle he makes during the 2008 season and Camilo Villegas will </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4481670" rsv="1445.00">It is the body primarily responsible for blood donation and related services in Australia. Blood donated in Australia has been tested for Hepatitis B since 1972, HIV-1 since 1985, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11745794" rsv="1419.00">At the time the Fund was established, the Academy defined its role as making “more widely known throughout Australia the benefits that accrue both internationally and to Australia </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8635827" rsv="1399.00">Under Louis XIV's reign, the work of these French researchers sent by the King had a notable influence on Chinese sciences, but continued to be mere intellectual games, and not too</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19197431" rsv="1398.00">He is a Member of the Jewellers Association of Australia. He has been a sponsor of Operation Smile, Australia, since 2001. The Lutwyche resident said his brother coaxed him to move</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2602512" rsv="1390.00">The Australian Research Council (ARC) is the Australian Government’s main agency for allocating research funding to academics and researchers in Australian universities. The ARC al</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12903882" rsv="1387.00">It is based in Melbourne, Australia, with offices in the United Kingdom and the United States. XSight is designed for commercial market researchers or those undertaking short term </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13100713" rsv="1381.00">Cormack Foundation Pty Ltd is an Australian investment company established for the purpose of raising funds for the Liberal Party of Australia. The company was originally set up us</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="505536" rsv="1380.00">Many donors donate as an act of charity, but some are paid and in some cases there are incentives other than money. Using this method an individual can donate plasma or platelets m</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15827675" rsv="1358.00">Ethical issues surrounding contribution donating pushed the Indian government to pass legislation banning the sale of organs. Nicholas Bequelin, a researcher for Human Rights Watch</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8613182" rsv="1355.00">The object then ascended in a north-westerly direction over the Melbourne suburb of Clayton South, Victoria, Australia. No record of this encounter was preserved in the National Ar</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13739096" rsv="1344.00">In recent years Weekend Sunrise has broadcast the event live for two hours across the rest of Australia. 2007 marked 40 years since Telethon began in Western Australia. Telethon 20</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9772355" rsv="1342.00">Ted Bloecher (born 1929) is an American ufologist. Researcher Jerome Clark described him as "highly regarded" for his scientific rigor, his detailed research, his efforts at balanc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17512873" rsv="1335.00">The Mobile Giving Foundation is a non-profit organization based in Washington, working to increase mobile donating in the US.  The organization in early 2008 fostered a deal betwee</snippet>
	</topic>
</inex-snippet-submission>
