<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE inex-snippet-submission SYSTEM "inex-snippet-submission.dtd">
<inex-snippet-submission participant-id="247" run-id="TheCNGL_DCU_SnippetTrack_2012_SRun03">
	<description>Bias factorto score sentences containing query terms more highly.sentence score = (number of query terms in the sentence)^2/number of terms in query.Summary of text is some the highest score sentences.</description>
	<topic topic-id="2012001">
		<snippet doc-id="3457121" rsv="1972.00">Doorman Perdomo shouted at Chapman, "Do you know what you've done?", to which Chapman calmly replied, "Yes, I just shot John Lennon." The first policemen to arrive were Steve Spiro</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5231203" rsv="1930.00">George Toogood Smith (1903–5 June 1955) was the maternal uncle, through marriage, of John Lennon. Smith told Lennon that words did not have to be taken at face value, as they had m</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15852" rsv="1919.00">Further information: Julia Lennon, Alfred Lennon, Mimi Smith, and George Toogood SmithJohn Winston Lennon was born in the Liverpool Maternity Hospital, Oxford Street, Liverpool, to</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14851312" rsv="1892.00">Julia Baird (née Dykins) (born 5 March 1947) is the eldest daughter of John 'Bobby' Albert Dykins (1918 - December 1965) and Julia Lennon (12 March 1914 – 15 July 1958). Dykins lat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7553287" rsv="1891.00">Rosaura Lopez Lorenzo (16 March 1932, Pontevedra, Spain – 19 September 2005, Pontevedra, Spain) was a maid of John Lennon and Yoko Ono in the Dakota apartment between 1976 and 1980</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5231097" rsv="1891.00">In July 1946, the returning Alf Lennon visited Mimi and took Lennon to Blackpool, ostensibly for a long holiday, but with the secret intention of emigrating to New Zealand with him</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2023257" rsv="1890.00">The Lives of John Lennon is a 1988 biography of musician John Lennon by Americanauthor Albert Goldman. Despite the damning from Goldman in the book, Lennon comes across much better</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1924705" rsv="1887.00">Milk and Honey is an album of music by John Lennon and Yoko Ono released in 1984. After a falling out with David Geffen, whose Geffen Records had initially released Double Fantasy,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13202488" rsv="1875.00">For information on the surname and given name "Lennon", see Lennon (name). Lennon may refer to: Geography: </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1149616" rsv="1872.00">Cynthia Lennon (née Powell) (born 10 September 1939 in Blackpool, Lancashire, England) is the former wife of John Lennon. Cynthia married Lennon the next day. Lennon and Cynthia ha</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5733759" rsv="1871.00">For the soundtrack to the film, see The U.S. vs. John Lennon (soundtrack). A soundtrack composed of John Lennon tracks was released by Capitol Records and EMI on 26 September 2006.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="614773" rsv="1863.00">Double Fantasy is the comeback album by John Lennon and Yoko Ono, released in 1980 initially on the newly-formed Geffen Records, and then from 1989 onwards through EMI. It is notab</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1740047" rsv="1859.00">Menlove Ave. is a John Lennon album, posthumously released in 1986 under the supervision of Yoko Ono, Lennon's widow. All songs by John Lennon, except where noted. Produced by John</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5721446" rsv="1853.00">"Love" is a ballad by John Lennon, originally released in 1970 on his John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band album. The song first came out on Lennon's 1970 album John Lennon/Plastic Ono Ban</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="875989" rsv="1852.00">Unfinished Music No.2: Life with the Lions is an album of experimental music released by John Lennon and Yoko Ono in 1969, and the successor to 1968's highly controversial . Unfini</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1770362" rsv="1851.00">The John Lennon Collection is a retrospective compilation album of John Lennon's solo music, released in 1982 (see 1982 in music) by Parlophone Records, through EMI and by Geffen R</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5987959" rsv="1850.00">Julia Stanley Lennon (née Stanley) (12 March 1914 – 15 July 1958) was the mother of John Lennon. Lennon chose Alf (twice) and then Julia walked away, but in the end Lennon (crying)</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18960141" rsv="1848.00">"Imagine" is a song by John Lennon, which appears on his 1971 album, Imagine. Nutopia is a  conceptual country created by John Lennon and Yoko Ono on April 1st 1973. In 2006 a Nuto</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81562" rsv="1845.00">John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band is the début solo album by English rock musician John Lennon. In 2000, Yoko Ono supervised a remixing of John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band for its remastere</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="614795" rsv="1845.00">Walls and Bridges is an album by John Lennon, released in October 1974. One of them, Elton John himself, has gone on record declaring Walls and Bridges the best Beatles solo album.</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012002">
		<snippet doc-id="9138522" rsv="3390.00">MEGA Brands, Incorporated TSX: MB (Formerly MEGA Bloks, Incorporated) is a publicly traded children's toy company based in Montreal, Canada. Mega Bloks is the name of their most po</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2438332" rsv="3127.00">This is an alphabetical list of video games. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2006923" rsv="2913.00">Servbot (Kobun in Japan, which roughly means "little follower") are a series of characters from the Mega Man Legends'' series. They first appear in Mega Man Legends as an enemy of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12715707" rsv="2695.00">Block-style figures are a type of collectible toy action figures marked by a generally simplistic representation of the human form, usually comprised of block-shaped apendages and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="146560" rsv="2506.00">A brickfilm is any film made using LEGO, Mega Bloks, or other similar plastic construction block toys. The first ever brickfilm was made between 1985-1989 in Perth, Western Austral</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="149671" rsv="2504.00">This is a list of games for the Game Boy Advance handheld game system, organized alphabetically by name. This includes games released in the US, Japan, and Europe for the system. T</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2159245" rsv="2451.00">The company name LEGO was coined by Christiansen from the Danish phrase leg godt, meaning "play well."  LEGO Group claims that "LEGO" means "I put together" or "I assemble" in Lati</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="708262" rsv="2423.00">This is the official list of games for the Game Boy Color. All games are released in Europe and the USA. organized alphabetically by name, followed by catalog number where known. S</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5994421" rsv="2331.00">Lego Mindstorms NXT is a programmable robotics kit released by Lego in late July 2006. It replaces the first-generation Lego Mindstorms kit, which was called the Robotics Invention</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3478140" rsv="2315.00">Lego Space theme featuring astronauts and spaceships. The first Lego Space sets were a leap forward in Lego design. It also made a special appearance in Lego Island 2 and was actua</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4957820" rsv="2257.00">This is not intended to be a complete list. For a list of all toys on which there are currently articles, see Toys. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6707496" rsv="2250.00">Pac-Mania contains several new features and significant differences from its original counterpart. The game takes place in four environments: "Block Town" (made up of Lego-like bui</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1390380" rsv="2217.00">This article lists notable events and releases in the timeline of the Lego Group. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2202938" rsv="2199.00">Minifigures are small, plastic figural toys produced by Danish toy manufacturer Lego, which are customarily sold with Lego sets, as characters intended to populate modular Lego env</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1318591" rsv="2155.00">Lego Baby is a line of blocks by the Lego Group for very young children. Lego Baby line had been combined with Lego Duplo Line to become Lego Explore during 2002 till mid 2004. The</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="631107" rsv="2150.00">In an overcrowded city like Mega-City One, tensions and rivalry between neighbouring city blocks are inevitable and, very occasionally, these feelings spill over into full-scale wa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10395475" rsv="2148.00">This list encompasses fictional characters with the paranormal or superhuman ability to generate and manipulate various forms of "earth", including, but not limited to, soil, stone</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4623220" rsv="2134.00">Since their introduction, LEGO pneumatics have featured in a variety of LEGO Technic and LEGO Educational (DACTA) products. The first generation of LEGO Pneumatics ran from 1984 th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5965052" rsv="2128.00">Clone Bricks are imitation LEGO Bricks, such as Mega Bloks, Tyco bricks, and others. The Lego Group has sought to put an end to clone bricks and retain sole manufacturing rights ov</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="198856" rsv="2120.00">LEGO Mindstorms is a line of Lego sets combining programmable bricks with electric motors, sensors, Lego bricks, and Lego Technic pieces (such as gears, axles, and beams). Little i</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012003">
		<snippet doc-id="9013183" rsv="2077.00">This article is a list of diseases of bananas and plantains (Musa spp.). </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="38940" rsv="1894.00">For other uses, see Banana (disambiguation). Banana chips are a snack produced from dehydrated or fried banana or plantain slices, which have a dark brown color and an intense bana</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="769420" rsv="1787.00">Black Sigatoka is a leaf spot disease of banana plants caused by ascomycete fungusMycosphaerella fijiensis Morelet. Black Sigatoka, also known as black leaf streak, was named for i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="312937" rsv="1755.00">Fusarium oxysporum, also referred to as Panama disease or Agent Green, is a fungus that causes Fusarium wilt disease in more than a hundred species of plants. Panama disease, also </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16465743" rsv="1755.00">The Banana industry in the Caribbean is widely spread to each island. In st.Vincent, there are about 5,000 banana growers. Bananas are also plentiful in Latin America &amp;amp; Africa,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12264177" rsv="1651.00">Banana bract mosaic virus (BBrMV) is a plant pathogenic virus of the family Potyviridae. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12264317" rsv="1629.00">Banana streak virus (BSV) is a plant pathogenic virus of the family Caulimoviridae. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12264210" rsv="1628.00">Banana bunchy top virus (BBTV) is a plant pathogenic virus of the family Nanoviridae. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9012366" rsv="1627.00">Lists of plant diseases are presented in the following table. Common Names of Diseases, The American Phytopathological Society </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19106136" rsv="1617.00">Banana production in Honduras plays an important role in the Economy of Honduras. The Honduran banana industry employed a significant Garifuna workforce from the Bay Islands off Tr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11818087" rsv="1615.00">Cylindrocarpon musae is a fungal plant pathogen that causes root rot in banana. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11817197" rsv="1615.00">Cordana johnstonii is a plant pathogen. It produces cordana leaf spot on bananas. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11817228" rsv="1611.00">Cordana musae is a plant pathogen. It produces cordana leaf spot on bananas. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="622746" rsv="1574.00">The Columbian Exchange has been one of the most significant events in the history of world ecology, agriculture, and culture. This exchange of plants and animals transformed Europe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4302211" rsv="1499.00">He administered the ranch until 1871, when he accepted an invitation from his brother Henry M. Keith to help build a railroad in the Central American nation of Costa Rica. By 1882,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11817399" rsv="1440.00">Guignardia musae is a plant pathogen that causes Freckle of banana a disease that forms water soaked lesions of banana fruit and is spread by rain splash. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16495842" rsv="1434.00">The Citrus industry in the Caribbean is a major one in the Caribbean. The main producing areas are the Pomona Valley and the Stann Creek Valley in the Stann Creek District. Citrus </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2146221" rsv="1427.00">Burrowing nematode or Banana-root nematode (Radopholus similis) is an important parasite of fruit, vegetable, and other crops. It is an especially important pest of bananas and cit</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11818219" rsv="1415.00">Mycosphaerella musicola is a fungal plant pathogen, which is the causal agent of Yellow Sigatoka leaf spot disease on banana plants. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="251116" rsv="1413.00">Kamphaeng Phet Historical Park is an archeological site in Kamphaeng Phet, Thailand. Major features in the Kamphaeng Phet Historical Park include archaeological remains of ancient </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012004">
		<snippet doc-id="8669149" rsv="2142.00">One source of SUVs' popularity is the perception of significant safety advantages over smaller vehicles,. To this, critics claim that SUVs are more likely to roll over, more likely</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="535476" rsv="1970.00">Besides, the numbers above are difficult to translate into any meaningful steps because the NHTSA does not define a car or a light truck very well (the PT Cruiser is classified as </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2450538" rsv="1923.00">The Jiangling Motors Landwind or JMC Landwind (Chinese: 陆风汽车) is a Chinese-built SUV. It is also sold in some European markets, being the first Chinese vehicle that has ever been e</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="700494" rsv="1918.00">The Mercedes-Benz GLK (code name X204) is a compact crossover competing with the Infiniti EX, Acura RDX, BMW X3 and Land Rover LR2/Freelander, as well as the upcoming Audi Q5, Volv</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="956354" rsv="1913.00">The BMW X5 is a mid-size crossover SUV sold by BMW since 1999. 4 years later, the BMW X3 was released, which used the "X" prefix applied to the BMW SUVs which were derivatives of t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6385842" rsv="1909.00">The Hyundai Veracruz is a mid-size crossover SUV sold by Hyundai in the countries of United States, Canada, South Korea, China, and the Middle East. The IIHS (Insurance Institute f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1826282" rsv="1904.00">The Daewoo Winstorm is a crossover SUV developed by General Motors's GM Daewoo design center in Bupyeong, South Korea. The Winstorm, which is given the model designation C100 is ba</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1092286" rsv="1899.00">Geo/Chevrolet Tracker is a mini SUV produced by Chevrolet and Geo In 1992 the Geo marque was brought to Canada so the Chevrolet Tracker became the Geo Tracker there as well. In 199</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="802817" rsv="1894.00">Main article: Ford Escape HybridIn 2004, the Ford Escape Hybrid was released. In January 2006, at the Washington Auto Show, Ford showed a prototype for an Escape Hybrid that would </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="47696" rsv="1890.00">A sport utility vehicle (SUV) is a generic marketing description for a rugged automotive vehicle similar to a station wagon but built on a light-truck chassis. Compact SUVs and min</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="989530" rsv="1886.00">In 1966, Congress held a series of highly publicized hearings regarding highway safety, and passed legislation to make installation of seat belts mandatory, and created several pre</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3014744" rsv="1880.00">The Ford Edge and Lincoln MKX are among the first vehicles to use Ford's new 3.5 L Duratec 35 V6 engine. A concept of the Ford Edge with the HySeries Drive was unveiled in the 2007</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="440246" rsv="1879.00">These are following by an extended period during which the passenger car CAFE standard, the observed average passenger car fuel economy, and the price of gasoline remained stable, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1887376" rsv="1859.00">Demand for the Santa Fe continued to be up but owners had several suggested changes for Hyundai. The last year of this Santa Fe saw few changes. In Malaysia, Hyundai Santa Fe is av</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1822962" rsv="1845.00">The Daewoo Lanos was a subcompact car manufactured by the Korean automaker Daewoo Motors from 1997 to 2002, and still made under a license agreement by the Fabryka Samochodów Osobo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5979772" rsv="1837.00">High and Mighty: SUVs - The World's Most Dangerous vehicles and how they got that way (ISBN 1-58648-123-1) is a book by Keith Bradsher which details the tax breaks, protectionism a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2372552" rsv="1833.00">The 2007 Saturn Outlook large crossover sport-utility equipped with side-impact airbags received a 5-star rating for its performance in the National Highway Traffic Safety Administ</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1097589" rsv="1831.00">The Mazda Navajo was a 2-door SUV introduced in 1991, and Mazda's very first off-roader. Main article: Firestone vs Ford Motor Company controversyIn May 2000, the National Highway </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1278102" rsv="1825.00">The Nissan Murano is a mid-size crossover SUV first manufactured by Nissan in December 2002 and sold as a 2003 model. Designed at Nissan Design America in La Jolla, California, the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1014707" rsv="1822.00">Based on the Audi Pikes Peak quattro concept car, the Q7 is designed more for on-road use, and was not meant for serious off-road use where a transfer case is needed. To underline </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012005">
		<snippet doc-id="887" rsv="1720.00">The Apple Newton, or simply Newton, is the iPhone's predecessor and was an early line of personal digital assistants developed and marketed by Apple Computer (now Apple Inc.) from </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1439045" rsv="1703.00">Renesas SH73180 (SH-Mobile3), Renesas SH73182 (SH-Mobile3+), Renesas SH73230 (SH-Mobile3A), Renesas SH73450 (SH-Mobile3A+) -- MBX Lite + VGP Lite + SH4AL-DSP(SH-X) Texas Instrument</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19611129" rsv="1692.00">Sleepy People should not be confused with the Oregonian New Wave indie rock band The Sleepy People or Californian progressive rock band Sleeping People. Sleepy People formed around</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9593665" rsv="1678.00">Liverpool Software Gazette was a short-lived computer magazine published by Bruce Everiss' Microdigital company who were based in Liverpool, UK. There were some regular columns suc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17527833" rsv="1672.00">A sagardotegi (pronounced ) is a type of cider house found in the Basque Country. Surnames  containing sagar appear in the written record from 1348 onwards: Sagastizabal "wide appl</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="264575" rsv="1647.00">This is a list of home and office computers by category where the main category is the home computer's CPU wordlength (8/16/32/64 bits) and the subcategory is the specific CPU used</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="264569" rsv="1625.00">Note: in cases of manufacturers who have made both home and  business-oriented personal computers, only machines fitting into the home  computer category are listed. For a home com</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6870355" rsv="1623.00">ChipWits is a 1984 game for the Apple Macintosh, programmed by Doug Sharp and Mike Johnston, and published by BrainPower software. ChipWits won numerous awards, including MACazine </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7754761" rsv="1604.00">Sharp Daily ( Chinese:爽報 Pinyin: Shuǎng Bào) is a free Chinese-language tabloid newspaper, published in Taipei, Taiwan by Next Media. Launched on October 24, 2006 as a rival to Col</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1979166" rsv="1583.00">The King of Chicago is a 1986 action adventure strategy computer game by Doug Sharp. The player starts in Chicago with a small mafia-type mob and follow Al Capone in being the mob-</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1688626" rsv="1537.00">"Homer's Barbershop Quartet" is the first episode of The Simpsons' fifth season. Homer explains that he, Principal Skinner, Barney, and Apu recorded a barbershop quartet album in 1</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9081996" rsv="1526.00">Flappy first appeared on the Sharp X1 home computer in 1983. The beautiful planet of Blue Star, home-planet to a young boy named FLAPPY, is invaded by Dark Emperor Ngalo-Ngolo. Wan</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="269240" rsv="1505.00">This article is about the company based in Hong Kong. Apple Daily and its parent company Next Media are thought to be pioneer of paparazzi and yellow Journalism in Hong Kong. Apple</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="703681" rsv="1498.00">For other uses, see Sharp. One of his first inventions was the Ever-Sharp mechanical pencil in 1915, from which the Sharp Corporation took its name. In 1953 Sharp started productio</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8953588" rsv="1492.00">This list is ; you can help by expanding it. The following is a list of notable computer system manufacturers. Please do not add entries without proper sources to indicate notabili</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="548115" rsv="1483.00">The Macintosh 128K was severely limited by a lack of upgrades. In fact due to the lack of memory, Apple intentionally chose to exclude the 128K from three of its most important ear</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1280893" rsv="1469.00">A cooking apple is an apple that is used primarily for cooking rather than eating fresh. Other variety such as Bramley or Golden Noble are cut into small segments for pies, tarts e</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11931183" rsv="1448.00">Ashmead's Kernel is a diploid cultivar of apple. Ashmead's Kernel is reported as having been raised by Dr Ashmead in Gloucester, England in the 1700's. Ashmead's Kernel makes a goo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="356878" rsv="1443.00">Xcode is a suite of tools for developing software on Mac OS X, developed by Apple. The Xcode suite includes a modified version of free software GNU Compiler Collection (GCC, apple-</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2094876" rsv="1425.00">Solanum aculeastrum is commonly known as Soda Apple, Sodaapple Nightshade, Goat Apple, Poison Apple, or more ambiguously as "bitter-apple". It is a poisonous nightshade species fro</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012006">
		<snippet doc-id="24032" rsv="2273.00">More commonly, a technique much like the reconstruction of computed tomography (CT) and single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) data is used, although the data set colle</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3557219" rsv="2175.00">A distinction is therefore made between "MRI imaging" and "functional MRI imaging" (fMRI), where MRI provides only structural information on the brain while fMRI yields both struct</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3457142" rsv="2078.00">Molecular Imaging is a new discipline that unites molecular biology and in vivo imaging. In Europe, others Networks of Excellence as DiMI (Diagnostics in Molecular Imaging) or EMIL</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17890739" rsv="1916.00">The Modular Neutron Array (MoNA) is a large-area, high efficiency neutron detector that is used in basic research of rare isotopes at Michigan State University's National Supercond</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16434531" rsv="1910.00">Main article: Single photon emission computed tomographySPECT is a branch of Nuclear Medicine and can be used to complement any gamma imaging study, where a true 3D representation </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="907554" rsv="1813.00">Next came SPECT and PET scans, which allowed scientists to map brain function because, unlike MRI and CT, these scans could create more than just static images of the brain's struc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2285280" rsv="1785.00">In 1989 a proposal was submitted to the National Science Foundation by representatives of Florida State University, Los Alamos National Laboratory, and the University of Florida fo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="44585" rsv="1724.00">For other uses, see Cyclotron (disambiguation). The spiral path of the cyclotron beam can only "synch up" with klystron-type (constant frequency) voltage sources if the accelerated</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1228679" rsv="1711.00">In physics, the gyromagnetic ratio (also sometimes known as the magnetogyric ratio in other disciplines) of a particle or system is the ratio of its magnetic dipole moment to its a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="347838" rsv="1689.00">Nuclear medicine differs from most other imaging modalities in that the tests primarily show the physiological function of the system being investigated as opposed to traditional a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2424135" rsv="1686.00">A second-generation prototype two-detector HIDAC-PET camera was assessed at the MRC Cyclotron Unit, Hammersmith Hospital, London, UK, during 1999. The first was purchased by Imperi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="170757" rsv="1684.00">Cyclotron radiation is electromagnetic radiation emitted by moving charged particles deflected by a magnetic field. Cyclotron radiation is emitted by all charged particles travelli</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1917699" rsv="1678.00">List of materials analysis methods: </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="439202" rsv="1668.00">Many diverse activities depend on electron cyclotron resonance technology, including The ECR ion source makes use of the Electron Cyclotron Resonance to heat a plasma. Some of thes</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2182716" rsv="1666.00">Fourier transform ion cyclotron resonance mass spectrometry, also known as Fourier transform mass spectrometry, is a type of mass analyzer (or mass spectrometer) for determining th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7405641" rsv="1665.00">Cyclotron is the name of two incarnations of the same fictional DC Comics character, Terry Curtis. Roy Thomas reinvented the character as Cyclotron, a reluctant supervillain, in Al</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1053016" rsv="1647.00">The Paul Scherrer Institute (PSI) is a multi-disciplinary research institute which belongs to the Swiss ETH-Komplex covering also the ETH Zurich and EPFL. It was established in 198</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5320931" rsv="1637.00">Cyclotron (band), the metal rock band. Cyclotron (comics), a minor character in the DC Universe. Cyclotron (Gladiators), an event from the television series  Gladiators. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11311306" rsv="1623.00">Thornton came to the Lawrence Radiation Laboratory of the University of California at Berkeley in 1933 and most of his later career was connected with that Laboratory where he work</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5320929" rsv="1620.00">For other uses, see Cyclotron (disambiguation). Cyclotron is an Industrial metal duo from Tucson, Arizona. It was formed in 1996 by Brad Lewellyn and Craig Leach but has since been</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012007">
		<snippet doc-id="81837" rsv="2319.00">The Crystal Palace was a cast-iron and glass building originally erected in Hyde Park, London, England, to house the Great Exhibition of 1851. The name Crystal Palace (coined by th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7630449" rsv="2167.00">This article is about the disused High Level station. For the open Low Level station, see Crystal Palace railway station. Crystal Palace (High Level) railway station was a station </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8000800" rsv="2145.00">New York Crystal Palace was an exhibition building constructed for the Exhibition of the Industry of All Nations in New York City in 1853. The building was directly inspired by The</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="538328" rsv="2118.00">Crystal Palace may refer to: </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10852310" rsv="2094.00">Idris "Alex" Ughiovhe (born 27 January, 1983 in Washington DC) is an American footballer currently playing for Crystal Palace Baltimore. In 2006 Alex played reserve matches for bot</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13341799" rsv="2078.00">The Crystal Palace was an exhibition hall built for the Montreal Industrial Exhibition of 1860, originally located at the foot of Victoria Street between St. Catherine and Cathcart</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="93961" rsv="2076.00">Crystal Palace is a residential area in South London, England named from the erstwhile local landmark, The Crystal Palace, which occupied the area from 1854 to 1936. It is the loca</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6883712" rsv="2058.00">The Crystal Palace and South London Junction Railway was built by the London, Chatham and Dover Railway to serve the Crystal Palace after it was moved to Crystal Palace from its or</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7900534" rsv="2053.00">The Glaspalast (Glass Palace) was a glass and iron exhibition building in Munich modeled after The Crystal Palace in London. The Glaspalast opened for the Erste Allgemeine Deutsche</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="319983" rsv="1974.00">The most easterly district of Upper Norwood is now also known as Crystal Palace and is the commercial hub of Upper Norwood - the 'Triangle'. A notable park in the area is Upper Nor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="103293" rsv="1944.00">The Great Exhibition, also known as Crystal Palace, was an international exhibition that was held in Hyde Park, London, England, from 1 May to 15 October 1851 and the first in a se</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7696093" rsv="1942.00">Woozley was born in Berkshire and began his career as a trainee with Crystal Palace, turning professional in August 1997. He was released shortly after the Southend game and in Jul</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8680137" rsv="1927.00">Coordinates: 51°25′3″N 0°4′2″W﻿ / ﻿51.4175, -0.06722The Crystal Palace Dinosaurs, also known as Dinosaur Court,  are a series of sculptures of dinosaurs and extinct mammals located</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="94222" rsv="1825.00">By 1862 Stanford's map of Londonhttp://www.mappalondon.com/london/south-east/map-london.htm shows large homes had been constructed along Penge New Road (now Crystal Palace Park Roa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="95333" rsv="1822.00">The London Borough of Bromley ( (·)) is a London borough of south east London, England and forms part of Outer London. Bromley is one of only five London Boroughs not to have at le</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19014712" rsv="1816.00">King's Field II is the second game in the King's Field RPG series. The game was developed by the Japanese game development company From Software, and released July 21st, 1995 in Ja</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15577871" rsv="1786.00">Main article: History of Crystal Palace F.C.Preceding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2006-07Succeeding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2008-09---- The 2007-08 season was C</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="816581" rsv="1785.00">Birkbeck station is a railway station and light rail stop in the London Borough of Bromley in the southern suburbs of London. The line was opened as a double-track branch of the We</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1091585" rsv="1773.00">Fuller spent the next season (2001–02) on loan at Scottish Premier League club Hearts. Fuller scored on his Preston debut, a 2–1 defeat at home to old club Crystal Palace, and soon</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18243235" rsv="1772.00">Main article: History of Crystal Palace F.C.Preceding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2007-08Succeeding article: Crystal Palace F.C. season 2009-10---- The 2008-09 season will </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012008">
		<snippet doc-id="4191796" rsv="1889.00">Taiaroa Head is a headland at the end of the Otago Peninsula in New Zealand, overlooking the mouth of the Otago Harbour. The part of Taiaroa Head where Northern Royal Albatrosses b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="62049" rsv="1842.00">For other uses, see South Island (disambiguation). The South Island is often called "the Mainland". Further information: List of New Zealand State Highways#South Island and State H</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="567412" rsv="1832.00">The Yellow-eyed Penguin (Megadyptes antipodes) or HoiHo is a penguin native to New Zealand. The Yellow-eyed Penguin was described by Jacques Bernard Hombron and Honoré Jacquinot in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="628345" rsv="1821.00">For other uses, see Dunedin (disambiguation). (clockwise from the city centre, starting at due north)Woodhaugh; Glenleith; Ross Creek; Dalmore; Pine Hill; Mt Cargill; Normanby; Mt </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="106354" rsv="1799.00">Oamaru ( (·)), the largest town in North Otago, in the South Island of New Zealand, also functions as the main town in the Waitaki District. Those at the Waitaki River mouth and at</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7539625" rsv="1771.00">Waitati is a small seaside settlement in Otago, New Zealand, within the city limits of Dunedin. The Main South Line railway curves from east to north through Waitati and a tourist </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7449877" rsv="1761.00">Dr Launcelot Eric Richdale OBE (1900-1983) was a New Zealand teacher and notable amateur ornithologist. Although his fieldwork was carried out in southern New Zealand, he spent som</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8103636" rsv="1761.00">Squirt is a New Zealand children's television show, produced in Dunedin. It was notable for Dunedin based production company TaylorMade, and Animation Research Limited's (ARL) pion</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7851400" rsv="1740.00">Thomas Burns (ca. 1796–1871) was a prominent early European settler and religious leader of the province of Otago, New Zealand. The proposal for a Free Church settlement in New Zea</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19197944" rsv="1731.00">The beach is divided into three roughly equal lengths, known as Saint Clair Beach, Middle Beach, and Saint Kilda Beach. Access is easiest at the Saint Clair end, with steps and ram</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1078914" rsv="1717.00">The settlement of Otakou lies within the boundaries of the city of Dunedin, New Zealand. In its original form 'Otago' it was the name of the channel off Wellers Rock but was transf</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="548507" rsv="1709.00">Otago Harbour is the natural harbour of Dunedin, New Zealand, consisting of a long, much-indented stretch of generally navigable water separating Otago Peninsula from the mainland.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5878270" rsv="1705.00">The city of Dunedin, New Zealand has played an important role in the history of New Zealand. More companies and institutions were founded in these years, the Dunedin Public Art Gal</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17155154" rsv="1691.00">Dunedin Public Libraries is a network of five libraries and two bookbuses in Dunedin, New Zealand, owned and operated by the Dunedin City Council. With local authority amalgamation</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7688435" rsv="1686.00">Natural History New Zealand Ltd (NHNZ) is a small New Zealand-based documentary production company that creates more than 60 hours of television programming each year. In addition </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1012608" rsv="1667.00">Hone Tuwhare (21 October 1922 – 16 January 2008) was a noted New Zealand poet of Māori ancestry. Hone Tuwhare was awarded the Robert Burns Fellowship from the University of Otago i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5884581" rsv="1656.00">Marples' Penguin (Palaeeudyptes marplesi) was a large species of the extinct penguin genus Palaeeudyptes. The precise relationship between this species and the slightly smaller Nar</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5852167" rsv="1638.00">Palaeeudyptes is an extinct genus of large penguins, currently containing four accepted species. Of the four species, two (P. gunnari and P. klekowskii) are known from numerous rem</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13836594" rsv="1633.00">The beach is a popular site for the Hooker's Sea Lion, Phocarctos hookeri, to bask on the sand. The bay is often thought by locals to have been named for a small biting insect know</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="168194" rsv="1632.00">The New Zealand author Janet Paterson Frame, ONZ,  CBE (August 28, 1924 - January 29, 2004) published eleven novels in her lifetime, together with three collections of short storie</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012009">
		<snippet doc-id="13160" rsv="2893.00">The gelatin obtained from acid treated raw material has been called type-A gelatin, and the gelatin obtained from alkali treated raw material is referred to as type-B gelatin. This</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="320594" rsv="2639.00">The Gummi Bear originates from Germany where it is popular under the name  (·) (rubber bear) or  (·) (little rubber bear). The traditional Gummi Bear is made from  sugar, glucose s</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18835733" rsv="2364.00">On July 5, 1999 David Osborne Hagger appeared by Statement 476 before the BSE Inquiry. On July 5, 1999 David Hagger appeared by Statement 476 before the inquiry into Bovine spongif</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19344418" rsv="2124.00">BSE is a type of transmissible spongiform encephalopathy (TSE). The finding of a second strain of BSE prion raises the possibility that transmission of BSE to humans has been under</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6058" rsv="1948.00">Collagen normally converts to gelatin, but survived due to the dry conditions. Over 90% of the collagen in the body, however, are of type I, II, III, and IV. The best stain for use</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8612989" rsv="1798.00">Nectar Lifesciences Limited is an integrated pharmaceutical company in India that manufactures generic products. Its name was changed to Nectar Lifesciences in Mar. 2004 after it b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16273260" rsv="1716.00">This is a list of companies listed on the Barbados Stock Exchange. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="491715" rsv="1663.00">The Bombay Stock Exchange was established in 1875. Around 6,000 Indian companies list on the stock exchange, and it has a significant trading volume. The index took only 10 trading</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13162" rsv="1660.00">The most common culinary use for gelatin is as a main ingredient in varieties of gelatin desserts. Unprepared gelatin for desserts is often marketed as a flavored powder or concent</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="586066" rsv="1656.00">Ballistic gelatin is a solution of gelatin powder in water. MacPherson's Figure 5-2, Velocity Variation Correction to Measured BB Penetration Depth, can be used to make corrections</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17482804" rsv="1648.00">BSE Pro (Formerly Blood Sweat and Ears) (or BSE Wrestling) is a Canadian independent professional wrestling organization, founded in 2005. BSE event results and rankings can be fou</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9848049" rsv="1645.00">The Beirut Stock Exchange (or BSE) is the principal stock exchange of Lebanon. Trading at that time was concentrated on gold and currency transactions, however in the 1930s there w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2114707" rsv="1632.00">The Budapest Stock Exchange (BSE) was re-opened in 1990 with headquarters in Budapest, Hungary. The Hungarian Stock Exchange, the ancestor of today’s Budapest Stock Exchange (BSE) </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="441549" rsv="1614.00">Breast self-examination (BSE) is an easy but unreliable method for finding possible breast cancer. A similar method of self-examination is known as the Seven P's of BSE: Though mos</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6946102" rsv="1614.00">In Sweden, the situation is similar to that in Norway but it is easier to find vegetarian food. In South America, vegetarianism is generally uncommon and vegetarian food is often d</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12195660" rsv="1614.00">John Mark Purdey (December 25 1953 – November 12 2006) was a British organic farmer who came to public attention in the 1980s, when he began to investigate the causes of bovine spo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="169365" rsv="1588.00">Commonly used stock market indices include: Note that the KLCI and Second Board comes under the umbrella of Bursa Malaysia. Electronic tech, computers, hardware, software, services</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11184911" rsv="1582.00">In Silver-gelatin photography, the emulsion consists of silver halide crystals suspended in gelatin, and the substrate may be glass, plastic film, paper or fabric. Photographic emu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16585" rsv="1578.00">The brand's popularity has led to its becoming a generic term for gelatin dessert across the US and Canada. During this same period, Jell-O 1-2-3, a gelatin dessert that separated </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="971278" rsv="1570.00">Aspic is a dish in which ingredients are set into a gelatine made from  a meat stock or consommé. The aspic may need additional gelatin in order to set properly. Since fish gelatin</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012010">
		<snippet doc-id="300215" rsv="2228.00">A thesis or dissertation committee is a committee that supervises a student's dissertation. At universities in the United Kingdom, the term thesis is usually associated with PhD/En</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8775" rsv="1971.00">In the Latin American docta, the admission to a Ph.D. program at an Argentine University requires the full completion of a Master's degree or a Licentiate's degree. Funding typical</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11041456" rsv="1943.00">(William) D'Arcy McNickle (1904–1977) was a writer, Native American activist and anthropologist. D’Arcy McNickle, an enrolled Salish Kootenai on the Flathead Reservation, became on</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6274827" rsv="1927.00">Alfred Kleiner (April 24,1849–July 3,1916) was Professor of Experimental Physics at the University of Alma Dohee, and was Albert Einstein's doctoral advisor or Doktorvater. Alfred </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14274604" rsv="1920.00">Naval Air Station (NAS) Banana River was a United States Naval Base in Satellite Beach, Florida. NAS Banana River was transferred to the United States Air Force on September 1, 194</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2449405" rsv="1874.00">Thesis can mean: A formal academic work, also known as a dissertation. The thesis statement (central argument) of a dissertation, essay, or other argumentative work. Thesis (repres</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18813064" rsv="1863.00">Herma (Greek for bond or foundation, and germ or embryo) is a piece for solo piano composed by Iannis Xenakis in 1961. It is based on a formulation of the algebraic equations of Bo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2297173" rsv="1838.00">In the usage of India, United Kingdom, United States, Australia, New Zealand, Hong Kong and some other countries, the Master of Philosophy (M.Phil.) is a research degree, requiring</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="859106" rsv="1792.00">Mauro Giuseppe Sergio Pantaleo Giuliani (July 27, 1781 – May 8, 1829) was an Italian guitarist and composer, and is considered by many to be one of the leading guitar virtuosos of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4263768" rsv="1790.00">There is no one Zapotec language:  in fact there are probably over 60 varieties of Zapotec. Zapotec languages and dialects fall into four broad divisions: Zapoteco de la Sierra Nor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="346628" rsv="1763.00">Ph.D. entrance requirements in the higher ranked schools typically require a student to have a master's degree by research, or a master's with a significant research component. The</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="977277" rsv="1747.00">In Argentina, the Licentiate degree (Castilian: Licenciatura) is a 4-5 year degree (6 years in some cases under the accomplishment of the licentia doctorandi thesis dissertation), </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1707089" rsv="1704.00">Kate L. Turabian (February 26, 1893–October 25, 1987) is best known for her book A Manual for Writers of Research Papers, Theses, and Dissertations, now in its seventh edition. Tur</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="519705" rsv="1702.00">In January 1880 Molien entered the Faculty of Physics and Mathematics of the University of Tartu (in German Kaiserliche Universität Dorpat) as a student of astronomy. The obtained </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13165225" rsv="1691.00">Kimberly K. Little is an American historian. She is marriad to the historian Scott Beekman. Scott Beekman </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="400504" rsv="1686.00">The Doctor of Education degree (Ed.D. or D.Ed.) is a discipline-based doctorate that prepares the student for academic, administrative, clinical or research positions in education.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="188886" rsv="1671.00">The best-known degree of this type is that of Doctor of Philosophy (PhD/DPhil) awarded throughout the world but others include the US degrees of Doctor of Engineering (DEng) and Do</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11832225" rsv="1668.00">He initially considered to enroll for the Ph.D. with a biography of well-known Holocaust denier David Irving as a dissertion topic, apparently at Irving's suggestion, but instead e</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1780292" rsv="1662.00">Patriot Bible University, formerly known as Patriot University, is an unaccredited fundamentalist Christian correspondence school located in Del Norte, Colorado. New Opportunities </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9596400" rsv="1643.00">For the scientific document, see dissertation. The Dissertation http://www.amazon.com/dp/0393306488 is a novel by R.M. Koster, part of the Tinieblas trilogy. The book is a mock-PhD</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012011">
		<snippet doc-id="878533" rsv="2584.00">The search and replace features of NoteTab are much more powerful than most text editors, and include regular expressions and a hierarchical search/replace of text in folders on a </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14885631" rsv="2492.00">The following is a list of software applications that use regular expressions. In some cases, only later versions of the applications use regular expressions. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="25717" rsv="2485.00">Regular expressions can be much more complex than these examples. Due largely to its expressive power, many other utilities and programming languages have adopted syntax similar to</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="261964" rsv="2470.00">Sam is a multi-file text editor originally designed at Bell Labs by Rob Pike (with the help of Ken Thompson and other Unix developers) in the early 1980s for the Blit windowing ter</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="46642" rsv="2311.00">Although grep is not strictly an acronym, the letters are taken from global / regular expression / print, a series of instructions for the ed text editor. The grep command searches</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16308759" rsv="2293.00">The centerpiece of UNA is a real-time collaborative editor. In addition to a real-time collaborative editor, UNA includes the following collaborative features: The Search &amp;amp; Rep</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="24521" rsv="2281.00">Pico is a text editor for Unix and Unix-based computer systems. It also cannot copy text from one file to another (though it is possible to read text into the editor from a file in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16260046" rsv="2265.00">Not to be confused with Norton Editor, see Peter Norton Computing ne (for "nice editor") is a console text editor for POSIX computer operating systems such as Linux or Mac OS X. It</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8233895" rsv="2223.00">The SemWare Editor (TSE) is a very flexible text editorwith roots in the MSDOS and MS Windows environment. TSE features a very capable macro language (SemWare ApplicationLanguage o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1038167" rsv="2196.00">vile is a text editor that attempts to combine the best aspects of the popular Emacs and vi editors. vile is an acronym which stands for "VI Like Emacs".  vile is featured in Chapt</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9771" rsv="2170.00">aed is the standard Unix text editor. 2i . %led is the standard Unix text editor.$$This is line number two.$3s/two/three/,led is the standard Unix text editor.$$This is line number</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1329953" rsv="2142.00">Notepad++ is a free source code editor for Windows. Notepad++ supports syntax highlighting for ActionScript,ASP,Ada,ASCII art,Assembly,AutoIt (Limited support for AutoHotKey),BAT,C</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10817747" rsv="2102.00">Kenneth Lane Thompson (born February 4 1943), commonly referred to as Ken Thompson (or simply ken in hacker circles), is an American pioneer of computer science notable for his wor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="279688" rsv="2099.00">The simplest pattern in pattern matching is an explicit value or a variable. However, it is possible to perform some string pattern matching within the same framework that has been</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="27163" rsv="2098.00">It reads input files line by line (sequentially), applying the operation which has been specified via the command line (or a sed script), and then outputs the line. The sed script </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1524877" rsv="2039.00">This article provides a basic feature comparison for several text editors. Additional feature details are available from the Text editor features|Category of text editor features a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="32494" rsv="2026.00">How the 'i' keystroke is processed depends on the editor mode.  (From insert mode, pressing the escape key switches the editor back to normal mode.) Any text typed thence gets adde</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="929837" rsv="2025.00">UltraEdit is a commercial text editor for Microsoft Windows created in 1994 by Ian D. Mead. A version called UltraEdit-32 was later created to run in Windows NT and Windows 95. Add</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3750893" rsv="2023.00">Diakonos is a customizable, usable curses-based (console-based, or text-based) text editor. Diakonos uses the common Macintosh/Windows keyboard shortcuts - Ctrl-C to copy, Ctrl-V t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1635937" rsv="2017.00">TextWrangler is a popular text editor for Mac OS X from Bare Bones Software. TextWrangler has features common to most programming text editors, such as syntax highlighting for vari</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012012">
		<snippet doc-id="2047900" rsv="2595.00">This article is about the Seinfeld episode. "The Contest" was the 51st overall episode of the NBC sitcom, Seinfeld. When David came up with using the idea for an episode of Seinfel</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5186697" rsv="2450.00">"The Masseuse" is the seventy-third episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. Elaine dates a man who shares the name of notorious serial killer Joel Rifkin and tries to convince him to c</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5186845" rsv="2272.00">"The Beard" is the 102nd episode of the hit NBC situation comedy Seinfeld. I'll tell you how so. She's bald!Elaine: What do you mean bald?George: What do you think I mean bald? Geo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="28606" rsv="2248.00">Jerry Seinfeld and Larry David pitched Seinfeld as a "show about nothing," similar to the self-parodying "show within a show" of Season 4 episodes "The Pilot". Main article: The Fi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5270278" rsv="2143.00">This is the only Seinfeld episode to have a title without the word "The" in front of it. As George tells Jerry that his girlfriend no longer wants to see him, Jerry mentions to Geo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3535188" rsv="2133.00">The narrative features the character of Jerry Seinfeld agreeing to attend a birthday party with Elaine Benes. "The Stake Out" is the first episode to feature Jerry's parents, and t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1924820" rsv="2123.00">"The Seinfeld Chronicles" (also known as "Good News, Bad News" for syndication) is the pilot episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. However, the production staff and writers refer to </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2104807" rsv="2111.00">"The Robbery" is the third episode of the first season of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. In the episode, the character of Jerry Seinfeld leaves Elaine Benes in charge of his apartment wh</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15507805" rsv="2109.00">"SeinfeldVision" is the first episode of the second season of 30 Rock and the twenty-second episode of the series. Lisa Schmeiser of Television Without Pity graded this episode as </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1765947" rsv="2104.00">"The Bart Wants What it Wants" is the eleventh episode of The Simpsons' thirteenth season. Bart finds Greta at a movie studio named Paramountie Studios (a parody of Paramount Pictu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7728211" rsv="2082.00">(DVD case background - Jerry's living room) (DVD case background - Monk's Cafe interior) (DVD case background - Jerry's building exterior) </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072787" rsv="2074.00">"The Stock Tip" is the fifth episode of the first season of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. In it, George Costanza tells Jerry Seinfeld and Elaine Benes that a friend of a friend of his h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7880167" rsv="2070.00">Season one of Seinfeld, an American television series created by Jerry Seinfeld and Larry David, originally aired  its pilot episode on July 5, 1989 as The Seinfeld Chronicles on N</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5186927" rsv="2066.00">"The Soup Nazi" is the title of the 116th episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld, which was the 6th episode of the 7th season. Jerry, George and Elaine go out to a new soup stand Krame</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072861" rsv="2057.00">The episode was the tenth episode for the show's third season. As a sign of gratitude for allowing him and Elaine to wait at his home, Jerry suggests the hosts stop by his apartmen</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072895" rsv="2055.00">"The Boyfriend" is a two part episode of the sitcom Seinfeld. Kramer and Newman take Hernandez back to a time when they were allegedly spit on by him; however, Jerry supports the "</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="104492" rsv="2052.00">On the show, Seinfeld played a caricature of himself. About his influences, Seinfeld, in his commentary for "The Gymnast" episode on "Seinfeld, Season 6," said, "He really formed m</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072796" rsv="2047.00">"The Pony Remark" is the seventh episode of the NBC sitcom Seinfeld. The episode was the second episode for the show's second season. Meanwhile, Kramer and Jerry bet over whether o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072792" rsv="2044.00">"The Ex-Girlfriend" is the sixth episode of Seinfeld. The episode was the first episode for the show's second season. Jerry begins seeing George's ex-girlfriend, Marlene, whom Geor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5072820" rsv="2044.00">"The Baby Shower" is the fifteenth episode of Seinfeld. The episode was the tenth episode for the show's second season. Though in the third season episode called The Fix-Up, when J</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012013">
		<snippet doc-id="8707733" rsv="2095.00">The following list of biogeographic provinces was developed by Miklos Udvardy in 1975. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8628301" rsv="1919.00">This is the 2006 archive of Geography portal selected pictures. ----__NOTOC__ ---- </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1003579" rsv="1916.00">The continent of Africa can be conceptually subdivided into a number of regions or subregions. Another common approach divides Africa by physical geography using features such as l</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4558169" rsv="1871.00">Horrible Geography is a series of books which is a spin-off of the Horrible Histories series written by Anita Ganeri, illustrated by Mike Phillips, and published in the UK by Schol</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12914725" rsv="1820.00">The Climate of Colombia is characterized for being tropical and isothermal as a result of its geographical location near the Equator presenting variations within five natural regio</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="66577" rsv="1770.00">Direct rays of the sun always shine in and between the tropics. When it's the first day of winter in the Northern Hemisphere, the direct rays are over the Tropic of Capricorn, whic</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="142824" rsv="1741.00">Return to top of page Return to top of page Return to top of page </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="23237" rsv="1737.00">The geography of China stretches some 5,026 kilometers across the East Asian landmass bordering the East China Sea, Korea Bay, Yellow Sea, and South China Sea, between North Korea </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5244370" rsv="1729.00">Geographically, South America is generally considered a continent forming the southern portion of the American landmass, south and east of the Panama-Colombia border by most author</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="203115" rsv="1711.00">Tropical and subtropical moist broadleaf forests (TSMF), also known as tropical moist forests, are a tropical and subtropical forest biome. Tropical and subtropical forest regions </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1707053" rsv="1696.00">Agriculture is the principal cause of habitat destruction. Habitat destruction is currently ranked as the most important cause of species extinction worldwide. Habitat destruction </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9336" rsv="1685.00">Ecuador is a country in western South America, bordering the Pacific Ocean at the Equator, for which the country is named.Ecuador encompasses a wide range of natural formations and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="636058" rsv="1659.00">It features the largest cat complex in North America; "Kingdoms of the Night" is the world's largest nocturnal exhibit and indoor swamp; the Lied Jungle is the world's largest indo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1268246" rsv="1656.00">Main article: North Region, Brazil Main article: Northeast Region, Brazil Main article: Southeast Region, Brazil </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18759220" rsv="1653.00">In this way, you will experience the rainforest but won't suffer too much hardship. We in the west have forgotten that life, but the people of the rainforest haven't. In the Ecuado</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8174361" rsv="1651.00">Phelsuma malamakibo is a terrestrial species that inhabits the evergreen rainforests, montane grassland, and heathland of Southern Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/sys</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="45394" rsv="1648.00">The Neotropic includes more tropical rainforest (tropical and subtropical moist broadleaf forests) than any other ecozone, extending from southern Mexico through Central America an</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="903" rsv="1641.00">A smaller, but important loss of arable land arises from the lack of renewal of rich flooding sediment due to flood control works. A large part of the arable land on earth is aroun</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="48139" rsv="1640.00">The Amazon Rainforest (Brazilian Portuguese: Floresta Amazônica or Amazônia; Spanish: Selva Amazónica or Amazonía) is a moist broadleaf forest in the Amazon Basin of South America.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18725460" rsv="1630.00">Chile boasts a great diversity of natural landscapes, from the Mars-like landscapes of the hyperarid Atacama Desert to the glacier-fed fjords of the Chilean Patagonia, passing by t</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012014">
		<snippet doc-id="939380" rsv="3782.00">Luigi first appeared in the arcade game Mario Bros., where he was featured as a main character alongside Mario. After his appearance in Super Mario World 2: Yoshi's Island, Kamek a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="399418" rsv="3660.00">Mario &amp;amp; Luigi: Superstar Saga, known in Japan as Mario &amp;amp; Luigi RPG (マリオ＆ルイージRPG, Mario ando Ruīji Ārupījī), is a role-playing game developed by AlphaDream and published by </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81345" rsv="3643.00">Another Nintendo source in the form of Super Smash Bros. Brawl has a trophy of Luigi that states Luigi to be, "Mario's younger twin brother." However, Solid Snake's Codec conversat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="153434" rsv="3438.00">Mario Golf is a sports video game series that was developed by Camelot Software Planning and published by Nintendo. The N64 and Game Boy Color versions can communicate each other v</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2257659" rsv="3427.00">This is a list of games that Mario has appeared in, or games with other Mario characters, organized by system. Over the years, Mario and his brother Luigi have appeared in several </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81341" rsv="3423.00">But our princess is in a another castle!" In Super Mario Bros. 2, a character named Toad made his first appearance as one of the four playable characters. When the later Mario Tenn</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="100061" rsv="3382.00">Wario is one of the original six playable characters and has been a playable character in every Mario Party game, with the exception of Mario Party Advance, where only Mario, Luigi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3624315" rsv="3295.00">Mario Golf (マリオゴルフ64, Mario Gorufu 64, Mario Golf 64) is a sports game developed by Camelot Software Planning and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo 64 in 1999. This game featu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81118" rsv="3295.00">In Luigi's Mansion, Professor E. Gadd arms Luigi with two of his inventions: the Poltergust 3000 and the Game Boy Horror. Luigi's Mansion begins with Luigi having won a mansion in </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="88528" rsv="3285.00">Paper Mario, known in Japan as Mario Story (マリオストーリー, Mario Sutōrī) is a role-playing (RPG) video game developed by Intelligent Systems and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo 6</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="100062" rsv="3269.00">Super Mario 64 (スーパーマリオ64, Sūpā Mario Rokujūyon) is a platform game developed by Nintendo Entertainment Analysis and Development and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo 64. Info</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2323682" rsv="3260.00">Other types of Goombas have appeared throughout the Mario series, although these largely vary from game to game. In The Super Mario Bros. Super Show! and The Adventures of Super Ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="389840" rsv="3240.00">Mario Kart: Double Dash!! is a racing game developed by Nintendo Entertainment Analysis and Development and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo GameCube. In April 2003, Nintendo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5249586" rsv="3212.00">In 1999, the Hudson game Mario Party was released for the Nintendo 64, a set of minigames for up to four players, with the most recent incarnation being Mario Party DS, which was r</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1902485" rsv="3208.00">Mario &amp;amp; Luigi: Partners in Time, known in Japan as Mario &amp;amp; Luigi RPG 2 (マリオ&amp;amp;ルイージRPG2, Mario ando Ruīji Ārupījī Tsū), is a console role-playing game developed by AlphaDr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1933408" rsv="3192.00">This article is a chronological list of Mario games. :Further information: List of Mario games by system and List of Mario games by genre Iconic Nintendo character Mario has appear</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81361" rsv="3178.00">His next appearance was in Super Mario Bros. for the Nintendo Entertainment System (NES), which would quickly be one of the most famous games on the console. 1996's  for the Super </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="81435" rsv="3171.00">For the video game starring her, see Super Princess Peach. Super Princess Peach marked the second time that Princess Peach was cast as the main hero in a video game, as Princess Pe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1394585" rsv="3155.00">However, most were first exposed to Mario's voice in the landmark 1996 game Super Mario 64. On November 15, 2007, Martinet made a guest appearance at the Game Store at Oxford Stree</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1577869" rsv="3142.00">The series achieved even greater success with Super Smash Bros. Melee, released in 2001 for the Nintendo GameCube, becoming the best selling game on that system. Since its release,</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012015">
		<snippet doc-id="13725692" rsv="2809.00">Example of widely used contactless smart cards are Hong Kong's Octopus card, Paris' Calypso_%28RFID%29/Navigo  and Lisbon' LisboaViva card, which predate the ISO/IEC 14443 standard</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1416441" rsv="2747.00">On 23 January 2008 the New South Wales government cancelled the Tcard contract with Integrated Transit Solutions Limited (ITSL). A replacement system, based on smart card technolog</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11582958" rsv="2708.00">San Francisco - In April 1999 the ERG Motorola Alliance was contracted to the largest smart card project in United States to design, build, operate and maintain the TransLink fare </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="59957" rsv="2560.00">A smart card, chip card, or integrated circuit card (ICC), is any pocket-sized card with embedded integrated circuits which can process data. A "smart card" is also characterized a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17171065" rsv="2548.00">OPUS is the name of a rechargeable contactless stored value smart card which is being gradually introduced in most of the  public transit systems in the Canadian province of Quebec</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10088295" rsv="2501.00">LuLuCa (ルルカ, LuLuCa) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Shizuoka, Japan, introduced by Shizuoka Railway (Shizutetsu) group, from Marc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="397763" rsv="2466.00">Near Field Communication or NFC, is a short-range high frequency wireless communication technology which enables the exchange of data between devices over about a 10 centimetre (ar</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2774698" rsv="2448.00">See Gemalto for current company information.Axalto was a smart card manufacturer with over 4,500 employees in 60 countries, one of the world's leading providers of microprocessor c</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="966955" rsv="2431.00">On December 3 2005, EZ-Link Pte Ltd announced that it was working with NETS to create a new hybrid card which will have the functions of both the EZ-Link card and the CashCard. Non</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5730712" rsv="2413.00">Like Suica and ICOCA, the underlying technology behind PiTaPa is Sony's FeliCa smart card system. "PiTaPa Basic Card" is the name given to the PiTaPa cards per se, and are issued b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="267624" rsv="2410.00">Making or recording a payment using the card for public transportation or while purchasing items at Octopus-enabled retailers can be done by holding the card against or waving it o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6880789" rsv="2407.00">myki (pronounced IPA: ) is the name of the contactless smartcard ticketing system to be introduced on public transport in Victoria, Australia. myki is designed to replace a number </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16886727" rsv="2362.00">Hayakaken (はやかけん, Hayakaken) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Fukuoka, Fukuoka Prefecture, Japan. Fukuoka City Transportation Burea</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16742549" rsv="2324.00">SAPICA (サピカ, Sapika) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Sapporo, Japan. The Sapporo IC Card Council (札幌ICカード協議会, Sapporo Aishī Kādo K</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13983074" rsv="2306.00">SUGOCA (スゴカ, Sugoka) is a Japanese rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Fukuoka Prefecture and the surrounding areas. SUGOCA will be introdu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10088292" rsv="2296.00">RapiCa (ラピカ, Rapika) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Kagoshima, Japan, introduced by Kagoshima City Transportation Bureau, Nangoku</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5027747" rsv="2295.00">This article is about the smart card ticket system. Pasmo (パスモ, Pasumo) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport introduced in Tokyo, Japan fr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12501708" rsv="2283.00">nimoca (ニモカ, Nimoka) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Fukuoka Prefecture, Japan. In future, there will be two other systems in Fuku</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2157976" rsv="2280.00">Similar to its predecessor "Seoul Bus Card", T-money can be used to pay for bus, subway and some taxi fares. Some stores and attractions including Lotte World amusement park, Kyobo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12501709" rsv="2277.00">Kitaca (キタカ, Kitaka) is a rechargeable contactless smart card ticketing system for public transport in Sapporo, Japan. Hokkaidō Railway Company (JR Hokkaidō) will introduce the sys</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012016">
		<snippet doc-id="6141751" rsv="3156.00">The Princess and the Frog will be a 2009 upcoming American musical feature film produced by Walt Disney Animation Studios and based upon the classic fairy tale The Frog Prince. The</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="357220" rsv="3031.00">This is a list of theatrical animated feature films produced and/or released by Walt Disney Productions/The Walt Disney Company: The following is a list of the fifty feature films </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5138153" rsv="2973.00">Enchanted is the first feature-length Disney live-action/traditional animation hybrid since Who Framed Roger Rabbit (1988), though the traditionally-animated characters do not inte</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2287636" rsv="2967.00">The name of the beautiful Sleeping Beauty is "Princess Aurora" (Latin for "dawn"), in this film, as it was in the original Tchaikovsky ballet; this name occurred in Perrault's vers</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2690296" rsv="2940.00">Princess Jasmine (Arabic: الأميرة ياسمين) is a fictional Arabian princess who originally appeared in the 1992 Disney film, Aladdin, followed with its two direct-to-video sequels, T</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="76361" rsv="2925.00">In 1989, Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs was added to the United States National Film Registry as being deemed "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant." Snow White </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="805496" rsv="2909.00">The Black Cauldron (also known as Taran and the Magic Cauldron in some countries) is the twenty-fifth animated feature in the Disney animated features canon. The Black Cauldron was</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="301574" rsv="2814.00">The Little Mermaid is a 1989 animated feature produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation with a pencil test beginning on September 23, 1988 and a first release on November 17, 1989 </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="492158" rsv="2801.00">Home on the Range is the 44th animated feature produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation and released by Walt Disney Pictures on April 2, 2004. The film is the forty-fifth animated</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="73170" rsv="2795.00">This article is about the Disney film. Aladdin is a 1992 animated feature produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, and released by Walt Disney Pictures on November 25, 1992. Char</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4744677" rsv="2791.00">Princess Ariel is a fictional character, a mermaid and the protagonist of Disney's 1989 animated film The Little Mermaid. Main article: The Little Mermaid (1989 film)As depicted in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4680612" rsv="2764.00">Meanwhile, Mushu tricks Shang into thinking Mulan is taking advantage of him. This means that Mushu gets to keep his job, and in his happiness, he accidentally reveals himself to S</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7942401" rsv="2740.00">The Annie Award for Best Animated Feature is an Annie Award, awarded annually to the best animated feature film and introduced in 1992. In 1998 the award was renamed Outstanding Ac</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="133462" rsv="2724.00">This film, one of the best known of the Disney studio's films, is based on the well-known fairy tale Beauty and the Beast, about a beautiful woman kept in a castle by a horrific mo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1970335" rsv="2719.00">This is a list of notable theatrical feature films produced by Walt Disney Productions and its successor label, Walt Disney Pictures. If Walt Disney Productions did not produce the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="358684" rsv="2713.00">The movie was released on May 20, 1994 and serves as the origin of the Aladdin animated series. After this, Jafar has Abis Mal take him to the palace, where he coerces Iago into se</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="55720" rsv="2709.00">This article is about the film "Mulan". Mulan is a 1998 animated feature film produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, and released by Walt Disney Pictures on June 19, 1998. The </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3395527" rsv="2703.00">Mickey's Magical Christmas: Snowed in at the House of Mouse is the first direct-to-video movie spin off from the Disney Channel animated television series House of Mouse. A snowsto</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11353299" rsv="2701.00">Disney Princess Enchanted Tales: Follow Your Dreams is a direct-to-video animated feature produced by DisneyToon Studios. It is the first film in the new Disney Princess Enchanted </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="399402" rsv="2684.00">Songs in the film include "A Dream Is a Wish Your Heart Makes", "Bibbidi-Bobbidi-Boo", "So This Is Love", "Sing Sweet Nightingale", "The Work Song", and "Cinderella." Cinderella wa</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012017">
		<snippet doc-id="7620833" rsv="3811.00">The Optimal Diet (or Optimal Nutrition) is a high fat, low carbohydrate diet developed by Polish doctor Jan Kwasniewski. The Optimal Diet has been used in Poland since the 1970s, b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="791546" rsv="3753.00">The "classic" ketogenic diet contains a 4:1 ratio by weight of fat to combined protein and carbohydrate. Most children improved in both seizure control and alertness: results that </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="437978" rsv="3706.00">The human body cannot store fat and burn fat at the same time, and Sears believes it takes time (significant time if insulin levels were high because of unbalanced eating) to switc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4330820" rsv="3421.00">The Atwater system (after Wilbur Olin Atwater) or derivatives of this system are used for the calculation of the available energy of foods. The Gross Energy of a food, as measured </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4297420" rsv="3339.00">The respiratory quotient (or RQ or respiratory coefficient), is a unitless number used in calculations of basal metabolic rate (BMR) when estimated from carbon dioxide production. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="459560" rsv="3245.00">The "Stillman Diet" is a high-protein, low-carbohydrate and low-fat diet. It is regarded as one of the first low-carbohydrate diets to become popular in the US.  Other low-carbohyd</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8095528" rsv="3215.00">During active weight loss, serum triglyceride levels decreased more and high-density lipoprotein cholesterol level increased more with the low-carbohydrate diet than with the low-f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="264746" rsv="3146.00">Saturated fat is fat that consists of triglycerides containing only saturated fatty acids. Harvard Nurses' Health Study found that diets lower in carbohydrate and higher in protein</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="215509" rsv="3117.00">For information on the dietary practices of Paleolithic humans, see Paleolithic#Diet and nutrition. The dietary regimen known as the Paleolithic diet (abbreviated paleo diet or pal</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="562788" rsv="3086.00">BMR decreases with age and with the loss of lean body mass. Increased muscle mass can increase BMR. Aerobic fitness level, a product of cardiovascular exercise, while previously th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8460" rsv="3071.00">Main article: Medical research related to low-carbohydrate dietsMany studies have focused on diets that reduce calories via a low-carbohydrate (Atkins diet, Scarsdale diet, Zone di</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="263487" rsv="3024.00">Researchers at the United States Department of Agriculture have investigated whether hydrogenation can be achieved without the side effect of trans fat production. Even within the </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7371778" rsv="2993.00">For a more comprehensive list, see the List of nutrition topics. Main article: History of nutrition Main article: Lists of nutrition topics </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5932" rsv="2985.00">The basic carbohydrate units are called monosaccharides, such as glucose, galactose, and fructose. The aldehyde or ketone group of a straight-chain monosaccharide will react revers</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="84121" rsv="2982.00">Atkins Nutritional Approach, popularly known as the Atkins Diet or just 'Atkins', is a well-known low-carbohydrate diet created by Dr.Robert Atkins from a diet he read in the Journ</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12534814" rsv="2932.00">It excludes dietary consumption of all carbohydrates and suggests fat as the main source of energy with sufficient protein. Stefansson and a friend later volunteered for a one year</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="613420" rsv="2927.00">According to the Atkin's diet, the low carbohydrate content of pork rinds makes them more nutritious than some low-fat snack foods, such as high-carbohydrate, fat-free pretzels. Sc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="66575" rsv="2902.00">A nutrient is food or chemicals that an organism needs to live and grow or a substance used in an organism's metabolism which must be taken in from its environment. A nutrient is e</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9503943" rsv="2885.00">Grain mixes with added molasses are usually called "Sweet feed" in the USA and "Coarse mix" in the United Kingdom. To do so, horse feed is measured by weight, not volume. Horses ac</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="305679" rsv="2875.00">A significant fraction of the human body is water. There are many methods that can be used to determine body water. Another method of determining total body water percentage (TBW%)</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012018">
		<snippet doc-id="286368" rsv="2094.00">For the Police Interceptor version used by law enforcement, see Ford Crown Victoria Police Interceptor. The Ford Crown Victoria is the current model name Ford uses for the rear-whe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="523329" rsv="2060.00">Corgi Toys first appeared in July 1956, manufactured by Mettoy Playcraft Ltd. in Swansea, Wales, as direct competition to Meccano's Dinky Toys model vehicles, which had dominated t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3399893" rsv="2037.00">Aside from the modified car drivers found at cruises there are several other groups which can be found at most cruises. Cruising and modifying have long been represented in the com</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="321651" rsv="2017.00">An example of a boy racer car of the old generation is the Ford Escort (both the early rear wheel drive versions such as the RS2000 and the later XR3i variants) due to their low co</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9092216" rsv="2004.00">Full-size Ford is the popular term for a long-running line of Ford vehicles which have been produced in North America with a large degree of similarity since the Model T in 1908, u</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1321710" rsv="1997.00">The phrase panda car refers to a small or medium-sized police car operated by British police forces. The first use of Panda cars seems to have been in Lancashire Constabulary area </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="331097" rsv="1991.00">The Saab 9-5 is an executive car produced by the Swedish automobile maker Saab. By 2008 this engine was producing 260HP even in the non-Aero model (US model). Currently, the 260hp </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="897080" rsv="1985.00">The Nash Metropolitan is a car that was sold from 1954 to 1962. In October 1956, Austin Motor Company obtained permission from American Motors to sell the Metropolitans in overseas</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5037907" rsv="1952.00">The Crown Victoria Police Interceptor (often referred to simply as CVPI or P71) is the law enforcement version of the Ford Crown Victoria. From 1993–1998, the police car models of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3612161" rsv="1946.00">Since the termination of the Chevrolet Caprice product, most police departments currently use the Ford Crown Victoria Police Interceptor as the standard patrol car. There are many </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1297380" rsv="1946.00">Commonly known names to describe police cars are (police) cruiser, squad car, panda car, area car and patrol car. In some areas of the world, the police car has become more widely </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="644652" rsv="1945.00">"Headlines" is a segment on The Tonight Show with Jay Leno airing weekly. Since the early 1980s, David Letterman has been doing a similar segment called "Small Town News" (albeit o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="623020" rsv="1938.00">The Lamborghini Gallardo (/ɡalˈlaɾdo/) is a sports car built by Lamborghini. At current U.S. prices, a 2008 Lamborghini Gallardo coupe costs USD $186,250 - $222,800, while a 2008 L</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="996951" rsv="1923.00">Throughout the James Bond series of films and novels Q Branch has given Bond a wide variety of vehicles with which to battle his enemies. Live and Let Die:(Two 1973 Chevrolet Novas</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1475902" rsv="1918.00">Dirty Mary, Crazy Larry is a cult 1974 car chase film starring Peter Fonda, Susan George, Adam Roarke, and Vic Morrow. White and Hanson (who, at the time, owned Eveready Batteries </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="725503" rsv="1910.00">Road &amp;amp; Track magazine considered the Valiant to be "one of the best all-around domestic cars." The Valiant was its own marque and advertised as the Valiant by Chrysler Corp wit</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2186972" rsv="1909.00">The Toronto Police Service (TPS), formerly the Metropolitan Toronto Police,  is the police force for the City of Toronto, Ontario, Canada. Toronto Police Department (up to 1953), M</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11693386" rsv="1903.00">During this time, Chrysler began designing the replacement for the then-new Dodge Dynasty, which was a mid-size car. The first generation of LH cars debuted with fanfare at the 199</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18101227" rsv="1900.00">This is partially true, however, as the wagon model from the B-pillar back was a carryover from the first-generation. Also with this generation, each model of Taurus received diffe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6179218" rsv="1897.00">Most popular in this category are 1:18 scale diecast automobile replicas. During the infancy of the 1:18 scale, Ertl and Revell were 2 of the few manufacturers selling a limited nu</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012019">
		<snippet doc-id="66400" rsv="2530.00">The American name to 106 was objectionable to some because Glenn T. Seaborg was still alive and hence his name could not be used for an element in accordance with the IUPAC rules. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="311180" rsv="2345.00">Prout's hypothesis was an early 19th century attempt to explain the existence of the various chemical elements through a hypothesis regarding the internal structure of the atom. In</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="164644" rsv="2183.00">Albert Ghiorso (born 15 July 1915) is an American nuclear scientist who helped discover numerous chemical elements on the periodic table. Albert Einstein was his idol scientist. He</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8174364" rsv="2143.00">Samuel Ruben met Professor Bergen Davis of Columbia University who tutored him and allowed him to sit in on some Columbia classes. Samuel Ruben established Ruben Laboratories in th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5659" rsv="2139.00">Put another way, a chemical element cannot be transformed into other chemical elements by chemical processes. The atomic number of an element, Z, is equal to the number of protons </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="104395" rsv="2121.00">This work provided evidence in favour of the atomic theory proposed by John Dalton: that inorganic chemical compounds are composed of atoms combined in whole number amounts. In dis</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1073114" rsv="2100.00">Gadolin discovered the chemical element yttrium. The oxide of the element gadolinium, gadolinia, was named after Gadolin by its discoverers. In an earlier paper in 1788 Gadolin sho</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8200" rsv="2086.00">The discovery of the elements known to exist today is presented here in chronological order. The elements are listed generally in the order in which each was first defined as the p</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10777" rsv="2077.00">Friedrich Wöhler (31 July 1800 - 23 September 1882) was a German chemist, best-known for his synthesis of urea, but also the first to isolate several of the elements. Wöhler was al</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="191850" rsv="2073.00">Louis Nicolas Vauquelin (May 16, 1763 - November 14, 1829), was a French pharmacist and chemist. In 1791 he was made a member of the Academy of Sciences and from that time he helpe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1267459" rsv="2060.00">Andrés Manuel del Río Fernández (Madrid, November 10, 1764 — Mexico City, March 23, 1849) was a Spanish–Mexican scientist and naturalist who discovered the chemical element vanadiu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="153260" rsv="2047.00">Friedrich Ernst Dorn (27 July 1848 – 16 December 1916) was a German physicist who was the first to discover that a radioactive substance, later named radon, is emitted from radium.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="191838" rsv="2045.00">Antoine Jérôme Balard (30 September 1802 - 30 April 1876) was a French chemist and the discoverer of bromine. This achievement brought him the reputation that secured his election </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="150986" rsv="2023.00">Charles Hatchett (2 January 1765 - 10 March 1847) was an English chemist who discovered the element niobium. Hatchett was born, raised, and lived in London. Since 1979, the Institu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13120" rsv="2015.00">Glenn Theodore Seaborg (Swedish: Glenn Teodor Sjöberg) (April 19, 1912 – February 25, 1999) won the 1951 Nobel Prize in Chemistry for "discoveries in the chemistry of the transuran</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="59483" rsv="2015.00">Scheele described the discovery of oxygen and nitrogen (1772-1773), in his only book, Chemische Abhandlung von der Luft und dem Feuer (Chemical Treatise on Air and Fire) in 1777, l</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7562549" rsv="2013.00">The ACS National Historic Chemical Landmarks Program was launched by the American Chemical Society in 1992 and has recognized 60 landmarks to date. The project is part of the ACS D</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="62200" rsv="2008.00">For example, although ununoctium is a member of the noble gas group, it could have a higher chemical reactivity than some elements outside this group. In addition to being far more</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="21278" rsv="2008.00">Following initial work between 1958-1964, in 1966, a team at the Flerov Laboratory of Nuclear Reactions (FLNR) reported that they had been able to detect 250Fm from the decay of a </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="352146" rsv="2006.00">When Fajans worked at the laboratory of Ernest Rutherford (with Henry G. Moseley) he was researching properties of the radioactive rows. Afterwards Fajans was working on the electr</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012020">
		<snippet doc-id="16621051" rsv="2070.00">Two new denominations were issued in the series, the NT$200 and NT$2,000.Notes From a Small Island, Virginia Sheng, Government Information Office, 1 September 2000 The NT$100 and N</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15313075" rsv="1981.00">The Estonian 100 Krooni bill (100 EEK) is a denomination of the Estonian currency. Lydia Koidula, who was an Estonian poetess and playwrigh (1843-1886), is featured on the front si</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12572331" rsv="1975.00">Danish writer Karen Blixen is currently featured on the front side of the bill, while the design on the reverse is inspired by a centaur from Landet Church on the island of Tåsinge</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15312026" rsv="1936.00">The Estonian 500 Krooni bill (500 EEK) is a denomination of the Estonian currency . Carl Robert Jakobson, who was an Estonian politician, publisher, writer and promoter of agricult</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1710548" rsv="1929.00">Two significant changes were made to the circulation of the Portrait Series since its beginning. Banknotes signed by BCCS Chairman Richard Hu (September 1999), MAS Chairman PM and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9738183" rsv="1888.00">The reverse of the 10 litų banknote features Lithuanian heroes, Steponas Darius and Stasys Girėnas. The 20 litų banknote released in 1930 also featured the same Statue of Liberty o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="208286" rsv="1863.00">In 1988, Austria produced the 5000 Schilling banknote (Mozart), which is the first foil application (Kinegram) to a paper banknote in the history of banknote printing. In 1988, aft</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="615913" rsv="1840.00">The EURion constellation is a pattern of symbols found on a number of banknote designs since about 1996. The EURion constellation is most prominent and was therefore first recognis</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3671365" rsv="1780.00">The issuing of banknotes in Northern Ireland is regulated by the Currency and Bank Notes Act 1928, the Coinage Act 1971, Bank Notes (Ireland) Act 1864 (c. 78), Bank Notes (Ireland)</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="334169" rsv="1746.00">Prince Shōtoku (聖徳太子, Shōtoku Taishi, 573–621), also known as Prince Umayado  (厩戸皇子, Umayado no ōji), was a regent and a politician of the Asuka period in Japan. "From the sovereig</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15313964" rsv="1743.00">The Estonian 25 Krooni bill (25 EEK) is a denomination of the Estonian currency . Anton Hansen Tammsaare, who was a famous Estonian writer of classical literature (1870-1940), is f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="54072" rsv="1730.00">Cyprus and Malta will not print euro notes for the time being, and will use previously issued banknotes from other eurozone member states. However, country codes have been reserved</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="596249" rsv="1692.00">The 10-peso banknote was issued months after the 5-piso banknote was issued. The reverse side of the banknote features the Barasoain Church in Malolos, Bulacan, site of the first P</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="477336" rsv="1668.00">The United States twenty-dollar bill ($20) is a denomination of United States currency. U.S. President Andrew Jackson is currently featured on the front side of the bill, which is </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11933037" rsv="1668.00">For stamp collecting, see Philately. For coin collecting, see Numismatic terminology. Notaphily is the study of paper money or banknotes. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1993277" rsv="1663.00">Saint Agnes of Bohemia (Czech: Svatá Anežka Česká), or Agnes of Prague (1211-March 6, 1282), was a medieval Bohemian princess who opted for a life of charity and piety over a life </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13261356" rsv="1661.00">Banknotes were issued in 1943 by the British Army for circulation in Tripolitania. The main feature of the notes is depiction of a lion standing on the King's Crown. The currency t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2341370" rsv="1661.00">The customary design of banknotes in most countries is a portrait of a notable citizen on the front (or obverse) and a different motif on the back (or reverse) - often something re</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="383936" rsv="1645.00">The new name is literally translated as "strong bolívar", but also references an old coin called the Peso fuerte worth 10 Spanish reales.. Coins are in denominations of 1, 5, 10, 1</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1403932" rsv="1642.00">Polymer banknotes also incorporate many security features not available to paper banknotes, making counterfeiting much more difficult. Trading as Securency, the RBA together with I</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012021">
		<snippet doc-id="12196101" rsv="3555.00">Beyond Vaudeville was a public access television show on Time Warner Cable in New York City that ran from 1986 to 1996. The show eventually made the move to network TV as Oddville,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7195382" rsv="3323.00">Susan Griffiths is a TV actress and popular Marilyn Monroe look-alike. She has been a Marilyn Monroe impersonator in "Legends in Concert" (1991). Since introducing her talents Susa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9055591" rsv="3285.00">As one of the most iconic actresses of the 20th century, Marilyn Monroe is frequently depicted and referenced in popular culture. The only volumes published while she was living wa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19318" rsv="2977.00">The newly formed Marilyn Monroe Productions would be paid $100,000 plus a share of profits for each film. Despite Monroe and Olivier clashing, Olivier later commented that in the f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8731260" rsv="2853.00">Mark Bellinghaus (born July 20, 1963), is a Marilyn Monroe activist and a collector of Monroe memorabilia. It was promoted as the "biggest and best collection of Marilyn Monroe mem</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4608195" rsv="2823.00">Toshiyuki Nishida was nominated for the Best Actor award at the 2004 Japanese Academy Awards for his performance as the head of a yakuza clan. The Japanese title  'Geroppa!'  is th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18062558" rsv="2743.00">Strawhead is a 1982 play by American writer Norman Mailer and Richard G. Hannum about Hollywood icon Marilyn Monroe. After deciding that Fitzpatrick was perfect to play Marilyn Mon</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="180417" rsv="2729.00">The Pierce Brothers Westwood Village Memorial Park Cemetery is located at 1218 Glendon Avenue in the Westwood Village area of Los Angeles, California. That changed over the years, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10018022" rsv="2661.00">The premiere featured contestants impersonating Little Richard, Howard Stern, Jack Nicholson, George W. Bush, Bono, Angelina Jolie, Celine Dion, Al Pacino, Lucille Ball, Simon Cowe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="848349" rsv="2599.00">Bardot became the first Australian act to debut at the #1 position with both its debut single, "Poison", and self-titled debut album. In July 2001, the group released "ASAP", the f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1957472" rsv="2580.00">The film featured Ashley Judd as Norma Jean Dougherty and Mira Sorvino as Marilyn Monroe. It was partially-based on "Norma Jean: My Secret Life With Marilyn Monroe" by actor Ted Jo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1228430" rsv="2541.00">In 1961, Dr. Ralph Greenson advised Marilyn Monroe, then living in an apartment on North Doheny Drive in Beverly Hills, to recruit Murray as a housekeeper/companion. In a photograp</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4292152" rsv="2540.00">The death of Marilyn Monroe is one of the most debated conspiracy theories of the twentieth century. Greenson himself refused to talk to Slatzer, having reacted to Norman Mailer's </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="554052" rsv="2534.00">The central role of Mrs. Johnstone has been played by, among others, Stephanie Lawrence, Clodagh Rodgers, Kiki Dee, Lyn Paul, Siobhan McCarthy, and four of the Nolan sisters (Linda</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2181741" rsv="2534.00">Media attention over the choice of North in the role that Monroe rejected resulted in North appearing on the cover of Life magazine with the coverline "Sheree North Takes Over From</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="179091" rsv="2515.00">The 1960s version of the group included Frank Sinatra, Dean Martin, Sammy Davis, Jr., Joey Bishop, Peter Lawford, and for a brief stint, Norman Fell. Marilyn Monroe, Angie Dickinso</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10553349" rsv="2512.00">Mister Lonely is a 2007 film directed by Harmony Korine, and co-written with his brother Avi Korine. During a show in an old people's home Michael Jackson meets Marilyn Monroe. Mis</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14286866" rsv="2498.00">This article is about the digital creation of virtual human beings. The process of creating such a virtual human on film, substituting for an existing actor, is known, after a 1992</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="76366" rsv="2479.00">For other uses, see Some Like It Hot (disambiguation). Some Like It Hot is a 1959 comedy film directed by Billy Wilder and starring Marilyn Monroe, Tony Curtis, and Jack Lemmon. Ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="468301" rsv="2462.00">Morton began her career as a child actor. Starring roles in Band of Gold (1995), and the film Under the Skin in 1997, raised her profile in the UK. The latter impressed Woody Allen</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012022">
		<snippet doc-id="618884" rsv="2672.00">Thermes de Cluny are an ancient Gallo-Roman ruin lying in the heart of Paris' 5th arrondissement and which are partly subsumed into the Musée de Moyen Age- Hôtel de Cluny. The best</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14358690" rsv="2492.00">The triumphal arch near the Roman town of Glanum, just outside Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, shows Roman soldiers leading away defeated prisoners. It was built according to the principle</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2068003" rsv="2485.00">For Gaul before the Roman conquest, see Gaul.Roman Gaul consisted of an area of provincial rule in the Roman Empire, in modern day France, Belgium, Luxembourg, and western Germany.</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2067852" rsv="2468.00">Dating to the first quarter of the first century AD, it originally stood in a temple in the Gallo-Roman civitas of Lutetia (modern Paris, France) and is one of the earliest pieces </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="618873" rsv="2400.00">The term Gallo-Roman describes the Romanized culture of Gaul under the rule of the Roman Empire. Gallo-Roman language persisted in the northeast into the Silva Carbonaria that form</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2929895" rsv="2362.00">Gallo-Roman religion was a fusion of Roman religious forms and modes of worship with Gaulish deities from . The imperial cult, centred primarily on the numen of Augustus, came to p</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2462183" rsv="2334.00">After the invasion of Chlodio the Roman armies at the Rhine-border became a Frankish "franchise", and Franks were known to levy Roman-like troops that were supported by a Roman-lik</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2691084" rsv="2320.00">The Arènes de Lutèce are among the most important remains from the Gallo-Roman era in Paris (formerly known as Lutèce in French or Lutetia in Latin), together with the Thermes de C</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1846758" rsv="2196.00">In 1511 he edited a new edition of De Architectura of the classical Roman writer Vitruvius, a book that had a major influence on the development of Renaissance architecture. He pub</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2698471" rsv="2151.00">La Graufesenque is an archaeological site 2km from Millau, Aveyron, France at the junction of the Tarn and Dourbie rivers. As Condatomagus (market of the confluent) it was famous i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="203582" rsv="2125.00">Syagrius preserved his father's rump state between the Somme and the Loire around Soissons after the collapse of central rule in the Western Empire, the so-called "Kingdom" of Syag</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2815281" rsv="2112.00">The antrustion was always of Frankish descent, and only in certain exceptional cases were Gallo-Romans admitted into the king's bodyguard. These Gallo-Romans then took the name of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="473019" rsv="2104.00">See also: History of ParisLutetia (sometimes Lutetia Parisiorum or Lucotecia, in French Lutèce) was a town in pre-Roman and Roman Gaul. The Gallo-Roman city was a forerunner of the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="36545" rsv="2099.00">Main articles: Roman Gaul and Gallo-Roman cultureThe Gaulish culture then was massively submerged by Roman culture, Latin was adopted by the Gauls, Gaul was absorbed into the Roman</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="353326" rsv="2081.00">The Hôtel de Cluny is partially constructed on the remains of Gallo-Roman baths dating from the third century (known as the Thermes de Cluny ), which are famous in their own right </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="21724" rsv="2079.00">Normandy (French: Normandie, Norman: Normaundie) is a geographical region corresponding to the former Duchy of Normandy. The descendants of Rollo and his followers adopted the loca</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2508454" rsv="2069.00">On sloping sites the cryptoporticus is often partially at ground level and supports a structure such as a forum or Roman villa, in which case it served as basis villae. The cryptop</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="263867" rsv="2048.00">Beauvais is a town and commune of northern France, préfecture (capital) of the Oise département. Main article: Beauvais CathedralIts cathedral, dedicated to Saint Peter (Cathédrale</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1126654" rsv="1997.00">During Roman times, a road linked Fécamp to Étretat, passing through the present-day village of Fond-Pitron. The history of Fécamp has always revolved around the fishing industry a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="86038" rsv="1981.00">In Celtic mythology, Arduinna (Arduina, Arduinnae, Arduinne) was the eponymous goddess of the Ardennes Forest and region, represented as a huntress riding a boar (primarily in the </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012023">
		<snippet doc-id="2772917" rsv="2857.00">Flute repertory is the general term for pieces composed for flute (particularly Western concert flute) and often played by flutists (or flautists). Pieces with an "(O)" originally </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2447312" rsv="2788.00">Bülent Evcil (born 1968) is a Turkish solo flutist and is the winner of the Royal Belgium Encouragement Medal of Art. He received the second place award in the Best Overall Perform</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18733165" rsv="2759.00">2000 "Klangillusion" for flute, piano, cello: 8' 1999 "Gemma" for solo flute: 6' 1989 Concerto for solo trombone and symphony orchestra 17' </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="617767" rsv="2752.00">The Symphony No. 15 in A major (Opus 141), Dmitri Shostakovich's last, was written in a little over a month during the summer of 1971 in Repino. The symphony is notable for many th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9773093" rsv="2682.00">Benjamin-Gunnar Cohrs (born 21 September 1965 in Hameln) is a German conductor, scholar, and publicist on music. Benjamin-Gunnar Cohrs gave his early conducting debut 1984 with the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8515261" rsv="2673.00">After being in the US for only 5 months, Chen won both the Young Artist Competition sponsored by the New World Youth Orchestras and Young Composer's Contest sponsored by the Univer</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15456860" rsv="2645.00">Born in Sisak, Croatia, Miletić graduated violin from the Zagreb Music Academy in 1953, in the class of Prof. Stjepan Šulek and I. Pinkava, and chamber music in the class of Antoni</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="620890" rsv="2633.00">Roussel was also interested in jazz, and wrote a piano-vocal composition entitled Jazz dans la nuit, which makes an interesting contrast to some of the other jazz-inspired composit</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4451623" rsv="2621.00">Lee has composed over a hundred works: six symphonies, ten string quartets, concerti for various instruments, choral works, song cycles and scores of chamber works. The rest - chor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1872612" rsv="2615.00">Toshi Ichiyanagi (一柳 慧, Ichiyanagi Toshi,  born 4 February 1933, Kobe, Japan) is a Japanese composer of avant-garde music. One of his most notable works is the 1960 composition, Ka</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19193763" rsv="2610.00">The following is an incomplete listof works by the polish composer Krzysztof Penderecki. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="596925" rsv="2590.00">Ernst Toch (pronounced [toʜ]) (7 December 1887 - 1 October 1964) was a composer of classical music and film scores. Toch was born in Vienna. Toch won the Pulitzer Prize for Music i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1816680" rsv="2573.00">Fauré had a major influence on Koechlin; in fact Koechlin wrote the first Fauré biography (1927), a work which is still of value. His compositions include the four symphonic poems </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1056463" rsv="2572.00">Eugène Joseph Bozza (April 4 1905 – September 28 1991) was a French composer. His chamber music for winds shows great familiarity with the capabilities of the instruments, often de</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16410974" rsv="2566.00">Viktor Kalabis (1923–2006) was a Czech composer. The Viktor Kalabis &amp;amp; Zuzana Růžičková Foundation was established in his memory. The Viktor Kalabis and Zuzana Růžičková Foundat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7652632" rsv="2556.00">Yeagley began playing the piano at the age of eleven. Yeagley received a Bachelor of Music degree in Piano Performance and Composition from the Oberlin Conservatory of Music, a Mas</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3896810" rsv="2547.00">This is a list of Mieczysław Weinberg's compositions by opus number. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1625597" rsv="2543.00">Dorff is currently composer-in-residence for the Haddonfield Symphony. His works have been commissioned by such ensembles as the Philadelphia Orchestra and the Minnesota Orchestra,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="141849" rsv="2540.00">Widor's best-known single piece for the organ is the final movement, Toccata, from his Symphony for Organ No. 5, which is often played as a recessional at wedding ceremonies and ev</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8146502" rsv="2533.00">Pedro Eustache (born August 18, 1959), is a creative solo flautist - "World Music" woodwinds-reeds-wind synthesizers and composer with extensive academic studies and more than 35 y</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012024">
		<snippet doc-id="294843" rsv="1524.00">Ursula Andress as 'Honey Ryder' in Dr. No (1962) is often considered the first and quintessential Bond Girl,  although Eunice Gayson, as 'Sylvia Trench', and Zena Marshall as 'Miss</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7708702" rsv="1445.00">Grunther is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service. Braun is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service. Felsen is a henchman in t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7708957" rsv="1444.00">A list of henchmen from the 1999 James Bond film The World Is Not Enough from the List of James Bond henchmen Gabor is a henchman in the James Bond film The World Is Not Enough. La</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10378603" rsv="1436.00">Bond Girls Are Forever is a 2002 James Bond documentary film hosted by actress Maryam d'Abo, who had played the role of Kara Milovy in the 15th James Bond film The Living Daylights</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2591028" rsv="1424.00">Philip Bond was born in Lancashire, England in 1966, and is "the son of a preacherman." His earliest comics work came out of his being "active in the British alternative comics sce</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19398853" rsv="1417.00">James Bond (also known as I Wish I Was James Bond) will be the sixth and final single from Scouting for Girls' debut album, Scouting for Girls. The song is about the spy James Bond</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2730931" rsv="1400.00">Dr. Christmas Jones is a fictional character from the James Bond movie The World Is Not Enough. Denise Richards has stated that she liked that her character was a Bond girl that wa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1484173" rsv="1400.00">Pussy Galore is a fictional character from the James Bond film and novel Goldfinger. Blackman and Diana Rigg are furthermore the only two Bond girls who are older than Bond himself</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12641342" rsv="1394.00">The Rich Central Campus serves the cities of Olympia Fields, Matteson, Richton Park, Country Club Hills, Chicago Heights, and Tinley Park. It is a part of Rich Township District 22</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1492745" rsv="1390.00">Vivienne "Viv" Michel is the main fictional character in Ian Fleming's James Bond novel The Spy Who Loved Me. At the time she meets Bond, Viv is 23 years old. Viv possesses some un</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7737220" rsv="1389.00">Kerim Bey is a Bond ally from the James Bond film From Russia with Love. When going to a Gypsy Camp, Bond and Kerim are interrupted by Krilencu's men who attempted to kill Kerim. R</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10481254" rsv="1387.00">Practically alone of all major Bond Girls of the Fleming canon, Gala Brand has not appeared as a character in a James Bond film, the movie version of the novel being an almost tota</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1891478" rsv="1377.00">Honeychile Rider is a fictional character in Ian Fleming's James Bond novel Dr. No. In the 1962 Bond film of the same name, her name was shortened and changed to Honey Ryder. The c</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13387115" rsv="1362.00">Sue Bond is a blonde British actress, cabaret singer, and comedienne best remembered for her appearances on The Benny Hill Show in the early 1970s. Alongside of her acting Sue also</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2235752" rsv="1359.00">}"Die Another Day" is the theme to the James Bond film of the same name recorded by Madonna. The single, released in late 2002, peaked at number eight in the United States and #3 i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12149652" rsv="1352.00">Teresa "Tracy" Bond (born Teresa "Tracy" Draco, and also known as the Contessa Teresa di Vicenzo) is a fictional character in the James Bond film and novel On Her Majesty's Secret </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18597979" rsv="1348.00">Under Construction Cellophane is the third album by the English rock band The Troggs, released in 1967. The album was re-released in 2003 with twelve bonus tracks by Repertoire Rec</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14701897" rsv="1348.00">Gemma Christina Arterton (born January 1986, in Gravesend, Kent) is an English actress. Arterton and her sister, Hannah Jane Arterton (born 1989, Gravesend), were raised by their f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16058740" rsv="1344.00">The following is a list of cast members who have portrayed characters appearing in the James Bond film series. The list is sorted by film and character, because of multiple actors </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9593869" rsv="1339.00">For the first time in a Bond film there is something that could be called emotion.” And another, “Bond is back with a bang.” Thus, the 21st Bond film, Casino Royale (2006), in addi</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012025">
		<snippet doc-id="142331" rsv="4421.00">In each case, except the Indo-Pakistani War of 1971, where the dispute concerned East Pakistan, the casus belli was the disputed Kashmir region. This resulted in the breaking out o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4500730" rsv="4005.00">Sardar Patel had argued against both, describing Kashmir as a bilateral dispute and its accession as justified by international law.In 1957, Kashmir was fully integrated into the U</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="429559" rsv="3989.00">The Tashkent Declaration of January 10, 1966 was a peace agreement between India and Pakistan. In September of 1965 before the two had engaged in the short run Indo-Pakistani War o</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16657283" rsv="3974.00">General Ashraf Rashid (Urdu: أشرف رشيد) (May 23 1948 – October 2 2004) was a Pakistani general and the former head of the Special Service Group division within the Pakistan Army fr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3665169" rsv="3942.00">The Lahore Declaration was a bilateral agreement between India and Pakistan signed on February 21, 1999 by the then-Prime Minister of India Atal Bihari Vajpayee and the then-Prime </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18023108" rsv="3919.00">Since the successful launch of the Delhi-Lahore Bus in 1999, both nations have worked to established multiple bus and train services connecting cities across the borders in the Pun</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="803754" rsv="3870.00">The Kargil War, also known as the Kargil conflict,(I) was an armed conflict between India and Pakistan that took place between May and July 1999 in the Kargil district of Kashmir. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="696760" rsv="3857.00">The Simla Agreement  was signed between India and Pakistan at 12:40am on July 3, 1972. Simla Agreement on Bilateral Relations between India and Pakistan signed by Prime Minister In</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5015591" rsv="3851.00">Operation Meghdoot was the name given to the attack launched by the Indian Military to capture the Siachen Glacier in the disputed Kashmir region, precipitating the Siachen Conflic</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14294333" rsv="3800.00">Lieutenant General Muhammad Masood Aslam SJ (born September 1, 1952) is the principal commander of Pakistan Army fighting the pro-Taliban forces in the Waziristan theater, part of </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8313471" rsv="3771.00">The Siachen Conflict, sometimes referred to as The Siachen War was a military conflict between India and Pakistan over the disputed Siachen Glacier region in Kashmir. In the 1970s </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2034675" rsv="3762.00">The Battle of Tololing was one of the pivotal battles in the Kargil War between India's armed forces and troops from the Northern Light Infantry who were aided by other Pakistan ba</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15734948" rsv="3757.00">The 7th Infantry Division, also known as the Golden Arrow (after its formation sign) and Peshawar Division, (after its garrison city) is the Pakistan Armys oldest and most battle-h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17981867" rsv="3746.00">The Srinagar-Muzaffarabad Bus is a passenger bus service connecting Srinagar, the capital of the Indian state of Jammu and Kashmir (also Indian-administered Kashmir) with Muzaffara</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5740934" rsv="3732.00">General Muhammad Aziz Khan (born January 1, 1947) is a retired Pakistani general who served as the Chairman Joint Chiefs of Staff, Chief of General Staff (CGS) and Commander IV Cor</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16945685" rsv="3705.00">The Delhi-Lahore Bus is a passenger bus service connecting the Indian capital of Delhi with the city of Lahore, Pakistan via the border transit post at Wagah. While the bus service</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5174257" rsv="3692.00">The 2001-2002 India-Pakistan standoff was a military standoff between India and Pakistan that resulted in the amassing of troops on either side of the International Border (IB) and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3872983" rsv="3639.00">Operation Safed Sagar was the codename assigned to the Indian Air Force's strike to support the Ground troops during Operation Vijay that was aimed to flush out Regular and Irregul</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="506952" rsv="3637.00">The Indo-Pakistani War of 1947, sometimes known as the First Kashmir War, was fought between India and Pakistan over the region of Kashmir from 1947 to 1948. In the Punch valley th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3030955" rsv="3596.00">Since the 1990s, the Indian state of Indian administered Jammu and Kashmir has been hit by confrontation between Kashmiri separatists, including militants whom India alleges are su</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012026">
		<snippet doc-id="18948043" rsv="3040.00">Main articles: Short-term effects of alcohol, Long-term effects of alcohol, Alcohol and cancer, Alcohol and cardiovascular disease, and Recommended maximum intake of alcoholic beve</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="404063" rsv="2918.00">Main article: Binge drinkingBinge drinking is sometimes defined as drinking alcohol solely for the purpose of intoxication, although it is quite common for binge drinking to apply </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5600440" rsv="2867.00">This article summarizes the recommended maximum intake (or 'safe limits') of alcohol as recommended by the health agencies of various governments. Main articles: Fetal alcohol synd</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="337566" rsv="2855.00">A meta-analysis of 35 previous studies of the effect of alcohol consumption on stroke risk found that: "Compared with abstainers, consumption of more than 60 g of alcohol per day (</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5770231" rsv="2781.00">The relationship between alcohol consumption and health has been the subject of formal scientific research since at least 1926, when Dr. Raymond Pearl published his book, Alcohol a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7697517" rsv="2745.00">College health professionals are often members of a national body, such as the American College Health Association. Marijuana use among college students is only topped by alcohol. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2797132" rsv="2724.00">Understanding specifically how alcohol improves cardiovascular health and reduces disease also significantly increases scientific confidence in the health benefits of moderate drin</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="295446" rsv="2695.00">Because mare's milk contains more sugars than the cow's or goat's milk fermented into kefir, kumis has a higher, though still mild, alcohol content. Kumis itself has a very low lev</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2701591" rsv="2671.00">In spite of the ideal of moderation, consumption of alcohol was often high. However, in 1690, England passed "An Act for the Encouraging of the Distillation of Brandy and Spirits f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3363" rsv="2671.00">For other uses, see Beer (disambiguation). Some of mankind's earliest known writings refer to the production and distribution of beer: the Code of Hammurabi included laws regulatin</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2322041" rsv="2668.00">The European Union and World Health Organization (WHO) have both specified that the advertising and promotion of alcohol needs to be controlled. This article on alcohol advertising</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1637334" rsv="2665.00">Armagnac (pronounced ) is a distinctive kind of brandy or eau de vie produced in the Armagnac region in Gascony, southwest France. Production is overseen by INAO and the Bureau Nat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1946" rsv="2663.00">In Britain a unit of alcohol is defined as 10 millilitres (or approximately 8 grams) of ethanol (ethyl alcohol). The number of units of alcohol in a drink can be determined by mult</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2842910" rsv="2660.00">The research evidence includes a study of over 120,000 subjects in the Netherlands that found no significant relationship between drinking and bladder cancer,  a study of high alco</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18617528" rsv="2637.00">In the United States, the term Prohibition refers to the period from 1920 to 1933, during which the sale, manufacture, and transportation of alcohol for consumption were banned nat</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="319138" rsv="2591.00">Therefore, the alcohol in wine could be a factor in the French paradox. Law and Wald (1999) used Criqui and Ringel’s (1994) study of alcohol and diet in explaining the French parad</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11651736" rsv="2564.00">Alcohol powder is a powder that will produce an alcoholic drink when mixed with water. When mixed with 0,25 litres of water it gives a drink with 4.8 % alcohol. Director Wim van Da</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19329865" rsv="2558.00">The short-term effects of alcohol on the human body can take several forms. They tend to over estimate the effects of alcohol. Other creatures are not immune to the effects of alco</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18450716" rsv="2506.00">Moderate alcohol consumption 30-60 minutes before bedtime catalyzes disruptions in sleep maintenance and sleep architecture that are mediated by blood alcohol levels [2]. Under con</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="32961" rsv="2494.00">For other uses, see Wine (disambiguation). One recent study suggests that for normal drinkers, vintage year may not be as significant to perceived wine quality as currently thought</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012027">
		<snippet doc-id="7701" rsv="2722.00">For other uses, see Cocaine (disambiguation). In this paper he declared coca and cocaine (at the time they were assumed to be the same) as being useful medicinally, in the treatmen</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="53292" rsv="2546.00">The coca leaf is listed on Schedule I of the 1961 Single Convention together with cocaine and heroin. Outside of South America, most countries' laws make no distinction between the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4419141" rsv="2384.00">The production, the distribution and the sale of cocaine products is restricted (and illegal in most contexts) in most countries. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6690" rsv="2307.00">For its manufacturer, see The Coca-Cola Company. The Coca-Cola Company owns minority shares in some of its largest franchises, like Coca-Cola Enterprises, Coca-Cola Amatil, Coca-Co</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="581712" rsv="2280.00">In 2005, the Coca-Cola Company announced it would produce a new formulation of Diet Coke sweetened with sucralose, to be called Diet Coke with Splenda, but it would continue to pro</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="284163" rsv="2265.00">Juan Evo Morales Ayma (born October 26, 1959 in Orinoca, Oruro), popularly known as Evo (pronounced ), is the President of Bolivia since 2006. On August 10, 2008, a recall referend</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="29972" rsv="2240.00">An herbal tea, tisane, or ptisan is an herbal infusion made from anything other than the leaves of the tea bush (Camellia sinensis). In some countries (but not in the United States</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="256077" rsv="2223.00">The growers of coca are named Cocaleros and part of the coca production for traditional use is legal in Peru, Bolivia and Chile. With the growth of the Colombian drug cartels in th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="63576" rsv="2161.00">When he was a druggist and chemist in Atlanta, Georgia, Pemberton began work on a coca and kola (cola) nut beverage. Pemberton used an old family recipe from his African American m</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="28152" rsv="2149.00">Since the Japanese firm Morita Kagaku Kogyo Co., Ltd. produced the first commercial stevia sweetener in Japan in 1971, the Japanese have been using stevia in food products, soft dr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1723479" rsv="2147.00">New Zealand's Misuse of Drugs Act is a national drug control law that classifies drugs into three classes, or Schedules, based on their risk of harm: New Zealand is a party to the </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6516741" rsv="2126.00">The International Business Leaders Forum (IBLF) is an organisation which promotes responsible business, particularly in emerging economies. Following the UK government's 2005 Commi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="93831" rsv="2084.00">A 2000 review of the available literature concluded that "under present and expected conditions of new use, there is no potential for Roundup herbicide to pose a health risk to hum</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3901072" rsv="2076.00">Coca tea comes from the coca plant, which has the biological name Erythroxylum coca and is from the family Erythroxylaceae. Coca Tea is a natural product. Coca tea and coca flour a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15966318" rsv="2046.00">In 1991, the U.S. Government forgave all of the $341 million debt owed by Bolivia to the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) as well as 80% ($31 million) of the amoun</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4697289" rsv="2043.00">While there is no justification for a soft drink to contain high levels of benzene ("There is a difference here between a small and unavoidable risk, and a small but avoidable risk</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6811" rsv="2035.00">The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (or CDC) is an agency of the United States Department of Health and Human Services based in unincorporated DeKalb County, Georgia, Un</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="38323" rsv="2018.00">For other uses, see Cigar (disambiguation). Perhaps the best-known cigar family in the world is the Arturo Fuente family. Further information: Tobacco and healthLike other forms of</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="225870" rsv="2010.00">The Coca-Cola formula is The Coca-Cola Company's secret recipe for Coca-Cola. To this day, Coca-Cola uses as an ingredient from coca leaf extract prepared by a Stepan Company plant</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9616807" rsv="1969.00">A report by Pien Metaal and others written for the Transnational Institute ("Coca yes, cocaine no?", p. 19) states that: Protagonists of coca recommend mass production of ypadu as </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012028">
		<snippet doc-id="16652593" rsv="3259.00">On December 15, 1989 KLM Flight 867 from Amsterdam was descending into Anchorage International Airport when the Boeing 747-400 flew though a thick cloud of volcanic ash from Mount </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2528948" rsv="3201.00">British Airways Flight 9, sometimes referred to as the Jakarta incident, was a scheduled British Airways flight from London Heathrow to Auckland, with stops in Mumbai, Chennai, Kua</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="162404" rsv="3048.00">A stratovolcano, also called a composite volcano, is a tall, conical volcano composed of many layers of hardened lava, tephra, and volcanic ash. Subduction-zone stratovolcanoes lik</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1459249" rsv="2927.00">The Alaska Volcano Observatory currently rates Mount Augustine as Level of Concern Color Code Green for aviation and the Volcano Alert Level is at Normal. On January 17, 2006, Alas</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1533051" rsv="2858.00">An eruption column consists of hot volcanic ash emitted during an explosive volcanic eruption. Eruption column heights are a useful way of measuring eruption intensity since for a </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="690526" rsv="2838.00">Laki is part of a volcanic system, centering on the Grímsvötn volcano and including the Eldgjá canyon and Katla volcano, and lies between the glaciers of Mýrdalsjökull and Vatnajök</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="198811" rsv="2793.00">Volcanic ash consists of small tephra, which are bits of pulverized rock and glass created by volcanic eruptions, less than 2 millimetres (0.079 in) in diameter. After the Galunggu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="254954" rsv="2753.00">Other volcanoes in the region are also known for their volcanic activity, including Saint-Vincent's Soufriere Hills, Guadeloupe's Soufriere volcano, Montserrat's Soufriere Hills, a</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15634312" rsv="2727.00">The Puff model is a volcanic ash tracking model developed at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. Puff was initially conceived and developed by Prof. H. Tanaka as a novel method for</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8921015" rsv="2709.00">In this article types of eruption will be used to refer to the mechanism causing the eruption. Large plinian eruptions — such as during 18 May 1980 at Mount St. Helens or, more rec</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="991545" rsv="2693.00">A pyrocumulus or fire cloud is a dense cumuliform cloud associated with fire or volcanic activity. A pyrocumulus cloud is produced by the intense heating of the air from the surfac</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="465179" rsv="2661.00">Accretionary lapilli are formed in an eruption column or cloud by moisture or electrostatic forces, with the volcanic ash nucleating on some object and then accreting to it in laye</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="904516" rsv="2644.00">Foreign object damage or foreign object debris (FOD) is a substance, debris or article alien to the vehicle or system which would potentially cause damage. Although airport ground </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="312891" rsv="2606.00">Main article: British Airways Flight 9The last major eruption on Galunggung was in 1982, which had a Volcanic Explosivity Index of 4 and killed 68 people. This eruption also brough</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1451152" rsv="2590.00">Mount Okmok is the highest point on the rim of Okmok Caldera (Unmagim Anatuu in Aleut) on the northeastern part of Umnak Island in the eastern Aleutian Islands of Alaska, USA. This</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4217801" rsv="2586.00">The Minoan eruption of Thera, also referred to as the Thera eruption or Santorini eruption,  was a major catastrophic volcanic eruption (VEI = 6, DRE = 60 km3) which is estimated t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="673671" rsv="2561.00">Superheated flow material flashed water in Spirit Lake and North Fork Toutle River to steam, creating a larger, secondary explosion that was heard as far away as British Columbia, </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1159922" rsv="2525.00">Plinian eruptions are volcanic eruptions marked by their similarity to the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in AD 79 (as described in a letter written by Pliny the Younger) that killed Pli</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="417762" rsv="2484.00">Commonly associated with explosive volcanic activity - such as Plinian or krakatoan eruption styles, or phreatomagmatic eruptions - pyroclastic deposits are commonly formed from ai</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="32571" rsv="2450.00">When it does reach the surface, a volcano is formed. Scientists usually consider a volcano to be active if it is currently erupting or showing signs of unrest, such as unusual eart</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012029">
		<snippet doc-id="2990519" rsv="4735.00">When he returned, Proeski held humanitarian concerts throughout the Republic of Macedonia. In April, Proeski released his album "Den Za Nas" ("A Day For Us"), which featured the ei</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11959661" rsv="3557.00">The former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia (FYR Macedonia) was represented by Tose Proeski and the song "Life". The song was written by Jovan Jovanov, who also participated in FYR M</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19624965" rsv="3434.00">On the 5th of October the Macedonian POP singer Tose Proeski held his last concert. All of the songs that Tose Proeski has ever written and sang were sang by the singers in attenda</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17873440" rsv="3382.00">"The Hardest Thing" is the first posthumous single released by Macedonian pop musician, Toše Proeski, from his upcoming English-language album. The music video for the song was cre</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7866955" rsv="3311.00">"Life" was the FYR Macedonia's entry in the Eurovision Song Contest 2004, performed in English (the first time the Macedonian entry had not featured at least some of the country's </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3402030" rsv="3250.00">Grigor Koprov (Macedonian: Григор Копров) (born September 30, 1943 in Ohrid, now Republic of Macedonia) is arguably one of the most famous pop music composers in the Republic of Ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8344420" rsv="3125.00">Skopje Fest (Macedonian: Скопје Фест) or Festival na zabavni melodii Skopje (Фестивал на забавни мелодии Скопје) is one of the main musical events in the Republic of Macedonia. The</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14356965" rsv="3082.00">However due to unilateral declaration of independence of its southern province Kosovo, the festival was delayed until March 9 when the semi-finals took place and the finals which t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5005968" rsv="3069.00">The Music School of Bitola or Muzicko Uciliste Bitola is a state school that is located in Bitola, Republic of Macedonia. It provides a full education which includes solfege, music</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4195663" rsv="3031.00">Martin Vučić (Macedonian Cyrillic: Мартин Вучиќ) (born 7 August, 1982 in Skopje, SFR Yugoslavia) is a famous Pop musician from the Republic of Macedonia. He was 'Singer of the Year</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6240669" rsv="2928.00">Esma Redžepova (Macedonian: Есма Реџепова) is a Romani Macedonian vocalist, songwriter, and humanitarian born in Skopje, Socialist Republic of Macedonia, then Yugoslavia. Esma was </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5244075" rsv="2897.00">Tose can refer to: Leonard Tose - businessman To�e Proeski - a Macedonian singer TOSE Software Company This  page lists articles associated with the same title. If an internal link</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1924921" rsv="2824.00">Tony Cetinski (born May 31, 1969 in Pula, Croatia is a famous Croatian pop singer. At this year's Croatian Radio Festival (Croatian festival where the prizes are given by the votes</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7850656" rsv="2766.00">"Od nas zavisi" (Macedonian Cyrillic: Од нас зависи, English translation: "It Depends On Us") was FYR Macedonia's entry at the Eurovision Song Contest 2002, performed in the Macedo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10045170" rsv="2711.00">Kaleš bre Angjo (in Macedonian: Калеш бре Анѓо) is a Macedonian patriotic folk song dating from the times of the Ottoman occupation. He is asking her to become his wife and he prom</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="330226" rsv="2674.00">In 2000, Karolina joined the record label Avalon Productions, on which her debut album "Jas imam pesna" (I've got a song) was released. Karolina released several singles off her fi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13910228" rsv="2631.00">Photo credit: Canan KalkanTodor "Toše" Proeski (Macedonian: Тодор „Тоше" Проески) (January 25, 1981–October 16, 2007) was a famous Macedonian singer who was popular across the enti</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11694533" rsv="2631.00">Photo credit: Canan KalkanTodor "Toše" Proeski (Macedonian: Тодор „Тоше" Проески) (January 25, 1981–October 16, 2007) was a famous Macedonian singer who was popular across the enti</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13134953" rsv="2614.00">Zajdi, zajdi, jasno sonce (O Set, O Set, Clear Sun; Macedonian: Зајди, зајди, јасно сонце; Bulgarian: Зайди, зайди, ясно слънце) is a popular Macedonian and  Bulgarian song which h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19496665" rsv="2582.00">Bobi Andonov (Macedonian: Боби Андонов) (born August 18, 1994 in Melbourne, Australia) is a Macedonian Australian singer who will represent Republic of Macedonia at the Junior Euro</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012030">
		<snippet doc-id="83907" rsv="2172.00">This article is about the SRY gene. SRY (Sex-determining Region Y) is a sex-determining gene on the Y chromosome in the therians (placental mammals and marsupials). Since its disco</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6988346" rsv="2141.00">Anthropometric history uses physical stature as an indicator of well-being to complement conventional indicators of living standards by the biological standard of living (Baten, 20</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7455643" rsv="2098.00">Human thermal comfort is defined by ASHRAE as the state of mind that expresses satisfaction with the surrounding environment (ASHRAE Standard 55). Factors determining thermal comfo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14818586" rsv="2029.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 18, also known as SOX18, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14819212" rsv="2024.00">Zinc finger protein, Y-linked, also known as ZFY, is a human gene. This gene encodes a zinc finger-containing protein that may function as a transcription factor. This gene was onc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="905957" rsv="2020.00">Human height varies according to both "nature" and "nurture". In the AFL, the average height of ruckmen is over 200cm (6' 7") tall and weight of over 100 kg.  Aaron Sandilands and </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14795865" rsv="2014.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 3, also known as SOX3, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="374298" rsv="2014.00">This article is about the general intelligence factor. Factor analysis techniques are not limited to producing single factors, and an analysis of human bodies might produce (for ex</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15354559" rsv="2011.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 12, also known as SOX12, is a human gene. Members of the SOX family of transcription factors are characterized by the presence of a DNA-binding h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14814646" rsv="2010.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 6, also known as SOX6, is a human gene. Unlike most transcription factors, SOX transcription factors bind to the minor groove of DNA, causing a 7</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16859948" rsv="1998.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 21, also known as SOX21, is a human gene. SRY-related HMG-box (SOX) genes encode a family of DNA-binding proteins containing a 79-amino acid HMG </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14763517" rsv="1993.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 4, also known as SOX4, is a human gene. This intronless gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14879794" rsv="1991.00">Doublesex and mab-3 related transcription factor 1, also known as DMRT1, is a human gene. This gene is found in a cluster with two other members of the gene family, having in commo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14797738" rsv="1989.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 5, also known as SOX5, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14723387" rsv="1981.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 9 (campomelic dysplasia, autosomal sex-reversal), also known as SOX9, is a human gene. It acts during chondrocyte differentiation and, with stero</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14800299" rsv="1960.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 13, also known as SOX13, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7860110" rsv="1951.00">Human sex determination refers to the processes by which an individual becomes either a male or female during development. However, Dr. MS Palmer later discovered a ZFY analogue on</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15075136" rsv="1939.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 15, also known as SOX15, is a human gene. This gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors involved in</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15417284" rsv="1937.00">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 14, also known as SOX14, is a human gene. This intronless gene encodes a member of the SOX (SRY-related HMG-box) family of transcription factors </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1475503" rsv="1921.00">Testis-determining factor (TDF) is a general term for the gene (or product thereof) that results in maleness in humans and some other species. Embryos are gonadally identical, rega</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012031">
		<snippet doc-id="17524651" rsv="2124.00">The Eurovision Song Contest 2009 will be the 54th Eurovision Song Contest, scheduled to take place between the 12 May and 16 May 2009. Telewizja Polska (TVP), the Polish broadcaste</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13954204" rsv="2100.00">Dansk Melodi Grand Prix 2008 was the selection for the song to represent Denmark at the Eurovision Song Contest 2008. Two semi-finals and two wildcard selections took place to sele</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9954" rsv="2092.00">For this year's Contest, see Eurovision Song Contest 2008. Further information: Voting at the Eurovision Song ContestThe voting systems used in the Contest have changed throughout </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7901609" rsv="2092.00">Euroviisut 2007 was the show in which Finland chose its entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007. Finland hosted the Eurovision Song Contest for the first time, after Lordi won i</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7442310" rsv="2089.00">Dansk Melodi Grand Prix 2007 was the selection for the song to represent Denmark at the Eurovision Song Contest 2007. Two semi-finals and two wildcard selections took place to sele</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15964926" rsv="2079.00">The Dutch entry was chosen during a national final called Nationaal Songfestival and the country would go on to the win the Eurovision Song Contest. Corry Brokken, who was already </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19638614" rsv="2070.00">Euroviisut 2008 was the Finnish national selection for the Finnish entry to the Eurovision Song Contest 2008, held in Belgrade, Serbia. Four semi-final took place before the final,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8366531" rsv="2055.00">Söngvakeppni Sjónvarpsins 2007 was the show in which Iceland selected its entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007, held in Helsinki, Finland. The winner was Eiríkur Hauksson wit</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12291379" rsv="2051.00">The Andorran National Final was held on March 15, 2004, hosted by Pati Molné and Xavier Graset with the winner being chosen by a mixture of an "expert" jury (5/7), SMS voting in An</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3606916" rsv="2046.00">Congratulations: 50 Years of the Eurovision Song Contest was a television programme organised by the European Broadcasting Union (EBU) to commemorate the Eurovision Song Contest's </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11435813" rsv="2045.00">Wixell performed the winning song "Annostädes vals" in English at the Eurovision Song Contest as "Absent Friends", making Sweden the first country to perform entirely in a non-nati</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7438722" rsv="2040.00">Melodi Grand Prix 2007 (shortened MGP 2007) was the television show in which the Norwegian entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007 was chosen. On the 12th October 2006, NRK anno</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3867528" rsv="2029.00">Greece has been participating in the Eurovision Song Contest since 1974, with the exception of 1975, 1982, 1984, 1986, 1999 and 2000. In 2006, the 51st Eurovision Song Contest was </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="16353941" rsv="2020.00">Greece and Ellinikí Radiofonía Tileórasi (ERT) chose to host a National Selection with the winner being chosen by  SMS voting (30%), televoting (30%) and an "expert" jury (40%). Ma</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15426108" rsv="2019.00">For the Danish national final with the same name - see Dansk Melodi Grand Prix 2008. Melodi Grand Prix 2008 (shortened MGP 2008) is the television show in which the Norwegian entry</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8402277" rsv="2003.00">EMA 2007 was the television show in which Slovenia selected its entry for the Eurovision Song Contest 2007. The final will took place in Ljubljana on the 3rd February 2007, with se</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="331425" rsv="2001.00">The current voting format is a variation on the Borda count similar to that used at the Eurovision Song Contest. See also: Sweden in the Eurovision Song Contest 2009In August 2008,</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4408017" rsv="1999.00">Televoting is a method of opinion polling usually conducted by telephone, which incorporates deliberative democratic principles. Televoting or televote is also the term used to des</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4461881" rsv="1995.00">The Eurovision Song Contest 2007 was the 52nd edition of the Eurovision Song Contest. "The way the voting is processed in the EBU is wrong, and needs updating", say many Eurovision</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1998116" rsv="1991.00">Serbia and Montenegro participated in the Eurovision Song Contest twice, from 2004 (see Eurovision 2004). No Name were close to becoming the national entry once more, for the 2006 </snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012032">
		<snippet doc-id="623280" rsv="2264.00">Ripley believes him to be another android; Bishop II claims to be the man who designed the Bishop series, sent by the company to show Ripley "a friendly face."  Mr. Aaron (Ralph Br</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="713" rsv="2123.00">For other uses, see Android (disambiguation). Hanson Robotics, Inc. of Texas and KAIST produced an android portrait of Albert Einstein, using Hanson's facial android technology mou</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14075240" rsv="2063.00">Evilhawk is a reptilian alien from the planet Luq with an android body. Dargin Bokk is an alien who was born on the planet Luq. Evilhawk was originally unable to use his healing po</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10203926" rsv="2049.00">Aliens: Extermination is a 3D shooter arcade game released in 2006, based on the movie Aliens. Making it back inside, human android Synthetics attack. Though the Pulse Rifle can do</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19423847" rsv="2047.00">Main article: Windam (Ultra monster) Alien Wild's character subtitle is Space Barbarian. Main article: Nurse (Ultra monster) </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17339036" rsv="2039.00">At the Batcave, Batman, Green Lantern, and Green Arrow convene with Martian Manhunter and Hawkman had been taken to. While working on trying to find the heroes using the strange ra</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8861419" rsv="2032.00">This article provides a list of episodes of the television series Lost in Space. Complete box sets of all 3 seasons (and the original pilot film) of the original TV series have bee</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9669953" rsv="2001.00">Following the events of The Sheriff and the Satellite Kid, Sheriff Hall and H-725 (here named Charlie Warren) still get no rest from the military: because the little alien has not </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1619971" rsv="1981.00">The Air-Walker (Gabriel Lan) is a character in the fictional Marvel Universe. Believing itself to be the original Gabriel Lan, the Air-Walker attempts to find the Surfer, but encou</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="602483" rsv="1953.00">Weyland-Yutani is a fictional corporation in the motion picture Alien and its sequels, often referred to simply as "The Company". At no time in Alien nor in the portfolio was the n</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8995799" rsv="1918.00">The only actor from the Alien films to appear in one of the prequels was Lance Henriksen, who had played the android Bishop in Aliens and a man claiming to be the android's creator</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4930032" rsv="1904.00">The Growing Man is an android and was created for the supervillain, Kang the Conqueror. Months later, Kang uses the Growing Man to abduct Tony Stark - the alter-ego of Iron Man - f</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="213251" rsv="1870.00">For the video games of the same name, see Alien 3 (video game), Alien 3 (1993 game) and Alien 3 (Game Boy). After going through several ideas, David Giler and Walter Hill, the film</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="26110" rsv="1869.00">This list of fictional robots and androids is a chronological list, categorised by medium. It includes all depictions of robots, androids and gynoids in literature, television, and</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1800005" rsv="1866.00">The Doctor and Sarah find themselves in the English village of Devesham near a Space Defence Station. The Doctor and Sarah duck and run, with the four in pursuit. Sarah and the Doc</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9017986" rsv="1852.00">The Commander of the shuttle-craft Vulture John Leslie Stott http://www.ukgameshows.com/page/index.php/John_Leslie UK Game Shows - John Leslie leads two teams of Scavengers to the </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1505455" rsv="1824.00">The tower construction is directed by Krug's most faithful android, Alpha Thor Watchman. Krug eventually learns of the android religion, and is appalled. With the collapse of their</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="6245494" rsv="1800.00">The Queen gives birth to "Newborn", which is half Alien half Human (more alien), which kills the Queen and accepts Ripley as its mother. See also: Alien vs. Predator video gamesThe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7872488" rsv="1777.00">Highway Encounter is a computer game released on the Sinclair ZX Spectrum 48K, Amstrad CPC, and Commodore 64 by Vortex Software in 1985. Players control a robotic "Vorton" (resembl</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4027932" rsv="1770.00">Flying aliens can be seen in Konami's Aliens, the arcade game  as a boss under the name Alien Dragon, in the Super Nintendo game Alien vs. Predator as an end-level boss (this one h</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012033">
		<snippet doc-id="3973131" rsv="2765.00">The term double jointed is often used to describe hypermobility, however the name is a misnomer and is not to be taken literally, as an individual with hypermobility in a joint doe</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8173442" rsv="2412.00">Xwrits periodically locks the X Window System while a brightly-colored hand, alternately clenching and stretching as if in pain, is displayed to remind the user to take a break. It</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3011904" rsv="2361.00">Blackberry thumb is a form of repetitive strain injury caused by the frequent use of the thumb(s) to press buttons on PDAs, smart phones, or other mobile devices. Symptoms of Black</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7474213" rsv="2321.00">The DataHand keyboard was introduced in 1995 by DataHand Systems, Inc.  Before that it was produced by Industrial Innovations as early as 1992. This allows you to place each hand w</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="25756" rsv="2222.00">A repetitive strain injury (RSI), also called cumulative trauma disorder (CTD), occupational overuse syndrome, or work related upper limb disorder (WRULD), is any of a loose group </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1053949" rsv="2169.00">Spinal cord injury can occur from many causes, including: Traumatic spinal cord injury is classified into five types by the American Spinal Injury Association and the International</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18842281" rsv="2144.00">A keyset or chorded keyboard (also called a chord keyboard or chording keyboard) is a computer input device that allows the user to enter characters or commands formed by pressing </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="56462" rsv="2100.00">For the Kid Koala album, see Carpal Tunnel Syndrome (album). Carpal tunnel syndrome (CTS) or median neuropathy at the wrist is a medical condition in which the median nerve is comp</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1272984" rsv="2089.00">Because of its proximity to the wrist joint, this injury is often called a wrist fracture. Specific types of distal radius fractures are Colles' fracture; Smith's fracture; Barton'</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13915654" rsv="2026.00">Jewish law on damages is grounded partly on the Written Torah, the Hebrew Bible, and partly on the Oral Torah, centered primarily in the Mishnaic Order of Nezikin. In Jewish law, s</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="56283" rsv="1940.00">Ketamine, a potent anesthetic, is being used as an experimental and controversial treatment for Complex Regional Pain Syndrome. Doctor Harbut and Doctor Graeme Correll (of Queensla</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14243136" rsv="1913.00">Medical Massage Is outcome based massage it is primarily the application of specific treatment protocols targeted to the specific problem(s) the patient presents with physician's d</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1918041" rsv="1908.00">However, in 1551, French military surgeon Ambroise Paré recorded the first documentation of phantom limb pain when he reported that, “For the patients, long after the amputation is</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1944613" rsv="1906.00">Chondromalacia Patella (also known as CMP, Patello-femoral Pain Syndrome, or Runner's Knee) is a term for a large and disparate group of medical conditions that can cause pain at t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="272541" rsv="1906.00">Tenosynovitis is the inflammation of the fluid-filled sheath (called the synovium) that surrounds a tendon. Symptoms of tenosynovitis include pain, swelling, and difficulty moving </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="504841" rsv="1905.00">OA affects nearly 21 million people in the United States, accounting for 25% of visits to primary care physicians, and half of all NSAID (Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs) pre</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2493928" rsv="1901.00">The South Wales Evening Post stated (on 8 August 2000) that around 40 weever stings are recorded in the Swansea and Gower area every year however many victims will not seek medical</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="490901" rsv="1897.00">For other uses, see Catch and release (disambiguation). In Switzerland, catch and release fishing is considered inhumane and will be banned beginning in September 2008. Fishermen h</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="307837" rsv="1891.00">Shoulder pain may be localized or may be referred to areas around the shoulder or down the arm. Shoulder pain or tenderness and, occasionally, a bump in the middle of the top of th</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="29666" rsv="1881.00">Syringomyelia causes a wide variety of neuropathic symptoms due to damage of the spinal cord. Scientists at the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke in Bethesda,</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012034">
		<snippet doc-id="246574" rsv="3682.00">Another type of case is fraudulent claims of possession. Maybe the most known work on the subject is the 1973 film The Exorcist, based on the book of the same name, which portrays </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3700127" rsv="3471.00">Exorcism (from Late Latin exorcismus, from Greek exorkizein - to adjure) is the practice of evicting demons or other evil spiritual entities from a person or place which they are b</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5033818" rsv="3465.00">The possessions at Louviers (Normandy, France), similar to those in Aix-en-Provence, occurred at the Louviers Convent in 1647. Sister Madeleine Bavent was 18 years old in the year </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2458960" rsv="3268.00">Anneliese Michel (September 21, 1952 – July 1, 1976) was a German  Catholic woman who was said to be possessed by demons and subsequently underwent an exorcism. The Roman Catholic </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="309564" rsv="3249.00">The problem of demon possession and spiritual warfare became the subject of a Christian Medical Association symposium that was held in 1975. Robert Guelich of Fuller Theological Se</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="174601" rsv="3138.00">Greek philosophers such as Porphyry, who claimed influence from Platonism, and the fathers of the Christian Church, held that the world was pervaded with spirits, the latter of who</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2571604" rsv="3103.00">The film is based on the true story of Anneliese Michel, a young Catholic woman from Germany who died in 1976 after unsuccessful attempts to cure her from the alleged state of demo</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5036540" rsv="3041.00">The 1634 case of demonic possession in Loudun, France, is arguably the most famous case of multiple or mass possession in history. Either the Bishop of Poiters approached Father Mi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="1623431" rsv="2982.00">Of Exorcisms and Certain Supplications (Latin: De Exorcismis et Supplicationibus Quibusdam) is an 84-page document of the Roman Catholic church describing the rite of exorcism. Fol</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11441994" rsv="2979.00">It was during these rites that the nuns accused Grandier of being in league with the devil and initiating their demonic possession. After some missions in Guyenne and Saintonge, Su</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="475322" rsv="2968.00">The Exorcist order was suppressed during the reforms of the minor orders after the Second Vatican Council by Paul VI. It remains in  societies which use the extraordinary form of t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="86351" rsv="2942.00">An elderly Jesuit priest named Father Lankester Merrin is leading an archaeological dig in northern Iraq and studying ancient relics. Father Damien Karras, who is currently going t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14914335" rsv="2890.00">José Antonio Fortea Cucurull (born in Barbastro, Spain, 1968), priest and specialized theologian in Demonology. In 1998 he defended his thesis (tesina) entitled Exorcism in the Pre</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="858169" rsv="2863.00">Father Walter Halloran, SJ (September 21, 1921 – March 1, 2005) was a Jesuit Roman Catholic priest who, at the age of twenty-six, assisted in the exorcism of a thirteen year old Lu</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="18904468" rsv="2840.00">In the year leading up to the attack on Bono, Johnson had been staying with his fiancee whose younger brother supposedly had been possessed by demons and whose family called in the</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="274932" rsv="2822.00">One relatively recent example of Christian demonology is the book War On The Saints, by Jessie Penn-Lewis, which purports to reveal what demons are, how they work at gaining posses</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="5271472" rsv="2814.00">Allen tracked down the sole survivor of the team that performed the exorcism, Father Walter Halloran as well as a copy of the diary kept by the team leader, Father William S. Bowde</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="7499196" rsv="2749.00">They are able to get information on where their father is after Meg is seemingly in an abundance of pain from the exorcism. With her trapped inside, both Bobby and Dean attempt ano</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="412826" rsv="2737.00">Deliverance ministries focus on casting out the spirit or spirits believed to cause an affliction. Though many people confuse deliverance with exorcism, they are not the same. Bish</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="10612300" rsv="2735.00">Graham H. Twelftree, Ph.D (born 8 July 1950) is an Australian born biblical scholar who currently serves as Distinguished Professor of New Testament at Regent University's School o</snippet>
	</topic>
	<topic topic-id="2012035">
		<snippet doc-id="13485592" rsv="1757.00">The Australian Electoral Commission regulates donations to political parties, and publishes a yearly list of political donors. Associated entities have become huge political donors</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15756092" rsv="1572.00">The Philippine Children's Fund of America is a non-profit organization registered under the state of California and is duly recognized by the United States Federal Government. Phil</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="190458" rsv="1546.00">It was patented in the U.S. in the 1940s by Colgate, though biolipid transesterification may have been discovered much earlier. In the 1940s, researchers were looking for a method </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="3628051" rsv="1526.00">Here follows a list of notable researchers and writers in the field of cryptozoology: Also see: Cryptozoology, Cryptids|Cryptids, zoology. </snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15298246" rsv="1518.00">Samuel H. Wood is a scientist noted for donating DNA that was used in somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT) to produce mature human embryos that were clones of Dr Wood. In January 2</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17462994" rsv="1501.00">Mobile donating refers to donating to an organization through a mobile device. The primary means for mobile donating is through  SMS.  Mobile donating can also refer to consumers d</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="14040996" rsv="1492.00">Eagles for St. Jude benefits St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital and is sponsored by Stanford Financial Group, which in 2007 assumed title sponsorship of the Stanford St. Jude Ch</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="4481670" rsv="1445.00">The Australian Red Cross Blood Service (ARCBS) is a branch of the Australian Red Cross. It is the body primarily responsible for blood donation and related services in Australia. V</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="11745794" rsv="1419.00">Between June 1986 and January 1987, Professor Derek Tribe with support from Australian aid (ADAB, now AusAID), the Australian Centre for International Agricultural Research (ACIAR)</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8635827" rsv="1399.00">France-China relations, also known as Sino-French relations or Franco-Chinese relations, refers to the interstate relations between China and France (Kingdom or later). Note that t</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="19197431" rsv="1398.00">Giovanni Antonaglia OAM (born 19 November 1938) is an Italian-born Australian businessman, supporter of community organisations and winer of the Medal of the Order of Australia. An</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="2602512" rsv="1390.00">The Australian Research Council (ARC) is the Australian Government’s main agency for allocating research funding to academics and researchers in Australian universities. The ARC wa</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="12903882" rsv="1387.00">QSR International develops qualitative data analysis (QDA) software products designed to help qualitative researchers organize and analyze non-numerical or unstructured data. QSR I</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13100713" rsv="1381.00">Cormack Foundation Pty Ltd is an Australian investment company established for the purpose of raising funds for the Liberal Party of Australia. The company was originally set up us</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="505536" rsv="1380.00">It was a significant problem in China in the 1990s, and up to 250,000 blood plasma donors may have been infected with HIV from shared equipment. The World Health Organization recog</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="15827675" rsv="1358.00">Organ trade is the trade involving human organs for transplantation. Most organ trade involves kidney or liver transplants. India’s Transplantation of Human Organs Act (THOA) requi</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="8613182" rsv="1355.00">The Westall UFO encounter is an event that occurred at 11.00 am on April 6th, 1966. At approximately 11.00 am on Wednesday, 6 April, 1966, a class of students and a teacher from We</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="13739096" rsv="1344.00">The Channel Seven Perth Telethon, also known simply as Telethon, is an annual telethon produced by TVW, a Seven Network owned television station in Perth, Western Australia for thr</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="9772355" rsv="1342.00">Bloecher became interested in UFOs during the wave of sightings across the U.S. in 1952. In the 1970s, Bloecher was associated with MUFON and CUFOS. In 1975, he co-investigated a s</snippet>
		<snippet doc-id="17512873" rsv="1335.00">The Mobile Giving Foundation is a non-profit organization based in Washington, working to increase mobile donating in the US.  The organization in early 2008 fostered a deal betwee</snippet>
	</topic>
</inex-snippet-submission>
