<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:04:13[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<building  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="102913152">
<library  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="103660909">
<header>
<title>Dunedin Public Libraries</title>
<id>17155154</id>
<revision>
<id>242404660</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-02T02:41:59Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Paul151</username>
<id>6740183</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>1908 establishments</category>
<category>Libraries in New Zealand</category>
<category>Buildings and structures in Dunedin</category>
<category>Carnegie libraries</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Library</name>
<parameters>
<website>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dunedinlibraries.govt.nz/">
www.dunedinlibraries.govt.nz</weblink></website>
<location>
<village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/628345.xml">
Dunedin</link></village>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/4913064.xml">
New Zealand</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</colony>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
</autocracy>
</location>
<collection_size>
700,000 items</collection_size>
<established>
1908</established>
<num_branches>
5 + 2 mobile</num_branches>
<library_name>
Dunedin Public Libraries<it>Kā Kete Wānaka O Ōtepoti</it>(<link>
Māori</link>)</library_name>
<library_logo>
<image width="350px" src="Dunedin_Public_Libraries_logo.jpg">
</image>
</library_logo>
<coordinates>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagenameDunedin_Public_Libraries&amp;params-45.872886_N_170.503526_E_">
45°52′22″S 170°30′13″E﻿ / ﻿-45.872886, 170.503526</weblink><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
Coordinates</link>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagenameDunedin_Public_Libraries&amp;params-45.872886_N_170.503526_E_">
45°52′22″S 170°30′13″E﻿ / ﻿-45.872886, 170.503526</weblink> (City library)</coordinates>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

<b>Dunedin Public Libraries</b> is a network of five libraries and two bookbuses in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/628345.xml">
Dunedin</link></village>
, <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/4913064.xml">
New Zealand</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_system>
</colony>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
</autocracy>
, owned and operated by the Dunedin City Council. The libraries collection includes over 700,000 items, and around 30,000 books and audiovisual items plus 15,000 magazines are added each year.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Members can borrow or return items from any library or bookbuses in the network.</p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>

<ss1>
<st>
City Library</st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Dunedin_Public_Libraries_-_City_Library2.jpg‎" type="thumb">
<caption>

City Library looking southeast
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Dunedin_Public_Libraries_-_City_Library.jpg‎" type="thumb">
<caption>

City Library looking southwest
</caption>
</image>

Dunedin's first Free Public Library opened on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/8356.xml">
2 December</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/34600.xml">
1908</link>, funded by a ₤10,000 grant from American philanthropist <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<philanthropist wordnetid="110421956" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../938/1938.xml">
Andrew Carnegie</link></philanthropist>
</person>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Situated at 110 Moray Place, the library offered a reference service only.</p>
<p>

In 1910 a Children’s Reading Room opened and then the Children’s lending Library. In 1911 lending services began for adults. In 1913, Dr. <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<farmer wordnetid="110078806" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<lawyer wordnetid="110249950" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/13445459.xml">
Robert McNab</link></creator>
</scholar>
</lawyer>
</professional>
</historian>
</adult>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</farmer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 presented his collection of 4,200 volumes of early voyages and New Zealand history to the library, which later became the basis of the McNab New Zealand collection.</p>
<p>

Other major donations were the Walt Whitman Collection (Mrs. J. W. Stewart) in 1927 and the <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../497/2014497.xml">
Alfred</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
 and Isabel Reed Collection including Bibles, early printing and manuscripts, Dickens and Johnston works in 1947.</p>
<p>

In 1936 the Library adopted its rental policy, whereby certain items would no longer be free. This included popular works of fiction, as well as certain magazine titles. The Library's first hospital service was started in 1938. 1950 saw more expanded services offered, with the addition of a Bookbus service and the unveiling of its Gramophone collection. Today this collection has been expanded to included DVDs, Videos, CDs, and other Audio Visual Items.</p>
<p>

In 1969 the first Housebound Readers Service was opened. In 1976 a second Bookbus was added, and the Children's Library had its very own card catalogue. Further children's services were offered in the following years, including Get Well bags in 1979.</p>
<p>

Dunedin Public Library moved to its current location at 230 Moray Place in 1981. In 1982 the automated circulation system was installed. The first fully computerised Library Management System was installed in 1993. The Taiehu Collection of Maoritanga was launched in 1986. Taiehu was a Maori chief who brought one of the first canoes to New Zealand.</p>
<p>

With local authority amalgamation in 1989, Dunedin Public Library became part of the Dunedin Public Libraries network. Two new Bookbuses were purchased in 1991 and the service was expanded to around 50 locations.</p>
<p>

In 1998 a major redevelopment of the Library was undertaken, with all the adult non-fiction lending collections combined, the opening up of three adult stack areas for improved public access to the collections, and the creation of a greatly expanded Audio-Visual area to reflect the increased use of these collections.</p>
<p>

Key events that have taken place include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1908	The Library opened its doors to the public on 2 December. The Librarian was Scottish-born William Barker McEwan.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1910	The Children’s Reading Room opened, providing both reference and lending services to children aged 10 and over. The age limit would subsequently be lowered.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1911	The Lending Library for adults opened (so children were able to borrow books before this privilege was extended to adults).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1913	Robert McNab offered his library to the City. At that time the collection amounted to 4200 items. Careful development has seen it grow to over 92,000.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1919	All but two of the staff were laid low with influenza, and the Library was closed for a month.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1933	Archie Dunningham became City Librarian.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1936	Dorothy Neal, later Dorothy Neal White and later still Dorothy Neal White Ballantyne, became Children’s Librarian. She would become one of New Zealand’s greatest-ever children’s librarians and advocates for children’s books. Also in that year the free/rental policy (which still persists) was introduced, the Library Bindery was established, and the collection of sheet music began.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1938	The Hospital Library Service began at the Public Hospital.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1939	The framed pictures lending service began, and the Children’s Library moved to the Club House building in Moray Place.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1946	The Children’s Library was relocated to Stuart Street.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1947	The Alfred and Isabel Reed Collection was gifted to the City.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1950	The Book Bus service began.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1960	Ada Fache became City Librarian.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1968	Mary Ronnie became City Librarian.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1969	The House-bound Readers’ service began.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1976	Michael Wooliscroft became City Librarian.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1981	The present Library building opened.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1987	Norah Familton became City Librarian.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1989	Allison Dobbie became City Librarian, the Colin McCahon painting Otago Peninsula was bequeathed to the Library, and local body amalgamation brought the Mosgiel, Port Chalmers, Blueskin Bay, and Waikouaiti Libraries into the Dunedin Public Libraries network.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

1993	The present Dynix automated library system was introduced.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2001	The LearnIT Centre, offering free Internet access, was opened.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2002	Bernie Hawke became City Librarian.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2006	The new Reed Gallery opened on the third floor.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

2008	We celebrate our Centenary, and look forward to another century of progress and service to the people of Dunedin!</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Mosgiel Library</st>
<p>

From as early as 1881 Mosgiel has had a functioning library. It was not until 1959 that the Mosgiel Public Library was officially opened, in the Electrical Refrigeration premises. Since then, the library has relocated twice – firstly to Souters Exchange building, and in 1979 to its present location on Hartstonge Ave.</p>
<p>

In 1989, Mosgiel Borough was amalgamated with Dunedin City, St Kilda Borough, Green Island Borough and Silverpeaks County. The Mosgiel Public Library became part of the Dunedin Public Libraries network, opening up access to items held by all the libraries involved. This access was further enhanced with the introduction of a computerised system in 1993.</p>
<p>

In 1999 the library took over responsibility for the Dunedin City Council Service Centre, ensuring that a DCC Customer Services presence stayed in the community.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Port Chalmers Library</st>
<p>

Port Chalmers Mechanics Institute started in 1864, and became the Port Chalmers Public Library under the direct control of the Borough Council in 1943. The library was eventually housed in the Town Hall building. In 1989 the library joined the Dunedin Public Libraries network as a result of local authority amalgamation.</p>
<p>

In 2004 the Port Chalmers Library and Service Centre was completely refurbished by the Dunedin City Council. Extensive consultation with the Historic Places Trust meant the historic facade and many interesting internal features could be retained. A number of art works have been added to the library collection, including works by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<painter wordnetid="110391653" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/1101524.xml">
Ralph Hotere</link></creator>
</artist>
</painter>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/8893871.xml">
David Elliot</link></creator>
</artist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, Robyn Belton, and Pamela Brown.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Waikouaiti Library</st>

<p>

The Waikouaiti Library was founded in 1862 by Rev A Fenton and Miss Emily Orbell and began with 100 books half of them given by Mr Fenton in the school room in Beach Street. His successor the Rv A Dasent took charge in 1863 and was Chairman of the library committee for 11 years. The Library later moved to Mechanics' Hall in 1875 and from this time a committee of seven was elected annual by the subscribers to the Library, and the subscription was lowered from one pound to ten shillings.</p>
<p>

In 1905 a new book room 24 feet by 9 feet was built as a connection between the librarian's cottage and the hall on the north side. By 1913 there were 107 subscribers and over 3000 books. In the late sixties the County Council took over responsibility for the Hall and the Library. The committee continued to meet until 1974 as a County Council committee, and then the Library was quite on its own. It was visibly separated from the Hall also, because in that year the books were moved across the street to the RSA Community Centre, while the former library buildings were replaced by a chemist's shop, doctors rooms, and meeting rooms.</p>
<p>

From around 2000 in 1970 issues were up to 22,000 a year by May 1988. Unfortunately the building soon began to need frequent maintenance, and it was obvious it was not a suitable place for a library which was expanding dramatically now that Waikouaiti was part of Dunedin City. With amalgamation the Library subsequently joined the Dunedin Public Libraries network in 1989. The Community Centre was demolished and a new Waikouaiti Library built in the last weeks of 1995.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Blueskin Bay Library</st>
<p>

Blueskin Bay Library opened in the school house in 1871. It moved to a separate building in 1903 and to the public hall in 1972. Both Waitati and Waikouaiti Libraries were administered by Silverpeaks County prior to local government amalgamation in 1989. Blueskin Bay Library was constructed in 1992 as an extension to the Waitati Hall. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Bookbuses</st>
<p>

The Library Committee bought a passenger bus in 1949 and equipped it for use as a traveling library. The first distribution of books was made on 17 April 1950. In 1991 two new Bookbuses were commissioned. They were painted with colourful scenes, one featuring penguins and the countryside and one a cityscape. The two Bookbuses currently visit customers in 51 locations throughout the city offering fiction, non-fiction and reference books for children and adults, large print, talking books, audio-visual material (on request) and magazines.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Branches</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 City - <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/3777136.xml">
Moray Place</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../263/711263.xml">
Mosgiel</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/430325.xml">
Waikouaiti</link></urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<port wordnetid="108633957" confidence="0.8">
<point wordnetid="108620061" confidence="0.8">
<geographic_point wordnetid="108578706" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<municipality wordnetid="108626283" confidence="0.8">
<geographical_area wordnetid="108574314" confidence="0.8">
<town wordnetid="108665504" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<urban_area wordnetid="108675967" confidence="0.8">
<city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/1067606.xml">
Port Chalmers</link></city>
</urban_area>
</district>
</town>
</geographical_area>
</municipality>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</geographic_point>
</point>
</port>
</region>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/7784078.xml">
Blueskin Bay</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 two bookbuses (visiting 51 locations weekly)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Centenary Celebrations</st>

<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Dunedin_Public_Libraries_Centenary_Logo_250px.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

DPL Centennial Logo
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

2008 marks Dunedin Public Libraries centenary. Celebrations will be held between October &amp; December 2008.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Centenary Events</st>

<p>

A number of events have been planned and include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Writing Workshop for Adults</it> - Workshops for those whose writing careers haven’t begun yet.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Follow the Reader</it> - A guided walk around Dunedin’s Literary History.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>How we began: the first six years of the Dunedin Public Library</it> - Reed Gallery Exhibition.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Blokes in Libraries</it> - Male staff speaking about working in the Library.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Books Roadshow</it> - Our Antiques Roadshow styled event.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>The Great Hundred-Year Hunt</it> - A family activity that will take you all over the Library.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Writing Workshop for Children</it> - A special session for children aged 8-13.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Edwardian Costumes: a Fashion Parade</it> - Discover what Dunedin people were wearing when they came to the Library in 1908.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Yotsume Toji: the art of Japanese bookbinding</it> - Create a beautiful blank book in a traditional style.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>100 Years – 100 Questions</it> - Our Centenary quiz.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Library Birthday</it> - Tuesday 2 December is exactly 100 years from the day our first Librarian, William Barker McEwan, opened the doors of the Carnegie Library to the public of Dunedin. Come in and enjoy the birthday atmosphere!</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

A full list of events planned <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dunedinpubliclibraries.wordpress.com/centenary/">
can be downloaded</weblink> from the library website.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Heritage Collections</st>
<p>

Dunedin Public Libraries has two specialist Heritage Collections both are located on the third floor of the City Library.</p>
<p>

The McNab New Zealand Collection contains around 83,000 items relating to the history of the New Zealand and Pacific regions. The Alfred and Isabel Reed Collection contains around 10,000 items dating from the tenth century to the present day relating to literature, religion, and the history of the book.</p>
<p>

The heritage collections are open to the public, but items can only be used within the third floor of the City Library and they are not available for borrowing to take home. There is also a collection of art works used to beautify spaces within the libraries.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Reed Gallery</st>

<p>

Opened in March 2006 the Reed Gallery fulfills A.H. Reed’s dream of a readily available heritage collection.</p>
<p>

Exhibition cabinets, revamped lighting and security have created a professional gallery space meeting international conservation standards, meaning collections can now be properly appreciated.</p>
<p>

The space features quarterly exhibitions, some themed, others with a changing “book of the month” display. Some of the material is very interesting, precious or rare, and few people have been able to see it. The area also features a seminar room for lectures and slide shows related to the exhibitions and the heritage collections.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Current Gallery Exhibition</st>

<p>

The current Reed Gallery exhibition <b><it>How We Began: the First Six Years of the Dunedin Public Library</it></b> commemorates the event by highlighting the early years of the Library’s history.</p>
<p>

These first few years were pivotal for the Library, which was growing by leaps and bounds. By the time the Library had been open for seven years, it had developed to include a large reference collection, a children’s library, an adult lending library, and housed a fine collection of New Zealand material donated by Dr Robert McNab. How We Began features books from each of these milestones.</p>
<p>

For more information visit <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dunedinlibraries.govt.nz/home/?page=Heritage">
www.dunedinlibraries.govt.nz - heritage collection</weblink></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dunedin.govt.nz/facilities/library">
Dunedin Public Libraries</weblink>".&#32;<it>Dunedin City Council</it>.&#32;Retrieved on <link>
2008-08-30</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Frame, Barbara&#32;(February 2008).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dunedinlibraries.co.nz/home/?MIvalObj=word2008feb">
100 Years!</weblink>". <it>the word</it>: p.7. Retrieved on <link>
2008-04-30</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Angus, Janet&#32;(February 1996).&#32;"A Brief History Of The Waikouaiti Library!". Retrieved on <link>
2008-05-08</link>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dunedinlibraries.govt.nz/">
Dunedin Public Libraries website - www.dunedinlibraries.govt.nz</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/dunedinpubliclibraries/">
Dunedin Public Libraries on Flickr.com</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nz.youtube.com/dunedinlibraries/">
Dunedin Public Libraries on YouTube</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dunedinpubliclibraries.wordpress.com/">
Dunedin Public Libraries News &amp; Reviews Blog</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</library>
</building>
</article>
