<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:42:03[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Cyclotron</title>
<id>44585</id>
<revision>
<id>239439260</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-19T02:08:30Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Cthunter01</username>
<id>3223207</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Particle accelerators</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="150px" src="Cyclotron.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A modern Cyclotron for radiation therapy
</caption>
</image>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../931/5320931.xml">
Cyclotron (disambiguation)</link>.
A <b>cyclotron</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/18589032.xml">
particle accelerator</link>.   Cyclotrons accelerate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/352541.xml">
charged particle</link>s using a high-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/10779.xml">
frequency</link>, alternating <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/32549.xml">
voltage</link> (potential difference).  A perpendicular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/36563.xml">
magnetic field</link> causes the particles to spiral almost in a circle so that they re-encounter the accelerating voltage many times.    <p>

<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../040/39040.xml">
Ernest Lawrence</link></scientist>
, of the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<ranking wordnetid="114429484" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/31922.xml">
University of California, Berkeley</link></ranking>
</university>
, is credited with the invention of the cyclotron in 1929. He used it in experiments that required particles with energy of up to 1 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/9598.xml">
MeV</link>. </p>

<sec>
<st>
 How the cyclotron works </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="Cyclotron_patent.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

Diagram of cyclotron operation from Lawrence's 1934 patent.
</caption>
</image>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/10008.xml">
electrode</link>s shown at the right would be in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../858/634858.xml">
vacuum chamber</link>, which is flat, in a narrow gap between the two <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/197632.xml">
poles</link> of a large magnet.</p>
<p>

In the cyclotron, a high-frequency <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/42986.xml">
alternating voltage</link> applied across the "D" electrodes (also called "dees") alternately attracts and repels <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/352541.xml">
charged particle</link>s.  The particles, injected near the center of the magnetic field, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/25th_century.xml">
accelerate</link> only when passing through the gap between the electrodes. The perpendicular <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/36563.xml">
magnetic field</link> (passing vertically through the "D" electrodes), combined with the increasing energy of the particles forces the particles to travel in a spiral path. </p>
<p>

With no change in energy the charged particles in a magnetic field will follow a circular path. In the cyclotron, energy is applied to the particles as they cross the gap between the dees and so they are accelerated (at the typical sub-relativistic speeds used) and will increase in mass as they approach the speed of light. Either of these effects (increased velocity or increased mass) will increase the radius of the circle and so the path will be a spiral.</p>
<p>

(The particles move in a spiral, because a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/6207.xml">
current</link> of electrons or ions, flowing perpendicular to a magnetic field, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../536/221536.xml">
experiences a perpendicular</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/10902.xml">
force</link>.  The charged particles move freely in a vacuum, so the particles follow a spiral path.)</p>
<p>

The radius will increase until the particles hit a target at the perimeter of the vacuum chamber. Various materials may be used for the target, and the collisions will create secondary particles which may be guided outside of the cyclotron and into instruments for analysis. The results will enable the calculation of various properties, such as the mean spacing between atoms and the creation of various collision products. Subsequent chemical and particle analysis of the target material may give insight into nuclear transmutation of the elements used in the target.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Uses of the cyclotron </st>
<p>

For several decades, cyclotrons were the best source of high-energy beams for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/21285.xml">
nuclear physics</link> experiments; several cyclotrons are still in use for this type of research.      </p>
<p>

Cyclotrons can be used to treat <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../219/105219.xml">
cancer</link>.   Ion beams from cyclotrons can be used, as in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../549/1164549.xml">
proton therapy</link>, to penetrate the body and kill tumors by <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../196/151196.xml">
radiation damage</link></disease>
, while minimizing damage to healthy tissue along their path.  </p>
<p>

Cyclotron beams can be used to bombard other atoms to produce short-lived <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../731/24731.xml">
positron</link>-emitting isotopes suitable for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/24032.xml">
PET imaging</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Problems solved by the cyclotron </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="Cyclotron_with_glowing_beam.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

60-inch cyclotron, circa 1939, showing a beam of accelerated ions (likely protons or deuterons) escaping the accelerator and ionizing the surrounding air causing a blue glow. This phenomenon of air ionization is analogous to the one responsible for producing the "blue flash" infamously noted by witnesses of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../651/949651.xml">
criticality accident</link>s. Though the effect is often mistaken for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/95166.xml">
Cherenkov radiation</link>, this is not the case.
</caption>
</image>

The cyclotron was an improvement over the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/273524.xml">
linear accelerator</link>s that were available when it was invented.  A linear accelerator (also called a linac) accelerates particles in a straight line through an evacuated tube (or series of such tubes placed end to end).  A set of electrodes shaped like flat donuts are arranged inside the length of the tube(s).  These are driven by high-power radio waves that continuously switch between positive and negative voltage, causing particles traveling along the center of the tube to accelerate.  In the 1920s, it was not possible to get high frequency radio waves at high power, so either the accelerating electrodes had to be far apart to accommodate the low frequency or more stages were required to compensate for the low power at each stage.  Either way, higher-energy particles required longer accelerators than scientists could afford. </p>
<p>

Modern linacs use high power <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/234132.xml">
Klystron</link>s and other devices able to impart much more power at higher frequencies.  But before these devices existed, cyclotrons were cheaper than linacs. </p>
<p>

Cyclotrons accelerate particles in a spiral path.  Therefore, a compact accelerator can contain much more distance than a linear accelerator, with more opportunities to accelerate the particles.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Advantages of the cyclotron</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cyclotrons have a single electrical driver, which saves both money and power, since more expense may be allocated to increasing efficiency.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Cyclotrons produce a continuous stream of particles at the target, so the average power is relatively high.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The compactness of the device reduces other costs, such as its foundations, radiation shielding, and the enclosing building.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Limitations of the cyclotron </st>
<p>

<image location="right" width="300px" src="LawrenceCyclotronMagnet.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The magnet portion of a large cyclotron. The gray object is the upper pole piece, routing the magnetic field in two loops through a similar part below. The white canisters held conductive coils to generate the magnetic field. The D electrodes are contained in a vacuum chamber that was inserted in the central field gap.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/61563.xml">
spiral</link> path of the cyclotron beam can only "synch up" with klystron-type (constant frequency) voltage sources if the accelerated particles are approximately obeying <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/55212.xml">
Newton's Laws of Motion</link>.   If the particles become fast enough that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/26962.xml">
relativistic</link> effects become important, the beam gets out of phase with the oscillating electric field, and cannot receive any additional acceleration.   The cyclotron is therefore only capable of accelerating particles up to a few percent of the speed of light. To accommodate increased mass the magnetic field may be modified by appropriately shaping the pole pieces as in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/15931773.xml">
isochronous cyclotron</link>s, operating in a pulsed mode and changing the frequency applied to the dees as in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/596987.xml">
synchrocyclotron</link>s, either of which is limited by the diminishing cost effectiveness of making larger machines. Cost limitations have been overcome by employing the more complex <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/599215.xml">
synchrotron</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/273524.xml">
linear accelerator</link>, both of which have the advantage of scalability, offering more power within an improved cost structure as the machines are made larger.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Mathematics of the cyclotron </st>

<ss1>
<st>
Non-relativistic</st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../534/7534.xml">
centripetal force</link> is provided by the transverse magnetic field <it>B</it>, and the force on a particle travelling in a magnetic field (which causes it to be angularly displaced, i.e spiral) is equal to <it>Bqv</it>. So,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\frac{mv^2}{r} = Bqv</math>
</indent>

(Where m is the mass of the particle, q is its charge, v is its velocity and r is the radius of its path.)</p>
<p>

The speed at which the particles enter the cyclotron due to a potential difference, V.
<indent level="1">

<math>v = \sqrt{\frac{2Vq}{m}}</math>
</indent>

Therefore,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\frac{v}{r} = \frac{Bq}{m}</math>
</indent>

v/r is equal to angular velocity, <it>ω</it>, so</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\omega = \frac{Bq}{m}</math>
</indent>

And since the angular frequency is</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>\omega = {2\pi} f_c </math>
</indent>

Therefore,</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>f_c = \frac{Bq}{2\pi m}</math>
</indent>
<image location="right" width="300 px" src="LawrenceCyclotronDees.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A pair of "dee" electrodes with loops of coolant pipes on their surface at the <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<science_museum wordnetid="104147364" confidence="0.8">
<facility wordnetid="103315023" confidence="0.8">
<depository wordnetid="103177349" confidence="0.8">
<museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../268/635268.xml">
Lawrence Hall of Science</link></museum>
</depository>
</facility>
</science_museum>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
. The particle exit point may be seen at the top of the upper dee, where the target would be positioned
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

This shows that for a particle of constant mass, the frequency does not depend upon the radius of the particle's orbit. As the beam spirals out, its frequency does not decrease, and it must continue to accelerate, as it is travelling more distance in the same time. As particles approach the speed of light, they acquire additional mass, requiring modifications to the frequency, or the magnetic field during the acceleration. This is accomplished in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/596987.xml">
synchrocyclotron</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Relativistic</st>
<p>

The radius of curvature for a particle moving relativistically in a static magnetic field is
<indent level="1">

<math>r = \frac{\gamma m v}{q B}</math>
</indent>
:where
<indent level="1">

<math>\gamma=\frac{1}{\sqrt{1-\left(\frac{v}{c}\right)^2}}</math> the <process wordnetid="100029677" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<phenomenon wordnetid="100034213" confidence="0.8">
<consequence wordnetid="111410625" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/732446.xml">
Lorentz factor</link></consequence>
</phenomenon>
</physical_entity>
</process>

</indent>

Note that in high-energy experiments energy, E, and momentum, p, are used rather than velocity, and both measured in units of energy.  In that case one should use the substitution,
<indent level="1">

<math>\frac{p}{E} = v</math>
</indent>
:where this is in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../615/24615.xml">
Natural units</link></p>
<p>

The relativistic cyclotron frequency is</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<math>f=f_c\sqrt{1-\left(\frac{v}{c}\right)^2}</math>,
</indent>

<indent level="1">

where 
</indent>
:<math>f_c</math> is the classical frequency, given  above, of a charged particle with velocity 
<indent level="1">

<math>v</math> circling in a magnetic field.
</indent>

The rest mass of an electron is 511 keV, so the frequency correction is 1% for a magnetic vacuum tube with a 5.11 kV direct current accelerating voltage.  The proton mass is nearly two thousand times the electron mass, so the 1% correction energy is about 9 MeV, which is sufficient to induce nuclear reactions.</p>
<p>

An alternative to the synchrocyclotron is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/15931773.xml">
isochronous cyclotron</link>, which has a magnetic field that increases with radius, rather than with time.  The de-focusing effect of this radial field gradient is compensated by ridges on the magnet faces which vary the field azimuthally as well.  This allows particles to be accelerated continuously, on every period of the radio frequency, rather than in bursts as in most other accelerator types.  This principle that alternating field gradients have a net focusing effect is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/13454888.xml">
strong focusing</link>.  It was obscurely known theoretically long before it was put into practice.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Related technologies</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The spiraling of electrons in a cylindrical vacuum chamber within a transverse magnetic field is also employed in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/20861.xml">
magnetron</link>, a device for producing high frequency radio waves (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/20097.xml">
microwaves</link>).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/599215.xml">
Synchrotron</link> moves the particles through a path of constant radius, allowing it to be made as a pipe and so of much larger radius than is practical with the cyclotron and synchrocyclotron. The larger radius allows the use of numerous magnets, each of which imparts angular momentum and so allows particles of higher velocity (mass) to be kept within the bounds of the evacuated pipe. The magnetic field strength of each of the bending magnets is increased as the particles gain energy in order to keep the bending angle constant.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/515382.xml">
Beamline</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../757/170757.xml">
cyclotron radiation</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../507/379507.xml">
synchrotron light</link> or its close relative, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/54147.xml">
bremsstrahlung</link> radiation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/439202.xml">
electron cyclotron resonance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/1363288.xml">
Gyrotron</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/13251197.xml">
ion cyclotron resonance</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/273524.xml">
Linear accelerator</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/18589032.xml">
Particle accelerator</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/19651322.xml">
Storage ring</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../987/596987.xml">
synchrocyclotron</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/599215.xml">
synchrotron</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <institute wordnetid="108407330" confidence="0.8">
<association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/683374.xml">
TRIUMF</link></association>
</institute>
 - largest cyclotron in the world</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/3209246.xml">
Radiation reaction</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber=1948384">
U.S. Patent 1,948,384</weblink><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.pat2pdf.org/pat2pdf/foo.pl?number=1948384">
&nbsp;</weblink> -- <it>Method and apparatus for the acceleration of ions''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iucf.indiana.edu/">
Indiana University Cyclotron Facility</weblink>  MPRI treats first patient using robotic gantry system.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://user88.lbl.gov/">
"The 88-Inch Cyclotron at LBNL"</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nscl.msu.edu/">
"The NSCL at Michigan State University"</weblink> Home of coupled K500 and K1200 cyclotrons; the K500, being the first superconducting cyclotron and the K1200 currently the most powerful in the world.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.physics.rutgers.edu/cyclotron/">
Rutgers Cyclotron</weblink> and <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.physicstoday.org/vol-57/iss-11/p30.html">
"Building a Cyclotron on a Shoestring"</weblink> Tim Koeth, now a graduate student at <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/80135.xml">
Rutgers University</link></university>
, built a 12-inch 1 MeV cyclotron as an undergraduate project, which is now used for a senior-level undergraduate and a graduate lab course.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.phy.ntnu.edu.tw/java/cyclotron/cyclotron.html">
"Cyclotron java applet"</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.niell.org/cyc2.html">
"Resonance Spectral Analysis with a Homebuilt Cyclotron"</weblink> an experiment done by Fred M. Niell, III his senior year of high school (1994-95) with which  he won the overall grand prize in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/1889522.xml">
ISEF</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://casa.colorado.edu/~wcash/APS3730/chapter6.pdf">
 Relativistic accelerator physics PDF</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.wired.com/news/politics/0,1283,69726,00.html?tw=wn_tophead_1#">
Wired news article</weblink> about a neighborhood cyclotron in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../698/7004698.xml">
Anchorage, Alaska</link></village>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iba.be">
web site of company IBA </weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://thecyclotronkids.com/">
The Cyclotron Kids</weblink> A group of high schooled students attempting to build their own 1 MeV cyclotron for experimentation.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
