<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:06:46[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<disputant  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109615465">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<reformer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110515194">
<farmer  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110078806">
<militant  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110315837">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<creator  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109614315">
<header>
<title>Mark Purdey</title>
<id>12195660</id>
<revision>
<id>242638853</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-03T01:10:05Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Good Olfactory</username>
<id>6454287</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>People from Hertfordshire</category>
<category>Old Haileyburians</category>
<category>British activists</category>
<category>2006 deaths</category>
<category>British farmers</category>
<category>Cancer deaths in England</category>
<category>People from Somerset</category>
<category>1953 births</category>
<category>Deaths from brain cancer</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>John Mark Purdey</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/8270.xml">
December 25</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/34865.xml">
1953</link> &ndash; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/21631.xml">
November 12</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link>) was a British organic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../688/58688.xml">
farmer</link> who came to public attention in the 1980s, when he began to investigate the causes of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/19344418.xml">
bovine spongiform encephalopathy</link> (BSE or "mad cow disease").<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref><p>

Purdey's interest in the disease was triggered when four cows he purchased for his farm developed the disease, though no animal raised on his farm ever contracted it.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> His early self-funded research concluded that BSE was not an infectious disease, contrary to the mainstream scientific view, but that it had an environmental cause. He suggested this might be <pesticide wordnetid="114980215" confidence="0.8">
<substance wordnetid="100019613" confidence="0.8">
<chemical wordnetid="114806838" confidence="0.8">
<insecticide wordnetid="114919948" confidence="0.8">
<part wordnetid="113809207" confidence="0.8">
<material wordnetid="114580897" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../993/6306993.xml">
Phosmet</link></material>
</part>
</insecticide>
</chemical>
</substance>
</pesticide>
, a systemic <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../629/959629.xml">
organophosphate</link> insecticide that was being spread along the spines of <right wordnetid="105174653" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../473/419473.xml">
intensively farmed</link></right>
 cows to eradicate <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../768/1233768.xml">
warble fly</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> Purdey argued that the chemicals, derived from military nerve gases,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> disturbed the balance of metals in the animals' brains, giving rise to the misfolded proteins called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/23048.xml">
prions</link> that are regarded as the cause of BSE. Through the High Court, he successfully challenged the British government's compulsory warble fly eradication program, which would have compelled him to treat his own cattle with the insecticide.</p>
<p>

His later research into BSE indicated that a combination of high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../051/19051.xml">
manganese</link> and low <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../293/125293.xml">
copper</link> in the soil, together with high environmental oxidizing agents, might "initiate a self-perpetuating free radical mediated neurodegenerative disease process (e.g., a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/235248.xml">
TSE</link>) in susceptible genotypes."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> He also argued that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../248/235248.xml">
transmissible spongiform encephalopathies</link> (TSEs or prion diseases) are linked to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/6302185.xml">
Parkinson's</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/18914017.xml">
Alzheimer's</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> His work was published in several peer-reviewed journals, and he collaborated with researchers at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../796/31796.xml">
Cambridge</link> and <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/572330.xml">
Kobe</link></university>
. He delivered lectures around the world to farmers and academics, and was invited to present his research to the British government's Phillips Inquiry into BSE.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> He called himself an "underground scientist" and "eco detective."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> He was awarded an Eco Agriculture Annual Achievement Award in 2001, and the Weston A. Price Foundation's Integrity in Science Annual Award in 2002.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

His view remains a minority one. The Phillips Inquiry concluded that "[t]he theory that BSE is caused by the application to cattle of organophosphorus pesticides is not viable, although there is a possibility that these can increase the susceptibility of cattle to BSE."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
Personal life</st>
<p>

Purdey was born in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/424709.xml">
Much Hadham</link></site>
, <county wordnetid="108546183" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../986/13986.xml">
Hertfordshire</link></county>
, to what <it>The Daily Telegraph</it> describes as a "long line of gifted eccentrics."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The <it>Telegraph</it> reports that an ancestor of his reportedly walked from Inverness to London to set up Purdey's gunsmiths, and that, after suffering <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../091/1019091.xml">
shell shock</link> during the First World War, his grandfather, Lionel Purdey, lobbied <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/246981.xml">
Lord Kitchener</link> to recognize shell shock as an illness that needed treatment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref></p>
<p>

He was educated at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/242825.xml">
Haileybury College</link>, Hertfordshire, but was reportedly expelled after his A-levels.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> He turned down a place at London University to study zoology and psychology and, according to <it> The Guardian</it>, "embarked on a kind of post-hippie bucolic existence."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

In his mid-twenties, he set up an organic dairy farm, first in Ireland, and later in Pembrokeshire, on which he bred a herd of pedigree Jersey cattle. He wrote on his website that he introduced semen from New Zealand, Denmark, and Canada, in order to produce a "high fat, high yielding, pasture-fed Jersey cow" with an ability to produce milk from a "self-sufficient arable/legume-grass rotational system with minimal reliance upon purchased in concentrate feed."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> In 1997, one of his cows was the highest yielding Jersey cow in the UK, with 10,150-litre lactation, after she had been sold to a conventional farm.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  He is reported to have enjoyed playing the saxophone to his cows to keep them calm.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>
<p>

He married Carol MacDonald in 1974, a marriage that produced a son and a daughter. When that relationship broke up, he set up home with Margaret Unwin, with whom he had four daughters and two sons. They married one year before his death. He died of a brain tumour on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/21631.xml">
November 12</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/36164.xml">
2006</link> on his farm in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/449183.xml">
Elworthy, West Somerset</link></district>
</location>
</region>
.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Views of Purdey</st>
<p>

<it>The Guardian</it> writes that Purdey was regarded as an "irritant" by the British scientific establishment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> When he died, <it>The Daily Telegraph</it> wrote that he was a "shambling, scarecrow-like figure who cared little about his appearance," regarded "by his critics as a deranged, dangerous agitator, and by his admirers as an enlightened and inspired visionary sleuth."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

His anti-establishment views, his doggedness, and his willingness to educate himself brought him some high-level contacts in the UK, including the <sovereign wordnetid="110628644" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<aristocrat wordnetid="109807754" confidence="0.8">
<acquirer wordnetid="109764201" confidence="0.8">
<heir wordnetid="110168584" confidence="0.8">
<recipient wordnetid="109627906" confidence="0.8">
<ruler wordnetid="110541229" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<representative wordnetid="110522035" confidence="0.8">
<prince wordnetid="110472799" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head_of_state wordnetid="110164747" confidence="0.8">
<negotiator wordnetid="110351874" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/46204.xml">
Prince of Wales</link></negotiator>
</head_of_state>
</causal_agent>
</leader>
</prince>
</representative>
</communicator>
</ruler>
</recipient>
</heir>
</acquirer>
</aristocrat>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</sovereign>
 and <politician wordnetid="110451263" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../364/302364.xml">
Lord King</link></politician>
, the former defence secretary, who regarded Purdey's work as a "classic piece of scientific investigation."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> It was King who, in April 1993, formally alerted the Ministry of Agriculture to Purdey's research, after Purdey forwarded King a letter from Professor Satoshi Ishikawa of Kitasato University, who wrote that Purdey's description "about Mad cows to organophosphates compounds and warble fly is exactly true."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref></p>
<p>

<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/416063.xml">
Teresa Gorman</link></person>
, MP for Billericay and <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/31034.xml">
Ted Hughes</link></person>
, the poet laureate, were also supporters, while readers of <it>The Guardian</it> contributed to a fund to help pay for his research into BSE and its human equivalent, <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/5617.xml">
Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</link></disease>
 (CJD).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
His research</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Origins</st>
<p>

Purdey's suspicions about Phosmet pre-dated the first recorded case of BSE in the UK. In the early 80s, he challenged the Warble Fly (England and Wales) Order 1982, which required farmers to treat their cattle with organophosphorus compounds (OPs) to combat an outbreak of warble fly. He first sought an exemption from the Animal Health Division of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/356598.xml">
Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food</link> (MAFF), entering into correspondence with them about his concerns about OP use, and asking permission to use an alternative warblecide, which was turned down in 1984. In 1985, he sought a judicial review of the legislation, and won an exemption from treating his cattle with OP compounds.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>
<p>

His legal victory attracted letters from farmers who believe that using OP compounds had caused them health problems. Purdey began to educate himself about the science of OPs just as the first recorded case of BSE was confirmed. He became convinced there was a connection, in part because cattle in Britain had been given unusually high doses of OPs; and in part because the theory that BSE was spread by contaminated meat and bone meal (MBM) did not, he argued, explain why the disease was not occurring in countries that had imported the same MBM from the UK.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>
<p>

Ignored at first because he was not a scientist, the <it>Telegraph</it> writes that the tide of public opinion started to turn his way after the BBC aired a documentary about his theory in 1988.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> </p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Papers by Purdey</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Auburn university research substantiates the hypothesis that metal microcrystal nucleators initiate the pathogenesis of TSEs," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2005 Oct 12. PMID 16226390</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Metal microcrystal pollutants; the heat resistant, transmissible nucleating agents that initiate the pathogenesis of TSEs?," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2005;65(3):448-77. PMID 15908137</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"The pathogenesis of Machado Joseph Disease: a high manganese/low magnesium initiated CAG expansion mutation in susceptible genotypes?," <it>J Am Coll Nutr</it>, 2004 Dec;23(6):715S-29S. PMID 15637221</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Elevated levels of ferrimagnetic metals in foodchains supporting the Guam cluster of neurodegeneration: do metal nucleated crystal contaminents evoke magnetic fields that initiate the progressive pathogenesis of neurodegeneration?," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2004;63(5):793-809. PMID 15488650</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Elevated silver, barium and strontium in antlers, vegetation and soils sourced from CWD cluster areas: do Ag/Ba/Sr piezoelectric crystals represent the transmissible pathogenic agent in TSEs?," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2004;63(2):211-25. PMID 15236778</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Chronic barium intoxication disrupts sulphated proteoglycan synthesis: a hypothesis for the origins of multiple sclerosis," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2004;62(5):746-54. PMID 15082100 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Does an infrasonic acoustic shock wave resonance of the manganese 3+ loaded/copper depleted prion protein initiate the pathogenesis of TSE?" <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2003 Jun;60(6):797-820. PMID 12699706</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

with Bounias M. "Transmissible spongiform encephalopathies: a family of etiologically complex diseases &mdash; a review," <it>Sci Total Environ</it>, 2002 Oct 7;297(1-3):1-19. PMID 12389776</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Does an ultra violet photooxidation of the manganese-loaded/copper-depleted prion protein in the retina initiate the pathogenesis of TSE?" <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2001 Jul;57(1):29-45. PMID 11421622 </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Ecosystems supporting clusters of sporadic TSEs demonstrate excesses of the radical-generating divalent cation manganese and deficiencies of antioxidant co factors Cu, Se, Fe, Zn. Does a foreign cation substitution at prion protein's Cu domain initiate TSE?" <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 2000 Feb;54(2):278-306. PMID 10790765</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"High-dose exposure to systemic phosmet insecticide modifies the phosphatidylinositol anchor on the prion protein: the origins of new variant transmissible spongiform encephalopathies?," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 1998 Feb;50(2):91-111. PMID 9572563</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"The UK epidemic of BSE: slow virus or chronic pesticide-initiated modification of the prion protein? Part 2: An epidemiological perspective," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>. 1996 May;46(5):445-54 PMID 8735882</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"The UK epidemic of BSE: slow virus or chronic pesticide-initiated modification of the prion protein? Part 1: Mechanisms for a chemically induced pathogenesis/transmissibility," <it>Med Hypotheses</it>, 1996 May;46(5):429-43. PMID 8735881</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Mad Cows and Warble Flies," <it>Ecologist</it>. 1994 24 (3) 100-104.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"Degenerative Nervous Diseases and chemical Pollution," <it>Ecologist</it>, 1994 24 (3) 100-104.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"BSE," <it>Ecologist</it>, 2002 32 (9) 33-37.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

"The manganese loaded/Copper depleted bovine brain fails to neutralise incoming shockbursts of low frequency infrasound; The Origins of BSE?" <it>Journal of Cattle Practice</it> ( J of British Cattle Veterinary Association ), 2002 October, Vol 10 (4) p 311-335.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

with Bounias M. "TSEs; a family of etiologically complex diseases," <it>The Science of the Total Environment</it>, 2002 297 (1-3) pp. 1-19. </entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?view=DETAILS&amp;grid=&amp;xml=/news/2006/11/18/db1802.xml">
"Mark Purdey"</weblink>, <it>The Daily Telegraph</it>, November 18, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.markpurdey.com/mark_purdey.htm">
Mark Purdey</weblink>, <it>markpurdey.com</it>.</entry>
<entry id="3">
Purdey, M. "Are Organophosphate Pesticides Involved in the Causation of Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE)? Hypothesis Based upon a Literature Review and Limited Trials on BSE Cattle," <it>Journal of Nutritional Medicine</it>, 1994, 4, 43-82; see also Purdey, M. "High-dose exposure to systemic phosmet insecticide modifies the phosphatidylinositol anchor on the prion protein: the origins of new variant transmissible spongiform encephalopathies?", <it>Med. Hypotheses</it>, volume 50, issue 2, pp. 91-111, 1998.</entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.markpurdey.com/">
Biography</weblink>, <it>markpurdey.com</it>.</entry>
<entry id="5">
Purdey, M. "Mad Cows and Warble Flies: A Link between BSE and Organophosphates?," <it>The Ecologist</it>, 1992, 22(2), 52-57, cited in <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bseinquiry.gov.uk/report/volume11/chaptec5.htm#482213">
"Scientists after Southwood; section 5, Challenges to the Government's approach, Mr. Mark Purdey"</weblink>, Phillips Inquiry, volume 11, p. 304.</entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bseinquiry.gov.uk/report/volume11/chaptec5.htm#482213">
"Scientists after Southwood; section 5, Challenges to the Government's approach, Mr. Mark Purdey"</weblink>, Phillips Inquiry, volume 11, p. 304.</entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bseinquiry.gov.uk/report/volume1/execsum4.htm">
"Volume 1: Findings and Conclusions. Executive Summary of the Report of the Inquiry. 3. The cause of BSE"</weblink>, Phillips Inquiry, October 2000.</entry>
<entry id="8">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?view=DETAILS&amp;grid=&amp;xml=/news/2006/11/18/db1802.xml">
"Mark Purdey"</weblink>, <it>The Daily Telegraph</it>, November 18, 2006; also see Purdey, Lionel. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://home.vicnet.net.au/~emhist/books.htm">
<it>History of the Purdey Family</it></weblink><it>.</it></entry>
<entry id="9">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.markpurdey.com/mark_purdey.htm">
Mark Purdey</weblink>, <it>markpurdey.com</it>.</entry>
<entry id="10">
Woffinden, Bob. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://environment.guardian.co.uk/waste/story/0,,1953067,00.html">
"Obituary"</weblink>, <it>The Guardian</it>, November 21, 2006.</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bseinquiry.gov.uk/files/yb/1992/12/22001001.pdf">
Letter from Satoshi Ishikawa to Mark Purdey"</weblink>, December 22, 1992, cited in <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bseinquiry.gov.uk/report/volume11/chaptec5.htm#482213">
"Scientists after Southwood; section 5, Challenges to the Government's approach, Mr. Mark Purdey"</weblink>, Phillips Inquiry, volume 11, p. 304.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.markpurdey.com/mark_purdey_tributes.htm">
"Tributes to Mark Purdey"</weblink>, <it>markpurdey.com''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Monbiot, George. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.purdeyenvironment.com/George%20Monbiot%20article.htm">
"Mad cows, Bretons and manganese"</weblink>, <it>The Guardian</it>, November 23, 2000.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/72866.stm">
"Farmer says chemicals cause BSE"</weblink>, BBC News, April 2, 1998.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YtyRMJx2VKw">
"Mad Cows and an Englishman"</weblink>, BBC documentary, 2001.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Connor, Steve. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://news.independent.co.uk/people/obituaries/article1990371.ece">
"Mark Purdey: One-man BSE campaigner"</weblink>, <it>The Independent</it>, November 17, 2006.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</creator>
</causal_agent>
</entity>
</militant>
</farmer>
</reformer>
</person>
</disputant>
</physical_entity>
</article>
