<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:24:26[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<organization  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="108008335">
<header>
<title>International Business Leaders Forum</title>
<id>6516741</id>
<revision>
<id>231875036</id>
<timestamp>2008-08-14T09:55:28Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>YBI</username>
<id>7490461</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>1990 establishments</category>
<category>Business ethics organizations</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>International Business Leaders Forum</b> (IBLF) is an organisation which promotes responsible business, particularly in emerging economies. It is backed by over 100 multinational companies, including <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../720/18998720.xml">
BP</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/32413.xml">
Volkswagen</link></company>
, <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/914869.xml">
The Coca-Cola Company</link></company>
 and <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/468997.xml">
Vodafone</link></company>
.<p>

IBLF was created in 1990 by The <sovereign wordnetid="110628644" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<aristocrat wordnetid="109807754" confidence="0.8">
<acquirer wordnetid="109764201" confidence="0.8">
<heir wordnetid="110168584" confidence="0.8">
<recipient wordnetid="109627906" confidence="0.8">
<ruler wordnetid="110541229" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<representative wordnetid="110522035" confidence="0.8">
<prince wordnetid="110472799" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<head_of_state wordnetid="110164747" confidence="0.8">
<negotiator wordnetid="110351874" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/46204.xml">
Prince of Wales</link></negotiator>
</head_of_state>
</causal_agent>
</leader>
</prince>
</representative>
</communicator>
</ruler>
</recipient>
</heir>
</acquirer>
</aristocrat>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</sovereign>
 and a group of international chief executives as a response to the changing face of globalisation, and in particular the fear that business was having a negative impact on society. It started work in central and eastern Europe - helping to stabilise society following the collapse of Communism, but now works in emerging markets globally.</p>
<p>

The International Business Leaders Forum partners with leading businesses to inspire and realize sustainable enterprise and global development.  In a world where trust and reputation are vital to sustainable business and relationships, IBLF enables business to connect its aspirations for global citizenship to opportunities on the ground.</p>
<p>

<b><person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/7893826.xml">
E. Neville Isdell</link></person>
, Chairman and CEO, The Coca-Cola Company:</b>
“We have found IBLF to be a dynamic, forward looking organisation, capable of anticipating emerging issues and contributing thoughtfully to how we manage those issues through the Coca-Cola system.”</p>
<p>

IBLF focuses its expertise on the critical business issues of:</p>
<p>

Leadership &amp; Exchange - connecting senior executives throughout its global corporate network &amp; enabling businesses to respond to new trends and innovations, identify mutual opportunities, and share good practices.</p>
<p>

Profile &amp; Branding - using its platforms to highlight partners and their sustainable business activities as examples for other companies, business partners, employees, consumers, regulatory authorities and media.</p>
<p>

Smarter Risk Management - identifying emerging social challenges across markets that could impact profitability and reputation, and developing proactive strategies to help business manage these risks.</p>
<p>

Business Standards - promoting improved standards for the environment, human rights, transparency, and diversity as a means to sustainable growth for business and communities.</p>
<p>

Public-private partnerships - facilitating multi-sector partnerships with government authorities, NGOs and companies to address local economic and social challenges.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Some key achievements </st>
<p>

Since 1999, IBLF has engaged major footwear manufacturers, the Vietnam Chamber of Commerce and Industry, the Government of Vietnam, NGOs, and health and safety specialists in a partnership to improve the working conditions in the footwear industry. After the first three years:
The partnership brought improved standards to 60% of the footwear and leather factories in Vietnam;
Over 500,000 workers in 120 factories were healthier and more committed to their employer;
64% of managers reported increases in productivity as a result of the improved working conditions; 
53% of managers said that orders had increased and they were more competitive.</p>
<p>

Across Central and Eastern Europe, IBLF has helped hundreds of companies to respond to the changing role of business in society since the collapse of communism.</p>
<p>

Following the UK government's 2005 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../664/1960664.xml">
Commission for Africa</link>, IBLF helped set up <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.businessactionforafrica.org">
Business Action for Africa</weblink>, a coalition of international businesses committed to eradicating poverty in Africa.</p>
<p>

<financial_institution wordnetid="108054721" confidence="0.8">
<foundation wordnetid="108406486" confidence="0.8">
<charity wordnetid="108406619" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link>
The Prince's Youth Business International</link></institution>
</charity>
</foundation>
</financial_institution>
 operated as part of IBLF from when it was set up in 1999 to its independence in 2008 - supporting the entrepreneurship of disadvantaged young people on six continents through seed funding, skills training, and business mentoring by IBLF Corporate Partners. The YBI network has helped to create 90,000 new businesses since its foundation.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 IBLF's programmes </st>

<p>

Digital Partnership - recycling ICT equipment from IBLF Corporate Partners to Africa and Asia, enabling affordable access to technology, training and the Internet and promoting socio-economic development. Digital Partnership has made technology &amp; training available to two million South African students.</p>
<p>

Health Partnership – developing profitable strategies for IBLF Corporate Partners to promote good health – combating diseases and health risks in the marketplace and at the workplace and community levels.</p>
<p>

The Partnering Initiative - promotes cross-sector partnerships for sustainable development</p>
<p>

Tourism Partnership - mobilizing travel and tourism companies to adopt environmentally, economically, and socially sustainable practices, enabling the sector to be a positive force for development.</p>
<p>

Youth Career Initiative - collaborating with business to equip and empower disadvantaged young people with vocational and life skills, increasing their employability, opportunities and choices. Through YCI, 1,500 disadvantaged youth have been trained for the service sectors, including tourism, banking, and nursing.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iblf.org">
IBLF website</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</organization>
</article>
