<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:38:27[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Anthropometric history</title>
<id>6988346</id>
<revision>
<id>239963228</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-21T09:07:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Tyler</username>
<id>5684039</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Anthropometry</category>
<category>Miscellaneous articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>Articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>History articles needing expert attention</category>
<category>History by topic</category>
<category>Pages needing expert attention</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_content.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.</b><p>

  may be able to help recruit one.
If a more appropriate  or 
portalexists, please adjust this template accordingly.</p>
</col>
</row>
</table>


<b>Anthropometric history</b> is a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/180184.xml">
term</link> coined in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/34847.xml">
1989</link> by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/6988554.xml">
John Komlos</link> to refer to the study of the history of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/905957.xml">
human height</link>, focusing on explaining <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/6746761.xml">
secular trend</link>s, cycles of various lengths and cross sectional patterns by changes in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../119/503119.xml">
socio-economic</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/66997.xml">
epidemiological</link> environment. 
<sec>
<st>
Development of the field</st>
<p>

The systematic study of human physical stature reaches back into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../570/34570.xml">
18th century</link> (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<baby_doctor wordnetid="109828760" confidence="0.8">
<medical_practitioner wordnetid="110305802" confidence="0.8">
<specialist wordnetid="110632576" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<health_professional wordnetid="110165109" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<doctor wordnetid="110020890" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/1335881.xml">
Tanner</link></doctor>
</professional>
</adult>
</health_professional>
</causal_agent>
</specialist>
</medical_practitioner>
</baby_doctor>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, 1981).  By the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/34795.xml">
1830s</link>, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/184215.xml">
Adolphe Quetelet</link></scientist>
 and <link>
René Villermé</link> recognized that biological outcomes were influenced by both the natural and the socio-economic environment (Villermé, 1829, Quetelet, 1842). However, until French historians of the <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<explanation wordnetid="105793000" confidence="0.8">
<theory wordnetid="105989479" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../316/1316.xml">
Annales School</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</theory>
</explanation>
</thinking>
</process>
 began to explore the socio-economic correlates of human height in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../545/34545.xml">
1960s</link>, the topic interested primarily scholars of sister disciplines such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/569.xml">
anthropology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/973095.xml">
auxology</link>, or even military history (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<historian wordnetid="110177150" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/376823.xml">
Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie</link></scholar>
</historian>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, Bernageau, and Pasquet, 1969). </p>
<p>

The true expansion of the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/330879.xml">
anthropometric</link>s in the social sciences began in the mid-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../555/34555.xml">
1970s</link> among cliometricians who were interested in measuring living standards in the past primarily in order to understand better hitherto hidden effects of economic development on the growth of the human organism. Anthropometric history uses physical stature as an indicator of well-being to <it>complement</it> conventional indicators of living standards by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../973/6988973.xml">
biological standard of living</link> (Baten, 2000; Craig and Weiss, 1998; Cuff, 2005; Steckel, 1995; Sunder, 2004; Woitek, 2003). </p>
<p>

Nevertheless, this is not to say that height itself has a direct benefit on economic success or an increased standard of living.  Rod Usher's "A Tall Story For Our Time" shows that one's tallness is a product of favorable living conditions. Thus, growth in human height within a designated area could well be an accurate measurement of economic growth and development there.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Significance</st>
<p>

There are many motivations to study the field (<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/1162218.xml">
Robert Fogel</link></scientist>
, 1994). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../183/210183.xml">
Developmental economists</link> are concerned both with the impact of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/21525.xml">
nutrition</link> on labor <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/424899.xml">
productivity</link>, and with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../274/852274.xml">
social policy</link> questions pertaining to poverty, particularly among children (Dasgupta 1993). The need for alternative measures of the standard of living is particularly important for economic historians exploring the distant past when conventional indicators are unavailable (Engerman, 1976; Steckel 1979). The most immediate concern of economic historians in the 1970s was to extend the existing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../270/15270.xml">
index</link>es of living standards backward in time, to illuminate the famous debate about the living conditions of workers during the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/14914.xml">
industrial revolution</link>, and to provide indexes where none existed before. For instance, conventional measures of money income obviously did not exist for subgroups of the society such as females or children or self-sufficient peasants (Komlos 1998).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Nutritional status</st>
<p>

The intake of nutrition and expenditure of energy is called net nutritional status. Among adults nutritional status affects weight, but not height. The relationship between the height of a population and its demographic and economic structure is based on the fact that human growth is related to food consumption, and therefore to such economic variables as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/23893.xml">
per capita income</link> and the price of food.  It is also related to demographic processes inasmuch as population growth affects agricultural productivity. Since the body's ability to process nutrients is influenced by its disease encounters the epidemiological environment, too, plays a role in determining the height of a population. The height of a population is, therefore, a historical record of the caloric and protein intake of the youth of that population as well as of environmental factors such as disease encounters.</p>
<p>

In addition, claims on nutrient intake such as work during adolescence, frequency, length and severity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../967/937967.xml">
endemic</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../981/66981.xml">
epidemic</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/8072.xml">
disease</link>s or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../872/24872.xml">
pollutant</link>s affect growth. Hence, improvements in medical technology and public <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../729/184729.xml">
sanitation</link> have a substantial impact on physical growth as they did in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/34558.xml">
20th century</link> (Komlos and Kriwy 2003). The cost of medical services are important as well as how medical institutions are organized because that affects transaction costs and entitlements to health services thereby determining access (entitlements) to health care facilities. The distribution of income within a society also matters insofar as there are diminishing returns to nutrient intake. That implies that the height of children of the rich are expected to increase by less than the decline of the children of the poor, and therefore the two effects do not cancel each other out. The net effect is negative: with income held constant an increase in inequality implies that average height diminishes. Hence, the average height of the population is sensitive to aspects of welfare that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/49808.xml">
GNP</link> per capita data do not capture. These include the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../044/46044.xml">
political economy</link> of health care systems, education, transfers to the poor, and government policy toward equality (hence taxation policy). The analysis often pertains to the determination of trends in height in order to eliminate possible genetic components and analysis of the effects on height of the various variables listed above (Komlos and Baur 2004).</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Conclusion</st>
<p>

Human physical stature is a useful supplementary <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../104/434104.xml">
indicator</link> of well-being. Height and weight are components and a relatively easily measured indicator of biological welfare. In addition, we gain hitherto unknown insights of the effect of economic processes on the human organism. Hence, anthropometric history emphasizes that well-being encompasses more than the command over goods and services. Rather, it is multidimensional, and height, weight, health in general, and longevity all contribute to it—independently of purchasing power. In many ways, such indexes provide a more nuanced view of the impact of dynamic economic processes on the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/47789.xml">
quality of life</link> than income or GNP per capita by itself. Anthropometric indicators are not meant to be substitutes for, but complements of, conventional measures of living standards.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/973095.xml">
Auxology</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Baten, J. (2000) "Economic Development and the Distribution of Nutritional Resources in Bavaria, 1797-1839," in Journal of Income Distribution 9, 89-106.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Craig, L. and T. Weiss (1998), ‘Nutritional Status and Agricultural Surpluses in the Antebellum United States’, in J. Komlos and J. Baten (eds), The Biological Standard of Living in Comparative Perspective, Stuttgart: Franz Steiner.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Cuff, T. (2005), The Hidden Cost of Economic Development: The Biological Standard of Living in Antebellum Pennsylvania, Aldershot, Hants, England: Ashgate.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dasgupta, P. (1995), An Enquiry into Well-Being and Destitution, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Engerman, S. (1976), ‘The Height of U.S. Slaves’, Local Population Studies, Vol. 16, no.1, 45-50.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Fogel, R. (1994), ‘Economic Growth, Population Theory, and Physiology: The Bearing of Long-Term Processes on the making of Economic Policy’, American Economic Review, 369-394.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Komlos, J. (1998) "Shrinking in a Growing Economy? The Mystery of Physical Stature during the Industrial Revolution," Journal of Economic History 58, 3: 779-802.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Komlos, J. (1989) Nutrition and Economic Development in the Eighteenth-Century Habsburg Monarchy: An Anthropometric History, Princeton University Press: 1989.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Komlos, J. and Baur, M. (2004) “From the Tallest to (One of) the Fattest: The Enigmatic Fate of the Size of the American Population in the Twentieth Century,” Economics and Human Biology 2, no. 1: 57-74.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Komlos, J. and Kriwy, P. (2003) “The Biological Standard of Living in the Two Germanies,” German Economic Review 4, 4: 493-507.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Le Roy Ladurie, E., N. Bernageau, and Y. Pasquet (1969), ‘Le Conscrit et l'ordinateur: Perspectives De Recherches Sur Les Archives Militaires du XIXe Siècle Francais’, Studi Storici, 10.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Quetelet, Adolphe M. (1842) A Treatise on Man and the Development of his Faculties. Edinburgh: Chambers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Steckel, R.H. (1979), ‘Slave Height Profiles from Coastwise Manifests’, Explorations in Economic History, Vol. 16, No. 4. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Steckel, R.H. (1995), ‘Stature and the Standard of Living’, Journal of Economic Literature, 1903-40.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sunder, M. (2004), ‘The Making of Giants in a Welfare State: The Norwegian Experience in the Twentieth Century’, Economics and Biology, 75-86.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Tanner, James M. (1981) A History of the Study of Human Growth. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Villermé, L. R. (1829), ‘Mémoire sur la taille de l'homme en France’, Annales d'Hygiène Publique et de Médicine Légale, pp. 351-396.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Woitek, U. (2003), ‘Height Cycles in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries’, Economics and Human Biology, 243-258.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
