<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:09:42[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<technique  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="105665146">
<header>
<title>Catch and release</title>
<id>490901</id>
<revision>
<id>244619294</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T19:02:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>LilHelpa</username>
<id>8024439</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Fishing techniques and methods</category>
<category>recreational fishing</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table style="text-align: center;" class="infobox">
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
fishing</link></header>
<row>
<col>
 <image location="center" width="90px" src="P7190945.JPG">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
the catch</header>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../966/12174966.xml">
rough fish</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/956854.xml">
panfish</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/2367285.xml">
priest</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../823/4699823.xml">
ike jime</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/9288150.xml">
bag limits</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/7370151.xml">
minimum size</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/490901.xml">
catch and release</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../842/16016842.xml">
tag and release</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
----</col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/705225.xml">
recreational</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/223418.xml">
angling</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col>
----</col>
</row>
<row>
<header>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/18425054.xml">
I N D E X</link></header>
</row>

</table>

For other uses, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../763/9366763.xml">
Catch and release (disambiguation)</link>.
<image location="left" width="200px" src="Catch_and_release_salmon.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

Releasing a rod-caught <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/1202747.xml">
Atlantic salmon</link> on the <stream wordnetid="109448361" confidence="0.8">
<body_of_water wordnetid="109225146" confidence="0.8">
<river wordnetid="109411430" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/2636809.xml">
Little Gruinard</link></river>
</body_of_water>
</stream>
 in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../919/1758919.xml">
Wester Ross</link>, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/26994.xml">
Scotland</link></country>

</caption>
</image>
<p>

<b>Catch and release</b> is a practice within <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../381/25381.xml">
recreation</link>al <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
fishing</link> intended as a  of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../216/216216.xml">
conservation</link>. After capture, the fish are unhooked and returned to the water before experiencing serious <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/235562.xml">
exhaustion</link> or injury. Using barbless hooks, it is often possible to release the fish without removing it from the water (a slack line is frequently sufficient).</p>

<sec>
<st>
 History of practice </st>

<p>

In the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, catch and release has been performed for more than a century by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../774/6527774.xml">
coarse fishermen</link> in order to prevent target species from disappearing in heavily fished waters.  Since the latter part of the 20th century, many <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../747/1202747.xml">
salmon</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/412877.xml">
sea trout</link> rivers have been converted to complete or partial catch and release. </p>
<p>

In the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
, catch and release was first introduced as a management tool in the state of <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../859/18859.xml">
Michigan</link></country>
 in 1952 as an effort to reduce the cost of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/14350773.xml">
stocking</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../770/1239770.xml">
hatchery</link>-raised <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/47326.xml">
trout</link>. Anglers fishing for fun rather than for food accepted the idea of releasing the fish while fishing in so-called "no-kill" zones. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../441/45441.xml">
Conservationist</link>s have advocated catch and release as a way to ensure <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/18413531.xml">
sustainability</link> and to avoid <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/478962.xml">
overfishing</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/1580005.xml">
fish stocks</link>. <link>
Lee Wulff</link> also promoted catch and release as he observed the Atlantic Salmon population dwindle.</p>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, catch and release caught on slowly, with some pioneers practicing it the 1960s, and the practice slowly becoming more widespread in the 1970s and 1980s.  Catch and release is now widely used to conserve &mdash; and indeed is critical in conserving &mdash; vulnerable fish species like the large, long lived native freshwater <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/405429.xml">
Murray Cod</link> and the prized, slowly growing, heavily fished <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../427/2155427.xml">
Australian bass</link>, heavily fished coastal species like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/10114422.xml">
Dusky Flathead</link> and prized gamefish like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/4433754.xml">
striped marlin</link>.</p>
<p>

In the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../560/14560.xml">
Republic of Ireland</link></country>
, catch and release has been used as a conservation tool for atlantic salmon and sea trout fisheries since 2003. A number of fisheries now have mandatory catch and release regulations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Catch and release for coarse fish has been used by sport anglers for as long as these species have been fished for on this island. However catch and release for Atlantic salmon has required a huge turn about in how many anglers viewed the salmon angling resource. To encourage anglers to practice catch and release in all fisheries a number of Government led incentives have been implemented.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> </p>
<p>

In <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
, catch and release is mandatory for some species. Canada also requires, in some cases, the use of barbless <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/989954.xml">
hooks</link> to facilitate release and minimize injury.</p>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/26748.xml">
Switzerland</link></country>
, catch and release fishing is considered inhumane and will be banned beginning in September 2008.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Catch and release techniques </st>

<p>

<image width="150px" src="Fishhook.jpg" type="frame">
</image>

<image width="150px" src="Professor_with_pinched_barb.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Professor with pinched barb
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

Effective catch and release fishing techniques avoid excessive fish fighting and handling times, avoid damage to fish skin, scale and slime layers (that leave fish vulnerable to fungal skin infections) by nets, dry hands and dry surfaces, and avoid damage to throat ligaments and gills by poor handling techniques.</p>
<p>

The use of barbless hooks is an important aspect of catch and release; barbless hooks reduce injury and handling time, increasing survival. Frequently, fish caught on barbless hooks can be released without being removed from the water, and the hook(s) effortlessly slipped out with a single flick of the pliers or leader.  Barbless hooks can be purchased from several major manufacturers or can be created from a standard hook by crushing the barb(s) flat with needle-nosed pliers.  Some anglers avoid barbless hooks because of the erroneous belief that too many fish will escape. Concentrating on keeping the line tight at all times while fighting fish, equipping lures that do not have them with split rings, and using recurved point or "Triple Grip" style hooks on lures, will keep catch rates with barbless hooks as high as those achieved with barbed hooks.  
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.mustad.no/products/premium/ultrapoint/up_36233bln_b.htm">
Triple Grip treble hooks</weblink> work particularly well with the barbs crushed.</p>
<p>

To make a hook barbless, the barb is simply crushed flat with a pair of needle-nosed pliers; a 2-second task.  Medium grit sandpaper can be further used to ensure complete removal of the barb, but this is not necessary and is rarely done.</p>
<p>

Key aspects of catch and release include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Using strong tackle, to minimize fighting times</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Using needle-nosed pliers to aid unhooking</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Using barbless hooks, for quick, easy hook removal and reduced handling times</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Leaving fish in the water during the unhooking and release process, to avoid any handling</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

If fish are removed from the water for unhooking and/or a photo, key aspects of handling include:   </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Avoiding the use of landing nets; if landing nets must be used, specially designed catch-and-release landing nets (e.g. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.troutlet.com/Loki-Catch-Release-Trout-Nets-P67.aspx">
Special Catch and Release nets</weblink>)are used</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Avoiding touching the fish with dry hands or dry surfaces (e.g. shirt fronts) or putting them down on dry surfaces (e.g. rocks, boat gunwhales, boat bottoms)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Never squeeze the fish or rip a hook out   </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Only touching the fish with wet hands and wet surfaces (e.g. wet towel)   </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Avoiding hanging fish from their jaw/mouth/gills   </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Holding fish horizontally, and supporting large fish with a second hand under the belly   </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Minimizing time out of the water (e.g. 20–30 seconds) </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Support the fish gently upright in the water until it swims away</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Place the fish in the water gently, supporting its mid-section</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Move the fish gently back and forth until you feel it start to swim away. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The effects of catch and release vary from species to species.  A number of scientific studies have shown extremely high survival rates (97%+) (e.g. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>) for released fish if handled correctly and particularly if caught on artificial baits such as lures.  Fish caught on lures are usually hooked cleanly in the mouth, minimising injury and aiding release.  Other studies have shown somewhat lower but encouragingly high survival rates for fish gut-hooked on bait if the line is cut and the fish is released without trying to remove the hook.  This procedure should be followed for any gut-hooked fish intended or required to be released.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Debate </st>

<p>

Catch and release is a conservation practice developed to prevent <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/478962.xml">
overharvest</link></issue>
 of fish stocks in the face of growing human populations, mounting fishing pressure, increasingly effective fishing tackle and techniques, inadequate fishing regulations and enforcement, and habitat degradation. Scientific studies are showing generally high rates of survival for released fish — which is the aim of catch and release — and the alternative of banning or severely restricting angling is generally unreasonable or not feasible.  Fishermen have been practicing catch and release for decades, including with some highly pressured fish species, and no significant, measurable effects from catch and release have been observed, indicating that mortality rates from catch and release are not excessive.  Conversely, had recreational fishing for these highly pressured species continued to the present on a totally catch and kill basis, some of these species fisheries would certainly have collapsed by now. Catch and release is criticized by some who claim it is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../258/9258.xml">
unethical</link> to stress fish for sport or amusement. Some oppose catch and release only but do not oppose fishing for food, <it>per se</it>.</p>
<p>

Proponents of catch and release dispute the suggestion that fish hooked in the mouth feel pain.  Many point to the fact that fish consume spiny, hard prey items such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../600/43600.xml">
crayfish</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/55038.xml">
molluscs</link> and other fish, and require a tough, insensitive mouth to do so; such a mouth is unlikely to feel a hook point. Some point to studies that claim fish lack the higher brain functions that physiologists often associate with the ability to feel pain. And some quote the many observations fishermen have made of fish succeeding in throwing a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/764520.xml">
lure</link> and then turning around and striking the same lure again, an unlikely behavior if being hooked in mouth causes pain.  Similarly, all observations from fishermen support the contention that hooked fish fight because they feel the pull of fishing line, <b>not</b> because the hook in their mouth hurts.  Suitably strong tackle reduces fighting times and reduces stress on captured fish.</p>
<p>

Opponents of catch and release point out that fish are highly evolved vertebrates that share many of the same neurological structures that, in humans, are associated with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../879/569879.xml">
pain perception</link>. They point to studies that show that, neurologically, fish are quite similar to "higher" vertebrates and that blood chemistry reveals that hormones and blood metabolites associated with stress are quite high in fish struggling against hook and line. The idea that fish do not feel pain in their mouths has been studied at the University of Edinburgh and the Roslin Institute by injecting bee venom and acetic acid into the lips of rainbow trout; the fish responded by rubbing their lips along the sides and floors of their tanks in an effort to relieve themselves of the sensation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> Lead researcher Dr. Lynne Sneddon wrote "Our research demonstrates nociception and suggests that noxious stimulation in the rainbow trout has adverse behavioral and physiological effects. This fulfills the criteria for animal pain."  However, others argue this may demonstrate a chemical sensitivity rather than pain; notably, no similar result has been obtained with trauma, such as using fishhooks.  Thus, the evidence for pain sensation in fish is at best ambiguous.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>  the last reference shows that fish can detect toxins, as demonstrated by Brown, but that this is very different from pain.  Some anglers accept the arguments that fish are highly evolved vertebrates that can feel pain, but again point out that that fish have tough, bony mouths that often consume spiny, hard prey items, and that hooks therefore do not cause fish pain, despite fish being capable of feeling pain.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Deep sea fishing and catch and release </st>

<p>

While a number of scientific studies have now found survival rates of shallow water fish caught-and-released on fly and lure have extremely high survival rates (95–97%) and modestly high survival rates on bait (70–90%, depending on species, bait, hook size, etc.) emerging research suggests catch and release does not work very well with fish caught when deep sea fishing.  </p>
<p>

Most deep sea fish species suffer from the sudden pressure change when wound to the surface from great depths; these species cannot adjust their body's physiology quickly enough to follow the pressure change.  The result is called "barotrauma".  Fish with barotrauma will have their enormously swollen swim-bladder protruding from their mouth, bulging eyeballs, and often sustain other, more subtle but still very serious injuries.  Upon release, fish with barotrauma will be unable to swim or dive due to the swollen swim-bladder.  The common practice has been to deflate the swim bladder by pricking it with a thin sharp object before attempting to release the fish.</p>
<p>

Emerging research <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.abc.net.au/nt/stories/s1996078.htm">
http://www.abc.net.au/nt/stories/s1996078.htm</weblink> indicates both barotrauma and the practice of deflating the swimbladder are both highly damaging to fish, and that survival rates of caught-and-released deep-sea fish is extremely low.  However, barotrauma requires that fish be caught at least 30 - 50 feet below the surface.  Many surface caught fish, such as billfish, and all fish caught from shore, do not meet this criterion and thus do not suffer barotrauma.</p>
<p>

In light of this research, anglers must show responsibility and restraint when deep sea fishing and, after catching and keeping a reasonable number of deep sea fish, cease fishing for them.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
Fishing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/223418.xml">
Angling</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/705225.xml">
Sport fishing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/218754.xml">
Fly fishing</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cfb.ie/fishing_in_ireland/CatchandRelease.htm">
Catch and Release for Atlantic Salmon</weblink> Central Fisheries Board Website</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cfb.ie/pr/catchandrelease07.htm">
Catch and Release Incentive Scheme</weblink> Central Fisheries Board Website</entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ussportsmen.org/NETCOMMUNITY/Page.aspx?pid=929&amp;srcid=55&amp;srctid=1&amp;e">
Animal Rights Law Passed in Switzerland - Catch and Release Fishing Banned</weblink></entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.publish.csiro.au/nid/126/paper/MF96108.htm">
Australian shallow reef fish study</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.buzzle.com/editorials/4-30-2003-39769.asp">
Vantressa Brown, “Fish Feel Pain, British Researchers Say,” Agence France-Presse, 1 May 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cnn.com/2003/WORLD/europe/04/30/fish.fear/index.html">
"Anglers carp at 'fish pain' theory,", CNN, April 30, 2003</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
http://uwadmnweb.uwyo.edu/Zoology/faculty/rose/Critique%20of%20Sneddon%20article2.doc</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.dnr.state.md.us/fisheries/articles/catch_release.shtml">
Practicing Catch and Release</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://seagrant.gso.uri.edu/factsheets/catch-release_fs.html">
Catch-and-Release Fishing</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nativefish.asn.au/cr.html">
Catch And Release Fishing</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sf.adfg.state.ak.us/statewide/flyfish/candr.cfm">
Catch and release</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/06/070601101117.htm">
Only Some Catch And Release Methods Let The Fish Live</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://saltfishing.about.com/od/catchandrelease/Catch_and_Release_Fishing.htm">
Catch and Release Fishing</weblink> - links from about.com</entry>
</list>
</p>


<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/307491.xml">
Fisheries</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
fishing</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../491/307491.xml">
Fisheries</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/1171019.xml">
Fisheries science</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/494704.xml">
Management</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../678/6145678.xml">
Quota</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../979/17169979.xml">
Wild</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../326/581326.xml">
Habitats</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/153520.xml">
Farmed</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/1634.xml">
Aquaculture</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../103/2579103.xml">
Fish types</link></col>
<col style="width:0%;padding:0px 0px 0px 2px;" rowspan="13">
<image width="160px" src="Trawer_Hauling_Nets.jpg">
</image>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../581/36581.xml">
Fishing</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/16015052.xml">
Fishing history</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../376/10079376.xml">
Fishing vessel</link>s&nbsp;·  <issue wordnetid="105814650" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../175/11017175.xml">
Environment</link></issue>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/491120.xml">
Industry</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/1028691.xml">
Commercial fishing</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/11967708.xml">
Processing</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/16673298.xml">
Products</link>&nbsp;·  <group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<selling wordnetid="101113068" confidence="0.8">
<transaction wordnetid="101106808" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<commerce wordnetid="101090446" confidence="0.8">
<sale wordnetid="101114824" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/16684864.xml">
Marketing</link></sale>
</commerce>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</transaction>
</selling>
</group_action>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/7332666.xml">
Markets</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/705225.xml">
Recreational</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/223418.xml">
Angling</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/525221.xml">
Game fishing</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/218754.xml">
Fly fishing</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/13089116.xml">
Techniques</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../599/16804599.xml">
Gathering</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/306254.xml">
Spearfishing</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../465/1282465.xml">
Line fishing</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../395/1137395.xml">
Netting</link>&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../840/335840.xml">
Trawling</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../490/4321490.xml">
Trapping</link></method>
</know-how>
</technique>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/1790672.xml">
Other</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/6209845.xml">
Tackle</link></col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../954/989954.xml">
Hook</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/47339.xml">
Line</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../621/2212621.xml">
Sinker</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../337/47337.xml">
Rod</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/18388052.xml">
Bait</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/764520.xml">
Lures</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../597/9470597.xml">
Artificial flies</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/12764618.xml">
Bite alarm</link>s</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Locations</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/16701166.xml">
Fishing by country</link>&nbsp;·  <diversion wordnetid="100426928" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<sport wordnetid="100523513" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/11289055.xml">
Localities</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</sport>
</event>
</diversion>
&nbsp;·  <stream wordnetid="109448361" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<body_of_water wordnetid="109225146" confidence="0.8">
<gathering wordnetid="107975026" confidence="0.8">
<community wordnetid="108223802" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<river wordnetid="109411430" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../616/6869616.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Fishing+community%22])">
Communities</link></river>
</group>
</community>
</gathering>
</body_of_water>
</social_group>
</stream>
&nbsp;·  <slope wordnetid="109437454" confidence="0.8">
<geological_formation wordnetid="109287968" confidence="0.8">
<bank wordnetid="109213565" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../792/2193792.xml">
Fishing banks</link></bank>
</geological_formation>
</slope>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="3" style=";" class="navbox-abovebelow">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/18429296.xml">
List of topics by subject</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>



</sec>
</bdy>
</technique>
</article>
