<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:30:53[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<sculpture  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104157320">
<creation  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103129123">
<structure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="104341686">
<building  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="102913152">
<artifact  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100021939">
<figure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113862780">
<art  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="102743547">
<plastic_art  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="103958097">
<shape  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100027807">
<attraction  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="106615561">
<solid_figure  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113863473">
<header>
<title>Crystal Palace Dinosaurs</title>
<id>8680137</id>
<revision>
<id>241424517</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-27T23:34:16Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>D6</username>
<id>75561</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Outdoor sculptures in England</category>
<category>Buildings and structures in Bromley</category>
<category>1854 architecture</category>
<category>Visitor attractions in London</category>
<category>Dinosaur sculptures</category>
<category>Grade I listed buildings in London</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../361/48361.xml">
Coordinates</link>: <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://stable.toolserver.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Crystal_Palace_Dinosaurs&amp;params=51_25_3_N_0_4_2_W_type:landmark_region:GB">
51°25′3″N 0°4′2″W﻿ / ﻿51.4175, -0.06722</weblink>
<image width="250px" src="London_-_Crystal_Palace_-_Victorian_Dinosaurs_1.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/513908.xml">
Megalosaurus</link> sculpture
</caption>
</image>

The <b>Crystal Palace Dinosaurs</b>, also known as <b>Dinosaur Court</b>,  are a series of sculptures of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/8311.xml">
dinosaur</link>s and extinct <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/18838.xml">
mammal</link>s located in <site wordnetid="108651247" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/93961.xml">
Crystal Palace</link></site>
, <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/17867.xml">
London</link></village>
. Commissioned in 1852 and unveiled in 1854, they were the first dinosaur sculptures in the world. Designed and sculpted by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<sculptor wordnetid="110566072" confidence="0.8">
<zoologist wordnetid="110806222" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/764829.xml">
Benjamin Waterhouse Hawkins</link></associate>
</creator>
</zoologist>
</sculptor>
</artist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</biologist>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
, they were <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../009/202009.xml">
Grade II listed buildings</link> from 1973 and upgraded to Grade I listed in 2007.<p>

The models themselves are now considered out of date and by and large inaccurate. </p>

<sec>
<st>
History</st>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="Model_by_Benjamin_Waterhouse_Hawkins,_circa_1852_.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

A model of one of Hawkins's Megalosauri
</caption>
</image>

Following the closure of the <link>
Great Exhibition</link> in October 1851, <structure wordnetid="104341686" confidence="0.8">
<building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<mansion wordnetid="103719053" confidence="0.8">
<dwelling wordnetid="103259505" confidence="0.8">
<housing wordnetid="103546340" confidence="0.8">
<house wordnetid="103544360" confidence="0.8">
<palace wordnetid="103878066" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../837/81837.xml">
The Crystal Palace</link></palace>
</house>
</housing>
</dwelling>
</mansion>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
 was bought and moved to Sydenham Hill, South London by the newly formed Crystal Palace Company; the grounds that surrounded it were then extensively renovated and turned into a public park with ornamental gardens, replicas of statues and two new man-made lakes. As part of this renovation <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<biologist wordnetid="109855630" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<sculptor wordnetid="110566072" confidence="0.8">
<zoologist wordnetid="110806222" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../829/764829.xml">
Benjamin Waterhouse Hawkins</link></associate>
</creator>
</zoologist>
</sculptor>
</artist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</colleague>
</biologist>
</person>
</peer>
</physical_entity>
 was commissioned to build the first ever life-sized models of extinct animals. He had originally planned to just re-create <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/49417.xml">
extinct</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../838/18838.xml">
mammal</link>s before deciding on building dinosaurs as well, which he did with advice from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/160886.xml">
Sir Richard Owen</link>, a celebrated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/2537522.xml">
biologist</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../084/23084.xml">
palaeontologist</link> of the time. Hawkins set up a workshop on site at the park and built the models there.</p>
<p>

The models were displayed on three islands acting as a rough time-line, the first island representing roughly the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../234/23234.xml">
Paleozoic</link> era, a second representing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/19322.xml">
Mesozoic</link> era, and a third representing the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../816/5816.xml">
Cenozoic</link> era. All of the mammals on the third island, however, were later moved  to other locations on in the park (which in many ways directly led to them falling into ill-repair). The models' realism was aided by the lake at the time being 'tidal' and rising and falling, revealing different amounts of the dinosaurs. To mark the 'launch' of the models Hawkins held a dinner on New Years Eve 1853 inside the mould of one of the <it>Iguanodon</it>.</p>
<p>

Hawkins benefited greatly from the public's reaction to them, which was so strong it led to what could be considered the first case of tie-in merchandising as a set of smaller versions of Hawkins's models were sold for £30 as educational products. But the building of the models was costly (having cost around £13,729) and in 1855 the Crystal Palace Company cut Hawkins's funding, leaving several planned models unmade or half finished and scrapped, despite protest from various sources including newspaper <it><newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../086/191086.xml">
The Observer</link></newspaper>
</it>. </p>
<p>

As further and fuller discoveries of the species included in Crystal Palace were made, the reputation of the models declined. By as early as 1895 experts looked on them with scorn and ridicule <it>The Crystal Palace Dinosaurs</it> by Steve McCarthy and Mick Gilbert quotes American fossil hunter <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../114/357114.xml">
Othniel Charles Marsh</link></scientist>
 who scorns the dinosaurs' 'friends' as doing them a great injustice and speaks angrily of the models. The models and indeed the park fell into ill-repair as the years went by, a process aided by the fire that destroyed the Crystal Palace itself in 1936. The visibility of the models became obscured by overgrown foliage, but a full restoration of the animals was carried out in the 1950s by Victor H.C. Martin; this is when the animals were moved around.</p>
<p>

Though general and often ad-hoc maintenance was carried up in the meantime (including the use of plasticine<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ihbc.org.uk/context_archive/75/dinosaurs/dinos.html">
http://www.ihbc.org.uk/context_archive/75/dinosaurs/dinos.html</weblink>) the dinosaurs did not undergo a full restoration until 2002; during that time the park had fallen into total disarray and at one point a guided tour of the dinosaurs was the only time the park was open to the public. In 2002 the Institute of Historic Building Conservation totally renovated the models, including properly fixing and re-painting the existing models (in much lighter or at times totally different colors, for instance the <it>Megatheirium</it> was changed from blue to beige during the restoration). The institute also had fiberglass replacements created for the missing <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/24824.xml">
pterodactyl</link>s and their cliff, cutting away a lot of the foliage and restoring the original recreations of plant life that accompanied the models in the 1850s.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
The sculptures</st>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="Iguanodon1.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The Iguanodon sculptures
</caption>
</image>

Fifteen species of extinct creatures currently reside in the park, as well as this at least three other <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../493/38493.xml">
genera</link> (<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/5603910.xml">
Dinornis</link></it>, a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/187897.xml">
mastodon</link>, and <it><chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../761/19346761.xml">
Glyptodon</link></animal>
</mammal>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
</it>s) were planned, and if contemporary reports are accurate at Hawkins began to build at least the mastodon before the Crystal Palace Company cut his funding in 1855. An inaccurate map of the time, reprinted in Steve McCarthy and Mick Gilbert's book <it>The Crystal Palace Dinosaurs</it>, even gives the planned locations of the <it>Dinornis</it> and mastodon. </p>
<p>

The fifteen genera that were completed were:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../739/18207739.xml">
Anoplotherium</link></animal>
</mammal>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
 An extinct mammal: Hawkins's models draw very much on speculation about its camel-like appearance, and they resemble <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/6598.xml">
camels</link> a great deal (it is now believed they look more like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/37764.xml">
hippopotamus</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/25142.xml">
pigs</link>). Three models were originally made, but one, with its head raised, has since gone missing in unknown circumstances. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<synapsid wordnetid="101719403" confidence="0.8">
<reptile wordnetid="101661091" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/5189380.xml">
Dicynodon</link></animal>
</reptile>
</synapsid>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
 Crystal Palace's <it>Dicynodon</it>, of which there are two, are based on fossils found in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/17416221.xml">
South Africa</link></country>
 which were largely incomplete, as such the models are based heavily on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../751/37751.xml">
turtles</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../618/140618.xml">
tortoises</link> complete with a shells and turtle stance. To date there is no evidence of any shelled <it>Dicynodon</it> and recent more complete fossils have revealed they looked more like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../764/37764.xml">
Hippopotamus</link>. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<diapsid wordnetid="101661818" confidence="0.8">
<archosaur wordnetid="101695681" confidence="0.8">
<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<dinosaur wordnetid="101699831" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<reptile wordnetid="101661091" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/1241943.xml">
Hylaeosaurus</link></animal>
</reptile>
</vertebrate>
</dinosaur>
</chordate>
</archosaur>
</diapsid>
 curiously, when their names are taken into consideration, it is <it>Hyleosaurus</it>, not <it>Iguanodon</it>, that most resembles the giant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../686/18958686.xml">
iguana</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/18956166.xml">
stereotype</link> of early ideas of dinosaurs. Today <it>Hylaeosaurus</it> is depicted similar to <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/983374.xml">
Ankylosaurus</link></it>; Hawkins's depiction is of a large Iguana-like beast with long sharp spines along its back. The head of the <it>Hylaeosaurus</it> model is in fact not the original but a fiberglass replica; the original head is positioned outside the park's visitor's centre.  </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../922/1951922.xml">
Ichthyosaurus</link> though a portion of the three <it>Ichthyosaurus</it> are submerged by water (though early shots show that unlike the <it>Mosasaurus</it> most of the model was completed) they are in fact basking on the land similar to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../261/60261.xml">
Seals</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../709/33709.xml">
Walrus</link> do today, something we now know would kill them. In the time of the Crystal Palace Dinosaurs' productions the beasts were considered more along the lines of crocodiles or the <it>Plesiosaurus</it>; recently it has been uncovered they have more in common with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../617/43617.xml">
shark</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/9061.xml">
dolphins</link> with a dorsal fin and fish-like tail, both of which are not present in Hawkins's models. Instead the tails are a flat protuberance from a straight backbone. A further discrepancy is that the models' eyes have exposed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/12109567.xml">
sclerotic plates</link> (bones that stopped their eyes from being crushed by the pressure under sea). However as a whole the Ichthyosaurs are one of the more accurate dinosaurs and became one of the three 'mascot dinosaurs' along with the <it>Iguanodon</it> and <it>Megalosaurus</it>. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<image width="250px" src="London_-_Crystal_Palace_-_Victorian_Dinosaurs.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

An <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../101/314101.xml">
Ichthyosaur</link> swims with a group of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../520/182520.xml">
Plesiosaur</link>s
</caption>
</image>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/228798.xml">
Iguanodon</link> Easily the most recognizable and most commonly shown of Hawkins's models are the pair of <it>Iguanodon</it>. The inaccuracy of having thumb spikes mistaken for horns is used repeatedly on documentaries about dinosaurs and their history when talking about Victorian ideas of the beasts. Aside from this the <it>Iguanodon</it>, like the <it>Megalosaurus</it>, were depicted as quadrupeds (walking on all fours) and look as though they are inspired by modern day dogs.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/19194155.xml">
Labyrinthodon</link> Three <it>Labyrinthodon</it> models were made for Crystal Palace, heavily based on frogs. One is smooth skinned and is based on the species <it>Labyrinthodon salamandroides</it>. Two were based on <it>Labyrinthodon pachygnathus</it> (both have since been re-classified). Casts of the animal's real footprints were included in the ground around the models (one of which had survived by the time of <it>The Crystal Palace Dinosaurs</it> being written).</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/803808.xml">
Irish Elk</link></animal>
</mammal>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
 also known as <it>Megaloceros</it>, Hawkins built a whole family unit of male, female and fawn; the adults bore antlers made from actual fossil antlers, though these have since been replaced. Moved from the third island, they had fallen into disrepair as they were in a place easily accessible by vandals. Until their antlers were replaced, the Elks were the most accurate of the models, though given that they are only large <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/38428.xml">
deer</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/38428.xml">
stag</link> anyway, there was much more reference for them in 1852.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/513908.xml">
Megalosaurus</link> Giant and visually impressive even by today's standards, the <it>Megalosaurus</it> became one of the park's three 'mascot dinosaurs' along with the <it>Iguanodon</it> and (less so) the Ichthyosaurs. Yet it is arguably the most inaccurate of all of Hawkins's models, depicted as a quadruped that looks like an elephant with a lizard's head and paws. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../590/88590.xml">
Megatherium</link></animal>
</mammal>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
 wholly more accurate than most of the dinosaur species, the <it>Megatherium</it> was part of the park's children's zoo for many years with its tail in the goats and guinea pigs enclosure. Once the zoo was closed, it became totally inaccessible, only to be seen through the railings that kept visitors out of the derelict area. Recent renovations demolished the zoo and a walkway has caused the <it>Megatherium</it> to become one of the models visitors can now get the closest to.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/2051142.xml">
Mosasaurus</link> At the time of the models being built, only skulls of <it>Mosasaurus</it> had been discovered. In a clever way of disguising this lack of information, Hawkins only built the head and back of the animal. He submerged the model deep in the lake so the water hid this fact, leaving little room for inaccuracy. Despite this it does look noticeably different from modern reconstructions of the beast. The <it>Mosasaurus</it> at Crystal Palace is positioned in an odd place near the secondary island that was originally a waterfall, and much of it is obscured if viewed from the lakeside path.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<mammal wordnetid="101861778" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/4004214.xml">
Palaeotherium</link></animal>
</mammal>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
 The herd of <it>Palaeotherium</it>, an extinct <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../669/248669.xml">
tapir</link>-like mammal, have suffered the most ill-repair of all of the models, and the standing model looked very little like the original model by Hawkins; prior to the 2002 restoration they were in such bad shape they were removed totally and were stored with miscellaneous equipment.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nyder.com/dinos/plate10.html">
http://www.nyder.com/dinos/plate10.html</weblink> They have since been restored and put back on show. Some sources state that these models were added at a later date but a <it>London News</it> illustration of Hawkins's workshop clearly shows them in the background, appearing to prove these sources inaccurate.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/1238513.xml">
Plesiosaurus</link> Each of the three plesiosaur models are intended to represent a different genus, and by and large are fairly accurate to today's standards with the exception of two models' incredibly flexible necks, which twist in nearly impossible ways.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../824/24824.xml">
Pterodactyl</link> The most common way of someone drawing a pterodactyl is to give the animal a head with an additional point, making its head almost symmetrical to its beak, but there were species of <it><diapsid wordnetid="101661818" confidence="0.8">
<archosaur wordnetid="101695681" confidence="0.8">
<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<pterosaur wordnetid="101722998" confidence="0.8">
<reptile wordnetid="101661091" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/24825.xml">
Pteranodon</link></animal>
</reptile>
</pterosaur>
</vertebrate>
</chordate>
</archosaur>
</diapsid>
</it> that had simple bald heads devoid of these points. Hawkins's pterodactyls are some of his more accurate models (again despite their pipe-cleaner style necks). At some point the two models that stood beside the <it>Iguanodon</it> on the central island went missing; they have since been restored in the recent 2002 renovations. </entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<diapsid wordnetid="101661818" confidence="0.8">
<chordate wordnetid="101466257" confidence="0.8">
<crocodilian_reptile wordnetid="101696633" confidence="0.8">
<crocodile wordnetid="101697178" confidence="0.8">
<vertebrate wordnetid="101471682" confidence="0.8">
<reptile wordnetid="101661091" confidence="0.8">
<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/5602881.xml">
Teleosaurus</link></animal>
</reptile>
</vertebrate>
</crocodile>
</crocodilian_reptile>
</chordate>
</diapsid>
 arguably Hawkins's most accurate model, the two Teleosaurs are depicted virtually the same as they are today (thin crocodiles with very long thin jaws and small eyes).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
In popular culture</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Ann Coates</link> wrote a children's book <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/10477240.xml">
Dinosaurs Don't Die</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it>. In the book a young boy who lives near Crystal Palace Park discovers Hawkins's models come to life; he befriends one of the <it>Iguanodon</it> and names it 'Rock' and they visit the natural history museum.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/1123192.xml">
Brett Anderson</link></artist>
, former singer in the band <musical_organization wordnetid="108246613" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/169547.xml">
Suede</link></group>
</musical_organization>
, uses the line 'So I went and sat in Crystal Palace, by the plastic dinosaurs' on his solo track <link>
To The Winter</link>, from his 2007 <album wordnetid="106591815" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/5313322.xml">
self-titled album</link></album>
.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sources</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>The Crystal Palace Dinosaurs</it> by Steve McCarthy and Mick Gilbert, originally published 1994 by the Crystal Palace Foundation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nyder.com/dinos/history.html">
Nyder's Diner's Crystal Palace Dinosaurs Page</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ihbc.org.uk/context_archive/75/dinosaurs/dinos.html">
IHBC's archive on their 2002 restoration of the models</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/london/content/articles/2004/08/10/cp_dinosaur_feature.shtml">
BBC feature</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</solid_figure>
</attraction>
</shape>
</plastic_art>
</art>
</figure>
</artifact>
</building>
</structure>
</creation>
</sculpture>
</article>
