<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 01:06:46[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<beginning  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100235435">
<change  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100191142">
<show  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100520257">
<entertainment  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100429048">
<ending  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106308765">
<morpheme  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106306233">
<change_of_state  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100199130">
<diversion  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100426928">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<action  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100037396">
<part  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="113809207">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<introduction  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100238022">
<language_unit  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="106284225">
<header>
<title>Beyond Vaudeville</title>
<id>12196101</id>
<revision>
<id>227987682</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-26T10:06:45Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Jgrosch</username>
<id>88185</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Orphaned articles from November 2007</category>
<category>1986 television series debuts</category>
<category>1996 television series endings</category>
<category>PBS network shows</category>
<category>All orphaned articles</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="44px" src="Wiki_letter_w.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article is  as few or no other articles <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Beyond_Vaudeville&amp;namespace=0">
link to it</weblink>.</b>
Please help  in articles on <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;as_qdr=all&amp;q=+site%3Aen.wikipedia.org+%22Beyond+Vaudeville%22">
related topics</weblink>. <it>(November 2007)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>

<p>

<b><it>Beyond Vaudeville</it></b> was a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../710/428710.xml">
public access television</link> show on Time Warner Cable in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../042/645042.xml">
New York City</link></village>
 that ran from 1986 to 1996. The show was hosted by Frank Hope with co-host David Greene and featured regular appearances by Joey the Monkey. Guests included various celebrities and New York City eccentrics. The show eventually made the move to network TV as <b>Oddville, MTV</b>.
<b>Beyond Vaudeville Episode List</b>
1) Mason Reese, Underdog dancer Suzanne Muldowney2) Al Lewis, poet Gretchen Weiner3) Omer Travers (broke into Yoko Ono's apartment), poet Chairman Steve, comedy team Book n Martino4) Psychic Frederick Davies, singer-songwriter Stryker5) Poet Gretchen Weiner, Joey the Monkey, Body By Bob6) Frank Nastasi (White Fang on Soupy Sales Show)7) Tuli Kupferberg of The Fugs, poet Chairman Steve8) Sammy Petrillo (Bela Lugosi Meets a Brooklyn Gorilla), former Burt Reynolds love interest Sen Tuna9) Quentin Crisp, mother-daughter comedy team Coco &amp; Penny10) Joe Franklin errand boy Chris Deola, Kerima the bellydancer11)Joyce Randolph, comedian Jackie Jason Exit12)Singer Arthur Tracy, actor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/17705910.xml">
Marshall Efron</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
13)Joe Franklin, artist Konstantin Bokov, elderly stripper Leola Harlow14)Lisa Sliwa, singer/songwriter Stryker, poet Chairman Steve15)Michael Musto, actor Joe Fleishaker, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb16)Memory expert Harry Lorrayne, Danny the Wonderpony, movie usher Martin Spund17)Billy Deans Knockouts18)Phoebe Legere, nudists, singer-songwriter Stryker, Underdog dancer Suzanne Muldowney19)Sci-Fi singer Roberta Rogow, Underdog dancer Suzanne Muldowney, singer Ada Love20)Brother Theodore, Uncle Sam impersonator Joe Erdelyi, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb21)Ed Herlihy, Lady Betty Aberlin, singer Starlady, T-shirt maker Martin Forro22)Joey Adams, Geoffrey Holder, Mr. Spoons23)Barry Williams, Wavy Gravy, Sukhreet Gabel24)Diver Dan, Rocky Horror Fan Club president Sal Piro, nosewhistler Jim Grosso, comic Al Lawrence25)Little Mike Anderson, musical saw player Moses Josiah, UFO expert26)Prof. Irwin Corey, Lady Betty Aberlin, female Elvis impersonator Dee Nack, driving instructor Bert Rapp, sci-fi collector Phil Depardo27)Judy Carne, Page Morton-Black, cryonicist Curtis Henderson, singer Al Boland28)Taylor Mead, Ethyl Eichelberger, Baird Jones, Jack the Fire, Frank's Home Movies29)Terry Sweeney, Flying Nun Fan Club president Sal Piro, Dracula dancer Suzanne Muldowney, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb30)Marie Wallace, Dave Van Ronk, UFO expert Ellie Crystal, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb31)Fred Willard, Underdog dancer Suzanne Muldowney, poet Wolf Pasmanik, comic Lou Bacala Cary32)Austin Pendleton, Irene the Gong Show Queen of Long Island, singer Ada Love, Raelians, Lady Betty Aberlin33)Singer John Wallowitch, singer Buddy Clayton34)NYC News anchor Sue Simmons, musical saw player Moses Josiah, actress Martha Greenhouse, psychic Morris Fonte35)Audrey Landers, David Peel, Alan Abel, Al Jolson impersonator Rich Curtis36)Warner Wolf, Tiny Tim, The Chordettes, comic Dave West37)Shirley Stoler, Ron Fazio, singer Tommy Ritaco, Robert Harmonica Stevens, Pieman Aron Kay38)Dan Lauria, Indian Elvis impersonator Nazar Sayegh, comedian Mildred Katz39)Lew "Clarabell" Anderson, Little Mike Anderson, singer Regis Philbin Jr., sci-fi expert Ronald Held, pogo-stick record holder Ashrita Furman40)Carel Struyken, singer Izzy Fertel, toy collectors Lance and Pat, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb41)World's Fastest Hot Dog Eater, poet Wolf Pasmanik, rapper Larry Love, sci-fi expert Ronald Held42)Fred Willard, singer Izzy Fertel, singer Ada Love, bellydancer Kerima, rappers, comedian Dave West, nose-whistler Jim Grosso43)Remo Pisani, singer Buddy Clayton, midget comic Ramon Pena Cartucho, Hawaiian singer Johnny Kai44)Bobby Boris Pickett, pierced guy, sci-fi expert Ronald Held, Klingon League of Assault Warriors, singer Austin Pendleton45)Tiny Tim, Benny Bell, tattoo experts Huggy Beark &amp; Eek, Renaissance Man George Kayatta, Mr. Lucky &amp; Stanley the Pig46)Sammy Petrillo, sci-fi expert Ron Held, comic Mikhail Bleyckman, bowling alley expert Bill Newman, horror expert John Link, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb47)Xmas Special. Wallowitch, William M. Gaines, Marilyn Monroe conspiracy expert M. Vinson Hayes, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb48)Bern Nadette Stanis, comic Mikhail Bleyckman, sci-fi singer Roberta Rogow, songwriter Stryker, Tiny Tim goes bowling49)Joey Faye, sci-fi expert Ronald Held, actor Joe Fleishaker, Marilyn Monroe conspiracy expert M. Vinson Hayes50)Pat Cooper, FDR Impersonator, Madonna impersonator Queerdonna, Trayman, Walt Paper51)Arthur Tracy, sci-fi expert Steve Maurer, Ice Bear Kingdom, Marilyn Monroe conspiracy expert M. Vinson Hayes, Trayman52)Underdog dancer Suzanne Muldowney, William Brown, singer Alan Chusid, Trayman53)Alison Steele, Chauncey Howell, anchor Marvin Scott, William Brown, Bagpipe player, comic Dave West54)Ron Palillo, William Brown, Trayman, Champ the Wonderdog, sci-fi expert Ronald Held55)Barton Heyman, William Brown, movie collectors Mike Tower and Arthur Ritzer, dancer Jimmy Del Rio56)Kitty Carlisle Hart, William Brown, Trayman, The Greater Gotham Gaylaxians, songwriter Stryker57)Singing nun Sister Beata, singer Margarita Pracatan, artist Hoop, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb, singer Austin Velez58)Virginia Graham, Sir Monte Rock III, artist Hoop, Frank Sinatra fan Bernice Perry, singer Tommy Ritaco59)Kaye Ballard, Lara Jill Miller, William Brown, singer Red Lightning, comic Arthur of New York60)Larry Storch, Banjo-Playing Priest George Swanson, nose-whistler Jim Grosso, Trayman, inventor Mr. Marchand61)Kim Hunter, Chauncey Howell, singer Margarita Pracatan, singer Red Lightning, angels expert62)Michael Berryman, actress Katy Dierlam, artist Ned Sontaag, sci-fi expert John Link, sci-fi collector Leslie Holcomb63)Shirley Jones, Marty Ingels, Trayman, Red Lightning64)Rick Derringer, comic Marty Gangursky, Three Stooges Fan Club, Chinese opera singer Chen Tsung Kit65)Jimmy Breslin, poet Chairman Steve, Yankees fan Freddie Sez, Al Jolson singer Rich Curtis, actor Marty Gangursky, Kenneth Keith Kallenbach66)Underdog dancer Suzanne Muldowney, Kenneth Keith Kallenbach, rapper/granny Fruity Nutcake, Marilyn Monroe conspiracy expert M. Vinson Hayes67)Imogene Coca, poet Chairman Steve, Quiz Show legend Herbert Stempell, singer Buddy Clayton, comic Neil Connie Wallace68)Jack Riley, Pat McCormick, comic Neil Connie Wallace, raconteur Mr. Sragow, Red Lightning69)Tom Arnold, comic Neil Connie Wallace, Underdog dancer Suzanne Muldowney, raconteur Mr. Sragow70)Soleil Moon Fry, The Singing Cowgirl from Queens, Marilyn Monroe conspiracy theorist M. Vinson Hayes, comic Neil Connie Wallace71)The Del Rubio Triplets, comic Neil Connie Wallace, comic cabbie Al Mustakoff72)Johnnie Whitaker, Billy Barty, Mr. Sragow, poet Chairman Steve73)Singer Joey Marlowe, poet Bingo Gazingo, comic Neil Connie Wallace74)Tiny Tim, Arthur Tracy, Izzy Fertel, poet Chairman Steve75)Tribute to KISS fans</p>

</bdy>
</language_unit>
</introduction>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</part>
</action>
</event>
</diversion>
</change_of_state>
</morpheme>
</ending>
</entertainment>
</show>
</change>
</beginning>
</article>
