<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 18:18:57[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<physical_entity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100001930">
<person  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007846">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<worker  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="109632518">
<servant  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110582154">
<housekeeper  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110188715">
<causal_agent  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100007347">
<domestic  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="110024119">
<header>
<title>Eunice Murray</title>
<id>1228430</id>
<revision>
<id>244246864</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T23:10:54Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>VolkovBot</username>
<id>3035831</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>American Swedenborgians</category>
<category>1992 deaths</category>
<category>1902 births</category>
<category>American housekeepers</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Eunice Murray</b> (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../652/34652.xml">
1902</link> - <time_off wordnetid="115118453" confidence="0.8">
<fundamental_quantity wordnetid="113575869" confidence="0.8">
<time_period wordnetid="115113229" confidence="0.8">
<vacation wordnetid="115137890" confidence="0.8">
<leisure wordnetid="115137676" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../350/19350.xml">
May 3</link></leisure>
</vacation>
</time_period>
</fundamental_quantity>
</time_off>
, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/34598.xml">
1993</link>) is notable for being <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<playmate wordnetid="110441037" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/19318.xml">
Marilyn Monroe</link></playmate>
</actor>
</person>
's <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../396/1389396.xml">
housekeeper</link> who was present in the actress' house at the time she died there. Murray has been accused by many authors and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/218985.xml">
LAPD</link> Sergeant <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/14248754.xml">
Jack Clemmons</link></person>
 of being involved in a cover-up of Monroe's death,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> although no one has proven what Murray's motive was or whom, if anyone, she was aiding and abetting.
<sec>
<st>
Early life</st>
<p>

She was born Eunice Joerndt in <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/6886.xml">
Chicago</link></village>
 and raised in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../978/67978.xml">
Urbana</link>, <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../199/22199.xml">
Ohio</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../429/254429.xml">
Swedenborgian</link>. She was educated at the Swedenborgian Urbana School and Academy until she dropped out at age sixteen in 1918. In 1921, she married John Murray and went on to have three children with him: Jaquelyn, Patricia and Marilyn. By the end of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/32927.xml">
Second World War</link> in 1945, the Murrays were living in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/28208.xml">
Santa Monica</link> in a <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/40455.xml">
Monterrey</link></village>
-style five-bedroom house, which, after she and her husband separated, Eunice sold to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../004/25004.xml">
psychiatrist</link> <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../200/13717200.xml">
Ralph Greenson</link></psychologist>
</scientist>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 in 1946. Greenson and other psychiatrists subsequently hired Eunice Murray as a support worker for some of their most <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/233002.xml">
prestigious</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../797/60797.xml">
client</link>s.  Murray never identified any psychiatrists for whom she may have worked besides Greenson, nor is it known which prestigious people, if any, she may have helped besides Monroe.  It is not clear what her husband John Murray did for a living or when he died.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Eunice Murray and Marilyn Monroe</st>
<p>

In 1961, Dr. Ralph Greenson advised Marilyn Monroe, then living in an apartment on North Doheny Drive in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/75346.xml">
Beverly Hills</link>, to recruit Murray as a housekeeper/companion.  When Monroe decided to buy a house, Murray located the small dwelling, which had no closets,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> on Fifth Helena Drive in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<vicinity wordnetid="108641113" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<section wordnetid="108648322" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../873/345873.xml">
Brentwood</link></section>
</location>
</area>
</vicinity>
</region>
 in which Monroe was to spend the last months of her life. After Monroe moved into it, Murray began spending many nights there, although she kept an apartment in nearby <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/28208.xml">
Santa Monica</link>.  Murray began (according to the testimonies of Monroe's friends) reporting to Greenson on the actress' daily activities. Murray accompanied Monroe on her publicized visit to <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3966054.xml">
Mexico</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 in February 1962, even introducing the star to some openly communist people south of the border whose association with Monroe caused the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/11127.xml">
FBI</link> to investigate the actress as a possible risk to national security.  </p>
<p>

In an attempt to assert her independence from Greenson, Monroe fired Murray in May 1962 but shortly afterward rehired her. However, in August 1962 when Murray requested a month's holiday, Monroe granted it, paid her, and asked her not to return. After spending Friday night, August 3, 1962 at her apartment, Murray arrived at Monroe's house the next day for her last contracted day of work, just hours before Monroe died.  Murray said consistently to police and reporters in 1962 and to author Robert Slatzer in 1973 that she and Monroe, the only people in the house, retired to their separate rooms late Saturday evening with Monroe aware that she would be spending the night.  When Murray awoke at approximately 3:00 a.m. and knocked on Monroe's door, the actress did not answer.  In a 1975 memoir, Murray changed her story slightly, recalling that the sight of a telephone extension cord running under Monroe's bedroom door caused her, at approximately 3:00 a.m., to use another extension to call Dr. Greenson. (In 1962 she had told police that she had contacted Greenson after becoming alarmed by Monroe's bedroom light shining through the space under the door.) In 1985 Murray made major changes to her story by claiming that Robert Kennedy was in the house at some point on Saturday and that "the doctor" arrived to help Monroe while she was unconscious but alive.  Murray never said, however, that Monroe might have wanted her out of the house.</p>
<p>

Murray never wavered in her claim that during her telephone conversation with Greenson, he instructed her to go outside and look through Monroe's bedroom window.  Murray then supposedly saw the actress lying "in an unnatural position," reported this to Greenson and he arrived at the house, broke the window and entered Monroe's room aware that she was dead. </p>
<p>

Many days later, when Murray attempted to cash her last paycheck from Monroe, it was declined and marked "deceased." This check, one of the last that Monroe ever wrote on her Roxbury Drive Branch account at City National Bank in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../346/75346.xml">
Beverly Hills</link>, is today on display at the <museum wordnetid="103800563" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../422/669422.xml">
Hollywood Heritage Museum</link></museum>
.  </p>
<p>

After Monroe's death, Murray lived quietly in various locations in West Los Angeles. From the mid 1960s until the mid 1970s, Murray rented a guest <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../397/908397.xml">
cottage</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/28208.xml">
Santa Monica</link> from relatives of the actor, <actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/935344.xml">
Richard Cromwell</link></actor>
, who had died in 1960. While there in 1973, she was interviewed by Robert Slatzer.  In a photograph of them together that is published in his 1974 book <it>The Life and Curious Death of Marilyn Monroe</it>, Murray appears to be laughing.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref>  During her years in the guest cottage she pursued her many interests, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../295/92295.xml">
sewing</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/736449.xml">
macrame</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/216260.xml">
horticulture</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/22nd_century.xml">
astrology</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/299965.xml">
tutoring</link>, and letter writing. In the late 1970s she married Franklin Blackmer, a Swedenborgian minister, and moved east with him to <village wordnetid="108672738" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/116165.xml">
Bath, Maine</link></village>
. After his death, she returned to her family in Southern California, living close to Monroe's former home in Brentwood. A crew from the <network wordnetid="108434259" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../654/19344654.xml">
BBC</link></network>
 videotaped Murray talking inside "a rundown apartment in Santa Monica" in 1985, according to <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../136/5294136.xml">
Anthony Summers</link></person>
,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> who was interviewing her. Later, Murray lived with her daughter in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/57180.xml">
Tucson</link>, Arizona, until her death in 1993. </p>
<p>

After Slatzer found her and talked with her, Eunice Murray published a 1975 memoir, <it>Marilyn: The Last Months</it> (co-authored by Rose Shade) and later talked with other biographers and journalists, including Anthony Scaduto, about Monroe.  It was not until she met Anthony Summers, however, that she admitted that Monroe had known the Kennedys or that "the doctor" had been in the star's house while she was unconscious but alive. Donald Wolfe, an author who began work on <it>The Last Days of Marilyn Monroe</it> shortly before Murray's death, theorized that <it>everything</it> in her story was a lie, including her retiring for bed late Saturday evening (with Monroe's approval) and the 3:00 a.m. awakening and phone call to Dr. Greenson.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Wolfe based the theory on an interview he conducted with a man who had been Murray's son-in-law in 1962.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> When the man told Wolfe his story in 1992, he was confined to a wheelchair in his <symbol wordnetid="106806469" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/1930.xml">
Arkansas</link></symbol>
 home.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> He died within a year,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> as did Eunice Murray.</p>
<p>

Donald Spoto, working on a Monroe biography in the early 1990s and Rachael Bell, making a television documentary years later, both concluded that Murray was covering up an inadvertently fatal dose of a sedative that a well-meaning person had given a despondent Monroe by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../877/83877.xml">
enema</link>.  Although Spoto and Bell did not investigate the story together, they agree that Murray had no connection to U.S. government officials or criminals. Barbara Leaming, whose Monroe biography came out within weeks of Wolfe's, does not believe that Eunice Murray played a sinister part in the events surrounding Monroe's death.</p>
<p>

Eunice Murray initially repeated the same story she had told Robert Slatzer in 1973 and the police in 1962. She apparently noticed the camera crew starting to pack up and then said, "Why, at my age, do I still have to cover this thing?"[9] Unknown to her, the microphone was still on. Murray went on to admit that Monroe had known the Kennedys.[10] She volunteered that on the night of the actress' death, "When the doctor arrived, she was not dead." [10] Murray died in 1993 without revealing further details.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<playmate wordnetid="110441037" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../318/19318.xml">
Marilyn Monroe</link></playmate>
</actor>
</person>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9638700866880419">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../152/4292152.xml">
Death of Marilyn Monroe</link></person>
</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Wolfe, Donald H. The Last Days of Marilyn Monroe. (1998) ISBN-10: 0787118079</entry>
<entry id="2">
 Hitchens, Neal and Riese, Randall. <it>The Unabridged Marilyn: Her Life From A To Z</it>. New York: Congdon &amp; Weed, 1987, p. 88 </entry>
<entry id="3">
Slatzer, Robert. <it>The Life and Curious Death of Marilyn Monroe</it>. New York: Pinnacle Books, Inc., 1975, photo section </entry>
<entry id="4">
 Summers, Anthony. <it>Goddess: The Secret Lives of Marilyn Monroe</it>. New York: Onyx, 1986 </entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Further reading</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Marilyn Monroe: The Biography</it>, by Donald Spoto (1993)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Marilyn: The Last Months</it>, by Eunice Murray, with Rose Shade (published in paperback by Pyramid Books, 1975)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>The Life and Curious Death of Marilyn Monroe</it>, by Robert Slatzer, published in hardback by Pinnacle Books, Inc., 1974. Includes a 1973 photograph of Murray with Slatzer.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</domestic>
</causal_agent>
</housekeeper>
</servant>
</worker>
</entity>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</article>
