<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 17.04.2009 04:43:10[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Alcohol use and sleep</title>
<id>18450716</id>
<revision>
<id>238517268</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-15T04:59:13Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Rmacker</username>
<id>7769830</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles that may contain original research since July 2008</category>
<category>Alcohol</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from July 2008</category>
<category>Articles to be merged since July 2008</category>
<category>All articles to be merged</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40px" src="Ambox_question.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section may contain an  of published material that conveys ideas not  to the original sources.</b>
Please help Wikipedia by adding sources whose main topic is "Alcohol use and sleep". See the for details. <it>(July 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>The  or style of this article or section may not be appropriate for Wikipedia.</b>
Specific concerns may be found on the . See Wikipedia's for suggestions. <it>(July 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-move" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Merge-arrow.svg">
<caption>

Merge arrow
</caption>
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 It has been suggested that this article or section be  into . ()</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../014/1014.xml">
Alcohol</link> is a highly-abused substance that greatly exacerbates sleep problems. During <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../546/18589546.xml">
abstinence</link>, residual disruptions in sleep maintenance and sleep architecture are the greatest predictors of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../513/1662513.xml">
relapse</link> [1].</p>

<sec>
<st>
Moderate alcohol consumption and sleep disruptions</st>

<p>

Moderate alcohol consumption 30-60 minutes before bedtime <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../914/5914.xml">
catalyzes</link> disruptions in sleep maintenance and sleep architecture that are mediated by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/4845.xml">
blood alcohol level</link>s [2]. Disruptions in sleep maintenance are most marked once alcohol has been completely <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/20374.xml">
metabolized</link> from the body. Under conditions of moderate alcohol consumption where blood alcohol levels average 0.06-0.08 percent and decrease 0.01-0.02 percent per hour, an alcohol clearance rate of 4-5 hours would coincide with disruptions in sleep maintenance in the second half of an 8 hr sleep episode [2]. In terms of sleep architecture, moderate doses of alcohol facilitate "rebounds" in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../184/167184.xml">
rapid eye movement</link> (REM) and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../834/27834.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Stages+of+sleep%22])">
stage 1 sleep</link>; following suppression in REM and stage 1 sleep in the first half of an 8 hr sleep episode, REM and stage 1 sleep increase well beyond baseline in the second half. Moderate doses of alcohol also increase <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../147/2708147.xml">
slow wave sleep</link> (SWS) in the first half of an 8 hr sleep episode [2]. Enhancements in REM sleep and SWS following moderate alcohol consumption are mediated by reductions in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../541/63541.xml">
glutamatergic</link> activity by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/89108.xml">
adenosine</link> in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/7251.xml">
central nervous system</link> [2]. In addition, tolerance to changes in sleep maintenance and sleep architecture develops within 3 days of alcohol consumption before bedtime [2].</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Alcohol consumption and sleep improvements</st>

<p>

Low doses of alcohol (one 12 oz. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/3363.xml">
beer</link>) are sleep-promoting by increasing total sleep time and reducing awakenings during the night. The sleep-promoting benefits of alcohol <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../572/164572.xml">
dissipate</link> at moderate and higher doses of alcohol (two 12 oz beers and three 12 oz. beers, respectively) [3]. Previous experience with alcohol also determines whether or not alcohol is a "sleep promoter" or "sleep disrupter." Under free-choice conditions, in which subjects chose between drinking alcohol or water, inexperienced drinkers were sedated while experienced drinkers were stimulated following alcohol consumption [4]. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/50798.xml">
insomnia</link>cs, moderate doses of alcohol improve sleep maintenance [5].</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Alcohol consumption and fatigue</st>

<p>

Sleepiness influences the severity of alcohol consumption. Conditions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../893/18597893.xml">
sleep deprivation</link> encourage more episodes of alcohol consumption [2]. Increased alcohol consumption during the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/34061.xml">
winter</link> months for Northern climate residents is attributed to escalations in fatigue [6].</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Alcohol abstinence and sleep disruptions</st>

<p>

Sleep and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../311/13311.xml">
hormonal</link> disruptions following withdrawal from chronic alcohol consumption are the greatest predictors of relapse [1]. During abstinence, recovering alcoholics have attenuated <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/285157.xml">
melatonin</link> secretion in the beginning of a sleep episode, resulting in prolonged sleep latencies [7]. Escalations in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/335380.xml">
cortisol</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../432/1156432.xml">
core body temperature</link>s during the sleep period contribute to poor sleep maintenance [7,8].</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Feige, B., Scaal, S., Hornyak, M., Gann, H., Riemann, D. Sleep electroencephalographic spectral power after withdrawal from alcohol in alcohol-dependent patients. ALcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research. 2007 Jan ; 31 (1): 19-27. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Roehrs, T., and Roth, T. Sleep, sleepiness, and alcohol use. Alcohol Research &amp; Health. 2001; 25(2):101-109. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Stone, B. Sleep and low doses of alcohol. Electroencephalography and Clinical Neurophysiology. 1980; 48: 706-709. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Schuckit, M.A. Low level of response to alcohol as a predictor of future alcoholism. Am J Psychiatry. 1994 Feb;151(2):184-189. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Rohers, T., Papineau, B.A., Rosenthal, L., Roth, T. Ethanol as a hypnotic in insomniacs: self administration and effects on sleep and mood. Neuropsychopharmacology. 1999 Mar; 20(3):279-86. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Levine, M.E., Duffy, L.K., Bowyer, R.T. Fatigue, sleep, and seasonal hormone levels: implications for drinking behavior in Northern climates. Drugs &amp; Society. 1994; 8(2): 61-70. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Kühlwein, E., Hauger, R.L., Irwin, M.R. Abnormal nocturnal melatonin secretion and disordered sleep in abstinent alcoholics. Biol Psychiatry. 2003; 54: 1437-1443. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="number">

 Danel, T., Libersa, C., Touitou, Y. The effect of alcohol consumption on the circadian control of human core body temperature is time dependent. Am J Physiol Regulatory Integrative Comp Physiol. 2001; 281: R52-R55.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
