<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:48:05[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>French paradox</title>
<id>319138</id>
<revision>
<id>244205400</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T19:51:06Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ardric47</username>
<id>110275</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All pages needing cleanup</category>
<category>All articles with unsourced statements</category>
<category>Paradoxes</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Articles with disputed statements </category>
<category>Articles with specifically-marked weasel-worded phrases</category>
<category>Cardiovascular diseases</category>
<category>Articles with unsourced statements since September 2007</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

The <b>French paradox</b>  refers to the observation that <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
the French</link></country>
 suffer a relatively low incidence of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/5069735.xml">
coronary heart disease</link>, despite having a diet relatively rich in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../746/264746.xml">
saturated fat</link>s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> The phenomenon was first noted by Irish physician <link>
Samuel Black</link> in 1819. The term <it>French paradox</it> was coined by Dr. Serge Renaud, a scientist from Bordeaux University in France in 1992.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref><p>

When a description of this paradox was aired in the <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
United States</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 on <it><series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/35061.xml">
60 Minutes</link></series>
</it> in 1991 with the proposal that red wine, or alcohol, decreases the incidence of cardiac diseases, the consumption of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
red wine</link> increased 44% and some wineries began lobbying for the right to label their products "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/2053494.xml">
health food</link>".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

However, some health researchers question the validity of this paradox. Statistics collected by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../583/33583.xml">
WHO</link> from 1990-2000 show that the incidence of heart disease in France may have been underestimated, and may in fact be similar to that of neighboring countries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> In 2008 it was found that high doses of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/342649.xml">
resveratrol</link> (a constituent of red wine) mimicked the benefits of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/1256165.xml">
caloric restriction</link> (extended lifespan and reduced effects of aging) in a mice study.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></p>

<sec>
<st>
 Overview </st>
<p>

According to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/11107.xml">
FAO</link> data,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref>&#91;&#93; the average French person consumed 108 grams per day of fat from animal sources in 2002 while the average American consumed only 72. The French eat four times as much butter, 60 percent more cheese and nearly three times as much pork. Although the French consume only slightly more total fat (171 g/d vs 157 g/d), they consume much more saturated fat because Americans consume a much larger proportion of fat in the form of vegetable oil, with most of that being soybean oil.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>  &#91;&#93; However, according to data from the British Heart foundation,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> in 1999, rates of death from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../735/5069735.xml">
coronary heart disease</link> among males aged 35–74 years was 115 per 100,000 people in the US but only 83 per 100,000 in France.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Wine</st>
<p>

It has been suggested that France's high <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
red wine</link> consumption is a primary factor in the trend. This theory was expounded in a <it><series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../061/35061.xml">
60 Minutes</link></series>
</it> broadcast in 1991.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The program catalysed a large increase in North American demand for red <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../961/32961.xml">
wine</link>s from around the world. It is believed&#91;&#93; that one of the ingredients in red wine potentially related to this effect is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/342649.xml">
resveratrol</link>.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Alcohol in wine</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/2797132.xml">
Alcohol and cardiovascular disease</link></it>
</indent>

<table style="margin: 0 0 1em 1em; border: 1px solid #AAA; float: right; padding:0.3em" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0">
<header style="padding: 0 5px; background: #CCF; text-align: center;">
Alcohol and Health</header>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/19329865.xml">
Short-term effects of alcohol</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/337566.xml">
Long-term effects of alcohol</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/2797132.xml">
Alcohol and cardiovascular disease</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../039/307039.xml">
Alcoholic liver disease</link></disease>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/644078.xml">
Alcoholic hepatitis</link></disease>
</col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/2842910.xml">
Alcohol and cancer</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/2785602.xml">
Alcohol and weight</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../854/602854.xml">
Fetal alcohol syndrome</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/1248929.xml">
Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
Alcoholism</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../402/9660402.xml">
Blackout (alcohol-related amnesia)</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../354/311354.xml">
Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome</link></col>
</row>
<row>
<col style="font-size: 90%; padding: 0 5px;">
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../440/5600440.xml">
Recommended maximum intake</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>

Research suggests that moderate drinkers are less likely to suffer <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../969/60969.xml">
heart attack</link>s than are abstainers or heavy drinkers (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../132/2797132.xml">
Alcohol and cardiovascular disease</link> for details). Therefore, the alcohol in wine could be a factor in the French paradox.</p>
<p>

However, the difference between US annual alcohol consumption (8.6 litres per year)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> and French consumption (11.4 litres per year) is only 2.5 litres per year.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref> French consumption is lower than <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/17515.xml">
Luxembourg</link></country>
 (15.6 litres), the <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../321/5321.xml">
Czech Republic</link></country>
 (13.0 litres), <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/13275.xml">
Hungary</link></country>
 (13.6 litres), <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/11867.xml">
Germany</link></country>
 (12.0 litres), and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/5573.xml">
Croatia</link></country>
 (12.3 litres) where no similar paradoxes are observed.</p>
<p>

There is a lack of medical consensus about whether moderate consumption of beer, wine, or distilled spirits has a stronger association with longevity. Of ten major studies, three found stronger evidence for wine, three for beer, three for liquor, and one study found no difference between alcoholic beverages.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Resveratrol</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/342649.xml">
Resveratrol</link></it>
</indent>

Wines, particularly red wines, are a source of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../649/342649.xml">
resveratrol</link> which has been linked to longevity and cancer prevention in other species.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Procyanidins and polyphenols</st>
<p>

Although research continues on resveratrol, the concentration in wine seems too low to account for the French paradox. Professor <link>
Roger Corder</link> and team have identified a particular group of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/362892.xml">
polyphenols</link>, known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../860/841860.xml">
oligomeric</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/4644002.xml">
procyanidins</link>, which they believe offer the greatest degree of protection to human blood-vessel cells. Tests with 165 wines showed that these are found in greatest concentration in European red wines from certain areas, which correlates with longevity in those regions.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref>
The highest procyanidins are found in wines from the <assortment wordnetid="108398773" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../064/2666064.xml">
Tannat</link></assortment>
 grape, grown in the Gers area of southwest France.</p>
<p>

Unlike resveratrol, procyanidins <it>are</it> present in wine in quantities that seem to be high enough to be significant: "Procyanidins are the most abundant flavonoid polyphenols in red wine – up to one gram per litre is found in some traditional style red wines."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> "… clinical trials of grape seed extract, which have shown that 200–300 mg per day will lower blood pressure. Two small glasses (125 ml glass) of a procyanidin-rich red wine, such as a Madiran wine from southwest France, would provide this amount." However several times this amount of procyanidin can be consumed by eating an apple.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref></p>
<p>

Other research suggests that polyphenols in wine reduce the absorption of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/2634246.xml">
malondialdehyde</link>, which is implicated in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../288/188288.xml">
arteriosclerosis</link>, cancer, diabetes and other diseases.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 French diet comparisons </st>
<p>

In his book, <it>The Fat Fallacy</it>, Dr. Will Clower suggests the French paradox may be narrowed down to a few key factors, namely:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Good fats versus bad fats — French people get up to 80% of their fat intake from dairy and vegetable sources, including <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/19714.xml">
whole milk</link>, cheeses, and whole milk <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../754/156754.xml">
yogurt</link>. Conversely, they consume very little animal-flesh fat. Dairy fats have been shown to be healthier than other forms of fats, and they make a person feel full earlier thus encouraging smaller portion sizes.  </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Higher quantities of fish (three times a week).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Smaller portions, eaten more slowly and divided among courses that let the body begin to digest food already consumed before more food is added.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Lower sugar intake — American low-fat and no-fat foods often contain high concentrations of sugar. French diets avoid these products preferring full-fat versions without added sugar.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Low incidence of snacks between meals.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Avoidance of common American food items, such as soda, deep-fried foods, snack foods, and especially pre-prepared foods which can typically make for a large percentage of the foods found in American grocery stores.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Clower tends to play down the common beliefs that wine consumption and smoking are greatly responsible for the French paradox. Even without wine consumption, the French diet tends to cause Americans to lose weight while visiting even if they are not wine drinkers. And while a higher percentage of French people smoke, this is not greatly higher than the US (35% in France vs. 25% in US) and is unlikely to account for the weight difference between cultures.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Climate and lifestyle </st>
<p>

Geographical and lifestyle factors may also go some way towards explaining the paradox. France from the Centrale region southwards has a warm <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/349628.xml">
Mediterranean climate</link>. The effects of good weather will encourage outdoor leisure pursuits (often physical) to a greater extent than predominantly inclement weather.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> Ferrieres cites a study by Scarabin et al. (2003) comparing activity and health statistics in men from Toulouse and Belfast that shows although the total levels of physical activity are similar for both cities, French men performed more physical activity in their leisure time, possibly accounting for decreased incidence of CHD compared to Northern Ireland.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Under-certification </st>
<p>

Another possible explanation for the paradox is under-certification of coronary heart disease related deaths by French physicians. However when the possible bias was accounted for and corrected, CHD mortality rates were still significantly lower than other similar western countries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Time lag hypothesis </st>
<p>

The time lag hypothesis states that if there was a delay in serum cholesterol concentrations increasing and a subsequent increase in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../305/490305.xml">
ischaemic</link> heart disease mortality, then the rate of current disease mortality must relate to past levels of serum cholesterol and fat consumption much more than current levels.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref> Law and Wald (1999) used Criqui and Ringel’s (1994) study of alcohol and diet in explaining the French paradox. On analysing past and recent data of serum cholesterol and fat consumption (when earlier data were entered and adjustment was made for under-certification of CHD), they found that France fits in with the trend of other countries with similar cholesterol and fat intake.  Also, recent data prediction for CHD mortality rates showed that France was similar to other countries.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Hydrogenated and trans fats </st>
<p>

In the book, <it>Cholesterol and The French Paradox</it>, there is another explanation given by clinical nutritionist Frank Cooper.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref> He argues that the French paradox is due to the lack of hydrogenated and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/263487.xml">
trans fats</link> in the French diet.&#91;&#32; &ndash; &#93; The French diet is based on natural ‘saturated fats’ such as cheese and cream that the human body finds easy to metabolise. But the American diet includes larger amounts of artificial ‘saturated fats’ made from a process of hydrogenating vegetable oils. These hydrogenated vegetable oils have an unusual molecular structure that the human body finds difficult to metabolise. In addition, these hydrogenated fats include small quantities of ‘trans fats’ that have a dangerous molecular structure that the human body sees as foreign, and cause damage to the structure of the cells in the body. Trans fats are well known to cause diabetes, heart disease and macular eye disease.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Whole diet </st>
<p>

In the book <it>In Defense of Food</it> Michael Pollan suggests the explanation is not any single nutrient, but the combination of nutrients found in unprocessed food; not any one nutrient, not the amount of carbohydrates or fats or proteins.  But, the whole length and breadth of nutrients found in "natural" foods as opposed to "processed" foods.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Validity questioned </st>
<p>

Nevertheless, the medical causes of the French paradox are still not entirely clear and research continues while some researchers have questioned altogether the validity of this paradox by dismissing dietary saturated fat as a cause of coronary heart disease, a view that has recently received support when the results of the 20 year-long <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/4617057.xml">
Nurses' Health Study</link> run by the <university wordnetid="108286163" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../949/1562949.xml">
Harvard School of Public Health</link></university>
 suggested, after accumulating over a decade of data on the diet and health of almost 300,000 Americans, that total fat consumed has no relation to heart disease risk, provided it is not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/263487.xml">
trans fat</link>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../499/460499.xml">
Mediterranean diet</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../158/5077158.xml">
French Women Don't Get Fat</link>''</it></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../002/11002.xml">
French cuisine</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../434/19566434.xml">
Stroke Belt</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
Ferrieres, J. (2004). The French Paradox; Lessons for other countries [Electronic version]. Heart, 90, 107–111.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.vitaminsontheweb.info/articles/the-french-paradox.html">
The French paradox</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.marininstitute.org/alcohol_policy/french_drinking.htm">
"Drink Like the French, Die Like the French"</weblink> </entry>
<entry id="4">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0002264">
Barger J. L. et al A Low Dose of Dietary Resveratrol Partially Mimics Caloric Restriction and Retards Aging Parameters in Mice</weblink></entry>
<entry id="5">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://faostat.fao.org/faostat/servlet/XteServlet3?Areas=68&amp;Areas=231&amp;Items=2941&amp;Items=2740&amp;Items=2741&amp;Items=2901&amp;Items=2733&amp;Elements=684&amp;Years=2002&amp;Format=Table&amp;Xaxis=Years&amp;Yaxis=Countries&amp;Aggregate=&amp;Calculate=&amp;Domain=FS&amp;ItemTypes=FS.NonPrimaryLivestockAndProducts&amp;language=EN">
FAOSTAT</weblink></entry>
<entry id="6">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://faostat.fao.org/faostat/servlet/XteServlet3?Areas=68&amp;Areas=231&amp;Items=2571&amp;Items=2573&amp;Items=2914&amp;Elements=684&amp;Years=2002&amp;Format=Table&amp;Xaxis=Years&amp;Yaxis=Countries&amp;Aggregate=&amp;Calculate=&amp;Domain=FS&amp;ItemTypes=FS.CropsAndProducts&amp;language=EN">
FAOSTAT</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.heartstats.org/datapage.asp?id=744ytfytfy">
Tab 3.5 RSD web08: Age-standardised rate of finished consultant episodes for operations for CHD by sex and local authority, all ages and under 75 years, 2001/06, England (Table)</weblink></entry>
<entry id="8">
WHO <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/whosis/database/core/core_select_process.cfm?countries=usa&amp;indicators=AlcoholConsumption&amp;indicators=TobaccoUseAdultMale&amp;indicators=TobaccoUseAdultFemale">
Core Health Indicators: United States of America</weblink></entry>
<entry id="9">
WHO <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/whosis/database/core/core_select_process.cfm?countries=fra&amp;indicators=AlcoholConsumption&amp;indicators=TobaccoUseAdultMale&amp;indicators=TobaccoUseAdultFemale">
Core Health Indicators: France</weblink></entry>
<entry id="10">
Edell, D. Eat, <it>Drink and be Merry: America’s Doctor Tells You Why the Health Experts are Wrong</it>. NY: HarperCollins, 1999, pp. 191-192</entry>
<entry id="11">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/548419">
Procyanidins May Be the Factor Behind Red Wine's Cardioprotective Effect</weblink>, from <it>Nature</it> vol. 444, p. 566; 30 November 2006</entry>
<entry id="12">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emaxhealth.com/74/8441.html">
Real Link Between Drinking Red Wine and Increased Longevity – Food and Health</weblink></entry>
<entry id="13">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://jn.nutrition.org/cgi/content/full/130/8/2086S">
Hammerstone J. F. et al. Journal of Nutrition. 2000;130:2086S–2092S</weblink></entry>
<entry id="14">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.economist.com/science/displaystory.cfm?story_id=11662560&amp;CFID">
Red wine exercises its benefits before it enters the bloodstream</weblink></entry>
<entry id="15">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/cgi-bin/sample.cgi/jafcau/2008/56/i13/html/jf703700d.html">
The Stomach as a “Bioreactor”: When Red Meat Meets Red Wine</weblink></entry>
<entry id="17">
Cooper, Frank A. <it>Cholesterol and The French Paradox</it>. Queensland Australia: Zeus Publications, 2006, pp 152-162.</entry>
<entry id="16">
(Law &amp; Wald, 1999)</entry>
<entry id="19">
Couzin, Jennifer <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/summary/311/5762/755">
Women's Health: Study Yields Murky Signals on Low-Fat Diets and Disease</weblink> <it>Science</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/10991.xml">
10 February</link> 2006: Vol. 311. no. 5762, p. 755 DOI: 10.1126/science.311.5762.755</entry>
<entry id="18">
Pollan, Michael <it>In Defense of Food</it>. Penguin Press, 2008.</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Other sources</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Abdulla, A. &amp; Badaway, B. (2001). Moderate alcohol consumption as a cardiovascular risk factor: the role of homocycteine and the need to re-explain the ‘French Paradox’ [Electronic version]. Alcohol &amp; Alcoholism, 36, 185–188. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Law, M. &amp; Wald, N. (1999).Why heart disease mortality is low in France: the time lag explanation.[Electronic version]. British Medical Journal, 318, 1471–1480.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Perdue, W. Lewis, <it>et al</it>. <it>the French Paradox and Beyond</it>. Sonoma, CA: Renaissance, 1993.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rozin, P., Kabnick, K., Pete, E., Fischler, C., &amp; Shields, C. (2003). The ecology of eating: Part of the French paradox results from lower food intake in French than Americans, because of smaller portion sizes. Psychological Science, 14, 450–454.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.inc-opc.com/content/view/44/62/">
Prof. Jack Masquelier – A Lifetime Devoted to Science</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.economist.com/science/displaystory.cfm?story_id=10423439">
How To Live Forever</weblink> <it><newspaper wordnetid="106267145" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../449/50449.xml">
The Economist</link></newspaper>
</it> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../789/15789.xml">
3 January</link> 2008</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</article>
