<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:03:16[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Portal:Beer/Selected article/July 2006</title>
<id>5770231</id>
<revision>
<id>61347791</id>
<timestamp>2006-06-30T09:33:51Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Feydey</username>
<id>212435</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
</header>
<bdy>

<image location="left" width="180px" src="Here_lieth_a_temperance_man_--_cartoon.jpg">
</image>

The relationship between <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../566/337566.xml">
alcohol consumption and health</link></b> has been the subject of formal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../833/26833.xml">
scientific research</link> since at least <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../609/34609.xml">
1926</link>, when Dr. <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../409/1732409.xml">
Raymond Pearl</link></scientist>
 published his book, <it>Alcohol and Longevity</it>, in which he reported his finding that drinking alcohol in moderation was associated with greater longevity than either abstaining or drinking heavily.<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Portal:Beer/Selected_article/July_2006#endnote_Pearl">
http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php/Portal:Beer/Selected_article/July_2006#endnote_Pearl</weblink>  Subsequently, various studies have examined the health effects of different degrees of alcoholic beverage consumption (Blackwelder <it>et al</it>., Ellison, Hennekens, Rimm <it>et al</it>., Rogers, Trevisan <it>et al</it>.). While it is widely recognized that <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../ury/30th_century.xml">
alcoholism</link> has negative health effects, moderate consumption, frequently defined as the consumption of 1-4 alcoholic drinks in a day (depending on the age and gender of the subjects) has been found to have a positive effect on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../206/196206.xml">
longevity</link> (Camargo <it>et al</it>., Yuan <it>et al</it>., Coate, Doll &amp; Peto, Klatsky). See <link>
Alcoholic beverages — recommended maximum intake</link> for a list of governments' guidances on alcohol intake which, for a man, range from two to six drinks per day. <p>

A number of independent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../116/24116.xml">
peer-reviewed</link> studies in modern <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../635/5242635.xml">
medical literature</link> support the finding that moderate alcohol consumption is associated with benefits in longevity because of reductions in coronary heart disease, stroke, and some other diseases (Dairdron <it>et al</it>.; Ely &amp; Berne; Facchini <it>et al</it>.; Langer <it>et al</it>.; Mennen <it>et al</it>,; Paassilta <it>et al</it>.; Rimm <it>et al</it>.; Thun <it>et al</it>,; Wang &amp; Barker; Zhang <it>et al</it>.).  Proposed mechanisms of these benefits include the effect of alcohol on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/6437.xml">
cholesterol</link> levels, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../895/14895.xml">
insulin</link> activity, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../558/56558.xml">
blood pressure</link>, and the chemistry of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/183058.xml">
blood clot</link>ting.  Frequently, such studies qualify these findings with admonitions against heavy alcohol consumption or abuse, due to the negative health effects often associated with this behavior.</p>
</bdy>
</article>
