<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:48:48[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Boy racer (subculture)</title>
<id>321651</id>
<revision>
<id>241896912</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-30T00:15:18Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Towel401</username>
<id>110639</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Wikipedia articles needing style editing from December 2007</category>
<category>All articles needing style editing</category>
<category>Articles with invalid date parameter in template</category>
<category>Vehicle modification</category>
<category>Youth culture in the United Kingdom</category>
<category>Articles lacking reliable references from September 2008</category>
<category>Stereotypes</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-content" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Question_book-new.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 <b>This article or section relies largely or entirely upon a .</b>
Please help <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://localhost:18088/wiki/index.php?title=Boy_racer_%28subculture%29&amp;action=edit">
improve this article</weblink> by introducing appropriate of additional sources. <it>(September 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

<p>

<image location="none" width="50px" src="Wiktionary-logo-en.svg">
<caption>

Wiktionary
</caption>
</image>

Look up  in <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../658/156658.xml">
Wiktionary</link></web_site>
, the free dictionary.</p>

<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="40x40px" src="Ambox_style.png">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 The current version of the article or section is <b>written like a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../001/21001.xml">
magazine</link> article</b>; it does not use the direct, balanced tone expected of an encyclopedia.
Please discuss this issue on the . is available.</col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Ajs.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

the AJS 7R 350 cc "Boy Racer
</caption>
</image>

<image location="right" width="250px" src="Poser.JPG" type="thumb">
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Boy racer</b> is a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/150349.xml">
sub-culture</link> based around passenger vehicles. </p>
<p>

__TOC__
Boy racer is now a New Zealand, British and Irish colloquial term for a person, usually a male in his late teens or early twenties, who drives his car in an intimidating or dangerous way for fun or competition. Their cars are most often regular models customised with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../740/1591740.xml">
spoilers</link>, wide <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../037/65037.xml">
tire</link>s, flared <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/5193283.xml">
fender</link>s and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/2998983.xml">
go-faster stripes</link>. Cars driven by boy racers are often small, and it's not uncommon that they are "all show and no go", in that the cars are not the highest performance model in the range or would not be considered competitive against "genuine" sports cars. Limited funds, high insurance rates that come with young age and inexperience at driving are reasons why a person might prefer to buy a base level, 1-litre <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../108/273108.xml">
Peugeot 106</link></car>
 and equip it with a body kit and sports exhaust rather than simply buying a harder to find and much more expensive to insure 106 GTi.</p>
<p>

An example of a boy racer car of the old generation is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/2227750.xml">
Ford Escort</link> (both the early rear wheel drive versions such as the RS2000 and the later XR3i variants) due to their low cost and easily tuned engine, while modern boy racers generally use <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../637/377637.xml">
hot hatchback</link>s such as the <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../410/543410.xml">
Renault Clio</link></car>
 and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../079/589079.xml">
Nova SR</link>. </p>
<p>

According to the stereotype the new generation doesn't know much about tuning the engine, though there is little evidence to prove that this is true of the majority of people who would be categorized as "boy racers". Not everyone who owns modified cars are willing to spend thousands of pounds/dollars on the engine.</p>
<p>

Films such as <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/248222.xml">
The Fast and the Furious</link></it> and MTV's <it><series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/681047.xml">
Pimp My Ride</link></series>
</it> have caused additional interest in boy racing. Boy racers tend to be dictated by trends from popular racer media such as <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.8">
<print_media wordnetid="106263609" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<press wordnetid="106263369" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../304/4159304.xml">
Max Power</link></publication>
</medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</press>
</creation>
</print_media>
</magazine>
</product>
</work>
 and <magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../562/7516562.xml">
Fast Car</link></magazine>
, spending lots of money to keep up with the trends. Recently they can been seen moving away from The Fast and The Furious influenced <it>Jap Style</it> into the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/1390192.xml">
drifting</link> bandwagon largely hyped by magazines, despite some owning unsuitable <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/755078.xml">
FWD</link> cars, causing a lot of displeasure amongst genuine drifting enthusiasts.</p>
<p>

Typical upgrades for a boy racer include large stereos (which often take up the whole boot and can be heard playing dance music or happy hardcore from down the road); extravagant paint jobs; over-sized exhaust pipes; large spoilers; hood scoops on non-turbocharged cars and neon lights underneath the chassis. Lowering a car is an extremely common modification.</p>
<p>

Such modifications are also favored by genuine enthusiasts. Boy racers would be distinguished from these enthusiasts by the overall performance and quality of the cars they drive and the modifications they make in relation to the overall performance of their car. For example, a stereotypical boy racer might own a Vauxhall Nova 1.1 with over-sized wheels and exhaust, and they might use it to drive round town centers at night showing off to the crowds of people heading for pubs and clubs, while the enthusiast might own a modified Toyota Supra which they drive only at weekends.</p>
<p>

Boy racers might also flout most motoring laws, such as running their fog-lights during the day, speeding, weaving through traffic, cornering too hard etc. Challenging superior sports cars is another dangerous pastime which seems extremely common; it is almost an occupational hazard for a sports car driver in the UK to be challenged at the lights by someone in a small hatchback.</p>
<p>

Not all young drivers with modified cars fall into this bracket, with many driving their cars in a sensible manner. Car modifiers and cruisers who take a pride in their vehicles are generally well behaved and often have respect for other road users. There is often no distinction in the mainstream media between the boy racer and modified car enthusiast which can lead to the latter being tarred with the same brush. In essence the boy racer is to the car scene what hooligans are to football; however, it seems that many young male drivers are regarded as boy racers regardless of circumstance. The 'Boy racer' term itself is considered by some to be derogatory, as not all car modifiers are necessarily in their teens, or of the male gender. Most 'boy racers' do not associate themselves with the term, and instead think of themselves as car enthusiasts. Some even have a wolf in sheep's clothing style car which looks like a standard 1.1 Ford Fiesta but underneath beholds a 2.0, thus looking like a boy racer, with low profile tyres on a lowered ride. Thus showing real enthusiasm about the mechanics of a vehicle rather than the all show and no go that is usually tagged along with boy racer name.</p>

<sec>
<st>
By country</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Australia</st>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
, the term <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/1943628.xml">
hoon</link></it> refers to those who drive in an anti-social and dangerous manner. </p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Canada</st>
<p>

In <region wordnetid="108630039" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/5042916.xml">
Canada</link></region>
, the term "rice" and "rice rocket" etc , is commonly substituted with the term "French", mostly in eastern <district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../218/22218.xml">
Ontario</link></district>
 near the border of the French-speaking province of <district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/7954867.xml">
Quebec</link></district>
. In Quebec and many other areas, the US term <it>Ricer</it> sees more common use.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
New Zealand</st>
<p>

Boy racers in New Zealand generally (but not always) drive Japanese imports as well as "old school" Euros, but also drive late models too. Often (But not always) these vehicles are modified with things designed to make the car look good rather than go fast, such as lowering (which may improve handling), changing the vehicles colour and putting larger wheels on (which also may improve handling), etc. </p>


<p>

But due to New Zealand having more relaxed laws on the modification of vehicles, a number of modifications not otherwise found in international practice  are often not only road legal, but saleable at specialist automotive dealerships.
The most commonly observed vehicles tend to be late model vehicles with the following standardized engine modifications, not limited to the following, but almost always including:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Turbocharging</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Supercharging</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Variable Valve Timing Control</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Modifiable Suspension setup</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

The proximity of Japan, and the liberal importation policy of New Zealand for used Japanese vehicles has also created a fleet of performance based vehicles within the country. Some specific models have a cult-like status, in particular :</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

R33, and R34 Nissan Skyline, particularly the GT-R, modified for Street Racing or Drifting. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

S14 and S15 Nissan Silvia, in the same fashion as for the Skyline.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nissan 180SX and 200SX, though these vehicles are becoming less common</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nissan 300ZX - a popular performance coupe, with myriad modifications</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Nissan 350Z</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Subaru Impreza, particularly sedans. Modifications are designed to mimic Rally practice for street use. They are less commonly modified for Drifting, though this form is seen to appear a competitive events on occasion. The desirable STI models will be aped in the form of spoilers decals etc. by less affluent owners wanting to be seen to own a performance vehicle.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Subaru WRX. Modifications are similar to those performed on the Impreza model. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mitsubishi Lancer. The Evo series are the most sought after, and it is not uncommon for owners of less well endowed variants to modify their vehicles with after-market parts to produce similar and sometimes excessive performance from a less expensive vehicle. In other cases (see below), most modifications are highly gratuitous.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Honda Civic VTEC (Coupe)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Toyota Altezza (Lexus IS200)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Toyota Celica</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Toyota Supra</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Toyota Levin Coupe</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Mazda RX7</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Rotary transplantation in late 1970s - early 1980s small two-door and four-door sedans of various manufacturers, not limited to Mazda.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

With the proximity of New Zealand to Japan with respect to free flow of technical information and after-market spares and parts, a number of tuning houses have become quite well known and even garner respect within Japan and other international markets for the quality of their workmanship.</p>
<p>

The following goals are followed by seriously-minded modifiers :
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Power increase - it is not uncommon to see road-going high performance vehicles with dyno-tuned engines producing outputs far in excess of specification, often inspired by Japanese practice, e.g. the 1000 BHP Nissan Skyline, and 400BHP variants of 2 litre straight-four powerplants from various manufacturers.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Decoupled Gas Turbines - The combination of Turbo- and Supercharging of a motor vehicle is often seen as <it>de riguer</it> in most performance circles. Given New Zealand's hitherto relaxed automotive noise regulations, it is very popular for manual vehicles equipped with turbochargers to have a chromed inter-cooler system dominating the front of their vehicle, along with a noisy waste-gate system to let all around know that they possess such a vehicle. Superchargers often require a through-flow exhaust system with a wide bore - this has given rise to another trend (see following list below)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Suspension Systems - these range from performance directed user-tunable systems through to exhibitionist gas-bag systems. As in other countries, lowering a car is considered a bare essential. The New Zealand Police are constantly examining, and de-registering cars for the illegal practice of cutting springs as opposed to fitting customized units designed for the purpose.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Braking Systems - improved braking tends to be the province of performance oriented modifiers, though an improvement in braking is often a requirement for vehicles with after-market very large diameter and therefore heavy chromed alloy wheels, whose rolling mass decreases the effectiveness of standard braking systems.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In consequence with these directions in modification, the following 'vulgarities' are often seen on New Zealand's roads:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Decals literally plastered on more ordinary model vehicles indicating a factory/after-market performance increase where none exists (e.g. NISMO for Nissans, STI for Subarus, MUGEN for Hondas, etc)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Big-bore exhausts to increase noise and appearance for vehicles with no supercharging - this is an incredibly common phenomenon in New Zealand, to the point that such an exhaust system of any kind is an automatic identifier of a boy racer, whether wannabe or capable enthusiast. Fake blow-off valves are another phenomenon.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Improperly/Illegally dropped suspensions - springs cut by an amateur are rightly considered a road-safety menace by the New Zealand Police, and are a subject of law enforcement. A recent fashion in New Zealand is to take older rear-wheel drive German sedans, mostly by BMW and Mercedes-Benz, and equip them with very large chromed alloy wheels, seeking to create a 'hip-hop look' and lower them improperly in an attempt to save money - which is instantly recognizable as an amateur job as the suspension geometry of the rear-wheels is so incorrect that the wheels appear 'splayed-out'. The rear wheels appear to be 'knock-kneed' - they have their upper edged nestling within the rear wheel-arch, and their contact area a sizable distance outside of the body-line. The New Zealand Police have also been targeting these vehicles for safety reasons - it is clearly impossible for these vehicles to have adequate road-traction in adverse conditions, and they therefore present a safety hazard to themselves and other motorists.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Interestingly, very few devotees of European marques go to quite the lengths of owners of Japanese vehicles - though this is most likely due to the very different attitudes to European cars in New Zealand and their fates in second-hand ownership as compared with Japanese vehicles. European vehicles, when new, tend to be the property of well-to-do professionals, and ownership patterns follow those of other countries and companies i.e Doctors, Lawyers, Directors etc. owning BMW, Audi, Mercedes, Porsche, etc. Less prestigious European brands, e.g. Volkswagen, Fiat, Skoda, tend to be own by the aforementioned professional's wives, and so retain even less desirability.</p>
<p>

One anomaly is Alfa Romeo, where values plummet even on newer vehicles, and so consequently tend to be prized by cognoscenti. The limit of 'boy racering' an Alfa tends to be factory-specific parts, wheels, and decals limited to Autodelta white cloverleaf triangles and Alfa Romeo shadow-decals, and occasionally manufacturer decals on 155's to make them look like DTM competitors. Alfas also tend to humble many Japanese wannabes in a traffic-light start, when driven by a competent Alfa enthusiast. The large fleet of Alfa 33's are now tending to become surf-wagons or else daily hacks as they crumble into rust, though occasionally a 33, and sometimes a 75, will be 'done up' as a boy-racer, though they are rare sights indeed.</p>
<p>

Older BMW 3-series, and Mercedes Benz E-180, anc C-class vehicles tend now to be favoured boy racer material, but their higher values make them less common sights on New Zealand's roads. There is known to be one 1980's Maserati Bi-turbo in Auckland whose owner is in the process of modifying the vehicle for higher performance.</p>
<p>

Unfortunately, a number of clubs devoted to performance cars have ties to the criminal gang subculture, and with fluctuations within membership and club direction, there is often no clear distinction between the two on the minds of the public or law enforcement services. Below is a list of a few example organizations:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Assyrian Performance</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Chosen Few</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

8 Ball Rollin</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Illist Car Club</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Slap n Tikle </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

MMC</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Xtreme Angles Drift Club</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Car Enthusiasts New Zealands</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kings of Diamonds</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

S.N.U</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

B.B.K</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

eXit</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Christchurch Underground</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

In New Zealand  the "boy racers" who do not follow the laws of New Zealand when modifying their cars and demonstrating bad driving. These are the few who give most "Boy Racers" (RE: Car Enthusiasts) a bad name, by driving dangerously and are a hazard to the public.</p>
<p>

Recent objections to boy racers in Christchurch have seen Police action to curb their activities within the weekend in the CBD. similar moves are taking place in Wellington for the Cuba Street locale, but these enforcement are not really possible in Auckland. Primary objections for residents and business owners have been centered around noise abatement (for big-bore exhausts and excessively loud turbocharger blow-off valves), and anti-social behavior on the part of drivers and their passengers, not limited to but including alcoholism, drug use and occasional violence. The main metropolitan areas of Auckland, Wellington and Christchurch are inevitably the haunts of boy-racers in New Zealand, yet in more populous towns there is a real presence, particularly Palmerston-North, Hastings and New Plymouth on the North Island, with Nelson and Dunedin being centers outside Christchurch on the South Island. Each town has their own distinct type of boy racers, with New Plymouth's boy racers been more 'drift' orientated than any other centre.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
United Kingdom</st>
<p>

In some parts of the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, where car culture is sometimes seen as being inextricably linked to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/926531.xml">
chav culture</link>, (the same can also be said for the links with  and Scobe Culture in Ireland) and the term "Barry Boy" can sometimes be used. It is interesting to note that because of the obvious links between chav culture and car culture the word chav may be used in reference to boy racers. During the height of the XR3's popularities in the eighties and early nineties as they were a choice of boy racers, they and owners were referred to as "XR3 Moron".</p>
<p>

The stereotypical <it>boy racers</it> in the UK can be easily identified. They tend to prefer small front wheel drive cars like Novas, Corsas, Saxos and Clios with small engines usually ranging between 1.0 litre and 1.4 litres. (Engines with higher capacity are usually sold in the UK as slightly sportier in character and due to increased insurance premiums, might be beyond the financial reach of the stereotypical boy racer). These smaller cars are then often fitted with large gauge exhausts to make them sound more powerful then they really are, though usually this can lead to it sounding like the car is making a "farting" sound as the engine is revved up, or when there is a gear change. Powerful stereos are also installed and generally heavy bass techno music is played, which normally can be felt more then heard. Due to bad installation and sound proofing, people can normally hear these cars coming before they come into sight.</p>
<p>

Latterly, the increase in popularity of <technique wordnetid="105665146" confidence="0.8">
<diversion wordnetid="100426928" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<sport wordnetid="100523513" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/1390192.xml">
drifting</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</method>
</contest>
</social_event>
</sport>
</event>
</know-how>
</diversion>
</technique>
 has seen a resurgence in the use of rear wheel drive cars by the boy racer fraternity. Popular models include the <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.8">
<self-propelled_vehicle wordnetid="104170037" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<wheeled_vehicle wordnetid="104576211" confidence="0.8">
<container wordnetid="103094503" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<motor_vehicle wordnetid="103791235" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../202/369202.xml">
Nissan 200SX</link></motor_vehicle>
</vehicle>
</container>
</wheeled_vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</self-propelled_vehicle>
</car>
</conveyance>
, <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<platform wordnetid="103961939" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link>
BMW 3 Series</link></platform>
</car>
, <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../444/232444.xml">
Ford Sierra</link></car>
 DOHC, and <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<link>
Opel Ascona</link></vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</conveyance>
. Any of these models offer cheap access to tail-out motoring whereas front wheel drive cars are not capable of generating power-<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../963/577963.xml">
oversteer</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Ireland</st>
<p>

Generally Irish boy racers are very similar to those from the U.K. However modification parts are harder to find so most cars will be fitted with ill-chosen sideskirts, bumpers etc. Also the roads in Ireland are far worse than those in the U.K. hence many boy racer cars will have cracked side skirts and chipped alloy wheels,the repair of which is expensive. Many people question the fitting of these items given Irelands poor roads. Irish boy racers will always drive Japanese cars, due to the perception of these as more "reliable" in Ireland.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
United States</st>
<p>

<body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
Americans</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 often use the somewhat derogatory term "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/463443.xml">
rice burner</link>", "rice rocket", or <it>ricer</it> to describe the boy racer concept, since most of the vehicles are of Asian manufacture.  It's generally used to describe one who drives a car with the "riced" look without any of the performance upgrades.  If a car is "riced out", it has the import tuner look, and may or may not actually have performance parts under the hood.  There's also the less popular term "wheat burner" or "Domestic Rice", which is the same thing, but with a domestic American model such as a <conveyance wordnetid="103100490" confidence="0.8">
<car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.8">
<self-propelled_vehicle wordnetid="104170037" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<wheeled_vehicle wordnetid="104576211" confidence="0.8">
<container wordnetid="103094503" confidence="0.8">
<vehicle wordnetid="104524313" confidence="0.8">
<motor_vehicle wordnetid="103791235" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/17837421.xml">
Dodge Neon</link></motor_vehicle>
</vehicle>
</container>
</wheeled_vehicle>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</self-propelled_vehicle>
</car>
</conveyance>
, <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/8943554.xml">
Ford Focus</link></car>
, or <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../166/684166.xml">
Chevrolet Cavalier</link></car>
. A "krauter" is a German model, usually a <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../790/291790.xml">
Volkswagen Jetta</link></car>
 or <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../188/182188.xml">
Volkswagen Golf</link></car>
.
The latter two categories are also sometimes referred to as "rice eaters", since their competition in the tuner scene is usually the more popular Asian models.</p>
<p>

Other terms include "tuner", "tuner kid", "street racer", among others.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Alternate uses</st>
<p>

In the United States, <b>Boy Racer</b> is more often used to describe a car (not a person) which has a sporty or "racy" character, despite being completely stock and not very fast.  This is because the car may stereotypically appeal to young ladies who want to race the boys.  Their cars, then, are "boy racers."  Such cars would include the <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../584/737584.xml">
Toyota Corolla</link></car>
, <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../413/363413.xml">
Honda Civic</link></car>
, and <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../203/873203.xml">
Dodge Avenger</link></car>
.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/11095.xml">
Ford</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../157/1396157.xml">
Grand Am Cup</link> racing model of the <car wordnetid="102958343" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../908/105908.xml">
Mustang</link></car>
, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../045/9143045.xml">
FR500C</link> was nicknamed "Boy Racer" by Ford executives.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link>
Café Racer</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../863/2076863.xml">
Car customizing</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../531/926531.xml">
Chav</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../207/2473207.xml">
Cruising (driving around)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/1943628.xml">
Hoon</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/1158504.xml">
Import Scene</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../767/2960767.xml">
Joyride (crime)</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../047/681047.xml">
Pimp My Ride</link></series>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<merchant wordnetid="110309896" confidence="0.8">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.8">
<capitalist wordnetid="109609232" confidence="0.8">
<distributor wordnetid="110018861" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<retailer wordnetid="110525436" confidence="0.8">
<supplier wordnetid="110677271" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/3510269.xml">
Ripspeed</link></supplier>
</retailer>
</causal_agent>
</distributor>
</capitalist>
</businessperson>
</merchant>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../470/1725470.xml">
Street racing</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

US Term: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../443/463443.xml">
Rice burner</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Contrast: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../233/874233.xml">
Sleeper (car)</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.boyracerguide.co.uk/">
boyracerguide.co.uk</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
