<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:23:25[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Cyclotron radiation</title>
<id>170757</id>
<revision>
<id>240551381</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-23T22:42:08Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>RJHall</username>
<id>91076</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Electromagnetic radiation</category>
<category>Plasma physics</category>
<category>Experimental particle physics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Cyclotron radiation</b> is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../426/9426.xml">
electromagnetic radiation</link> emitted by moving <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/9804.xml">
charge</link>d particles deflected by a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/36563.xml">
magnetic field</link>.  The <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../631/18631.xml">
Lorentz force</link></concept>
</idea>
 on the particles acts perpendicular to both the magnetic field lines and the particles' motion through them, creating an acceleration of charged particles that causes them to emit radiation (and to spiral around the magnetic field lines).<p>

The name of this radiation derives from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../585/44585.xml">
cyclotron</link>, a type of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../032/18589032.xml">
particle accelerator</link> used since the 1930s to create highly energetic particles for study. The cyclotron makes use of the circular orbits that charged particles exhibit in a uniform magnetic field. Furthermore, the period of the orbit is independent of the energy of the particles, allowing the cyclotron to operate at a set <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../779/10779.xml">
frequency</link>, and not worry about the energy of the particles at a given time. Cyclotron radiation is emitted by all charged particles travelling through magnetic fields, however, not just those in cyclotrons. Cyclotron radiation from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/3532455.xml">
plasma</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/170818.xml">
interstellar space</link> or around <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../650/4650.xml">
black hole</link>s and other astronomical phenomena is an important source of information about distant magnetic fields.  The planet <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../930/38930.xml">
Jupiter</link> in particular is a large source of cyclotron radiation. The <idea wordnetid="105833840" confidence="0.8">
<concept wordnetid="105835747" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../236/24236.xml">
power</link></concept>
</idea>
 (energy per unit time) of the emission of each electron can be calculated using:</p>
<p>

<math>{-dE \over dt}={\sigma_t B^2 V^2 \over c \mu_o} </math></p>
<p>

where <it>E</it> is energy, <it>t</it> is time, <math> \sigma_t </math> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/624714.xml">
Thomson cross section</link> (total, not differential), <it>B</it> is the magnetic field strength, <it>V</it> is the velocity perpendicular to the magnetic field, <it>c</it> is the speed of light and <math> \mu_o </math> is the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../964/4602964.xml">
permeability of free space</link>. In the context of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../634/1690634.xml">
magnetic fusion energy</link>, cyclotron radiation losses translate into a requirement for a minimum <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../455/3532455.xml">
plasma</link> energy density in relation to the magnetic field energy density (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/1631015.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Power+density+and+energy+balance%22])">
Aneutronic fusion#Power density and energy balance</link>).</p>
<p>

Cyclotron radiation would likely be produced in a high altitude nuclear explosion. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../290/18616290.xml">
Gamma ray</link>s produced by the explosion would <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../611/59611.xml">
ionize</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../902/902.xml">
atom</link>s in the upper atmosphere and those free electrons would interact with the earth's magnetic field to produce cyclotron radiation in the form of an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../097/41097.xml">
electromagnetic pulse</link> (EMP).  This phenomenon is of concern to the military as the EMP may damage solid state equipment.</p>
<p>

Cyclotron radiation has a  spectrum with its main spike at the
same fundamental frequency as the particle's orbit, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../232/41232.xml">
harmonic</link>s at higher integral factors. Harmonics are the result of imperfections in the actual emission environment, which also create a broadening of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/177320.xml">
spectral line</link>s. The most obvious source of line broadening is non-uniformities in the magnetic field; as an electron passes
from one area of the field to another, its emission frequency will change with the strength of the field. Other sources of broadening include collisional broadening from the electron failing to follow a perfect orbit, distortions of the emission caused by interactions with the surrounding plasma, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/26962.xml">
relativistic</link> effects if the charged particles are sufficiently energetic.  When the electrons are moving at relativistic speeds, cyclotron radiation is known as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../808/170808.xml">
synchrotron radiation</link>.</p>
<p>

The recoil experienced by a particle emitting cyclotron radiation is called <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/3209246.xml">
radiation reaction</link>. Radiation reaction acts as a resistance to motion in a cyclotron; and the work necessary to overcome it is the main energetic cost of accelerating a particle in a cyclotron. Cyclotrons are prime examples of systems which experience radiation reaction.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 See also </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/2992945.xml">
auroral kilometric radiation</link> (AKR)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/2817855.xml">
Larmor formula</link></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
