<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 15:45:39[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Carpal tunnel syndrome</title>
<id>56462</id>
<revision>
<id>244304568</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-10T04:50:40Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Lightbot</username>
<id>7178666</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Syndromes</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox_Disease</name>
<parameters>
<MeshID>
D002349</MeshID>
<eMedicineTopic>
455</eMedicineTopic>
<MedlinePlus>
000433</MedlinePlus>
<ICD10>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../352/3530352.xml">
G</link><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/classifications/apps/icd/icd10online/?gg56.htm+g560">
56.0</weblink></ICD10>
<DiseasesDB>
2156</DiseasesDB>
<Caption>
Transverse section across the wrist and digits. (The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/231462.xml">
median nerve</link> is the yellow dot near the center. The carpal tunnel is not labeled, but the circular structure surrounding the median nerve is visible.)</Caption>
<eMedicineSubj>
orthoped</eMedicineSubj>
<Image>
Gray422.png</Image>
<eMedicine_mult>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emedicine.com/pmr/topic21.htm">
pmr/21</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emedicine.com/emerg/topic83.htm">
emerg/83</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emedicine.com/radio/topic135.htm">
radio/135</weblink></eMedicine_mult>
<ICD9>
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.icd9data.com/getICD9Code.ashx?icd9354.0">
354.0</weblink></ICD9>
<OMIM>
115430</OMIM>
</parameters>
</template>

<p>

This article is about the medical condition.&#32;&#32;For the anatomical structure, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/10799487.xml">
Carpal tunnel</link>.  For the Kid Koala album, see <album wordnetid="106591815" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../798/2078798.xml">
Carpal Tunnel Syndrome (album)</link></album>
.</p>
<p>

<b>Carpal tunnel syndrome</b> (CTS) or <b>median neuropathy at the wrist</b> is a medical condition in which the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/231462.xml">
median nerve</link> is compressed at the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../901/234901.xml">
wrist</link>, leading to pain, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/398940.xml">
paresthesia</link>s, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../190/3266190.xml">
muscle weakness</link> in the hand.  True carpal tunnel only elicits symptoms in the thumb, index, and middle fingers, along the median nerve distribution, but some patients may experience symptoms in the palm as well.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> A form of compressive neuropathy, CTS is more common in women than it is in men and has a peak incidence around age 42, though it can occur at any age.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> The lifetime risk for CTS is around 10% of the adult population.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Most cases of CTS are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/545165.xml">
idiopathic</link> (without known cause). Repetitive activities are often blamed for the development of CTS along with several other possible causes. However, the correlation is often unclear. </p>
<p>

It is a multi-faceted problem and can therefore be challenging to treat. Still, there are a multitude of possible treatments: treating any possible underlying disease or condition, immobilizing braces, prioritizing hand activities, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/9606.xml">
ergonomics</link>.   Recent studies have shown that medications have not been able to modify the extent of the disease.  Ultimately, carpal tunnel release surgery may be required in which outcomes are generally good.</p>


<sec>
<st>
 History </st>
<p>

Although the condition was first noted in medical literature in the early 20th century, the first use of the term “carpal tunnel syndrome” was in 1939.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> The pathology was identified by physician Dr. George S. Phalen of the <hospital wordnetid="103540595" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../958/1278958.xml">
Cleveland Clinic</link></hospital>
 after working with a group of patients in the 1950s and 1960s.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref> CTS became widely known among the general public in the 1990s because of the rapid expansion of office jobs.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Anatomy </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/10799487.xml">
Carpal tunnel</link></it>
</indent>
The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../462/231462.xml">
median nerve</link> passes through the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../487/10799487.xml">
carpal tunnel</link>, a canal in the wrist that is surrounded by bone on three sides, and a transverse carpal ligament on the fourth. Nine <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../865/144865.xml">
tendon</link>s—the flexor tendons of the hand—pass through this canal.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The median nerve can be compressed by a decrease in the size of the canal, an increase in the size of the contents (such as the swelling of lubrication tissue around the flexor tendons), or both. Simply bending the wrist at 90 degrees will decrease the size of the canal.</p>
<p>

Compression of the median nerve as it runs deep to the TCL causes wasting of the thenar eminence, weakness of the flexor pollicis brevis, adductor pollicis, opponens pollicis, abductor pollicis brevis, as well as sensory loss in the distribution of the median nerve distal to the transverse carpal ligament, sparing the superficial sensory branch given that its branch point is normally proximal to the TCL and travels superficially thus avoiding compression.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Symptoms </st>

<p>

Many people that have carpal tunnel syndrome have gradually increasing symptoms over time. The first symptoms of CTS may appear when sleeping and typically include numbness and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../940/398940.xml">
paresthesia</link> (a burning and tingling sensation) in the thumb, index, and middle fingers, although some patients may experience symptoms in the palm as well.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> These symptoms appear at night because many people sleep with bent wrists which further compresses the carpal tunnel. If the median nerve is already under stress, the increased compression of the bent wrist results in numbness and tingling. Difficulty gripping and making a fist, dropping objects, and weakness are symptoms of progression. In early stages of CTS individuals often mistakenly blame the tingling and numbness on restricted blood circulation and they believe their hands are simply “falling asleep”. In chronic cases, there may be wasting of the <it>thenar</it> muscles (the body of muscles which are connected to the thumb)</p>
<p>

Unless numbness or paresthesia are among the predominant symptoms, it is unlikely the symptoms are primarily caused by carpal tunnel syndrome. In effect, pain of any type, location, or severity with the absence of <it>significant numbness or paresthesia</it> is not likely to fall under this diagnosis.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Causes </st>

<p>

Most cases of CTS are <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/545165.xml">
idiopathic</link>: without a known cause.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref> A common factor in developing carpal tunnel symptoms is increased hand use or activity. While repetitive activities are often blamed for the development of CTS, the correlation is often unclear. Physiology and family history may have a significant role in individual's susceptibility. CTS is associated with stress, trauma, pregnancy, as well as several diseases including multiple myeloma, amyloid, rhematoid arthritis, acromegaly, mucopolysaccharidoses, hypothyroidism.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Work related </st>
<p>

The international debate regarding the relationship between CTS and repetitive motion and work is ongoing. The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../123/227123.xml">
Occupational Safety and Health Administration</link> (OSHA) has adopted rules and regulations regarding cumulative trauma disorders. Occupational risk factors of repetitive tasks, force, posture, and vibration have been cited. However, the <association wordnetid="108049401" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../242/7973242.xml">
American Society for Surgery of the Hand</link></association>
 (ASSH) has issued a statement that the current literature does not support a causal relationship between specific work activities and the development of diseases such as CTS. </p>
<p>

The relationship between work and CTS is controversial; in many locations workers injured at work are entitled to time off and compensation.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref> Many cases of carpal tunnel syndrome are provoked by repetitive grasping and manipulating activities, and the exposure can be cumulative. Symptoms are commonly exacerbated by forceful and repetitive use of the hand and wrists in industrial occupations.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> Carpal tunnel syndrome results in billions of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/8100.xml">
dollar</link>s of workers compensation claims every year.</p>
<p>

Studies done by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/520540.xml">
National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health</link> (NIOSH) indicated that job tasks that involve highly repetitive manual acts or that necessitate stressful wrist postures were connected with incidents of CTS and related problems.  In addition, a 2005 study found that people who have shoulder and neck pain or who work with their shoulder in elevation (signs of poor posture) are more likely to develop a repetitive overuse injury.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref> These factors can affect the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../355/105355.xml">
biomechanics</link> of the upper limb or tissue tolerance to repetitive tasks resulting in injury, or both. Postural and spinal assessment along with ergonomic assessments should be included in the overall determination of the condition. Addressing these factors has been found to improve the status of work related upper limb injuries.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref></p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/65845.xml">
Hypothyroidism</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/504841.xml">
osteoarthritis</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../677/44677.xml">
diabetes</link> were most often associated with CTS-like symptoms, as were variables such as age, obesity and wrist dimension. In a 1998 study, only 35 of 297 subjects were aware of the underlying health condition which could account for their CTS-like symptoms.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> Hence, these causes would be missed by doctors if they were relying on a patient's health history to rule out other causative factors. It is important that a doctor rule out other causes of CTS-like symptoms. If a patient does not have CTS, corrective surgery is destined to fail.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Stress related </st>

<p>

Studies have also related carpal tunnel and other upper extremity complaints with psychological and social factors. A large amount of psychological distress showed doubled risk of the report of pain, while job demands, poor support from colleagues, and work dissatisfaction also showed an increase in the report of pain, even after short term exposure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref> A minority viewpoint holds that stress is the main cause, rather than a contributing factor, of a large fraction of pain symptoms usually attributed to carpal tunnel syndrome.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Trauma related </st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../943/839943.xml">
Fractures</link> of one of the arm <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../099/4099.xml">
bone</link>s, particularly a <disease wordnetid="114070360" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../903/760903.xml">
Colles' fracture</link></disease>
.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/795334.xml">
Dislocation</link> of one of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../704/63704.xml">
carpal bone</link>s of the wrist.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Strong blunt trauma to the wrist or lower forearm, incurred for example by using arm extremity to cushion a fall or protecting oneself from falling heavy objects.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../811/684811.xml">
Hematoma</link> forming inside the wrist, because of internal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/146315.xml">
hemorrhaging</link>.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Deformities from abnormal <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../217/239217.xml">
healing</link> of old bone fractures.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Non-traumatic </st>


<p>

Non-traumatic causes generally happen over a period of time, and are not triggered by one certain event. Many of these factors are manifestations of physiologic aging. Examples include:</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/70425.xml">
Inflammation</link> of the thin mucinous membrane around the tendons. Part of the process of inflammation is swelling, and this compresses the nerve. Swelling of this membrane is the final common pathway for most cases of carpal tunnel, whether caused idiopathically, through exposure, or medically.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 With <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../587/1771587.xml">
pregnancy</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/65845.xml">
hypothyroidism</link>, fluid is retained in tissues, which swells the tenosynovium.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../850/65850.xml">
Acromegaly</link>, a disorder of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../072/173072.xml">
growth hormone</link>s, compresses the nerve by the abnormal growth of bones around the hand and wrist.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../214/31214.xml">
Tumor</link>s (usually benign), such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../278/12278.xml">
ganglion</link> or a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../150/288150.xml">
lipoma</link>, can protrude into the carpal tunnel, reducing the amount of space. This is exceedingly rare (less than 1%).</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it>Double crush syndrome</it>, where there is compression or irritation of nerve branches contributing to the median nerve in the neck or anywhere above the wrist. This then increases the sensitivity of the nerve to compression in the wrist. This, while a possible factor, is also a rare contributor in most cases.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/545165.xml">
Idiopathic</link> causes are common.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Common activities that have been identified as contributing to repetitive stress induced carpal tunnel syndrome include:</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Use of power tools</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Typing on a computer keyboard or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../365/44365.xml">
typewriter</link></entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Construction work such as handling many bricks, stone and/or lumber</entry>
<entry level="2" type="bullet">

 Excessive play of percussion instruments (especially piano) and stringed instruments</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Often people suffering from carpal tunnel syndrome can have multiple contributing factors which are aggravated by vigorous hand activities and repetitive stress trauma to the hand.</p>
<p>

Proper attention to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/9606.xml">
ergonomic</link> considerations can reduce or eliminate these kinds of exposures.</p>
<p>

While carpal tunnel syndrome is often called a "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/25756.xml">
repetitive strain injury</link>" (RSI) or "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../756/25756.xml">
cumulative trauma disorder</link>" (CTD), these labels are discouraged by physicians, particularly hand specialists. <it>Carpal tunnel</it> is a specific condition with specific symptoms that responds fairly reliably. Most of the time, carpal tunnel is not caused by a "strain" or "trauma" of any type. RSI and CTD are relatively non-specific terms with non-specific symptoms that respond variably to treatment. </p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Diagnosis </st>

<p>

Clinical assessment by history taking and physical examination can frequently diagnose CTS.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../063/822063.xml">
Phalen's maneuver</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 is performed by flexing the wrist gently as far as possible, then holding this position and awaiting symptoms.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref> A positive test is one that results in numbness in the median nerve distribution when holding the wrist in acute flexion position within 60 seconds. The quicker the numbness starts, the more advanced the condition.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../628/1150628.xml">
Tinel's sign</link>, a classic, though less specific test, is a way to detect irritated nerves. Tinel's is performed by lightly tapping (<it>percussing</it> for those who don't know what "tapping" means) the area over the nerve to elicit a sensation of tingling or "pins and needles" in the nerve distribution.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link>
Durkan test</link>, <it>carpal compression test</it>, or applying firm pressure of the palm over the nerve for up to 30 seconds to elicit symptoms has also been proposed.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

Other conditions may also be misdiagnosed as carpal tunnel syndrome. Thus, if, based on history and physical examination, a CTS diagnosis is suspected but not clear, patients will likely be tested electrodiagnostically with <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../459/1877459.xml">
nerve conduction studies</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/997173.xml">
electromyography</link>; <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../446/19446.xml">
MRI</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/143357.xml">
ultrasound imaging</link> are also used.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Prevention </st>

<p>

One way to prevent carpal tunnel syndrome is to take frequent breaks from repetitive movement such as <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../281/18842281.xml">
computer keyboard</link></method>
</device>
</know-how>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 usage or use of browser based games that encourage the user for excessive finger movement. Free software programs such as <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../889/7750889.xml">
Workrave</link></software>
 and <software wordnetid="106566077" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../442/8173442.xml">
Xwrits</link></software>
 are available to remind users to take breaks and stretch their wrists. There are also other ways to prevent Carpal Tunnel Syndrome such as reduce your force and relax your grip. Most people use more force than needed to perform many tasks involving the hands. If your work involves a cash register, for instance, hit the keys softly. For prolonged handwriting, use a big pen with an oversized, soft grip adapter and free-flowing ink. This way you won't have to grip the pen tightly or press as hard on the paper. </p>
<p>

Take frequent breaks. Every 15 to 20 minutes give your hands and wrists a break by gently stretching and bending them. Alternate tasks when possible. If you use equipment that vibrates or that requires you to exert a great amount of force, taking breaks is even more important. </p>
<p>

Watch your form. Avoid bending your wrist all the way up or down. A relaxed middle position is best. If you use a keyboard, keep it at elbow height or slightly lower. </p>
<p>

Improve your posture. Incorrect posture can cause your shoulders to roll forward. When your shoulders are in this position, your neck and shoulder muscles are shortened, compressing nerves in your neck. This can affect your wrists, fingers and hands. </p>
<p>

Keep your hands warm. You're more likely to develop hand pain and stiffness if you work in a cold environment. If you can't control the temperature at work, put on fingerless gloves that keep your hands and wrists warm.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Treatment </st>

<p>

There has been much discussion as to the most effective treatment for CTS.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref> CTS is a multi-faceted problem and can be challenging to treat from a clinician's perspective. Nevertheless, starting therapy early, when carpal tunnel is in a mild stage, is associated with improved long-term results. The patient can choose a variety of treatment options ranging from alternative medicine therapies such as Occupational therapy, chiropractic or acupuncture, to traditional allopathic approaches such as physical therapy and surgery.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref> </p>

<ss1>
<st>
 Reversible causes </st>

<p>

Some causes of CTS are secondary to other conditions — metabolic disorders such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/65845.xml">
hypothyroidism</link>, for example. Treatment of the primary disorder often resolves CTS symptoms.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Immobilizing braces </st>

<p>

<image width="300px" src="Carpal_tunnel_splint.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

A splint can keep the wrist straight.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

The importance of wrist <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../861/2373861.xml">
braces</link>  and  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../783/711783.xml">
splints</link> in the carpal tunnel syndrome therapy is known, but many people are unwilling to use braces. In 1993, The American Academy of Neurology recommend a non-invasive treatment for the CTS at the beginning (except for sensitive or motor deficit or grave report at EMG/ENG): a  therapy using splints was indicated for light and moderate pathology.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref> Current recommendations generally don't suggest immobilizing braces, but instead activity modification and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../071/22071.xml">
non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug</link>s as initial therapy, followed by more aggressive options or specialist referral if symptoms do not improve.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref></p>
<p>

Many health professionals suggest that, for best results, one should wear braces at night and, if possible, during the activity primarily causing stress on the wrists.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2225%22])">25</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2226%22])">26</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Physiotherapy </st>

<p>

Physiotherapy offers several ways to treat and control carpal tunnel syndrome. This procedure should be directed specifically towards the pattern of pain / symptoms and dysfunction assessed by the therapist. As such, it may include a range of modalities ranging from soft tissue massage, conservative stretches and exercises and techniques to directly mobilize the nerve tissue. It can also include the aforementioned immobilizing braces.</p>
<p>

Clinically, sometimes a patient will present with a hand that is very inflamed and swollen with severe symptoms of pain, tingling and numbness and almost a fear of use because of the pain. In these cases a physiotherapist may focus on techniques to reduce the pain and inflammation, and exercises to encourage improved circulation. A comprehensive review of effectiveness of hand therapies in carpal tunnel management demonstrates that there is some valid scientific evidence for a range of therapeutic modalities.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2227%22])">27</ref>
For instance, Body Awareness Therapy such as the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/245089.xml">
Feldenkrais method</link> has positive effects in relation to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../049/318049.xml">
fibromyalgia</link> and chronic pain.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2228%22])">28</ref> Structured exercise programs using these therapies to reduce wrist pain have been developed.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Localized steroid injections </st>

<p>

Steroid injections can be quite effective for temporary relief from symptoms of CTS for a short time frame while a patient develops a longterm strategy that fits with his/her lifestyle.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2229%22])">29</ref> In certain patients an injection may also be of diagnostic value.  This treatment is not appropriate for extended periods, however. In general, medical professionals only prescribe to localized steroid injections until other treatment options can be identified.  For most patients, permanent relief requires surgery.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2230%22])">30</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Occupational therapy</st>

<p>

Occupational therapy offers ergonomic suggestions to prevent worsening of the symptoms and occupational therapist facilitates hand functions through functional activities and helps to regain the functions which are necessary for the functional living through remedial adaptive approaches.</p>
<p>

Any forceful and repetitive use of the hands and wrists can cause upper extremity pain. More frequent rest can be useful if it can be orchestrated into one's schedule. It has been shown that taking multiple mini breaks during the stressful activity is more effective than taking occasional long breaks. There are computer applications that aid users in taking breaks. All of these applications have recommended defaults, following the most effective average break configuration, which is a 30 sec. pause every 3 to 5 minutes (the more severe the pain, the more often one should take this break).  There are also programs that automatically click the mouse. Before investing in these types of programs, it's best to consult with a doctor and research whether computer use is causing or contributing to the symptoms, as well as getting a formal diagnosis.</p>
<p>

More pro-active ways to reducing the stress on the wrists which will alleviate wrist pain and strain involve adopting a more ergonomic work and life environment. Switching from a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../213/25213.xml">
QWERTY</link> computer keyboard layout to a more optimised ergonomic layout such as <message wordnetid="106598915" confidence="0.8">
<structure wordnetid="105726345" confidence="0.8">
<arrangement wordnetid="105726596" confidence="0.8">
<request wordnetid="106513366" confidence="0.8">
<layout wordnetid="105837271" confidence="0.8">
<design wordnetid="105728678" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/46960.xml">
Dvorak</link></design>
</layout>
</request>
</arrangement>
</structure>
</message>
 was commonly cited as beneficial in early CTS studies, however some <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/62329.xml">
meta-analyses</link></method>
</know-how>
 of these studies claim that the evidence that they present is limited.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2231%22])">31</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2232%22])">32</ref></p>
<p>

It is also important that one's body be aligned properly with the keyboard. This is most easily accomplished by bending ones elbows to a 90 degree angle and making sure the keyboard is at the same height as the elbows. Also it is important not to put physical stress on the wrists by hanging the wrist on the edge of a desk, or exposing the wrists to strong vibrations (e.g. manual lawn mowing). Position the computer monitor directly in front of your seat, so the neck is not twisted to either side when viewing the screen.</p>
<p>

Exercises that relax and strengthen the muscles of the upper back can reduce the risk of a <it>double crush</it> of the median nerve.</p>
<p>

Massage is one of the most overlooked methods for treatment of the symptoms of CTS.  The use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/2441939.xml">
myofascial release</link> and active stretch release can erase the pain, numbness, tingling and burning in minutes.  Then following up with the stretches and exercises afore mentioned will lengthen the relief attained by these release techniques.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Medication </st>

<p>

Using an over-the-counter anti-inflammatory such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../525/1525.xml">
aspirin</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../627/155627.xml">
ibuprofen</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/501250.xml">
naproxen</link> can be effective as well for controlling symptoms. Pain relievers like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../406/83406.xml">
paracetamol</link> will only mask the pain, and only an anti-inflammatory will affect inflammation. Non-steroidal inflammatory medications theoretically can treat the root swelling and thus the source of the problem. Oral steroids (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../515/530515.xml">
prednisone</link>) do the same, but are generally not used for this purpose because of significant side effects. The most common complications associated with long-term use of anti-inflammatory medications are gastrointestinal irritation and bleeding. Also, some anti-inflammatory medication have been linked to heart complications. Use of anti-inflammatory medication for chronic, long-term pain should be done with doctor supervision.</p>
<p>

A more aggressive pharmaceutical option is an injection of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/197296.xml">
cortisone</link>, to reduce swelling and nerve pressure within the carpal tunnel.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/5124725.xml">
Mecobalamin</link>/<compound wordnetid="105870180" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/5124725.xml">
Methylcobalamin</link></compound>
 has been helpful in some cases of CTS.
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2233%22])">33</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
 Carpal tunnel release surgery </st>

<p>

Either a Neurosurgeon or Hand Surgeon may perform the procedure. The first step would be examination of the hands and a review of the symptoms. If CTS is suspected, depending on the severity and the situation, the surgeon may first prescribe non-operative treatment with splinting and anti-inflammatory drugs. Nerve conduction tests will positively determine the level of compression, if any.</p>

<ss2>
<st>
 Indications </st>
<p>

If symptoms resolve with non-surgical interventions, surgery can frequently be avoided. If not, then the "carpal tunnel release" surgery is recommended.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2234%22])">34</ref> In general, milder cases can be controlled for months to years, but severe cases are unrelenting symptomatically and are likely to result in surgical treatment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2235%22])">35</ref></p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Procedure </st>
<p>

In carpal tunnel release surgery, the goal is to divide the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../438/3996438.xml">
transverse carpal ligament</link> in two. This is a wide ligament that runs across the hand, from the base of the thumb to the base of the fifth finger. It also forms the top of the carpal tunnel, and when the surgeon cuts across it (i.e., in a line with the middle finger) it no longer presses down on the nerves inside, relieving the pressure.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2236%22])">36</ref></p>
<p>

There are several carpal tunnel release surgery variations: each surgeon has differences of preference based on their personal beliefs and experience. All techniques have several things in common, involving brief <link>
outpatient</link> procedures; palm or wrist incision(s); and cutting of the transverse carpal ligament.</p>
<p>

The two major types of surgery are <it>open-hand surgery</it> and <it><link>
endoscopic surgery</link></it>. Most surgeons perform open surgery, widely considered to be the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/723000.xml">
gold standard (test)</link>. However, many surgeons are now performing endoscopic techniques. Open surgery involves a small incision somewhere on the palm about an inch or two in length. Through this the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../874/17874.xml">
ligament</link> can be directly visualized and divided with relative safety. Endoscopic techniques involve one or two smaller incisions (less than half inch each) through which instrumentation is introduced including probes, knives and the scope used to visualize the operative field.</p>
<p>

All of the surgical options typically have relatively rapid recovery profiles (days to weeks depending on the activity and technique), and all usually leave a cosmetically insignificant scar.</p>

</ss2>
<ss2>
<st>
 Efficacy </st>
<p>

Surgery to correct carpal tunnel syndrome has high success rate, especially using endoscopic surgery techniques. Up to 90% of patients were able to return to their same jobs after surgery. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2237%22])">37</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2238%22])">38</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2239%22])">39</ref> In general, endoscopic techniques are as effective as traditional open carpal surgeries,<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2240%22])">40</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2241%22])">41</ref> though the faster recovery time typically noted in endoscopic procedures may be offset by higher complication rates.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2242%22])">42</ref><ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2243%22])">43</ref> Success is greatest in patients with the most typical symptoms. The most common cause of failure is incorrect diagnosis, and it should be noted that this surgery will only fix carpal tunnel syndrome, and will not relieve symptoms with alternative causes. Recurrence is rare, and apparent recurrence usually results from a misdiagnosis of another problem. Complications can occur, but serious ones are infrequent to rare.</p>
<p>

Carpal tunnel surgery is usually performed by a hand surgeon, <asset wordnetid="105154517" confidence="0.8">
<forte wordnetid="105159225" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../380/430380.xml">
orthopaedic</link></forte>
</asset>
 or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/42048.xml">
plastic surgeon</link>; some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../848/21848.xml">
neurosurgeons</link> and general surgeons also perform the procedure.</p>

</ss2>
</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Long term recovery </st>

<p>

Most people who find relief of their carpel tunnel symptoms with conservative or surgical management find minimal residual or "nerve damage".<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2244%22])">44</ref> Long-term chronic carpal tunnel syndrome (typically seen in the elderly) can result in permanent "nerve damage", i.e. symptoms of numbness, muscle wasting and weakness.</p>
<p>

While outcomes are generally good, certain factors can contribute to poorer results that have little to do with nerves, anatomy, or surgery type. One study showed that mental status parameters, alcohol use, yield much poorer overall results of treatment.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2245%22])">45</ref></p>
<p>

Many mild carpal tunnel syndrome sufferers either change their hand use pattern or posture at work or find a conservative, non-surgical treatment that allows them to return to full activity without hand numbness or pain, and without sleep disruption. Other people end up prioritizing their activities and possibly avoiding certain hand activities so that they can minimize pain and perform the essential tasks.</p>
<p>

Changing jobs is also commonly done to avoid continued repetitive stress tasks. Others find success by adjusting their repetitive movements, the frequency with which they do the movements, and the amount of time they rest between periods of performing the movements.</p>
<p>

While recurrence after surgery is a possibility, true recurrences are uncommon to rare.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2246%22])">46</ref> Such recurrence can also be non-CTS hand pain. Such hand pain may have existed prior to the surgery, which is one reason it is very important to get a proper diagnosis.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References in popular culture </st>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/68315.xml">
protagonist</link> of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/662577.xml">
Chopping Block</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/161176.xml">
webcomic</link>, Butch Reginald Mann, suffers CTS, as depicted in the first strip published on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../804/15804.xml">
July 25</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../548/34548.xml">
2000</link>. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.choppingblock.org/d/20000725.html">
http://www.choppingblock.org/d/20000725.html</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Principal Duvell from <album wordnetid="106591815" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/10565718.xml">
Mean Girls</link></movie>
</album>
 suffers from carpal tunnel sundrome. This was not a part of the original script, but added because <actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../208/629208.xml">
Tim Meadows</link></actor>
 broke his hand before shooting began and had to wear a cast.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 The recording artist, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<musician wordnetid="110340312" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<artist wordnetid="109812338" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<creator wordnetid="109614315" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../151/19357151.xml">
Kid Koala</link></creator>
</entertainer>
</artist>
</causal_agent>
</musician>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, released an album entitled, Carpal Tunnel Syndrome, in 2000.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Rock band <musical_organization wordnetid="108246613" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../090/14498090.xml">
Fall Out Boy</link></group>
</musical_organization>
 have a song titled 'The Carpal Tunnel of Love'</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In the South Park episode, <episode wordnetid="106396330" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../389/7230389.xml">
Make Love, Not Warcraft</link></episode>
, Kyle suffers from Carpal Tunnel Syndrome while fighting Jenkins.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 In <series wordnetid="108457976" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../605/11269605.xml">
The Big Bang Theory</link></series>
 episode 7 'The Dumpling Paradox', Sheldon attempts to insult Penny by saying that she has Carpal Tunnel Syndrome and that she deserves it.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Michelsen H, Posner M&#32;(2002).&#32;"Medical history of carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Hand Clin</it>&#32;<b>18</b>&#32;(2): 257–68. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0749-0712%2801%2900006-3">
10.1016/S0749-0712(01)00006-3</weblink>. PMID 12371028.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Treaster DE, Burr D&#32;(2004).&#32;"Gender differences in prevalence of upper extremity musculoskeletal disorders". <it>Ergonomicdsvss</it>&#32;<b>47</b>&#32;(5): 495–526. PMID 15204301.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
<it><weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.emedicine.com/EMERG/topic83.htm">
EMERG/83</weblink></it> at <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../243/3549243.xml">
eMedicine</link></entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kao SY&#32;(2003).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.jabfm.org/cgi/content/full/16/6/533">
Carpal tunnel syndrome as an occupational disease</weblink>". <it>The Journal of the American Board of Family Practice / American Board of Family Practice</it>&#32;<b>16</b>&#32;(6): 533–42. PMID 14963080.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Sternbach G&#32;(1999).&#32;"The carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>J Emerg Med</it>&#32;<b>17</b>&#32;(3): 519–23. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0736-4679%2899%2900030-X">
10.1016/S0736-4679(99)00030-X</weblink>. PMID 10338251.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Derebery J&#32;(2006).&#32;"Work-related carpal tunnel syndrome: the facts and the myths". <it>Clin Occup Environ Med</it>&#32;<b>5</b>&#32;(2): 353–67, viii. PMID 16647653.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Werner R&#32;(2006).&#32;"Evaluation of work-related carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>J Occup Rehabil</it>&#32;<b>16</b>&#32;(2): 207–22. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs10926-006-9026-3">
10.1007/s10926-006-9026-3</weblink>. PMID 16705490.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="8">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Werner R, Franzblau A, Gell N, Ulin S, Armstrong T&#32;(2005).&#32;"A longitudinal study of industrial and clerical workers: predictors of upper extremity tendonitis". <it>J Occup Rehabil</it>&#32;<b>15</b>&#32;(1): 37–46. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs10926-005-0872-1">
10.1007/s10926-005-0872-1</weblink>. PMID 15794495.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="9">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Cole D, Hogg-Johnson S, Manno M, Ibrahim S, Wells R, Ferrier S&#32;(2006).&#32;"Reducing musculoskeletal burden through ergonomic program implementation in a large newspaper". <it>Int Arch Occup Environ Health</it>&#32;<b>80</b>&#32;(2): 98–108. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs00420-006-0107-6">
10.1007/s00420-006-0107-6</weblink>. PMID 16736193.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="10">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Atcheson SG, Ward JR, Lowe W&#32;(1998).&#32;"Concurrent medical disease in work-related carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Arch Intern Med</it>&#32;<b>158</b>&#32;(14): 1506–12. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001%2Farchinte.158.14.1506">
10.1001/archinte.158.14.1506</weblink>. PMID 9679791.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="11">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Atcheson SG&#32;(1999).&#32;"Carpal tunnel syndrome: is it work-related?". <it>Hosp Pract (Minneap)</it>&#32;<b>34</b>&#32;(3): 49–56; quiz 147. PMID 10089926.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="12">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Nahit ES, Pritchard CM, Cherry NM, Silman AJ, Macfarlane GJ&#32;(2001).&#32;"The influence of work related psychosocial factors and psychological distress on regional musculoskeletal pain: a study of newly employed workers". <it>J Rheumatol</it>&#32;<b>28</b>&#32;(6): 1378–84. PMID 11409134.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="13">
 <cite style="font-style:normal" class="book">Cush JJ, Lipsky PE&#32;(2004). Approach to articular and musculoskeletal disorders, In: Harrison's Principles of Internal Medicine, 16th,&#32;McGraw-Hill Professional,&#32;p. 2035. ISBN 0-07-140235-7.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="14">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gonzalez del Pino J, Delgado-Martinez AD, Gonzalez Gonzalez I, Lovic A&#32;(1997).&#32;"Value of the carpal compression test in the diagnosis of carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>J Hand Surg [Br]</it>&#32;<b>22</b>&#32;(1): 38–41. PMID 9061521.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="15">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Durkan JA&#32;(1991).&#32;"A new diagnostic test for carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>J Bone Joint Surg [Am]</it>&#32;<b>73</b>: 535–538. PMID 1796937.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="17">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Bland J&#32;(2005).&#32;"Carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Curr Opin Neurol</it>&#32;<b>18</b>&#32;(5): 581–5. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097%2F01.wco.0000173142.58068.5a">
10.1097/01.wco.0000173142.58068.5a</weblink>. PMID 16155444.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="16">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Wilder-Smith E, Seet R, Lim E&#32;(2006).&#32;"Diagnosing carpal tunnel syndrome--clinical criteria and ancillary tests". <it>Nat Clin Pract Neurol</it>&#32;<b>2</b>&#32;(7): 366–74. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038%2Fncpneuro0216">
10.1038/ncpneuro0216</weblink>. PMID 16932587.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="19">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Wilson JK, Sevier TL&#32;(2003).&#32;"A review of treatment for carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Disabil Rehabil</it>&#32;<b>25</b>&#32;(3): 113–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F0963828021000007978">
10.1080/0963828021000007978</weblink>. PMID 12648000.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="18">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Jarvik J, Yuen E, Kliot M&#32;(2004).&#32;"Diagnosis of carpal tunnel syndrome: electrodiagnostic and MR imaging evaluation". <it>Neuroimaging Clin N Am</it>&#32;<b>14</b>&#32;(1): 93–102, viii. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.nic.2004.02.002">
10.1016/j.nic.2004.02.002</weblink>. PMID 15177259.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="21">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">American Academy of Neurology&#32;(2006).&#32;"Quality Standards Subcommittee: Practice parameter for carpal tunnel syndrome.". <it>Eura Medicophys</it>&#32;<b>Neurology</b>&#32;(43): 2406–2409. PMID 16557211.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="20">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gerritsen AA, de Vet HC, Scholten RJ, Bertelsmann FW, de Krom MC, Bouter LM&#32;(2002).&#32;"Splinting vs surgery in the treatment of carpal tunnel syndrome: a randomized controlled trial". <it>JAMA</it>&#32;<b>288</b>&#32;(10): 1245–51. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001%2Fjama.288.10.1245">
10.1001/jama.288.10.1245</weblink>. PMID 12215131.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="23">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Katz JN, Simmons BP&#32;(2002).&#32;"Carpal tunnel syndrome.". <it>NEJM</it>&#32;<b>346</b>: 1807–1812. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1056%2FNEJMcp013018">
10.1056/NEJMcp013018</weblink>. PMID 12050342.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="22">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons&#32;(1996).&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.guideline.gov">
Clinical Guideline on wrist pain. National Guideline clearinghouse</weblink>".</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="25">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Premoselli S, Sioli P, Grossi A, Cerri C&#32;(2006).&#32;"Neutral wrist splinting in carpal tunnel syndrome: a 3- and 6-months clinical and neurophysiologic follow-up evaluation of night-only splint therapy". <it>Eura Medicophys</it>. PMID 16557211.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="24">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Harris JS&#32;(1998).&#32;"ed. Occupational Medicine Practice Guidelines: evaluation and management of common health problems and functional recovery in workers.". <it>Beverly Farms, Mass.: OEM Press</it>. ISBN 978-1-883595-26-5.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="27">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Muller M, Tsui D, Schnurr R, Biddulph-Deisroth L, Hard J, MacDermid J&#32;(2004).&#32;"Effectiveness of hand therapy interventions in primary management of carpal tunnel syndrome: a systematic review". <it>J Hand Ther</it>&#32;<b>17</b>&#32;(2): 210–28. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1197%2Fj.jht.2004.02.009">
10.1197/j.jht.2004.02.009</weblink>. PMID 15162107.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="26">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Michlovitz SL&#32;(2004).&#32;"Conservative interventions for carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</it>&#32;<b>34</b>&#32;(10): 589–600. PMID 15552705.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="29">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Marshall S, Tardif G, Ashworth N&#32;(2007).&#32;"Local corticosteroid injection for carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Cochrane database of systematic reviews (Online)</it>&#32;(2): CD001554. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F14651858.CD001554.pub2">
10.1002/14651858.CD001554.pub2</weblink>. PMID 17443508.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="28">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Gard G&#32;(2005).&#32;"Body awareness therapy for patients with fibromyalgia and chronic pain". <it>Disabil Rehabil</it>&#32;<b>27</b>&#32;(12): 725–8. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080%2F09638280400009071">
10.1080/09638280400009071</weblink>. PMID 16012065.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="31">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Lincoln A, Vernick J, Ogaitis S, Smith G, Mitchell C, Agnew J&#32;(2000).&#32;"Interventions for the primary prevention of work-related carpal tunnel syndrome.". <it>Am J Prev Med</it>&#32;<b>18</b>&#32;(4 Suppl): 37–50. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2FS0749-3797%2800%2900140-9">
10.1016/S0749-3797(00)00140-9</weblink>. PMID 10793280.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="30">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hui AC, Wong S, Leung CH, Tong P, Mok V, Poon D, Li-Tsang CW, Wong LK, Boet R&#32;(2005).&#32;"A randomized controlled trial of surgery vs steroid injection for carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Neurology</it>&#32;<b>64</b>&#32;(12): 2074–8. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1212%2F01.WNL.0000169017.79374.93">
10.1212/01.WNL.0000169017.79374.93</weblink>. PMID 15985575.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="34">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Hui AC, Wong SM, Tang A, Mok V, Hung LK, Wong KS&#32;(2004).&#32;"Long-term outcome of carpal tunnel syndrome after conservative treatment". <it>Int J Clin Pract</it>&#32;<b>58</b>&#32;(4): 337–9. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111%2Fj.1368-5031.2004.00028.x">
10.1111/j.1368-5031.2004.00028.x</weblink>. PMID 15161116.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="35">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Kouyoumdjian JA, Morita MP, Molina AF, Zanetta DM, Sato AK, Rocha CE, Fasanella CC&#32;(2003).&#32;"Long-term outcomes of symptomatic electrodiagnosed carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Arq Neuropsiquiatr</it>&#32;<b>61</b>&#32;(2A): 194–8. PMID 12806496.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="32">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Verhagen A, Karels C, Bierma-Zeinstra S, Burdorf L, Feleus A, Dahaghin S, de Vet H, Koes B&#32;(2006).&#32;"Ergonomic and physiotherapeutic interventions for treating work-related complaints of the arm, neck or shoulder in adults.". <it>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</it>&#32;<b>3</b>: CD003471. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F14651858.CD003471.pub3">
10.1002/14651858.CD003471.pub3</weblink>. PMID 16856010.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="33">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Sato Y, Honda Y, Iwamoto J, Kanoko T, Satoh K&#32;(2005).&#32;"Amelioration by mecobalamin of subclinical carpal tunnel syndrome involving unaffected limbs in stroke patients..". <it>J Neurol Sci</it>&#32;<b>231</b>&#32;(1-2): 13–8. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.jns.2004.12.005">
10.1016/j.jns.2004.12.005</weblink>. PMID 15792815.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="38">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Quaglietta P, Corriero G&#32;(2005).&#32;"Endoscopic carpal tunnel release surgery: retrospective study of 390 consecutive cases". <it>Acta Neurochir Suppl</it>&#32;<b>92</b>: 41–5. PMID 15830966.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="39">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Park SH, Cho BH, Ryu KS, Cho BM, Oh SM, Park DS&#32;(2004).&#32;"Surgical outcome of endoscopic carpal tunnel release in 100 patients with carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Minim Invasive Neurosurg</it>&#32;<b>47</b>&#32;(5): 261–5. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1055%2Fs-2004-830075">
10.1055/s-2004-830075</weblink>. PMID 15578337.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="36">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.handuniversity.com/topics.asp?Topic_ID=16">
A patient's guide to endoscopic carpal tunnel release</weblink></entry>
<entry id="37">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Schmelzer RE, Della Rocca GJ, Caplin DA&#32;(2006).&#32;"Endoscopic carpal tunnel release: a review of 753 cases in 486 patients". <it>Plast Reconstr Surg</it>&#32;<b>117</b>&#32;(1): 177–85. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097%2F01.prs.0000194910.30455.16">
10.1097/01.prs.0000194910.30455.16</weblink>. PMID 16404264.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="42">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Thoma A, Veltri K, Haines T, Duku E&#32;(2004).&#32;"A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials comparing endoscopic and open carpal tunnel decompression". <it>Plast Reconstr Surg</it>&#32;<b>114</b>&#32;(5): 1137–46. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097%2F01.PRS.0000135850.37523.D0">
10.1097/01.PRS.0000135850.37523.D0</weblink>. PMID 15457025.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="43">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Chow JC, Hantes ME&#32;(2002).&#32;"Endoscopic carpal tunnel release: thirteen years' experience with the Chow technique". <it>J Hand Surg [Am]</it>&#32;<b>27</b>&#32;(6): 1011–8. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1053%2Fjhsu.2002.35884">
10.1053/jhsu.2002.35884</weblink>. PMID 12457351.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="40">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Scholten RJ, Gerritsen AA, Uitdehaag BM, van Geldere D, de Vet HC, Bouter LM&#32;(2004).&#32;"Surgical treatment options for carpal tunnel syndrome". <it>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</it>&#32;(4): CD003905. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F14651858.CD003905.pub2">
10.1002/14651858.CD003905.pub2</weblink>. PMID 15495070.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="41">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">McNally SA, Hales PF&#32;(2003).&#32;"Results of 1245 endoscopic carpal tunnel decompressions". <it>Hand Surg</it>&#32;<b>8</b>&#32;(1): 111–6. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1142%2FS0218810403001480">
10.1142/S0218810403001480</weblink>. PMID 12923945.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="46">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Ruch DS, Seal CN, Bliss MS, Smith BP&#32;(2002).&#32;"Carpal tunnel release: efficacy and recurrence rate after a limited incision release". <it>J South Orthop Assoc</it>&#32;<b>11</b>&#32;(3): 144–7. PMID 12539938.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="44">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Olsen KM, Knudson DV&#32;(2001).&#32;"Change in strength and dexterity after open carpal tunnel release". <it>Int J Sports Med</it>&#32;<b>22</b>&#32;(4): 301–3. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1055%2Fs-2001-13815">
10.1055/s-2001-13815</weblink>. PMID 11414675.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="45">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Katz JN, Losina E, Amick BC 3rd, Fossel AH, Bessette L, Keller RB&#32;(2001).&#32;"Predictors of outcomes of carpal tunnel release". <it>Arthritis Rheum</it>&#32;<b>44</b>&#32;(5): 1184–93. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002%2F1529-0131%28200105%2944%3A51184%3A%3AAID-ANR202%3E3.0.CO%3B2-A">
10.1002/1529-0131(200105)44:51184::AID-ANR202&amp;gt;3.0.CO;2-A</weblink>. PMID 11352253.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.oxfordclinic.org.uk/education-research/hand-wrist/OxfordClinic-CarpalTunnelRelease.php">
Carpal Tunnel Release - Information for patients</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/carpal_tunnel/detail_carpal_tunnel.htm">
Carpal Tunnel Syndrome Fact Sheet (National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke)</weblink></entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
