<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:44:26[mciao0827] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<fictional_character  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="109587565">
<header>
<title>List of characters in the Alien series</title>
<id>8995799</id>
<revision>
<id>244241725</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-09T22:44:48Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Energicko</username>
<id>7120751</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Alien (franchise) characters</category>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>Lists of television characters</category>
<category>Alien (franchise) lists</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(June 2008)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>

</p>
<p>

This article lists characters and actors in the <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/6245494.xml">
<it>Alien</it> series</link></movie>
 of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../787/26787.xml">
science fiction</link> films. The series spans four films: <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/1937693.xml">
<it>Alien''</it></link></movie>
 (1979), <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/213472.xml">
<it>Aliens''</it></link></movie>
 (1986), <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/213251.xml">
Alien 3</link></movie>
</it> (1992), and <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/213246.xml">
Alien Resurrection</link></movie>
</it> (1997). The only recurring actress in all four films is <actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/64965.xml">
Sigourney Weaver</link></actor>
, who portrays the series' central character <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/620093.xml">
Ellen Ripley</link></fictional_character>
. </p>
<p>

The film series was subsequently crossed-over with the <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/14919990.xml">
<it>Predator''</it></link></movie>
 films with the releases of <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/901421.xml">
<it>Alien vs. Predator''</it></link></movie>
 (2004) and its sequel  (2007). Together the two <it>Alien vs. Predator</it> films serve as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../007/156007.xml">
prequel</link>s to the <it>Alien</it> series. The only actor from the <it>Alien</it> films to appear in one of the prequels was <actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/639133.xml">
Lance Henriksen</link></actor>
, who had played the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/713.xml">
android</link> Bishop in <it>Aliens</it> and a man claiming to be the android's creator in <it>Alien 3</it>. Henriksen returned for <it>Alien vs. Predator</it>, in which he played Charles Bishop Weyland.</p>

<sec>
<st>
<it>Alien''</it></st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/1937693.xml">
Alien (film)</link></movie>
</it>
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ash</b></entry>
</list>

Ash (<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../137/171137.xml">
Ian Holm</link></actor>
</person>
) is the <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/1937693.xml">
Nostromo's</link></it> science officer. He administers <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../957/18957.xml">
medical</link> treatment, conducts <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../632/9127632.xml">
biological</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/25524.xml">
research</link> and is responsible for investigating any alien life forms the crew may encounter. It is at Ash's insistence that the crew investigates the mysterious signal emanating from LV-426. Ripley becomes suspicious of him when he breaks quarantine protocol by allowing Kane, Dallas, and Lambert to re-enter the <it>Nostromo</it> while the Alien facehugger is attached to Kane. Captain Dallas later informs Ripley that Ash had abruptly replaced the ship's previous science officer, whom Dallas had done six previous mission with, just as the <it>Nostromo</it> left Thedus for its return journey to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../228/9228.xml">
Earth</link>. Over Ripley's objections, Dallas entrusts Ash with all science-related decisions.</p>
<p>

After the Alien has eliminated several of the other crew members, Ripley discovers through the ship's computer "MOTHER" that Ash has been given special orders by the <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/602483.xml">
Weyland-Yutani</link></institution>
</company>
 Corporation to ensure the return of the Alien to the company's laboratories, even at the expense of the crew. When confronted by Ripley, Ash attacks her. He is hit in the head by Parker, and the force almost completely severs his head. It is at this point that Ash is revealed to be an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/713.xml">
android</link>. After suggesting that the crew will not survive the Alien's attacks and giving them his sympathies, Ash is destroyed by Parker using a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../868/70868.xml">
flamethrower</link>.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Brett</b></entry>
</list>

Brett (<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/163146.xml">
Harry Dean Stanton</link></actor>
</person>
) is an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../477/6997477.xml">
engineering technician</link> on board the Nostromo and is a good friend of Parker. He, like Parker, demands more money for his job. He is the first to encounter the fully grown Alien while searching for Jones. He becomes the second victim of the alien after it injects its inner jaw into his head. He is then dragged into an air duct. In a deleted scene shown in the 2003 Director's Cut, Ripley and Parker barely see him get carried into the air duct before he is dragged away. His blood rains down on them in a manner similar to  <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../830/74830.xml">
Jaws</link></movie>
</it>. His death clearly saddened Parker. Also in the 2003 Director's Cut, Ripley enters a storage room which the Alien has transformed into its lair. There she finds Dallas and Brett, the first 2 victims of the Alien aboard the Nostromo (and whose bodies had not been found). Dallas begs Ripley to kill him, as he is mutating into an Alien egg, or possibly being coccooned for mutation into an Alien drone. Brett, at a later stage of this metamorphis, has been almost completely transformed into an Alien egg.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Dallas</b></entry>
</list>

Dallas (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../414/719414.xml">
Tom Skerritt</link></actor>
) is the laid-back captain of the <it>Nostromo</it>; he has sole access to Mother, the on-board computer. He was attacked by the Alien in the air duct tunnels trying to blow the alien out of the ship into outer space through the airlock. In the 2003 Director's Cut, he is later found by Ripley in the Alien's lair, begging to be killed and is. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Kane</b></entry>
</list>

Thomas Kane (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../390/164390.xml">
John Hurt</link></actor>
) serves as executive officer aboard the <it>Nostromo</it>. During his investigation of the derelict space ship, an unknown life-form (later known as an Ovomorph, or face-hugger) attaches itself to his face and (unknown to him and to the crew) impregnates him with an alien creature. Kane remains unconscious while the creature is attached. He regains consciousness after the attached creature dies and falls off. However, the Alien unexpectedly bursts through his chest and kills him during the crew's dinner.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Lambert</b></entry>
</list>

Lambert (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/1360329.xml">
Veronica Cartwright</link></actor>
) is the only other female on the ship besides Ripley; she serves as navigator and pilots the <it>Nostromo</it>. She resents Ripley for her decision to leave Kane, Dallas and herself outside of the ship, when the facehugger was attached to Kane. She expressed a wish to leave the ship when crew members started getting killed off by the Alien. It is during the preparation to leave the Nostromo that, frozen in horror, she witnesses Parker's death and is then killed herself.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Parker</b></entry>
</list>

Parker (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../464/589464.xml">
Yaphet Kotto</link></actor>
) works as the chief engineer aboard the ship, with Brett as his assistant. Pushy and acerbic, he is a constant complainer who demands more money for investigating the alien transmission. He is occasionally at odds with Ripley over getting paid, however as the crisis unfolds he respects the plans that she creates to keep them safe. When the Alien matured, he grew extremely distressed at the deaths of Brett and Dallas. He and Lambert save Ripley from Ash, and he personally incinerates the decapitated Ash after interrogation. He dies when he is unable to attack the Alien with his flamethrower due to Lambert being in the way. He tries to physically assault the Alien but is almost instantly overpowered. The Alien then impales his head, killing him instantly.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ripley</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/620093.xml">
Ellen Ripley</link></fictional_character>
</it>
</indent>
Ellen Ripley (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/64965.xml">
Sigourney Weaver</link></actor>
) serves as a warrant officer aboard the <it>Nostromo</it>. She has a strong distrust of her fellow crew mate Ash after he disobeys her order not to let the infected Kane back on the ship. Eventually she becomes the only survivor of the crew's encounter with the alien.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>The Alien</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <hypothetical_creature wordnetid="109484313" confidence="0.8">
<monster wordnetid="109491966" confidence="0.8">
<extraterrestrial_being wordnetid="109484465" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<race wordnetid="107472657" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/612467.xml">
Alien (Alien franchise)</link></psychological_feature>
</race>
</contest>
</imaginary_being>
</social_event>
</fictional_character>
</event>
</extraterrestrial_being>
</monster>
</hypothetical_creature>
</it>
</indent>
The Alien (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/1937693.xml">
Bolaji Badejo</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
) was a parasite that erupted from Kane's body after gestating inside his chest. It grew rapidly, shedding its skin as it did so. It proceeded to kill off the remaining crew members of the Nostromo one by one. The Alien was eventually killed when Ripley blew it into the vacuum of space and propelled it away from the Narcissus using the craft's engines.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<it>Aliens''</it></st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/213472.xml">
Aliens (film)</link></movie>
</it>
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Apone</b></entry>
</list>

Sergeant First Class Apone (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../420/1307420.xml">
Al Matthews</link></actor>
) was with the squad that went to investigate <planet wordnetid="109394007" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/1164250.xml">
LV-426</link></planet>
. Apone was far more liked and respected than Lieutenant Gorman. During the first incursion into the atmospheric processor, he enforced <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Gorman%22])">
Gorman's</link></b> orders not to use pulse rifle and smartgun ammunition. He also laughed and asked Ripley to put the storage container in "Bay 12, please".  Shortly after finding a still-alive cocooned colonist whose chest bursts to reveal an alien, Apone grabbed a flamethrower from Frost to incinerate it. Aliens ambushed the marines shortly after, and in the confusion while trying to communicate with his squad, he is grabbed by an alien. Apone's importance to the squad is shown in this scene, as the squad loses unit cohesion shortly after his capture, and Gorman freezes up. Hudson later points out that the readouts on the APC show he was not killed in the attack; thus he was presumably impregnated by an alien and died when the atmosphere processor exploded or possibly from an alien fully gestating in his body.</p>


<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Bishop</b></entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/623280.xml">
Bishop (Alien)</link></it>
</indent>
Bishop (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../133/639133.xml">
Lance Henriksen</link></actor>
) was the android assigned to the <it>Sulaco</it>, primarily responsible for planetary maneuvering. Unlike Ash, he was loyal to his seniors, colleagues and especially Ripley. Although Bishop tried to be friendly to Ripley, she didn't trust him until he had proven himself. He pointed out to them the atmospheric processor's emergency venting and saved them by bringing down the second dropship. After returning to the <it>Sulaco</it>, he was ripped apart by the Alien queen but his upper half was still functional and he managed to save Newt from being sucked into the airlock. He was put into hypersleep for the journey home.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Burke</b></entry>
</list>

Carter Burke (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/340663.xml">
Paul Reiser</link></actor>
) was a corporate executive who often comforted Ripley and became her friend while she was at Gateway Station. After revealing that Ripley had been frozen for 57 years, and that her daughter had since deceased, he exhibits some sensitivity and condolence towards a heartbroken Ripley.
After learning of the derelict ship from Ripley, he agrees to help regain her flight license in return for her returning to LV-426 to investigate. He accompanied the squad aboard <it>Sulaco</it>, presumably to safeguard the company's investment in the terraforming colony.  Burke sides with her against Gorman when she points out that the marines' weapons could rupture the station's cooling system, explaining that the station is basically a big fusion reactor, and they could trigger a thermal nuclear explosion. However, when Ripley suggests they take off and nuke the site from orbit, Burke says he cannot authorize that kind action, and the site has a substantial dollar value attached to it. He also reasons, against Ripley and Vasquez that the Aliens are an important species and they don't have the right to exterminate them. Ripley then points out the operation is under military jurisdiction and Hicks is next in chain of command (Gorman is unconscious at this point). Burke then reasons that Hicks cannot make that kind of decision as the site is a multi-million dollar installation. Hicks then radios Ferro and orders immediate evacuation, planning to nuke the planet from orbit.</p>
<p>

Burke would betray Ripley and the Marines, as a captured alien would have great potential for research and bioweapons, which would earn him a lucrative promotion- he specifically targets Ripley for this, after she discovers his intention. He planned to smuggle the alien past quarantine through Ripley and Newt. He attempts to get them impregnated by locking them in a room with a pair of facehuggers; he later turns off the room's security camera. He would then sabotage the cryochambers in order to kill the marines, but his plan was foiled after Ripley triggered the smoke detector and the Marines rescued her. She then exposed Burke.</p>
<p>

The Marines planned to kill Burke after they realized that the aliens were approaching the medlabs. In the confusion, Burke escapes and seals himself off from the pursuing marines. An alien then attacks him from behind. While he is presumed dead, there was a cut scene where Ripley sees him in the hive and he tells her that he can feel the alien moving and she gives him a grenade to cut his anguish short.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Crowe</b></entry>
</list>

Private Crowe (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../871/1427871.xml">
Tip Tipping</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
) is one of the first marines killed when the platoon is attacked in the alien hive. He dies when the ammo Frost was carrying explodes and he was hurled into a wall, breaking his neck. He was barely seen in the entire movie and he was given one line of dialog.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Dietrich</b></entry>
</list>

Corporal Dietrich (<link>
Cynthia Dale Scott</link>) was the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../777/2233777.xml">
corpsman</link> who gave Newt an examination after they found her. Dietrich later became the first victim of the Aliens when her Marine squad entered the hive (atmosphere processing station). When grappled by an alien, she accidentally used her flamethrower in panic, killing Frost and igniting the bag of ammunition he was wearing. It was presumed that she became cocooned by the Aliens to be impregnated by a facehugger and killed by the atmosphere processing station's explosion or possibly from an alien fully gestating in her body.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Drake</b></entry>
</list>

Private Drake (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../732/1249732.xml">
Mark Rolston</link></actor>
) was the smartgunning partner of Vasquez. The two marines shared a special bond. While covering the marines' evacuation to the APC, he was killed during the first encounter with the aliens, when Vasquez shot an Alien beside him, and he was covered in its acidic blood.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ferro</b></entry>
</list>

Corporal Ferro (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../109/6028109.xml">
Colette Hiller</link></actor>
) was the dropship pilot, staying with the craft during the alien ambush. When Corporal Hicks ordered an evacuation from the planet, Ferro was killed in midair by an alien that had sneaked onto the dropship, after she called for Private Spunkmeyer who was already killed by the same alien. Her death is not shown but there is a large amount of blood sprayed on the windshield of the dropship before it hits the ground.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Frost</b></entry>
</list>

Private Frost (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../795/3163795.xml">
Ricco Ross</link></actor>
) was a trooper in the <it>Sulaco</it> unit that investigated LV-426, and acted throughout the movie as a jokester. Frost was the driver of the unit's APC. He seemed to have a good friendship with some of the marines including Hicks and Hudson. During their investigation of the Alien Hive, Frost was given the task of carrying the platoon's ammunition when they entered the hive under the nuclear reactor. He was killed when Corporal Dietrich accidentally triggered her flamethrower and he fell over a rail.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Gorman</b></entry>
</list>

Lieutenant Gorman (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../911/1427911.xml">
William Hope</link></actor>
) led the ill-fated mission to LV-426 until the first encounter with the aliens. As he was recruited by Burke (likely as an unwilling pawn, as Burke's secret agenda is to retrieve an alien sample) the marines do not take kindly to Gorman (Hicks complaints that their Lieutenant is too good to eat with his men). He was inexperienced, having gone through 38 simulated drops, but only one previous combat drop. He is also slow to understand situations and often needs things explained to him. When Ripley points out that he's sending his men into combat under the colony's heat-exchanger, he needs Burke to explain to him in simple language what happens if the cooling system of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/55017.xml">
fusion reactor</link> is damaged. Gorman provided command and support to the marines when they first secured the abandoned colony, and when they explored the atmospheric processor. When the aliens sprung their ambush, there was confusion and disarray among the marines who were no longer responding to Gorman's order, causing him to lose his cool. In Ripley's subsequent rescue attempt, Gorman was knocked unconscious by falling objects. Vasquez blames Gorman for Drake's death and tries to strike him, being held back by the other marines.</p>
<p>

Gorman later regains consciousness, having deferred to Cpl. Hicks as they planned their defense of the colony. Gorman assisted the marines in killing the face-huggers attacking Ripley and Newt. When <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Vasquez%22])">
Vasquez</link></b> was injured during their escape, he volunteered to go back and get her out. Realizing that they are trapped by aliens, he assisted her in committing a double-suicide/self-sacrifice by setting off one of his grenades, earning him the respect of Vasquez, despite her last words to him-"You always were an asshole, Gorman."  This is however almost affectionate, meaning that Gorman could simply never do anything right (in this case, even in trying to do something good).</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Hicks</b></entry>
</list>

Corporal Dwayne Hicks (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../995/468995.xml">
Michael Biehn</link></actor>
) was one of the Colonial Marines who took charge when the squad's Sergeant Apone was taken alive by the Aliens and commanding officer Lt. Gorman was knocked out. He was later wounded after a burst of acid on an alien encounter began to burn through his armor.</p>
<p>

While not comfortable taking over the role as squad leader, his demeanor, unlike the machismo bravado of other squad members showed a thoughtful intelligence. Sincere and impartial, he was open to any suggestions as to how to defeat the Alien invasion. During the holdout after surviving the first alien encounter, it becomes clear that a bond of mutual respect and affection(perhaps something stronger) developed with Ripley  (as seen demonstrating to her the operation of the pulse rifle). He is among the four remaining survivors in Aliens. 
Hicks is killed at the beginning of <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/213251.xml">
Alien 3</link></movie>
</it> after being impaled by a broken support brace during hypersleep.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Hudson</b></entry>
</list>

Private William Hudson (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../960/303960.xml">
Bill Paxton</link></actor>
) was the squad's jokester and computer tech expert. He seemed arrogant and overconfident of his squad's firepower and abilities. However, he soon cracked under large amounts of stress after most of his Marine squad were taken during the Alien attack in the hive. Later on, he was able to pull himself together and regain his composure. Like Vasquez, Private Hudson bravely fought to the end in the colony's operation room where Ripley and the rest of the few remaining Marines made their last stand. At the last minute, he was pulled through a floor grating by an Alien while he was providing cover for Ripley, Newt and the rest of his fellow Marines as they escaped. It was presumed he was taken to the hive to be cocooned and impregnated in the nest which was later destroyed by the nuclear explosion.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Newt</b></entry>
</list>

Rebecca "Newt" Jorden (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<terror wordnetid="110702483" confidence="0.8">
<imp wordnetid="110200047" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<child wordnetid="109917593" confidence="0.8">
<schoolteacher wordnetid="110560352" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<teacher wordnetid="110694258" confidence="0.8">
<juvenile wordnetid="109622049" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../537/1323537.xml">
Carrie Henn</link></entertainer>
</juvenile>
</teacher>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</schoolteacher>
</child>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</actor>
</imp>
</terror>
</person>
</physical_entity>
) was the only survivor amongst the colonists of LV-426. She had been living in the air ducts within the compound and was discovered by the marines after they picked her up on the motion tracker. Newt bonded rather quickly with the marines and it was her strength of mind, for somebody so young, that helped to bring Hudson back from the brink of despair.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ripley</b></entry>
</list>

Ellen Ripley (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/64965.xml">
Sigourney Weaver</link></actor>
) goes with the Marines to LV-426 as a civilian advisor, having encountered the aliens previously.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Spunkmeyer</b></entry>
</list>

Private Spunkmeyer (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../155/6028155.xml">
Daniel Kash</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
) was the dropship chief and weapons officer. He didn't go with the other soldiers to the hive, but stayed with Ferro at the dropship. He is presumed to be killed shortly after takeoff, by an Alien that had snuck aboard the dropship.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Van Leuwen</b></entry>
</list>

Van Leuwen (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../089/3418089.xml">
Paul Maxwell</link></actor>
) was the chairman of the Interstellar Commerce Commission board that reviewed Ripley's case concerning the destruction of the Nostromo in Alien. He dismissed Ripleys's claims of a hostile organism and then decided to have her flight license revoked, as well as putting her through months of medical evaluations.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Vasquez</b></entry>
</list>

Private Jenette Vasquez (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../356/1312356.xml">
Jenette Goldstein</link></actor>
) was a smartgunner on the <it>Sulaco</it>, partnered with <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Drake%22])">
Drake</link></b>. Vasquez survived the hive and helped seal off the complex from the aliens. She fought, together with Drake, and killed many aliens during the attack. She was injured when acidic blood from an alien that was shot at point blank range landed on her leg disabling her. <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Gorman%22])">
Gorman</link></b> and Vasquez together put their hands on a live grenade to avoid being taken by the aliens. Though the character is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../522/18522.xml">
Latina</link>, the actress who plays her is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../913/15913.xml">
Jewish</link>. Scholar <sovereign wordnetid="110628644" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<representative wordnetid="110522035" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<king wordnetid="110231515" confidence="0.8">
<head_of_state wordnetid="110164747" confidence="0.8">
<ruler wordnetid="110541229" confidence="0.8">
<negotiator wordnetid="110351874" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../168/2158168.xml">
Judith Halberstam</link></negotiator>
</ruler>
</head_of_state>
</king>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</representative>
</physical_entity>
</sovereign>
, in her book titled <it>Female Masculinity</it>, wrote that the character is a strong example of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/11096.xml">
female</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../058/240058.xml">
masculinity</link> in film. The <it>Aliens: Colonial Marines</it> comic book limited series features her younger sister (<it>Carmen Vasquez</it>), also a Marine.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Wierzbowski</b></entry>
</list>

Private Wierzbowski (<link>
Trevor Steedman</link>) is barely seen at all in the film. He is injured when the ammunition bag, which had been carried by Frost, detonates and is then attacked and either killed or taken by an Alien off-screen. It's presumed he died shortly after since Hudson did not mention his vital signs when he noticed Apone's and Ditrich's.  He was armed with a flamethrower.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Mary</b></entry>
</list>

Mary is one of the cocooned colonists whom the Marine squad discover alive in the hive. She pleads with the Marines to kill her, as Corporal Dietrich tries to comfort her. She subsequently dies when a chestburster erupts from her and her body was torched by Apone.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Russ Jorden</b></entry>
</list>

Russ Jorden (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../212/17157212.xml">
Jay Benedict</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
) is Newt's father, one of the "wildcatters" whom Operating Manager Al Simpson sends beyond the colony to search for a derelict ship (<animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/2396423.xml">
Space Jockey</link></animal>
’s spacecraft ) on vague orders of Carter Burke back on Earth. Russ Jorden and his wife went inside the <animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/2396423.xml">
Space Jockey</link></animal>
’s derelict spacecraft to investigate, and discovered the ancient Alien egg nest, where he was then implanted by a facehugger. He is the second known human to be implanted by a face hugger since Nostromo crewmember Kane's discovery of the Alien egg nest and subsequent facehugger implantation 57 years earlier.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ann Jorden</b></entry>
</list>

Ann Jorden (<link>
Holly de Jong</link>) is Newt's mother. She accompanied her husband inside the discovered Space Jockey's derelict ship and presumed to have discovered the ancient Alien egg nest inside the ship. She later drags her husband's body (who was implanted by a facehugger) back to the family's tractor to radio for help from the colony.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Tim Jorden</b></entry>
</list>

Tim Jorden (<link>
Christopher Henn</link>) is Newt's brother. He keeps his little sister company in the family's tractor as their parents investigate inside the <animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/2396423.xml">
Space Jockey</link></animal>
’s ship. Tim is the only person who calls Newt by her real name, Rebecca.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>The Alien Queen</b></entry>
</list>

The Queen Alien is the chief antagonist of <it>Aliens</it>. The Queen is the mother and leader of the Aliens on LV-426. The Queen lived in a large chamber with hundreds of eggs and several guards. It was killed by Ripley when it was blasted out of the airlock of the <it>Sulaco</it> and into the vacuum of space.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<it>Alien 3''</it></st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/213251.xml">
Alien 3</link></movie>
</it>
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Francis Aaron</b></entry>
</list>

Francis Aaron (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../411/2235411.xml">
Ralph Brown</link></actor>
) is Superintendent Andrews' assistant and serves as the prison guard. He is not a religious man because he believes that so long as he has a job he does not need faith (although he ironically has lots of faith in Weyland-Yutani). At his arrival, several prisoners catch a glance at his personal file, discovering his IQ is only 85, which they began using as a nickname for him. Aaron will often respond by telling whoever said it to not do so again, but this is always ignored. Aaron has a very strong trust in Weyland-Yutani, his employer. He usually acts as Andrews' parrot, echoing his opinions without stating any of his own. After Andrews died, Aaron attempts to take charge but the prisoners promptly refuse to allow him to do so. Ripley later tries to convince him several times that they do not care about him or any other employee, and in fact care more about capturing the two Aliens. He and Morse often got into heated arguments, especially after Morse let Golic out, who in turn allowed the alien to escape from the toxic waste dump they had contained it in. When Ripley tells him to send the rescue ship away, he sternly refuses, explaining that he wants to leave and see his wife and children again. Aaron eventually assists Ripley with the bio-scan she performs on herself aboard the crashed EEV and is one of the few people to know she is subject to Alien gestation.</p>
<p>

After the scan is performed, Wayland-Yutani immediately sends a message to the prison stating that the rescue ship will arrive in a matter of hours to pick her up. At this point Aaron slowly arrives to a conclusion (that Weyland-Yutani does not care about him or the prisoners and only cares about the alien) that he exemplifies near the end of the film. When the prisoners decide to lure the alien into the lead, Aaron calls them crazy and locks himself into his office. It is apparent that while in his office he continued to think about the recent events and loses most, if not all, of his faith in Weyland-Yutani. When Michael Bishop lands with his team and tries to convince Ripley to leave with him, Aaron strikes Bishop with a large metal rod, nearly ripping his ear off. One of the soldiers accompanying Bishop immediately pushes Aaron out into the open and shoots him several times in the back. Aaron falls from a great height, landing on his back. He takes one last breath before dying with a look of disbelief on his face.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Harold Andrews</b></entry>
</list>

Superintendent Harold Andrews (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../736/594736.xml">
Brian Glover</link></actor>
) is the warden of Fury 161. He often begins his addresses to the prisoners with the line "this is Rumor Control, here are the facts...". Andrews often mocked the prisoners behind their backs, calling them "Dillon's God Squad". He becomes increasingly annoyed with Ripley as she leaves the infirmary, and also takes this frustration out on Clemens, who he has never trusted. When Murphy is killed in the ventilation fan, Andrews further places blame on Ripley, suggesting that Murphy was concentrating more on her than he was on his work. When Golic returns from the scene of Boggs' and Rains' death covered in blood, Andrews believes that the "simple bastard" has murdered them. He does not believe Ripley's story concerning the Alien and her past involvement with the creature. He also tells Ripley that there are no weapons of any kind available to fend off her creature. Andrews quarantines Ripley to the infirmary having heard her story once he knows that Weyland-Yutani find her to be a high priority. Andrews attempts to organize a search party for Boggs and Rains in the mess hall when Ripley bursts in screaming after Clemens' death in the infirmary. Andrews becomes increasingly frustrated with her and orders Aaron to escort her back to the infirmary as not to cause a panic. The Alien then reaches down from an overhead air duct and pulls Andrews into the ceiling. A shower of blood rains down from the air duct, and the prisoners run amok in a panic. </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Jonathan Clemens</b></entry>
</list>

Jonathan Clemens (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../192/2060192.xml">
Charles Dance</link></actor>
) was the medical doctor of Fury 161. When Ripley crashes into the oil sea, he nurses her back to health and begins showing her around. He even starts a personal relationship with her, much to the annoyance of Andrews. 
Clemens performs the autopsy on Newt as Ripley requested. He asks what they are looking for in the body of a girl who had obviously drowned, and Ripley tells him that they are investigating a possible case of cholera. Clemens firmly responds by stating that there hasn't been a case of cholera reported for 200 years. He knows that Ripley is hiding something from him, and to show that he would not lie to her, he explains why he has a bar code on the back of his head. When Clemens was on a residency, he got drunk after a long shift. The same night, there was a boiler explosion, causing forty injuries. Clemens was called back and, by prescribing the wrong pain killer dosage, was responsible for the deaths of 11 men. He was sentenced to Fiorina 161 and served his time, but chose to stay behind with the other inmates after they refused to leave. When Clemens ends his story, Ripley again lies about what has been going on around the prison. As Clemens injects her with a syrum, the Alien lowers itself down behind him and lashes out through the curtains. After a very brief struggle, the Alien releases its inner jaw into Clemens' skull. Ripley and the mentally unstable Golic, strapped down in a bed, are the only witnesses.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Dillon</b></entry>
</list>

Lenard Dillon (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../445/1779445.xml">
Charles S. Dutton</link></actor>
) is what could be described as the religious preacher of Fury 161 and the leader of the prisoners. He not only leads them in prayer but stirs them to action in rousing speeches. He had a history as a murderer and rapist of women, but like the remaining prisoners, he somehow managed to find God while incarcerated. He acts as an unofficial religious consultant for the other inmates and tries to keep the peace between them, attempting to appease Rains and Boggs's misgivings over Golic, and violently beating the men who attempt to rape Ripley. </p>
<p>

Dillon was one of the only prisoners who spoke to Ripley shortly after her arrival, asking her if she had any faith and reassuring her that the prisoners had faith enough to accept and tolerate anyone. He wrote an eloquent prayer which he used for the eulogy of the funeral for Newt and Hicks, which briefly caused Ripley to weep. He later reprimands Boggs and Rains for their highly negative opinion on Golic, which they display openly. When prisoners try to rape Ripley, Dillon intervenes and beats them severely with a crowbar. After the Alien kills Andrews, Dillon leads a prayer stating that "the apocalypse" is upon the prisoners. During the attempt to trap the Alien in the toxic waste dump he looks most towards the safety of the prisoners and afterward leads a sermon that acts as an ode to the prisoners who died to ensure their victory. </p>
<p>

After Golic kills Arthur and lets the Alien out, Dillon displays passionate anger towards Aaron and Morse, who are violently bickering. He orders Morse to get all the remaining prisoners together so they can formulate a new plan. Dillon was one of the few people that Ripley informed about the Alien embryo within her. He was disgusted with Ripley after she asked him to kill her and the alien that was inside of her. He does not comply, promising that he will sort her out in a "quick, easy, and painless" fashion once the Alien that is slaughtering the inmates is destroyed. Ripley explains to him that the Alien, if it escapes, will destroy all life in the universe. Dillon responds apathetically, stating that the prisoners have (or had) their own separate world on Fury 161. Shortly afterward, he rallies the prisoners together to trap the Alien in the foundry and kill it by pouring hot lead on it. The strategy to draw the Alien into the mould quickly falls apart though, and he is forced to improvise a new while as the Alien attacks. After the piston is activated, he nobly faces the Alien, enticing it to attack him to keep it in the lead mould. When Ripley reminds him of their pact and begs her to kill him, he only replies "God will take care of you now".  He was eventually killed by the Alien while fighting it in the lead mold, hoping to stall it long enough for Ripley to pour the lead. He was killed by the beast moments before the area was filled with molten lead.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Arthur</b></entry>
</list>

Arthur is a huge inmate of what seems to be Jamaican descent. He is first seen in the group of prisoners who attempt to rape Ripley but are stopped when Dillon intervenes. He is present when Andrews gives his second 'Rumor Control' speech in the mess hall and is a witness of his death. Arthur is seen again later when the group decide who is in charge. When the prisoners prepare to capture the Alien, Arthur and Troy are seen checking flashlight batteries briefly, and Troy complains about the difficulty of the job. After the explosion, Arthur is in a search party for surviving prisoners, though they find none. He is then put on a guard duty to watch the door of the waste tank. Back in the infirmary, Morse releases Golic from his strait jacket after he begs him to do so. While Arthur is on duty, Golic approaches the waste tank. Arthur tells the insanely babbling criminal to get lost, but Golic quickly slits his throat with a straight razor. Arthur looks at Golic in stunned disbelief, and quickly bleeds to death from the injury while Golic screams a panicked, maniacal apology.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Michael Bishop</b></entry>
</list>

The designer of the android Bishop. Michael is a scientist in the employ of the Wayland-Yutani corporation. Ripley meets him in the furnace and first assumes that he is a droid sent by the company, the same model as Bishop, but he reveals who he really is. He also tells her that he and his medical team will extract the alien queen inside her and destroy it. Ripley knows that he is a liar and backs away towards the furnace. He lets his cover slip and pleads that it is a magnificent specimen and that he <it>must</it> have it. She willingly sacrifices herself by free falling into the giant lead smelter, much to his despair.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Boggs</b></entry>
</list>

Edward Boggs (Leon Herbert) is a large inmate who is assigned to accompany Rains and Golic on a routine foraging mission through the tunnels of the prison complex on Fiorina 161. He and Rains are both very vocal about not minding the dark tunnels, but they do firmly state that they feel uncomfortable around Golic, stating that he is crazy and smells bad. Dillon is the one to remind them that he is now one of the brothers as well. Boggs and Rains have no choice but to go with Golic. As the three are measuring the size of a large compartment, the candles they have lit to see in the dark start blowing out. A perplexed Rains goes back to light them again, but he doesn't come back. Boggs and Golic venture out to see what is happening after hearing his screams, though they arrive too late. The two of them find the bloody body and Boggs is subsequently lifted to the ceiling and bitten in the cranium by the Alien. His blood sprays all over Golic's face, who screams in terror and runs down the hallways.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>David</b></entry>
</list>

David (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/181418.xml">
Pete Postlethwaite</link></actor>
) is an older, more educated inmate who knew about the hazardous materials stored in the facility's toxic waste dump. He also explains to Ripley why they call Aaron "85." He was killed by the Alien during the "bait and chase" plan to trap it in the furnace. While he was looking through the small window of a door he had managed to close between him and the creature, he thought he was safe. Unbeknown to David, the Alien found another way into the corridor and snuck up behind him.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Eric</b></entry>
</list>

Eric (Niall Buggy) is the jittery inmate who serves as the cook on Fiorina. He is killed by the Alien during the plan to trap it in the furnace. He uses a meat cleaver as a weapon against the monster, and his body is found by Ripley.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Frank</b></entry>
</list>

Frank (Carl Chase) has served many years in his life sentence and is a good friend of Murphy. It is hinted that he was sentenced to Fiorina for killing women, as he states that the only way to have a good relationship is to treat women abusively. He is killed by the alien when it grabs him. As a result, he drops a paintbrush full of quinitricetyline, which in turn causes a massive explosion that kills several.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Junior</b></entry>
</list>

Junior (AKA Ted Gillas) is a younger and more silent prisoner, sentenced for aggressive sexual crimes. He is easily recognizable via the teardrop tattoo he has below his right eye and the welding goggles he often wears. He led a group of prisoners who attempted to rape Ripley and in turn was assaulted by Dillon for doing so. He later sacrifices himself during the quinitricetyline accident to allow Ripley and the remaining prisoners escape. He succeeds in helping them in their plan, which was to trap the alien in the toxic waste dump. After briefly looking at Ripley, who is trying to distract the alien so he can escape, Junior decides to sacrifice himself and reach redemption for his rape attempt. He runs inside the waste dump, the alien follows, and the door is closed behind them. He is heard screaming shortly afterwards.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Golic</b></entry>
</list>

Walter Golic (<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../330/92330.xml">
Paul McGann</link></actor>
</person>
) was found guilty of 32 accounts of murder and dismemberment and 13 accounts of arson. It is implied that Golic went insane at one point when he recalls that as a young man women were very attracted to him before he abruptly stops speaking and whispers "for a while" in a remorseful tone. He is something of an outcast in the prison. Although he has friends in the prison (including Morse), many prisoners dislike him, believing him to still be insane. He goes out on trips to forage supplies from abandoned areas of the prison with Boggs and Rains, who particularly dislike him. The only survivor of the alien's attack in the tunnel, where Boggs and Rains were, in his words, "slaughtered like pigs!" He is then strapped down to one of the beds in the infirmary, being closely watched by Clemens and Ripley due to the others' belief that he is mentally ill. Andrews reveals shortly after his isolation that Golic was imprisoned for crimes that were particularly brutal, even when compared to the crimes of other prisoners there. He refers to the alien as "The Dragon." In the medical ward he tells Ripley briefly about how he used to be more normal when he was younger, before he committed his brutal crimes (see above). He utters an almost-mute "magnificent" after seeing Clemens killed by the Alien. The fate of Golic in the director's cut of Alien 3 is unknown, as he is not seen to meet his demise at the hands of the Alien on screen.</p>
<p>

In the theatrical cut, after the alien kills Clemens and deems Ripley unfit to kill (as she was carrying a queen embryo at the time), it is depicted that the Alien drags Golic into the ventilation shaft along with it. It is assumed the creature kills him up there.</p>
<p>

In the assembly cut, Golic persuades Morse to unstrap him in the medical ward after hearing that the Alien has been trapped. He then knocks Morse out, kills Arthur, who is guarding the waste tank containing the trapped alien, and is killed himself after he releases it while worshipping it and asking it what he should do next. He believes that the alien is a holy creature, and frequently talks to it via what seems to be telepathy. It is unknown if the alien was actually speaking to him or he was imagining this as a result of his condition.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Gregor</b></entry>
</list>

Gregor (Peter Guinness) was one of the prisoners who assisted Junior in the attempted rape of Ripley at the junkyard. When Dillon makes it to the scene and attacks Junior, it is evident that Gregor was severely beaten as well. The Assembly Cut shows him to be badly burned in the fire and thus explains the white bandaging he wears for the second half of the film. After the failed attempt to trap the alien in the toxic waste dump, Gregor joins the rest of the inmates and uses himself as bait to lure the Alien into the lead mold. As he runs down a hall away from the Alien, he has a head on collision with Morse and the two fall to the floor. They both stand up and, assuming that the other prisoner is the alien, attempt to attack each other before recognizing each other. Finding some humor in this situation, the two of them share a lighthearted moment, laughing and fooling around. As the two giggle at their predicament, the creature charges up from behind Morse and bites Gregor in the neck.</p>
<p>

In the assembly cut, Gregor's character is expanded upon and it is revealed that he is one of the only <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/54359.xml">
agnostic</link> prisoners.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Jude</b></entry>
</list>

Jude (Vincenzo Nicoli) appears to be of central European descent, possibly Slovak. He was sentenced to life imprisonment for murder in the first degree without a weapon. When the prisoners band together to trap the Alien in lead, Jude carries a pair of scissors to use as a weapon against the beast. In one of the film's only scenes of comic relief, he is reprimanded by Morse for carrying them the wrong way. As more and more inmates are killed off, Jude eventually is chased towards the end of a corridor where Dillon is waiting for him. Dillon calls for Jude to run faster, but the Alien catches up quickly. Jude does reach Dillon, but is pulled back into the corridor before the door can finish closing and is gored by the Alien while screaming for help.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Kevin</b></entry>
</list>

Kevin (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../141/14068141.xml">
Phil Davis</link></actor>
) is a jittery and nervous inmate, almost violently so. He first appears as the inmate who assists Clemens with the autopsy of Newt that Ripley requests early in the film (in the theatrical cut). He alerts Clemens to the odd searches Ripley is performing on the body. He later argues with David about the alien and its capabilities shortly after they witness it killing Andrews. Later on, Kevin is one of the prisoners acting as bait to lead the Alien into the lead mold. After he closes a door, cutting himself off from the creature in the corridors, he warns everyone that the alien is very "pissed off." When the Alien eventually catches him, it pulls him onto the ceiling where Dillon eventually finds him and pulls him down. Dillon and Ripley drag him towards the furnace, but Kevin soon bleeds to death on the floor of the piston chamber. After he dies, Ripley suggests they leave the body, but the Alien quickly returns, takes the body, and causes the piston to start too early.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Morse</b></entry>
</list>

Robert Morse (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../729/5903729.xml">
Danny Webb</link></actor>
) is one of the smaller prisoners of Fiorina 161 and is one of the only friends of Golic. Morse can be physically distinguished by his many gold teeth. He is loud, argumentative, and cynical. At first, he blames Ripley for bringing the alien to the planet. After Andrews's death he and Aaron often got into heated arguments. When guarding Golic after trapping the Alien, Golic (now insane) convinces Morse to let him loose. Golic knocks Morse out and goes to release the Alien, killing himself and Arthur in the process. After Dillon's death, Morse helps Ripley get to the top of furnace so that she may throw herself into it, killing herself and the queen. While helping her, he is shot in the leg by a Weyland-Yutani soldier. He is the only resident of Fury 161 to survive. At the end of the film he is seen being led away by <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/602483.xml">
Weyland-Yutani</link></institution>
</company>
 personnel, and smiles as he realizes his success. He is vocal about his initial skepticism of trying to survive the encounter with the Alien, stating that although it killed many of his friends he wants to wait for Weyland-Yutani firepower to show up- in the end, however, he agrees to Ripley's course of action. According to the novelization of Alien: Resurrection, it is likely he wrote about his experiences, invoking the android Call to take action.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Murphy</b></entry>
</list>

Thomas Murphy (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/4260377.xml">
Christopher Fairbank</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
) is a prisoner who is younger than most of the prisoners on Fiorina. He spent most of his early life on the run from the law. A conversation between Frank and Murphy in the assembly cut implies that he has been sentenced to prison for sexual deviance and probably abuse as well. He appears to have a shorter prison sentence than most and often volunteers to help in efforts (like finding survivors from the EEV) in attempts to shave a few months off of his sentence. He is the first person killed by the Alien. He is first introduced in the theatrical cut searching the EEV for survivors with his dog, and later mourns over it after the alien emerges from it (though he thinks a human did it). Later, he is seen cleaning the giant air ducts of the prison. He steps on the aliens shed skin and is clearly disgusted by his find. He hears noises coming from a hole in the wall, and goes to investigate, believing it to be his dog, Spike. He soon realizes it is not his pet pooch but a juvenile Alien. Before he can pull his head out of the hole, the alien spits acid into his face. He stammers backwards in agony and accidentally tumbles into a large spinning fan, killing him "instantaneously". In the theatrical cut, Murphy's dog Spike is the victim of the <link>
facehugger</link>, resulting in an Alien with more mammalian features. However, in the assembly cut of Alien³, the dog was not the creature attacked and impregnated. </p>
<p>

The song Murphy sings while cleaning the vent shafts is <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<medium wordnetid="106254669" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../015/926015.xml">
In the Year 2525</link></medium>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
 by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/386003.xml">
Zager &amp; Evans</link>.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Rains</b></entry>
</list>

Rains (Christopher John Fields) is one of the first inmates to see Clemens bring Ripley back inside from the beach where he discovers her. He vocalizes his distaste for Golic with Boggs when they are assigned to go on a routine foraging expedition in the tunnels, but is reprimanded by Dillon for his attitude. As the three of them measure the size of a pitch black compartment, they realize their candles are being blown out. Rains takes a torch and investigates, believing that someone is fooling around. He paces down the tunnel and is alerted when some barrel containers are knocked over, with fleeting shadows being cast on the wall. While searching a small alcove, he hears something dripping next to his feet and looks down to see the alien, which prolongs his agonising demise. Boggs and Golic hear the comotion, but upon seeing what is happening, abandon their foraging mission and run down huge sewer tunnels for several minutes before arriving where they started, finding Rains' mutilated corpse sitting against a wall.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ripley</b></entry>
</list>

Ellen Ripley (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/64965.xml">
Sigourney Weaver</link></actor>
) is the main character of all four Alien movies. In this movie, she appears when the escape pod containing her, Newt, Corporal Hicks and Bishop crash lands on Fiorina 161 after an onboard fire on the Sulaco. She soon discovers that she is the only female on the prison colony. Ripley soon discovers she has an Alien Queen embryo growing inside of her and takes that the Weyland Yutani Company will be on the colony soon to retrieve it. At the end of the movie, Ripley commits suicide by jumping into the gigantic furnace to prevent the company from getting their hands on the Alien Queen.     </p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Troy</b></entry>
</list>

Troy (Paul Brennen) is a prisoner who serves as a technician and handyman with Fiorina's equipment. He was addicted to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/30942.xml">
tobacco</link> and was almost always seen chewing it. Troy was a quieter prisoner and when he did speak he was almost always complaining. During the attempt to trap the alien, he and Arthur sifted through batteries to find some that worked and he loudly complained about how few were in working condition. In the film's bait and chase climax, he was grabbed by the alien and "stuck" to the ceiling while trying to assist the other prisoners.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Vincent</b></entry>
</list>

Vincent is one of the inmates who uses himself as bait to try and trap the Alien in the lead works. At one point, David rounds a corner and finds a corpse on the floor, calling out "I think I've found Vincent!" He is the first inmate to be killed during the plan to lure the creature into the leadworks. The role is not listed in the film's credits, as Vincent is primarily an extra who is killed in the bait and chase sequence.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>William</b></entry>
</list>

William (<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../714/4070714.xml">
Clive Mantle</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
) is a large but panicky inmate. He is revealed in the Assembly Cut to be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../359/54359.xml">
agnostic</link>. William was a member of the group of prisoners who tried to rape Ripley. He was later seen agonizing over who would direct the prisoners after Andrews' death. He and Gregor are later paired together during the attempt to drown the alien in hot lead. He was killed in an offscreen death.                                                                                                             
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>The Dog Alien</b></entry>
</list>

Due to having been gestated in a quadrupedal host (a dog in the theatrical cut, an ox in the extended edition), the parasite now bears several traits evocative of the animal it was spawned from, such as double jointed hind legs, a quadrupedal posture and a lack of dorsal tubes common in the human spawned variety.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
<it>Alien Resurrection''</it></st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/213246.xml">
Alien Resurrection</link></movie>
</it>
</indent>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Call</b></entry>
</list>

Annalee Call (<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<manufacturer wordnetid="110292316" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/34078.xml">
Winona Ryder</link></actor>
</manufacturer>
</person>
) is the newest member of the <it>Betty</it> crew, and has a secret mission to destroy <b><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Ripley+(=238)%22])">
Ripley</link></b> before the Scientists can remove the queen embryo from her. Unbeknown to everyone, Call is actually a "second generation" android; a robot designed and built by other robots. Although no one else knew this, Ripley probably sensed it, saying "no human being is that humane." The humans who created the first generation androids panicked when they discovered that their creations had built new android designs of their own, and initiated a "recall", which was in truth a massacre which wiped out almost all of the second generation androids, although a handful of second generation androids, such as Call, managed to escape.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Christie</b></entry>
</list>

Christie (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/665612.xml">
Gary Dourdan</link></actor>
) is a muscular, dreadlocked mercenary amongst the <it>Betty</it> crew. Christie is first mate and second in command of the <it>Betty</it>, and carries two disposable guns attached to his wrists. He is forced to carry Vriess on his back ("Just like old times," as he says) in a back-harness when they flee underwater. He suffers severe corrosion when an alien spits acid in his face, and sacrifices himself by detaching himself from Vriess. He is later seen cocooned in the queen's chamber along with the ship's scientists.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>DiStephano</b></entry>
</list>

Vincent DiStephano (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../845/7232845.xml">
Raymond Cruz</link></actor>
) is a soldier of the United Systems Military. He was one of the soldiers sent to capture the crew of the <it>Betty</it>, but is captured himself and is left in the custody of the mercinaries when the other soldiers abandon ship. He then agrees to help everyone escape the <it>Auriga</it>. He also briefly explains the history of Autons when it is discovered that Call is one of them. He and the group eventually board the <it>Betty</it> and strap themselves in, preparing to return to Earth. The ship's cargo hatch is open however and Call goes to fix it, where she is confronted by the stowaway newborn. DiStephano soon comes to check on her, sensing danger. He then sees the hideous newborn, which crushes his head with its bare hands.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Elgyn</b></entry>
</list>

Frank Elgyn (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../567/1802567.xml">
Michael Wincott</link></actor>
) is the raspy-voiced captain of the <it>Betty</it>. Elgyn provides General Perez with kidnapped humans still in cryostasis for a large sum of cash. He was also romantically involved with Hillard. He is killed when an alien baits him with a collection of weapons in a stray corridor, where he is pulled through the floor grating and killed.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Gediman</b></entry>
</list>

Dr. Jonathan Gediman (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/454019.xml">
Brad Dourif</link></actor>
) is one of five scientists who perform the operation on the Ripley clone to retrieve the queen embryo. He becomes the first victim of the aliens when he enters the aliens' cage to investigate their disappearance. He is then grabbed by an alien and taken below decks to the Queen's chamber. He is then cocooned by the Aliens. When Ripley is taken to the alien queen, Gediman (who may have gone insane during his cocooning) is overjoyed to witness the queen painfully give birth to the mutant newborn. The newborn shares a bonding moment with its mother before killing her, much to Gediman's horror. It then advances toward Gediman and bites into the top of his skull, spilling his brains. In the book, shortly after his death by the newborn, a chestburster bursts from his body.
During his dealings with and on the subject of Ripley, he referred to her as a <it>she</it>, while Wren called her an <it>it</it>. He seemed to sympathize somewhat with Ripley, unlike Wren.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Hillard</b></entry>
</list>

Sabra Hillard (<actress wordnetid="109767700" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../832/6133832.xml">
Kim Flowers</link></actress>
) is the assistant pilot of the <it>Betty</it> and is the romantic partner of Elgyn. She is eventually taken by the aliens when they swim below the cooling station. She either drowns, dies from a chestburster, or is killed when the <it>Auriga</it> crashes on Earth.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Johner</b></entry>
</list>

Johner (<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../532/854532.xml">
Ron Perlman</link></actor>
</person>
) is a somewhat physically imposing, scarred member of the <it>Betty</it> crew. He is a dark-humored joker and has a short temper. He constantly argues with Vriess, who he teases for being handicapped. Frequently seen with a rather toxic liquor of his own concoction, the container of which conceals a pistol. He is one of only four characters to survive and land on Earth.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>General Perez</b></entry>
</list>

General Martin Perez (<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/1573975.xml">
Dan Hedaya</link></actor>
</person>
) is the commanding military General of the medical research lab where Ripley is being cloned for the alien queen's resurrection. After destroying an escape pod carrying a stowaway alien, he is bitten in the back of the head by yet another creature, exposing his brains, which he proceeds to examine before dying.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Purvis</b></entry>
</list>

Larry Purvis (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../320/4076320.xml">
Leland Orser</link></actor>
) was rescued by the team unexpectedly. He was one of the many test subjects who were kidnapped for experimentation and impregnated. Call offers to take him along so they can be freeze him in cryostasis, where they can later remove the embryo. He dies when the group are ambushed by the evil Dr. Wren. While Wren is arguing with the crew, Purvis is convulsing as blood pours out of his mouth. Purvis eventually gets to his feet and staggers over to the mad scientist, surviving numerous gunshots before relentlessly pounding the villain into some steel steps. Purvis then manages to kill Wren by positioning himself so that his chestburster forces its way through his chest and Wren's skull.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Ripley Clone #8</b></entry>
</list>

Ripley Clone #8 (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../965/64965.xml">
Sigourney Weaver</link></actor>
) was a human hybrid clone, generated from recovered DNA samples of the original Ellen Ripley. She was the 8th clone, and the only successful one. She shares similar traits to the aliens, such as an emphatic link to the rest of the hive, acidic blood, enhanced strength and agility, and also exhibits a sense of morbid cynicism.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Vriess</b></entry>
</list>

Vriess (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../904/1007904.xml">
Dominique Pinon</link></actor>
) is a member of the <it>Betty</it>. He is handicapped and confined to a wheelchair, but still remains a valuable member to the crew. The chief engineer, he is able to hide a shotgun in various pieces upon his chair to avoid detection. He is apparently good friends with Christie and seems to have a strong friendship with Call, who is relatively new to the group. He is one of the few characters to survive the endeavour.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Carlyn Williamson</b></entry>
</list>

Dr. Carlyn Williamson is a scientist on the <it>Auriga</it>. She teaches Ripley how to speak early in the film, and accidentally triggers memories in her of Newt. She is with Gediman when the aliens capture him,if you look closely at the escape pod scene she is there along with marine survivors.
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Wren</b></entry>
</list>

Dr. Mason Wren (<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../003/11386003.xml">
J. E. Freeman</link></actor>
) is one of the five scientists who worked on resurrecting the alien queen. He exposed Call as a "terrorist" who was searching for information on the aliens and ordered soldiers to kill her and the other mercenaries. This failed and they captured him. He acted as a guide until he betrayed them, shooting Call non-fatally and heading to the <it>Betty</it>, hoping to get there before the others and escape, stranding them with the aliens. He is killed when Purvis attacks him in a violent fit of rage, forcing Wren's head to his chest moments before the chestburster emerges, killing them both.</p>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<b>Newborn</b></entry>
</list>

The Newborn Alien is the first of its kind. It was created due to the fact that the DNA of Ripley and the alien inside her was combined during the cloning process. While the Ripley clone had alien characteristics, the queen that grew inside her had human characteristics as well. She, after laying 13 eggs, developed a womb. This caused only one baby to be born instead of hundreds of eggs being laid. It burst out of her womb and was nearly as big as the queen herself. The Newborn walked upright and had facial features similarly like a human. It then proceeded to kill the queen, not believing she was its mother, seeing the Ripley clone as a surrogate mother. After killing Gediman, it boarded the <it>Betty</it> and ambushed Call. It seemed to have some sort of feelings toward Call, but her abject revulsion at the creature caused it to turn violently upon DiStephano and then Call herself. It prepared to tear her torso apart, but was eventually sucked through a hole in the ship's window, after Ripley flung some of her acidic blood onto the surface of the glass.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/15137377.xml">
List of characters in the Alien vs. Predator series</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Beautiful Monsters: The Unofficial and Unauthorised Guide to the Alien and Predator Films</it> (by <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<communicator wordnetid="109610660" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<writer wordnetid="110794014" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../260/2708260.xml">
David A. McIntee</link></writer>
</causal_agent>
</person>
</communicator>
</physical_entity>
, Telos, 272 pages, 2005, ISBN 1-903889-94-4)</entry>
</list>
</p>

<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/6245494.xml">
Alien</link></movie>
, <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/14919990.xml">
Predator</link></movie>
</it>, and <it><product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<oeuvre wordnetid="103841417" confidence="0.8">
<end_product wordnetid="103287178" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../332/511332.xml">
Alien vs. Predator</link></end_product>
</oeuvre>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
''</it></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<it>Alien</it> films</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/1937693.xml">
Alien</link></movie>
&nbsp;·  <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../472/213472.xml">
Aliens</link></movie>
&nbsp;·  <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../251/213251.xml">
Alien 3</link></movie>
&nbsp;·  <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/213246.xml">
Alien Resurrection</link></movie>
''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<it>Predator</it> films</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/230481.xml">
Predator</link></movie>
&nbsp;·  <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/620034.xml">
Predator 2</link></movie>
''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
<it>Alien vs. Predator</it> films</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../421/901421.xml">
Alien vs. Predator</link></movie>
&nbsp;·  ''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Film characters</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<hypothetical_creature wordnetid="109484313" confidence="0.8">
<monster wordnetid="109491966" confidence="0.8">
<extraterrestrial_being wordnetid="109484465" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<race wordnetid="107472657" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../467/612467.xml">
The Alien</link></psychological_feature>
</race>
</contest>
</imaginary_being>
</social_event>
</fictional_character>
</event>
</extraterrestrial_being>
</monster>
</hypothetical_creature>
&nbsp;·  <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/623280.xml">
Bishop</link></fictional_character>
&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<imaginary_being wordnetid="109483738" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<race wordnetid="107472657" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/7467334.xml">
The Predator</link></psychological_feature>
</race>
</contest>
</imaginary_being>
</social_event>
</fictional_character>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <fictional_character wordnetid="109587565" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../093/620093.xml">
Ellen Ripley</link></fictional_character>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/8995799.xml">
<it>Alien</it> characters</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../475/11437475.xml">
<it>Predator</it> characters</link>&nbsp;·   <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../377/15137377.xml">
<it>Alien vs. Predator</it> characters</link></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Comic books</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<it><physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/3503918.xml">
Aliens</link></entertainer>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../323/1007323.xml">
Aliens versus Predator</link></entertainer>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../589/1964589.xml">
Aliens versus Predator versus The Terminator</link></entertainer>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../504/12963504.xml">
Mindhunter</link></entertainer>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <title wordnetid="106345993" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../006/7588006.xml">
Batman/Aliens</link></title>
&nbsp;·  <title wordnetid="106345993" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../575/3387575.xml">
Batman versus Predator</link></title>
&nbsp;·  <title wordnetid="106345993" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../939/2222939.xml">
Green Lantern versus Aliens</link></title>
&nbsp;·  <story wordnetid="106369829" confidence="0.8">
<storyline wordnetid="106373645" confidence="0.8">
<literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<plot wordnetid="106373314" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/7609237.xml">
Judge Dredd vs. Aliens</link></plot>
</fiction>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
</storyline>
</story>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/7552573.xml">
Predator</link></entertainer>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  <beginning wordnetid="100235435" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<plot wordnetid="106373314" confidence="0.8">
<change_of_state wordnetid="100199130" confidence="0.8">
<story wordnetid="106369829" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<storyline wordnetid="106373645" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<introduction wordnetid="100238022" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../917/7593917.xml">
Predator vs. Judge Dredd</link></introduction>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</fiction>
</action>
</storyline>
</event>
</story>
</change_of_state>
</plot>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
</change>
</beginning>
&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../271/11058271.xml">
Superman and Batman versus Aliens and Predator</link>&nbsp;·  <beginning wordnetid="100235435" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<plot wordnetid="106373314" confidence="0.8">
<change_of_state wordnetid="100199130" confidence="0.8">
<story wordnetid="106369829" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<storyline wordnetid="106373645" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<introduction wordnetid="100238022" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../065/3389065.xml">
Superman/Aliens</link></introduction>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</fiction>
</action>
</storyline>
</event>
</story>
</change_of_state>
</plot>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
</change>
</beginning>
&nbsp;·  <beginning wordnetid="100235435" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<plot wordnetid="106373314" confidence="0.8">
<change_of_state wordnetid="100199130" confidence="0.8">
<story wordnetid="106369829" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<storyline wordnetid="106373645" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<introduction wordnetid="100238022" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/7880703.xml">
Superman vs. Predator</link></introduction>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</fiction>
</action>
</storyline>
</event>
</story>
</change_of_state>
</plot>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
</change>
</beginning>
&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<comedian wordnetid="109940146" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../344/5121344.xml">
WildC.A.T.s/Aliens</link></entertainer>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</comedian>
</physical_entity>
&nbsp;·  ''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Novels</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<it><literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<novel wordnetid="106367879" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../215/7555215.xml">
Aliens</link></novel>
</fiction>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  <book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../333/7402333.xml">
Aliens vs. Predator</link></book>
&nbsp;·  <literary_composition wordnetid="106364329" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<fiction wordnetid="106367107" confidence="0.8">
<novel wordnetid="106367879" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../775/7552775.xml">
Predator</link></novel>
</fiction>
</writing>
</written_communication>
</literary_composition>
''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Alien games</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/15998162.xml">
Alien 3</link></it>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/15998162.xml">
<it>Alien 3 </it> (SNES)</link>&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../391/5415391.xml">
<it>Alien 3</it> (Game Boy)</link>&nbsp;·  <it>&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/7556035.xml">
Alien Trilogy</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../185/7614185.xml">
Aliens Online</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../579/7556579.xml">
Alien Resurrection</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  ''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Predator games</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<it><event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../466/7646466.xml">
Predator</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../869/7646869.xml">
Predator 2</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</it>&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../809/7649809.xml">
<it>Predator 2</it> (Perfect 10)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../267/7648267.xml">
<it>Predator</it> (mobile)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <it>''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Alien vs. Predator 
games</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../576/4899576.xml">
<it>Alien vs Predator</it> (SNES)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../387/1314387.xml">
<it>Alien vs. Predator</it> (arcade)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../703/2908703.xml">
<it>Alien vs Predator</it> (Jaguar)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../034/7645034.xml">
<it>Alien vs Predator</it> (Lynx)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/1127017.xml">
Aliens versus Predator</link>&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../052/1251052.xml">
Aliens versus Predator 2</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../626/2684626.xml">
Alien vs. Predator 2D</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
</it>&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../371/7647371.xml">
<it>Alien vs. Predator</it> (mobile)</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  <it><event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../008/7649008.xml">
Alien vs. Predator 3D</link></psychological_feature>
</game>
</contest>
</social_event>
</event>
&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  ''</it></col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Alien and Predator 
universe</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-even">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/4027932.xml">
Castes from the <it>Alien</it> expanded universe</link>&nbsp;·   <planet wordnetid="109394007" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../250/1164250.xml">
LV-426</link></planet>
&nbsp;·  <spacecraft wordnetid="104264914" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../693/1937693.xml">
<it>Nostromo''</it></link></spacecraft>
&nbsp;·  <artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<weapon wordnetid="104565375" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<instrument wordnetid="103574816" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../996/15285996.xml">
Predator technology</link></instrument>
</device>
</weapon>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
&nbsp;·  <animal wordnetid="100015388" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/2396423.xml">
Space Jockey</link></animal>
&nbsp;·  <spacecraft wordnetid="104264914" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../292/947292.xml">
<it>Sulaco''</it></link></spacecraft>
&nbsp;·  <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/8301750.xml">
Val Verde</link></country>
</district>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
&nbsp;·  <company wordnetid="108058098" confidence="0.8">
<institution wordnetid="108053576" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../483/602483.xml">
Weyland-Yutani</link></institution>
</company>
</col>
</row>
<row style="height:2px">

</row>
<row>
<col style=";;" class="navbox-group">
Miscellaneous</col>
<col style="text-align:left;border-left:2px solid #fdfdfd;width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../827/3305827.xml">
Alien 2</link></movie>
</it>&nbsp;·  <it><computer wordnetid="103082979" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<device wordnetid="103183080" confidence="0.8">
<machine wordnetid="103699975" confidence="0.8">
<web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../334/1588334.xml">
Alien Loves Predator</link></web_site>
</machine>
</device>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</computer>
</it>&nbsp;·  <it><product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.8">
<show wordnetid="106619065" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../975/3317975.xml">
Alien Quadrilogy</link></psychological_feature>
</show>
</movie>
</social_event>
</event>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</it>&nbsp;·  <event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<drive wordnetid="100307631" confidence="0.8">
<change wordnetid="100191142" confidence="0.8">
<action wordnetid="100037396" confidence="0.8">
<social_event wordnetid="107288639" confidence="0.8">
<journey wordnetid="100306426" confidence="0.8">
<contest wordnetid="107456188" confidence="0.8">
<travel wordnetid="100295701" confidence="0.8">
<game wordnetid="100456199" confidence="0.8">
<motion wordnetid="100279835" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../418/3501418.xml">
Alien War</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</motion>
</game>
</travel>
</contest>
</journey>
</social_event>
</action>
</change>
</drive>
</event>
&nbsp;·  &nbsp;·  <it>''</it></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</fictional_character>
</article>
