<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 23:51:08[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<movie  confidence="0.9508927676800064" wordnetid="106613686">
<header>
<title>Everything Happens to Me</title>
<id>9669953</id>
<revision>
<id>240205162</id>
<timestamp>2008-09-22T11:25:42Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Alex gettinby</username>
<id>7409159</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Films directed by Michele Lupo</category>
<category>Comedy films</category>
<category>Italian-language films</category>
<category>1980 films</category>
<category>Italian films</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<template>
<name>Infobox Film</name>
<parameters>

<image width="150px" src="">
</image>
<runtime>
(Italy) 99 minutes</runtime>
<preceded_by>
Uno Sceriffo extraterrestre - poco extra e molto terrestre</preceded_by>
<director>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/19201363.xml">
Michele Lupo</link></director>
<country>
Italy</country>
<released>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/34640.xml">
1980</link></released>
<imdb_id>
0080530</imdb_id>
<name>
Everything Happens To Me</name>
<producer>
<link>
Elio Scardamaglia</link></producer>
<cinematography>
<link>
Franco Di Giacomo</link></cinematography>
<language>
<language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../708/14708.xml">
Italian</link></language>
, <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../916/8569916.xml">
English</link></language>
</language>
<writer>
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../439/19176439.xml">
Marcello Fondato</link>, <link>
Francesco Scardamaglia</link></writer>
<starring>
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/3841.xml">
Bud Spencer</link></actor>
</person>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/4866843.xml">
Cary Guffey</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../224/17868224.xml">
Ferruccio Amendola</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
, <link>
Claudio Undali</link></starring>
</parameters>
</template>


<it>Everything Happens to Me</it> may also refer to the Tommy Dorsey song, a cover version of which was an early hit for Frank Sinatra.<p>

<b><it>Everything Happens to Me</it></b> (original Italian title: Chissà perché... capitano tutte a me) is a children's comedy movie starring <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../841/3841.xml">
Bud Spencer</link></actor>
</person>
 and child actor <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<performer wordnetid="110415638" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<actor wordnetid="109765278" confidence="0.8">
<entertainer wordnetid="109616922" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../843/4866843.xml">
Cary Guffey</link></entertainer>
</actor>
</causal_agent>
</performer>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 that was released in cinemas in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../640/34640.xml">
1980</link>. It is a direct sequel of the 1979 movie <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/4869325.xml">
The Sheriff and the Satellite Kid</link></it> and is also know under the title <b><it>Why Did You Pick on Me?</it></b></p>

<sec>
<st>
Plot</st>
<p>

Following the events of <it>The Sheriff and the Satellite Kid</it>, Sheriff Hall and H-725 (here named Charlie Warren) still get no rest from the military: because the little alien has not yet grasped the meaning of keeping a low profile, they are constantly on the move, and H-725’s father has to pick them out of a tight spot too many times already.</p>
<p>

Hall and Charlie finally arrive at the city of Munroe, where petty crime, from vandalism to armed robberies, is running rampant, more so because the town currently has no sheriff. Charlie pushes Hall into staying in this place, and somewhat reluctantly Hall takes up the job in this chaotic place, with the help of the local radio jock and City Mayor Howard (Ferruccio Amendola). Soon the riff-raff in town learns not to underestimate the new sheriff as he metes out hard-hitting advice to stay out of trouble.</p>
<p>

However, the local thugs are the smallest of Hall’s problems. A task force of hostile alien invaders are preparing to enslave mankind with the use of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../417/14417.xml">
hypno-wave devices</link> and advanced <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../713/713.xml">
androids</link>; already they control the local authorities and military installations. Charlie immediately senses the true nature of these individuals, however, and after much persuasion convinces his big friend to look into the matter. But this arouses the suspicion of the alien leader (Claudio Undali); he has Hall arrested for snooping into matters of national security and Charlie kidnapped.</p>
<p>

Hall manages to sneak out of prison, and after Howard has told him what happened to Charlie, the sheriff decides to take up the fight. Through the public announcement system Howard appeals to the citizens of Munroe for help, and the thugs and hooligans whom Hall has previously thrashed join forces with the sheriff, just as the alien leader executes the final stage of his plan to take over Munroe by sending the local <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../240/964240.xml">
state police</link> force to the El Dorado festival and round up the townspeople. Hall and his helpers engage the officers in a massive fist-fight, though, and begin to win the upper hand until the alien chief decides to use his hypno-wave machine. The rioters are quickly subjugated – except for the sheriff, who wanders as if in trance to the military base which serves as the alien’s headquarters.</p>
<p>

As Hall arrives there, the alien leader and his androids discover that their hypno-waves have no effect on the sheriff (due to an earlier treatment by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/4869325.xml">
Charlie’s wonder device</link>. The androids are sent against Hall, but the sheriff’s fists prove to be tougher than they are, and soon the androids’ <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../542/1729542.xml">
neural nets</link> end up completely scrambled. The alien leader tries to activate a self-destruct device, but the sheriff takes a swing at him and he shatters like glass (probably to avoid censorship). Charlie is released from captivity and happily rejoins the sheriff.</p>
<p>

However, as the town celebrates their rescuers, once again the military arrives to try and apprehend Charlie once more. Fed up with the constant pestering, Hall and Charlie take off into space with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../691/337691.xml">
old-timer</link> automobile they were riding at the parade to join Charlie’s family. But as soon as they have left the atmosphere, a small inconvenience makes Hall grumble once more: “Why does everything happen to me!”</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Trivia </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

The amusement park in which the film's major slugfest takes place is the same as in its predecessor film.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0080530/">
<it>Everything Happens to Me</it> </weblink> at the <web_site wordnetid="106359193" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../554/2855554.xml">
Internet Movie Database</link></web_site>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.budterence.tk/chissaperche.php">
Bud Spencer and Terence Hill movie website</weblink> (Italian)</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</movie>
</article>
