<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:24:54[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<food  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100021265">
<header>
<title>Pork rind</title>
<id>613420</id>
<revision>
<id>244630147</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-11T19:56:20Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>J3ff</username>
<id>58906</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>All articles with unsourced statements</category>
<category>Condiments</category>
<category>Peasant foods</category>
<category>Pork</category>
<category>Articles with specifically-marked weasel-worded phrases</category>
<category>Snack foods</category>
<category>British cuisine</category>
<category>Serbian cuisine</category>
<category>American cuisine</category>
<category>Danish cuisine</category>
<category>Articles with unsourced statements </category>
<category>Cuisine of Newfoundland and Labrador</category>
<category>Filipino cuisine</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="PorkSkins_saltadded.JPG" type="thumb">
<caption>

Pork rinds in bags, from the central United States
</caption>
</image>

<b>Pork rind</b> (known as <b>pork scratchings</b> in the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, and <b>pork crackle</b> in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../264/4689264.xml">
Australia</link></country>
) is the skin of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../142/25142.xml">
pig</link>. Cooked, this may be either eaten warm with a meal, or served cold as a snack. In both forms, any fat attached to the skin of pig at the time of frying is absorbed in the process.</p>

<sec>
<st>
Pork rind as a snack</st>
<p>

When used as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/330718.xml">
snack food</link>, chunks of cured pork skins are deep-fried and puffed into light, irregular curls, and often seasoned with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/74225.xml">
chili pepper</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../135/37135.xml">
barbecue</link> flavouring.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../017/58017.xml">
Microwavable</link> pork rinds are sold which are microwaved in bags that resemble microwave <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/232176.xml">
popcorn</link> (although not exhibiting the 'popping' sound) and can be eaten still warm. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/2259607.xml">
Pickled</link> pork rinds, on the other hand, are often enjoyed refrigerated and cold. Unlike the crisp and fluffy texture of fried pork rinds, pickled pork rinds are very rich and buttery, much like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../149/230149.xml">
foie gras</link>.  Unfried pork rind is also processed into colorful and appealing shapes for use as fish <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../692/566692.xml">
bait</link>.</p>
<p>

When he was in the <building wordnetid="102913152" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/33057.xml">
White House</link></building>
, <post wordnetid="108624385" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../113/24113.xml">
U.S. President</link></post>
 <president wordnetid="110468559" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<businessperson wordnetid="109882716" confidence="0.9173553029164789">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../955/11955.xml">
George H. W. Bush</link></businessperson>
</person>
</president>
 said that pork rinds were his favorite snack.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Health issues</st>
<p>

Though generally considered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/64083.xml">
junk food</link> and among the unhealthiest of foods there is some interest in pork rinds as an alternative snack food due to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../121/84121.xml">
Atkins diet</link>, since pork rinds contain no <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../932/5932.xml">
carbohydrate</link>s (unless flavored). They are, however, high in fat and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../826/26826.xml">
sodium</link>. The fat content of pork rinds is similar to that of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/24851.xml">
potato chips</link>, but the amount of sodium in a serving of pork rinds is nearly five times that of a serving of potato chips.  </p>
<p>

For example, a 14 gram serving of <trade_name wordnetid="106845599" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/9496641.xml">
Utz</link></trade_name>
 Regular Pork Rinds contains 5 g of fat and 230 mg of sodium, whereas the same serving of Utz Regular Potato Chips contains 4.5 g of fat and 47 mg of sodium.  Pork rinds generally contain 8 g of protein in a 14 g serving, more than most foods except dried meats such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../612/167612.xml">
jerky</link>.  The fat content of jerky, however, is much lower.  Microwaveable pork rinds are lower in fat than the deep-fried variety, with only 2 g of fat per 14 g serving and no saturated fat, although the sodium level may be as high as 350 mg per serving. According to the Atkin's diet, the low carbohydrate content of pork rinds makes them more nutritious than some low-fat snack foods, such as high-carbohydrate, fat-free pretzels.</p>
<p>

According to <it><magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/349340.xml">
Men's Health</link></magazine>
</it>:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref></p>
<p>

A 1-ounce (=28.35g) serving contains zero carbohydrates, 17 grams (g) of protein, and 9 g fat. That's nine times the protein and less fat than you'll find in a serving of carb-packed potato chips. Even better, 43 percent of a pork rind's fat is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../748/264748.xml">
unsaturated</link>, and most of that is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../100/661100.xml">
oleic acid</link> — the same healthy fat found in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../478/22478.xml">
olive oil</link>. Another 13 percent of its fat content is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../511/338511.xml">
stearic acid</link>, a type of saturated fat that's considered harmless, because it doesn't raise cholesterol levels.</p>
<p>

Another thing to consider, however, is that deep-frying creates large amounts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../952/1466952.xml">
advanced glycation endproducts</link>, which are very damaging to the body.</p>
<p>

Moreover, although there is some protein present in pork rinds, the quality of that protein, called hydrolyzed gelatin protein, is quite low.  Because they have a protein efficiency ratio lower than 40% as dictated by the FDA, their nutrition label usually states "0%" in % Daily Value or "Not a significant source of protein" as recommended by the FDA.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Origin</st>
<p>

The consensus&#91;&#93; is that pork scratchings originated as solid scraps, a bi-product left over during the process of rendering pork fat down into (liquid) lard.</p>
<p>

Sometimes the fine layer of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../313/14313.xml">
hair</link> is removed from the skin by burning; however this is not completely effective and some pieces still have the hair attached.</p>
<p>

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/495814.xml">
Butcher</link>s started selling pork scratchings in the 1930s, and more recently a product called pork crunch has been developed, in which much of the fat is scraped off, resulting in a lower-fat, softer alternative.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Variations</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Canada</st>
<p>

<b>Scrunchions</b> is a <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../803/21803.xml">
Newfoundland</link></language>
 term for small pieces of pork rind or pork fat-back fried until <link>
rendered</link> and crispy. They are often used as a flavoring over other foods, such as salt fish and potatoes. It is mainly used as a condiment for <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/4699915.xml">
fish and brewis</link>. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.heritage.nf.ca/dictionary/azindex/pages/3947.html">
http://www.heritage.nf.ca/dictionary/azindex/pages/3947.html</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.billcasselman.com/canadian_food_words/cfw_two.htm">
http://www.billcasselman.com/canadian_food_words/cfw_two.htm</weblink></p>
<p>

In <district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/7954867.xml">
Quebec</link></district>
, they are often called "Oreilles de Christ" (christ ears) or "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../846/4016846.xml">
Oreilles de crisse</link>", and are eaten almost exclusively as a condiment for traditional meals with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../886/19886.xml">
maple syrup</link>.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
United Kingdom</st>
<p>

<b>Pork Crackling</b> is the British name for the salted crunchy pork rind produced when roasting a joint of pork. The heat of the oven causes the fatty pork skin to dry, bubble up and become crunchy. The layer of fat underneath is retained, and can be eaten with the skin or removed. Some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/51862.xml">
supermarkets</link> now sell just the layer of skin and fat (no meat), in a raw form for home grilling or roasting, or cooked and ready to eat from hot food counters.</p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="150px" src="Large_Pork_Scratching.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

A pork scratching from a bag purchased in the UK.  Approximate dimensions: 55mm x 45mm.  The soft fat is to the center, below the hard rind around the upper and right-hand edges.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<b>Pork Scratchings</b> is the British name for deep fried salted crunchy pork rind with fat produced separately from the meat. This is then eaten cold. </p>
<p>

Pork Scratchings are typically heavy, hard and have a crispy layer of fat under the skin, some still retain the hair of the pig, and are flavored only with salt. The pig hair is usually removed by quickly burning the skin of the pig before it is cut into pieces and cooked in hot fat. Hair removal is not 100% effective which is why some retain a few hairs. The hairs are what usually makes people question the desirability of these pub snacks, but to some, these can also be highly desirable.</p>
<p>

In the <autocracy wordnetid="108361001" confidence="0.8">
<system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<monarchy wordnetid="108363812" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<political_system wordnetid="108367880" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../717/31717.xml">
United Kingdom</link></democracy>
</group>
</economy>
</political_system>
</political_unit>
</state>
</monarchy>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</system>
</autocracy>
, pork scratchings (though not crackling &mdash; see above) are sold as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/330718.xml">
snack food</link> in the same way pork rinds are in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
USA</link>. Unlike the physically large, but relatively light bags of 'deep fried skin without the fat' sold around the world, in the UK they are sold in relatively small bags which usually weigh between 42g and 90g. Traditionally they are eaten as an accompaniment to a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../881/222881.xml">
pint</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/3363.xml">
beer</link> in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/24578.xml">
pub</link>, just like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../851/24851.xml">
crisps</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/55602.xml">
peanut</link>s. Fewer and fewer pubs stock scratchings as the years go by. One sign of a traditional pub is the availability of Pork Scratchings. Scratchings can also be bought from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../814/495814.xml">
butchers</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../862/51862.xml">
supermarkets</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../521/2163521.xml">
newsagents</link>.</p>
<p>

They have been taken to both the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../836/21836.xml">
North Pole</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../011/19631011.xml">
South Pole</link> on various expeditions, this is due to their lack of weight and high amount of energy which is essential on these types of trips.</p>
<p>

They have been popular in the UK and especially in the <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<area wordnetid="108497294" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../131/171131.xml">
Black Country</link></location>
</area>
</region>
 since the times when families would fatten up a "tunkey pig" (This is a pig fattened especially for <vacation wordnetid="115137890" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../237/6237.xml">
Christmas</link></vacation>
), then slaughter it for meat and slice the skin with the fat into strips which they would then deep fry. Some believe that their popularity grew in the early 1800s when new uses were found for offcuts from pigs.</p>
<p>

In the UK, the term 'pork rind' usually refers to the <it>uncooked</it> layer of skin on bacon or a joint of pork.  Many people choose to cut the raw rind off their bacon before cooking it&#91;&#93;.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
United States</st>
<p>

<b>Cracklings</b> is the American name for pork rind produced by frying or roasting, though it can be expanded to include the skin of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../484/50484.xml">
goose</link> or another animal. Pieces of fried meat, skin, or membrane produced as a byproduct of rendering <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../997/18621997.xml">
lard</link> are also called cracklings.</p>
<p>

As a snack, <it>cracklings</it> is usually understood to consist of cooked pork rind that has had salt rubbed into it and that has been scored with a sharp knife. This produces a crisp, bubbly outer surface with a layer of cooked fat on the underside. Crackling is considered by some to be an essential part of joint of roast <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/19719929.xml">
pork</link>. However, the term in cooking also applies to a variety of fatty materials, fried to crispness, such as poultry skin or the remains of trying out for fat of a number of animal products [beef, lamb, etc.]. </p>
<p>

A <b>cracklin</b> is a fried piece of pork fat with a small amount of attached skin. Cracklins are generally considered to be part of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../910/27910.xml">
soul food</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../186/6186.xml">
Cajun cuisine</link>. Cracklins are not frequently served as part of a regular meal unless they are served in <it>cracklin bread</it>, which is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../786/244786.xml">
cornbread</link> in which cracklins have been placed in the batter prior to its being baked or fried. Rather, they are a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/330718.xml">
snack</link> item which would typically be served at times other than regular mealtimes, and are regarded as more of a delicacy or treat.</p>
<p>

Cracklins are naturally very high in fat and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../437/6437.xml">
cholesterol</link>, which is to be expected considering what they are composed of and the fact that they are generally prepared by being deep- or skillet-fried in lard. Cracklins prepared by persons who conduct the home butchering of hogs, which is still occasionally conducted in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../614/212614.xml">
rural</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../553/179553.xml">
South</link> although with decreasing frequency, have a decidedly different taste from those which are distributed nationally or internationally.</p>
<p>

In the early 1960s the FDA implemented new rules regarding the commercial preparation and sale of cracklins, and the availability of the traditional cracklins diminished rapidly. Today's commercial versions, which are light and airy, bear little resemblance in either appearance or taste to the old-fashioned cracklins which used to be available from local butchers and supermarkets. The new version is heavily fried and light in taste compared to the older cracklins, which are greasy and occasionally have hair still attached to the fried flesh and fat combination.</p>
<p>

Many aficionados much prefer the original variety of cracklins which today sometimes can be found in small enclaves, such as the <group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/19346935.xml">
Amish</link></group>
, who still prepare the product using traditional methods. But the Amish are reluctant to sell them to outsiders, unless they know them personally, due to the newer federal rules.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Europe</st>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
 pork rinds are known as <it>grattons</it> and are an essential ingredient to some slow cooked stews <dish wordnetid="103206908" confidence="0.8">
<crockery wordnetid="103133538" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<instrumentality wordnetid="103575240" confidence="0.8">
<article wordnetid="100022903" confidence="0.8">
<ware wordnetid="104550840" confidence="0.8">
<container wordnetid="103094503" confidence="0.8">
<tableware wordnetid="104381994" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../847/577847.xml">
Cassoulet</link></tableware>
</container>
</ware>
</article>
</instrumentality>
</artifact>
</crockery>
</dish>
 adding body &amp; depth of flavour. In <system wordnetid="108435388" confidence="0.8">
<economy wordnetid="108366753" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/26667.xml">
Spain</link></group>
</economy>
</system>
 they are called <it>cortezas de cerdo</it> when they don't have any solid fat attached, and <it>chicharrones</it> or <it>torreznos</it> when they do. In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../033/23033.xml">
Portugal</link></country>
, you must distinguish between <it>torresmos</it> (like the picture in the top of the article) and <it>couratos</it>, these ones are normally on sale from stands near large popular gatherings, such as football stadiums, usually in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../425/82425.xml">
sandwich</link> presentation, and are accompanied with a well chilled <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../363/3363.xml">
beer</link>. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../148/21148.xml">
The Netherlands</link> they are known as <it>knabbelspek</it>, which translates to 'munching bacon.' They are usually sold with no flavourings other than salt. As the name implies, they are usually eaten as a snack food. They are sold at most butchers and supermarkets. In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../972/76972.xml">
Denmark</link></country>
 they are known as "flæskesvær" ("flæsk" means pork, "svær" means rind) and can be found in most grocery stores and kiosks.</p>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../275/13275.xml">
Hungary</link></country>
 they are known as 'tepertő' or 'töpörtyű' and are still a very popular food. They are fried in lard usually and eaten when hot with huge slices of bread and spring onion. Tepertő is a traditional food in Hungary, connected to peasant cookery. They first remove the hair, then cut it into small pieces and fry. Pork scratchings are also still available in some shops.  In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/29265.xml">
Serbia</link></country>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../573/5573.xml">
Croatia</link></country>
, pork rinds are called <it><link>
čvarci</link></it> and they are a popular home-made peasant food in the lowland, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../367/311367.xml">
Pannonian regions</link>. They are usually deep-fried in fat. The skin may or may not be attached, but any hair is generally removed.  Čvarci are most often made during the traditional <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../339/18621339.xml">
slaughter of pigs in Croatia and Serbia</link>, when they are also first tasted by the participants.  A special kind of čvarci exists in Serbia called <it><link>
duvan čvarci</link></it> (lit. "<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../942/30942.xml">
tobacco</link> cracklings"): it is made by pressing čvarci during the preparation so that at the end they have appearance of tobacco.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Latin America</st>
<p>

Pork rinds are also popular in <environment wordnetid="113934596" confidence="0.8">
<grouping wordnetid="101012360" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="100024720" confidence="0.8">
<sphere wordnetid="114514039" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<situation wordnetid="113927383" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<categorization wordnetid="101012712" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../524/18524.xml">
Latin America</link></categorization>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</situation>
</act>
</sphere>
</state>
</event>
</grouping>
</environment>
. In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../825/26825.xml">
Spanish-speaking countries</link>, and Spanish-speaking states they are known as <it><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../120/1943120.xml">
chicharrones</link></it> (the singular form, <it>chicharrón,</it> is also used as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../990/41990.xml">
mass noun</link>).  They are eaten alone as a snack, or as the meat portion in various stews and soups, which can be eaten with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../360/1731360.xml">
cachapa</link>s, or as a stuffing in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../564/1503564.xml">
arepa</link>s, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../428/1660428.xml">
pupusa</link>s, or in a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../985/29985.xml">
taco</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../602/2003602.xml">
gordita</link> with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/714128.xml">
salsa verde</link>. </p>
<p>

They are usually made with different cuts of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/19719929.xml">
pork</link>, but sometimes with other meats, like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../197/23197.xml">
poultry</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../968/36968.xml">
beef</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../563/17158563.xml">
ram</link>, etc. In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../481/5042481.xml">
Cuba</link></country>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../041/23041.xml">
Puerto Rico</link></country>
 and <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/32374.xml">
Venezuela</link></country>
 chicharrones are also made with chicken and, in <city wordnetid="108524735" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../905/18951905.xml">
Argentina</link></country>
</city>
 with beef. In these cases they are consumed mostly as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/330718.xml">
snack</link>s.</p>
<p>

In <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../383/3383.xml">
Brazil</link></country>
, pork rinds (called <it>torresmo</it> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../915/23915.xml">
Portuguese</link>) are eaten as snack with beer, or as a side to some dishes, like <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../596/623596.xml">
feijoada</link>.</p>
<p>

The <it>cueritos</it> type is a <body wordnetid="107965085" confidence="0.8">
<social_group wordnetid="107950920" confidence="0.8">
<political_orientation wordnetid="106212839" confidence="0.8">
<colony wordnetid="108374049" confidence="0.8">
<state wordnetid="108168978" confidence="0.8">
<political_unit wordnetid="108359949" confidence="0.8">
<group wordnetid="100031264" confidence="0.8">
<democracy wordnetid="106217103" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../054/3966054.xml">
Mexican</link></democracy>
</group>
</political_unit>
</state>
</colony>
</political_orientation>
</social_group>
</body>
 snack. It is made with pork skins and marinated in vinegar instead of being deep fried. They are eaten as a snack.</p>
<p>

In the Island of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../606/1830606.xml">
Utila</link>, in <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../394/13394.xml">
Honduras</link></country>
, it is deep fried in a huge pot at the beach on Sundays, and is garnished with fried green <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../945/38945.xml">
plantains</link> or fried <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/54146.xml">
breadfruit</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../382/916382.xml">
coleslaw</link>.</p>
<p>

In Mexico and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/3434750.xml">
USA</link>, snack-food companies have commercialized a vegetarian version of the deep-fried type, with <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../225/74225.xml">
chile</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../456/261456.xml">
lime</link> flavorings.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Philippines</st>
<p>

Fried pork skins go by various names in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../222/2047222.xml">
Filipino cuisine</link>, including <it>tsitsaron</it> (from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../752/878752.xml">
Spanish</link> word <it>chicharrón</it>).  They may also be referred to by their English name "cracklings" if they contain a considerable portion of meat. Another form of crackling in the Philippines, <it>tsitsarong manok</it>, is made from seasoned chicken skin fried in its own rendered fat. Usually, pork rinds are eaten to absorb the sourness of some types of Filipino stews and soups like <it>sinigang</it> or <it>paksiw</it>. Though the pork present in these dishes does have a rind, they are not strictly considered snacks.</p>
<p>

Crunchy pork rinds are one of the more popular choices for finger foods, locally called <it>pulutan</it>, during drinking sessions. They are served with a spicy vinegar dip. A popular beer snack is <it>tsitsarong bulaklak</it> ("flower" crackling) which is fried <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/489301.xml">
chitterlings</link> (pork intestines).</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>


<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=health&amp;res=950DE2DE103BF934A35755C0A96F948260">
Suddenly, Pork Rinds Are Classy Crunch</weblink>".&#32;Retrieved on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../349/19349.xml">
2 May</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../165/36165.xml">
2007</link>.</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.menshealth.com/cda/article.do?site=MensHealth&amp;channel=nutrition&amp;conitem=7a5d8e208b4e9010VgnVCM100000cfe793cd____&amp;page=1">
Genius Junk Food</weblink> from <it><magazine wordnetid="106595351" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/349340.xml">
Men's Health</link></magazine>
''</it></entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hairybarsnacks.com/">
Hairy Bar Snacks - Pork Scratchings Website</weblink> Images, History, Reviews, Links</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.porkscratchingworld.com/">
Pork Scratching World</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.freshersfoods.co.uk/history.htm">
http://www.freshersfoods.co.uk/history.htm</weblink> - The first history available on the internet written and researched by Julie Openshaw back in 1999.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</food>
</article>
