

The Audi Q7 is a full-size luxury sport utility vehicle (SUV) produced by German automaker Audi since its unveiling at the Los Angeles Auto Show in January 2006. 

In its name Q7, the "Q" denotes a new family of vehicles for Audi, and the designation "7" marks its placement between the A6 and A8 in Audi's model range.  

The Q7 utilizes a modified version of the Volkswagen Group 7L platform, the 4L.  Based on the Audi Pikes Peak quattro concept car, the Q7 is designed more for on-road use, and was not meant for serious off-road use where a transfer case is needed. In an off road test through the Australian outback it fared well for a "soft roader" but in a test published in The Sunday Times it was described as "an absolutely useless off-roader". Although it lacks a low-range transfer case, it has quattro permanent four wheel drive system with a central differential lock, and an adjustable-height air suspension which helps in off road situations.

Audi's 350 PS (345 hp/257 kW), 440 N·m (325 lb·ft) 4163 cc V8 and 280 PS (276 hp/206 kW), 360 N·m (266 lb·ft) V6 3596 cc petrol engines, both with FSI technology, are offered.  Interestingly, Q7 using either engine has the same 0 - 100 km/h performance.  

Two diesel options are available; a 240 PS (237 hp/177 kW) 3.0L V6 and in mid-2007 the 4.2 litre 331 PS (326 hp/243 kW) diesel with 760 N·m (561 lb·ft) torque known from the Audi A8 was introduced.  Audi is reportedly going to introduce a hybrid version of the Q7 in 2008

To underline the racing success of its diesel engined Le Mans-winning R10 racer, Audi presented a concept-version of the car with a new V12 TDI Q7 at the 2006 Paris Auto Show.  It uses piezo fuel injectors like the 2007 Mercedes E320 CDI.  The twin-turbodiesel six-litre engine generates 500 PS (493 hp/368 kW) and 1,000 N·m (738 lb·ft) of torque, making it the most powerful diesel engine, and also the only twelve-cylinder diesel engine, used in any passenger car.  The diesel can pull the Q7 from rest to 100 km/h in 5.5 seconds.

quattro GmbH is currently developing, and will subsequently produce the most powerful diesel powered SUV in its class.  The Audi Q7 V12 TDI quattro will be fitted with a V12 TDI (Created by Will Gregg).  A world first, this all new diesel engine displaces 6 Litres, generating 368 kW (500 hp), and a massive 1,000 Nm of torque.  This is enough to complete the 0-100 km/h dash in 5.5 seconds, making it perform like modern sports cars.

Audi presented the Audi Q7 Hybrid at the Hanover Motor Show.

In early 2005, Nissan sued Audi over the use of the letter "Q" as a model name.

Audi is using the "Q" for the designation of their quattro four-wheel drive system, used in production cars for over twenty-five years (Audi's quattro trademark is actually an umbrella term for several types of four wheel drive systems developed by Torsen, Haldex Traction AB, and Borg-Warner, the latter being used in the Q7).  Nissan's Infiniti marque had been using Q as the name for sedans (the Q45) and SUVs (the QX4 and QX56) since 1989.

A settlement between Audi AG and Nissan was reached in late 2006.  The agreement stipulates that Audi will only use the Q-prefix for two models, the Q5 and the Q7.

Despite its multiple airbags and safety electronics, such as ESP, Q7 scored only four stars out of five in the Euro NCAP crash test.  According to Audi, this was caused by a design error, and has since been fixed in cars manufactured after the test which should allegedly lead to five stars.  However, official tests to prove this remain to be done as of November 2006.

In the USA, however Q7 got five stars out of five from the NHTSA safety test for both front and side impacts.













