

Spinal cord injury causes myelopathy or damage to white matter or myelinated fiber tracts that carry sensation and motor signals to and from the brain.  It also damages gray matter in the central part of the spine, causing segmental losses of interneurons and motorneurons.  Spinal cord injury can occur from many causes, including:

The American Spinal Cord Injury Association or ASIA defined an international classification based on neurological levels, touch and pinprick sensations tested in each dermatome, and  strength of ten key muscles on each side of the body, i.e. shoulder shrug (C4), elbow flexion (C5), wrist extension (C6), elbow extension (C7), hip flexion (L2). Traumatic spinal cord injury is classified into five types by the American Spinal Injury Association and the International Spinal Cord Injury Classification System.   

In addition, there are several clinical syndromes associated with incomplete spinal cord injuries.     

One can have spine injury without spinal cord injury.  Many people suffer transient loss of function ("stingers") in sports accidents or pain in "whiplash" of the neck without neurological loss and relatively few of these suffer spinal cord injury sufficient to warrant hospitalization.  In the United States, the incidence of spinal cord injury has been estimated to be about 35 cases per million per year, or approximately 10,500 per year (35 * 300).  In China, the incidence of spinal cord injury was recently estimated to be as high as 65 cases per million per year in urban areas.  If so, assuming a population of 1.3 billion, this would suggest an incidence of 84,500 per year (65 * 1300).   

The prevalence of spinal cord injury is not well known in many large countries.  In some countries, such as Sweden and Iceland, registries are available.  About 450,000 people in the United States live with spinal cord injury (one in 670), and there are about 11,000 new spinal cord injuries every year (one in 30,000). The majority of them (78%) involve males between the ages of 16-30 and result from motor vehicle accidents (42%), violence (24%), or falls (27%). This is likely due to increased risk-taking behavior in men.



The exact effects of a spinal cord injury vary according to the type and level injury, and can be organized into two types:

In addition to a loss of sensation and motor function below the point of injury, individuals with spinal cord injuries will often experience other complications of spinal cord injury:

Knowing the exact level of the injury on the spinal cord is important when predicting what parts of the body might be affected by paralysis and loss of function. 

Below is a list of typical effects of spinal cord injury by location (refer to the spinal cord map to the right). Please keep in mind that while the prognosis of complete injuries are predictable, incomplete injuries are very variable and may differ from the descriptions below.

Cervical (neck) injuries usually result in full or partial tetraplegia (Quadraplegia). Depending on the exact location of the injury, one with a spinal cord injury at the cervical level may retain some amount of function as detailed below, but are otherwise completely paralyzed.



Injuries at the thoracic level and below result in paraplegia. The hands, arms, head, and breathing are usually not affected.



The effect of injuries to the lumbar or sacral region of the spinal canal are decreased control of the legs and hips, urinary system, and anus.



Central cord syndrome (picture 1) is a form of incomplete spinal cord injury characterized by impairment in the arms and hands and, to a lesser extent, in the legs.  This is also referred to as inverse paraplegia, because the hands and arms are paralyzed while the legs and lower extremities work correctly.

Most often the damage is to the cervical or upper thoracic regions of the spinal cord, and characterized by weakness in the arms with relative sparing of the legs with variable sensory loss. 

This condition is associated with ischemia, hemorrhage, or necrosis involving the central portions of the spinal cord (the large nerve fibers that carry information directly from the cerebral cortex). Corticospinal fibers destined for the legs are spared due to their more external location in the spinal cord. 

This clinical pattern may emerge during recovery from spinal shock due to prolonged swelling around or near the vertebrae, causing pressures on the cord.  The symptoms may be transient or permanent.

Anterior cord syndrome (picture 2) is also an incomplete spinal cord injury.  Below the injury, motor function, pain sensation, and temperature sensation is lost; touch, proprioception (sense of position in space), and vibration sense remain intact.  Posterior cord syndrome (not pictured) can also occur, but is very rare.

Brown-Séquard syndrome (picture 3) usually occurs when the spinal cord is hemisectioned or injured on the lateral side.  On the ipsilateral side of the injury (same side), there is a loss of motor function, proprioception, vibration, and light touch.  Contralaterally (opposite side of injury), there is a loss of pain, temperature, and deep touch sensations.

Treatment for acute traumatic spinal cord injuries have consisted of giving a high dose methylprednisolone if the injury occurred within 8 hours.  The recommendation is primarily based on the National Acute Spinal Cord Injury Studies (NASCIS) II and III.  Some of the claims of the studies have been challenged as being from faulty interpretation of the data.

Scientists are investigating many promising avenues of treatment for spinal cord injury.  Thousands of articles in the medical literature describe work, mostly in animal models, aimed at reducing the paralyzing effect of injury to the spinal cord and promoting regrowth of functional nerve fibers. Despite the devastating effects of the condition, commercial funding for spinal cord cure research is limited, owing primarily to the small size of the population of potential beneficiaries. Despite this, a number of experimental treatments have reached controlled human trials. In addition, nerve protection and regeneration strategies are being studied in more common conditions like Alzheimer's Disease, Parkinson's Disease, Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis and Multiple sclerosis.  There are many similarities between these neurodegenerative diseases and spinal cord injury, and this research adds considerable new information relevant to spinal cord injury treatment. 

Advances in the science of spinal cord injury treatment are newsworthy, and considerable media attention is drawn towards new developments. Aside from the use of methylprednisolone, none of these developments have reached even limited use in the clinical care of human spinal cord injury. Around the world, proprietary centers offering stem cell transplants and treatment with neuroregenerative substances are fueled by glowing testimonial reports of neurological improvement. Independent validation of the results of these treatments is lacking.









