

Mister Lonely is a 2007 film directed by Harmony Korine, and co-written with his brother Avi Korine.

The story, according to Celluloid Dreams, is of "a young American man lost in Paris. He scratches out a living as a Michael Jackson look-alike, dancing on the streets, public parks, tourist spots and trade shows. Different from everyone else, he feels as if he's floating between two worlds. During a show in an old people's home Michael Jackson meets Marilyn Monroe. Haunted by her angelic beauty he follows her to a commune in the Highlands, joining her husband Charlie Chaplin and her daughter Shirley Temple. A place where everyone is famous and no-one gets old. Here, The Pope, The Queen of England, Madonna, James Dean and other impersonators build a stage in the hope that the world will visit and watch them perform. Nuns fall out of airplanes and children ride ponies. Everything is beautiful. Until the world shifts, and reality intrudes on their utopian dream."  

The Screen International interview describes specifically  "scenes being shot in an old people's home in the Ville de Bonnueil, an hour outside Paris, and the next day in the Luxembourg Gardens and Montparnasse," that "show typical Korine improvisational touches." It goes on to say: "In the retirement villa, where 'Michael' first meets 'Marilyn', Luna is dressed as a Dangerous-era Jackson, delivering some trademark whoops around some seriously aged Parisian senior citizens, singing, "You're never gonna die, I want you to live forever," as the residents fall asleep in their chairs. Morton proceeds to comfort a nonagenarian non-actor who appears to be hitting himself with a plastic hammer." 



Mister Lonely received mixed reviews from critics. As of May 2, 2008, the review aggregator Rotten Tomatoes reported that 44% of critics gave the film positive reviews, based on 55 reviews — with the consensus that the film is not only "less biting than Korine's earlier works, but frustratingly dull." Metacritic reported the film had an average score of 53 out of 100, based on 21 reviews.

The film opened in the United States in very limited release on May 2, 2008 and grossed $19,100 in 1 theater its opening weekend.

As of May 4, 2008, the film has grossed an estimated $164,304 worldwide — 19,100 in the United States and $145,204 in other territories.

Half of the music for the film was written and performed by Sun City Girls, with the other half being created by Spiritualized frontman, Jason "Spaceman" Pierce





