The current series of Danish banknotes (as of 2007) were introduced during 1997-1999, replacing the 1972 series. During 2002-2005, additional security devices were added. 



The Danish 50 kroner bill (DKK50) is a denomination of Danish currency.  Danish writer Karen Blixen is currently featured on the front side of the bill, while the design on the reverse is inspired by a centaur from Landet Church on the island of Tåsinge.  The current version for this bill came into circulation on 25 August 2005.

The face of the banknote has a portrait of writer Karen Blixen (17 April 1885 to 7 September 1962). She is acclaimed for writing Seven Gothic Tales (1935) and her memoirs Out of Africa (1937). The face of the banknote is also decorated with flowers, of which Karen Blixen was very fond.

The image on the reverse of the 50 krone banknote is inspired by a stone relief from Landet Church on the island of Tåsinge. The 50 krone banknote has the word "femti", not "halvtreds" which is the usual Danish word for fifty. Femti is a word used for cheques. The Danish National bank first used it on the 50 krone banknote issued in 1957, and the present banknote is thus the third to use this word.



The Danish 100 kroner bill (DKK100) is a denomination of Danish currency.  Danish composer Carl Nielsen is featured on the front side of the bill and a basilisk from Tømmerby Church is featured on the reverse.  This version began circulation on 27 November 2002.

The face of the banknote has a portrait of the composer Carl Nielsen (9 June 1865 to 3 October 1931). Carl Nielsen was an orchestra leader, conductor, and music teacher, but above all a very versatile composer.  He is known for writing operas such as Maskerade (1905-06), and many symphonic works.

A basilisk from Tømmerby Kirke in Vester Hanherred in northern Denmark is the inspiration for the motif on reverse of the 100 kroner banknote. A basilisk is part snake, dragon, and rooster. Basilisk means "little king" and the figure is recognisable by its crown. Around half of all Danish banknotes in circulation are 100 kroner banknotes, making it the principal banknote in the series.

The 100 kroner bill is sometimes referred to as a hund (dog) taken from a shortening of the word hundrede (a hundred).



The Danish 200 kroner bill (DKK200) is a denomination of Danish currency.  Danish actress Johanne Luise Heiberg is currently featured on the front side of the bill, while a lion from the apse of Viborg Cathedral is featured on the reverse side.  The current version of this bill came into circulation on 9 April 2003.

The face of the banknote has a portrait of Johanne Luise Heiberg (22 November 1812 to 21 December 1890). She was one of the greatest Danish actresses of the 19th century and took Royal Theatre in Copenhagen by storm on countless occasions. Her autobiography Et liv genoplevet i erindringen (English: A Life Relived in Memory) is a major literary work from the Danish golden age.

The motif on the reverse of the 200 kroner banknote is a lion from the apse of Viborg Cathedral.



The Danish 500 kroner bill (DKK500) is a denomination of Danish currency.  Danish nuclear physicist Niels Bohr (7 October 1885 to 18 November 1962) is featured on the front side of the bill.  Niels Bohr was a major contributor to modern science and was very influential on the development of modern nuclear physics. Niels Bohr won many awards including the Nobel Prize for physics in 1922.

A knight in armour fighting a dragon is featured on the reverse side. The design comes from a stone relief from Lihme Church in northern Jutland.

The current version of this bill came into circulation on 24 September 2003.

The 500 kroner bill is sometimes referred to as a plovmand (ploughman) because previously circulations of the bill featured a picture of a man with a plough.



The Danish thousand-kroner bill (DKK1000) is a denomination of Danish currency.  Danish artists Anna and Michael Ancher are currently featured on the front side of the bill, while a tournament scene inspired by Bislev Church is featured on the reverse side.  It is currently the largest denomination in circulation, and the current version of this bill came into circulation on 25 November 2004.  The banknote is 165 mm x 72 mm.

The front of the banknote has a double portrait of artists Anna and Michael Ancher (18 August 1859 to 15 April 1935, and 9 June 1849 to 19 September 1927). The couple are known for their paintings depicting everyday life in the fishing town of Skagen. The portraits featured on the banknote were inspired by two paintings Danish artist Peder Severin Krøyer made in 1884. The paintings were originally hung on the walls in the dining room at Brøndums Hotel in Skagen. The anchor background pattern on the banknote does not directly refer to the artists' surname (anker means anchor in Danish), but to a necklace worn by Anna. 

A tournament scene from a sepulchral monument located in Bislev Church in northern Jutland is the inspiration for the motif on the back of the banknote.

The 1000 kroner bill is sometimes referred to as a tudse (toad) taken from a wordplay on the word tusinde (a thousand).

The design of each banknote in the series incorporates various security devices. When the banknotes are tilted, various motifs appear in the hologram. Also, fluorescent colours, which are visible under ultraviolet light, are used on both sides of the banknotes.

50 kroner: The hologram alternately shows the figure 50, the Roman numeral L and a flower. Fluorescent effects: Centaur on obverse and green print on the reverse.

100 kroner: Hologram: Two musical notes, the Roman numeral "C." and the number "100." When the note is tilted the "C" grows larger and a rainbow appears. Using a magnifying glass, it is possible to see a microprinted "100" in the outer line around the letter "C." Fluorescent effects: Basilisk on obverse and orange print on the reverse.

200 kroner: Hologram: A lion, the Roman numeral "CC," and the number "200." When the note is tilted the "CC" grows larger. Fluorescent effects: Lion on obverse and green print on the reverse.

500 kroner: Hologram: An atom, the number 500, and the Roman numeral "D". The current version of the 500 kroner banknote was designed to be very hard to counterfeit. The hologram cannot be colour copied. Fluorescent effects: Knight on obverse and orange print on the reverse.

1000 kroner: 1000 kroner: Hologram: A palette, the number 1000 and the Roman numeral "M". Fluorescent effects: Horseman on obverse and orange print on the reverse.



