

QSR International is the world’s largest qualitative research software developer. It is based in Melbourne, Australia, with offices in the United Kingdom and the United States. QSR International develops qualitative data analysis (QDA) software products designed to help qualitative researchers organize and analyze non-numerical or unstructured data.

More than 450 organizations hold site licenses for QSR software and the company has 350,000 clients across 90 countries. QSR’s customers are drawn from the academic, government and commercial sectors and its largest geographic markets are Europe, the United States and Australia. 

QSR International is a Microsoft Gold Certified Partner and has launched eight major software releases in the last 10 years, and many more minor releases.

QSR International’s software products – XSight and NVivo – are both designed to help researchers and other people working with non-numerical or unstructured data to compile, compare and make sense of their information quickly and easily.

XSight is designed for commercial market researchers or those undertaking short term qualitative research projects. The software provides a range of analysis frameworks for importing, classifying and arranging data; tools for testing theories and connections between items; and the ability to visually map and report thoughts and findings. XSight was first released in 2004.

NVivo is a Qualitative Data Analysis (QDA) software package designed for qualitative researchers working with very rich text-based and/or mulitimedia information, where deep levels of analysis on small or large volumes of data are required. NVivo was first released in 1999, although it supersedes the NUD*IST product range which was first released in 1981.



The first generation of computer-assisted qualitative data analysis (QDA) software emerged in the mid to late 1980s and involved basic word processors and databases with a focus on data management. The programs were designed to help qualitative researchers manage unstructured information like open-ended surveys, focus groups, field notes or interviews.  

Second generation QDA software introduced functions for coding text and for manipulating, searching and reporting on the coded text.  The approach of employing software tools for qualitative analysis was initially developed in the social sciences arena but is now used in an extensive range of other disciplines.

The third generation of QDA software goes beyond manipulating, searching and reporting on coded text.  It assists actual analysis of the data by providing tools to help researchers examine relationships in the data and assist in the development of theories and in testing hypotheses. Some software supports rich text, diagrams and the incorporation of images, movies and other multimedia data. Other programs have tools that enable the exchange of data and analyses between researchers working together collaboratively.



