

The Channel Seven Perth Telethon, also known simply as Telethon, is an annual telethon produced by TVW, a Seven Network owned television station in Perth, Western Australia for three main beneficiaries; Princess Margaret Hospital for Children, the Telethon Institute for Child Health Research and the Telethon Speech and Hearing Centre. It is regarded as the most successful fundraising event per capita in the world, raising over AUD$85 million in its 41-year history.

The Channel 7 Telethon Trust is the charitable trust behind the event and its related fundraising activities.

The event is a 26 hour, almost continuous live broadcast aired across Western Australia on TVW and the Golden West Network, held at the Perth Convention Exhibition Centre. The event raises money from donations from private citizens and corporations, as well as from special fundraising events and the public auction of a specially built Telethon home.

Stars from Seven Network shows such as Home and Away, Sunrise and All Saints make the journey west for the weekend to entertain the audience, visit sick children and read donations on air. In addition, musical guests are also a big part of the weekend. Over the years many acts including Sir Cliff Richard, Michael Jackson, Harry Connick Jr., Whitney Houston, Stevie Wonder, Tina Turner, Julian Lennon, Sammy Davis Jr. and Céline Dion have performed during Telethon.

In recent years Weekend Sunrise has broadcast the event live for two hours across the rest of Australia.

Telethon first began in 1968, when the Trust was established by a group of senior executives at TVW. Before moving to the Perth Convention Exhibition Centre, it was previously held at the Burswood Dome and the Seven Studios at Tuart Hill.

2007 marked 40 years since Telethon began in Western Australia. Telethon Weekend 2007 raised more than $6.5 million. This was more than double the previous record amount of $3 million. Telethon 2008 raised a further $7.5 million, with the Australian Federal Government contributing $1.5 million, and a lottery winner donating $1 million of her winnings to the cause. The 2008 event also featured an Australian rules football match in tribute to Chris Mainwaring, a former West Coast Eagles player and TVW sports presenter who had died the previous year.





