Eagles for St Jude is a program created during Stanford Financial Group’s inaugural sponsorship year of the Stanford St. Jude Championship out of the desire to provide a season-long fundraising component to the Memphis PGA tournament.  The tournament raises money for St. Jude Children's Research Hospital, the world’s premier pediatric cancer research center.   Eagles for St. Jude benefits St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital and is sponsored by Stanford Financial Group, which in 2007 assumed title sponsorship of the Stanford St. Jude Championship, a top PGA Tour event that has benefited St. Jude since 1970.   The Eagles for St. Jude program is also supported by The Golf Channel, which provides season-long updates and promotional support for Eagles for St. Jude. 

For each eagle carded on the PGA and LPGA TOUR during the 2008 season, Stanford Financial Group will donate $1,000 per eagle to the Eagles for St. Jude campaign. Additionally, Vijay Singh, who serves as the Eagles for St. Jude Ambassador, is personally donating $5,000 for every eagle he makes during the 2008 season and Camilo Villegas will donate $3,000 for each of his eagles.  

Fans of the PGA and LPGA TOUR are encouraged to participate in the program by either donating per eagle carded by Vijay Singh, per eagle recorded by any PGA or LPGA professional on the tour, or by making a one-time donation to the Eagles for St. Jude program.  A scorecard is available on www.eaglesforstjude.com that provides fans the opportunity to view the cumulative number of eagles carded for Singh and other PGA TOUR professionals. In addition, visitors can view the Eagles for St. Jude commercial featuring Singh and St. Jude patients and read about patients that are featured in the commercial.  

During the 2007 PGA TOUR, 1,222 eagles were made, which resulted in Stanford Financial Group donating $1,222,000 to the Eagles for St. Jude program.  Eagles for St. Jude Ambassador Vijay Singh, who made 12 eagles and was slated to donate $1,000 per eagle, donated $50,000 for the 2007 season, a $38,000 donation above his commitment.   

Full listAs of the end of the 2007 season.

Professional golfer Vijay Singh is featured in their commercials. Their motto is:



