 

Evilhawk is a fictional character in the Marvel Universe.

Evilhawk is a reptilian alien from the planet Luq with an android body.  He is an enemy of Darkhawk.

Dargin Bokk is an alien who was born on the planet Luq. He later became an intergalactic crime-lord, using his resources to commission five scientists to create the Darkhawk androids. But when the scientists eventually used it to assault Bokk, he manages to take one of the crystals and uses it to assume the Darkhawk body called Evilhawk. However, in the ensuing fight, as the starship is sucked into Null Space, Bokk's original body was destoryed in the explosion, trapping him in his android body.

Eventually, Evilhawk learned that of Chris Powell has gained access to the Darkhawk technology and traveled to Earth to face him. When he arrived on Earth, Evilhawk confronted Darkhawk. Evilhawk attacks Darkhawk, destorying his android body as his conscious ended up in his human body within the starship. Evilhawk battled St. Johnny and the Powell family before returning to the starship to execute his place, transfering his mind into Chris' body. But the plan failed and Evilhawk's was destroyed by Darkhawk.

Bokk later battled Osch, one of the aliens who helped build the Evilhawk armor, on the psychic plane, but failed to create a new android body for himself.

Like Darkhawk, Evilhawk's body is an android body powered by the extraterrestrial amulet he wears. The body was designed and manufactured by Mondu, Mendeja, Byron, Graczia, Kig, and Osch. The Evilhawk body has enhanced physical abilities, including strength, durability, agility and reflexes. He has a claw-cable on his right hand which can be propelled as a grappling hook, and he has retractable glider wings enabling him to fly. He also has the ability to project concussive Darkforce blasts and defense shields from his body using his amulet as a focal point. He possesses telescopic and infra-red vision, and possibly other powers as yet unrevealed, plus (theoretically) the ability to heal from almost any wound by reverting to his original form. Evilhawk was originally unable to use his healing power because his original body had been destroyed, when his Evilhawk android body was destroyed, he existed only as a disembodied consciousness.

Dargin Bokk was a skilled planner and organizer, and learned the basic hand-to-hand combat skills known on the planet Luq.

