For other persons named Samuel Wood, see Samuel Wood. 

Samuel H. Wood is a scientist noted for donating DNA that was used in somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT) to produce mature human embryos that were clones of Dr Wood. In January 2008, Wood and Andrew French, Stemagen's chief scientific officer in California, announced that they had successfully created the first 5 mature human embryos using DNA from adult skin cells, aiming to provide a less-controversial source of viable embryonic stem cells. Dr. Wood and a colleague donated skin cells, and the DNA from those cells was transferred to human eggs. It is not clear if the embryos produced would have been capable of further development, but Dr. Wood stated that if that were possible, using the technology for reproductive cloning would be both unethical and illegal.  The 5 cloned embryos, created in Stemagen Corporation lab, in La Jolla, were later destroyed.

Dr. Wood is an M.D. and a Ph.D., and is an acclaimed reproductive endocrinologist in San Diego who specializes in infertility. He is the founder and Medical Director at Reproductive Sciences Center and the surrogacy agency, the Select Surrogate. In addition to being a medical doctor, Dr. Wood's distinguished academic background includes a Master's degree in Psychology and a Ph.D. in Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics. After a residency in Obstetrics and Gynecology at the University of North Carolina, he completed a fellowship in Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility at UCSD and is Board Certified in both Obstetrics and Gynecology and Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, achieving both certifications in the minimal time possible. He is also  CEO of Stemagen corporation.

Dr. Wood and five other researchers published their findings in the online research journal Stem Cells, in an article entitled Development of Human cloned Blastocyst Following Somatic Cell Nuclear Transfer (SCNT) with Adult Fibroblasts.

Miodrag Stojković, a researcher and peer reviewer of the paper publishing the findings, responded to critics' claims that the work is not groundbreaking:  "Stemagen's work is the first time anyone has documented that this could be done with adult skin cells." 



