The Philippine Children's Fund of America is a non-profit organization registered under the state of California and is duly recognized by the United States Federal Government. It is based in San Francisco, CA., with a Philippine office in Clark Field, Angeles City. Philippine Children's Fund of America is the most widely supported Filipino-American non-profit organization in the United States. 

Was created by the US and Philippine governments in 1991. To assist impoverished Filipino children of American ancestry by providing educational scholarships, employment and working visas to the United States. Philippine Children's Fund of America envisions a stable and viable community that will uphold the rights, welfare and aspiration of Filipino families especially the children towards authentic human development.   Philippine Children's Fund of America was founded to serve the needs of children left behind by the U.S. military closure. Pearl S. Buck International foundation estimates there are 52,000 Amerasian scattered throughout the Philippines. "The majority of the children have been abandoned by their American fathers," said Jocelyn Bonilla, the manager of the Pearl S. Buck center in Angeles City. Today it's serving more children, families and communities including 150 charitable groups all over the Philippines. Serving poor children including those left behind from the closure of US bases. Provides transitional home for American children we fly from the Philippines. 

Designed to provide educational assistance to poor but deserving children. By providing the poor access to education, the chances of improving the Filipino family's very infavorable condition caused by extreme poverty could be strengthened. Children can now enjoy their right to education, families will be more empowered, hence, better lives and stronger communities.

 By definition, an Amer-Asian is any person fathered by a citizen of the United States of America (i.e. an American servicemen, expatriate, or government employee whether government or contractual) and whose mother is or was an Asian national. 

Is a program designed to help Non-Government Agencies in the Philippines raise their own funds so that they will be able to push for quality development programs and services for the needy Filipino community. It is conceived to be an effective fund raising activity that will not require the participating agencies to invest any capital/resources in risky fund sourcing ventures.

Is a fund raising program of the Philippine Childrens Fund of America (PCFA) designed to provide funding on different programs of the organization.

Is a joint project of the Philippine Childrens Fund (PCF) and the Angeles City government. Along Sto. Entierro St. at the City Library and Information Center, the ACCL is an interactive library which houses a wide selection of books, toys and other learning materials that the kids enjoy. 

"Build Better Lives and Stronger Communities", 

Head office is based in San Francisco, CA. They have a Philippine office in Clark Field, Angeles City. 



