Daniel Dorff (born March 7, 1956 in New Rochelle, New York) is an American composer. He graduated magna cum laude from Cornell University and earned his master's degree in composition from the University of Pennsylvania, studying composition with George Crumb, George Rochberg, Karel Husa, Henry Brant, Ralph Shapey, Elie Siegmeister, and Richard Wernick. Dorff is currently composer-in-residence for the Haddonfield Symphony. His works have been commissioned by such ensembles as the Philadelphia Orchestra and the Minnesota Orchestra, and performed by groups and individuals including the Baltimore Symphony, Eastman Wind Ensemble, Chicago Symphony chamber ensembles, pianist Marc-André Hamelin, clarinetist John Bruce Yeh, and flutist Donald Peck. He has also created arrangements for Sir James Galway and pop musicians Keith Emerson and Lisa Loeb.

Dorff has written works for orchestra, concert band, piano, chorus, and a variety of chamber ensembles, including often neglected instruments as contrabassoon, piccolo, and tenor saxophone. He has taken a particular interest in exposing young people to classical music; many of his works are written for young audiences, including Three Fun Fables, a setting for narrator and orchestra of familiar Aesop tales; Billy and the Carnival, a narrated guide to the instruments of the orchestra; Blast Off!, a travelog of a trip to outer space (the score to which was flown by NASA on the 100th mission of the Space Shuttle); and familiar stories such as Goldilocks and the Three Bears and The Three Little Pigs.

In addition to his compositional career, Dorff is a clarinetist and saxophonist; he was previously bass clarinetist for the Haddonfield Symphony, as well as having performed his own works. He frequently lectures on music engraving and notation, a subject he is expert in. Dorff is currently vice president of publishing for music publisher Theodore Presser Company; his input has also been sought in the development of leading music notation software.



