Viktor Kalabis (1923–2006) was a Czech composer. 

Born in Červený Kostelec, a town in the Czech Republic, on February 27, 1923, Kalabis was an important 20th century Czech composer. Viktor was interested in music from a young age, but due to the Nazi occupation of Prague during the Second World War, he was unable to study music in Prague.  After the end of the war, Kalabis studied at the Prague Conservatory and at the Academy of Music and Charles University.  

In 1952, Kalabis married Zuzana Růžičková, who became a famous harpsichord player.  They both refused to join the Communist party, making the beginning of their music careers difficult. Eventually, Viktor got work in the children's music section at Prague Radio.  It was in this post that he established the now internationally known Concertino Praga competition for young musicians. 

He truly established himself as an international composer when in 1957, Manuel Rosenthal performed Kalabis' Concert for violoncello op. 8 at the Orchestera de Paris at the Theatre de Champs Élysée.  Many of his works were commissioned, for example, by the Czech Philharmony, the Dresden Philharmony, Camerata Zurich, Josef Suk, The Suk Trio, János Starker, Maurice André, The Prague Spring Festival and many others. His composition Sinfonia pacis is one of the world's most-played Czech contemporary music compositions. 

Although most of the works of Viktor Kalabis are symphonic, concertante or chamber compositions, his vocal works such as the cantata Canticum Canticorum, the chamber cantata Vojna (The War), song cycles and choruses are of a similar high standard.  For stage he was written the Fable for chamber orchestra and the two-part ballet score Two Worlds, inspired by Lewis Carroll's book Alice's Adventures in Wonderland.  The video recording of this ballet was given the "Parents' Choice Award" of 1993 in the United States. In 1967, he received the Prize of the Czechoslovak Music Critics and in 1969 he was awarded the State Prize.

In an interview with Ales Brezina, a close friend of Kalabis, he described Viktor's musical influence.

"I would place his music not only in the Czech context but also in the European one, because he was a well educated man who spoke several languages fluently and was interested in everything that happened – also in philosophy and other things. And I would say that his music started where the masters of neo-classicism stopped. His beginnings in the fifties and in the early sixties were deeply influenced by people like Stravinsky and Hindemith, and Honegger and Bartók – and Martinů of course."

Eventually, Kalabis became President of the Bohuslav Martinů Foundation. Here he established the Bohuslav Martinů Institute for studies and information, launched the Martinů Festival and competition, and created a dynamic base from which Bohuslav Martinů’s work has become far better known.

Kalabis died on September 28, 2006.  The Viktor Kalabis &amp; Zuzana Růžičková Foundation was established in his memory. Růžičková is the President of the Board of Directors for the Foundation and is dedicated to promoting Kalabis' music throughout the world.

Classical music editor, Rob Barnett, describes a number of Kalabis's compositions:

"The Harpsichord Concerto is dedicated to the composer's wife whose eminent recordings of the Poulenc and Martinů concertos have for years been staples of first the LP catalogue and latterly the CD. Kalabis's concerto is in three movements. The outer ones have the notes rushing in pealing relentlessly Gothic torrents with the instrument probably recorded with much more prominence than you would hear in the concert hall."

"The Violin Concerto starts with awesome spleen but rapidly establishes itself in Olympian realms. This is a contemplative kingdom half way between Bax and Rawsthorne. This continues through the middle movement. The allegro vivace is almost Walton – almost Frankel. The concerto is dedicated to the memory of Hana Webrová-Hlavsová who died under tragic circumstances in 1960. This work has some superbly lyrical Mediterranean sunset writing – especially in the finale. Quite a discovery, I should say."

"The Largo is the oldest recording in this anthology – not that it sounds deficient. It is tough going – not specially dissonant but certainly bleak. The music retains long lines but it is, overall, a rather fatalistic piece with little to hold the hope of rising from the gloom. The notewriter suggests that its negative charge reflected life in a totalitarian society. Impressive if not endearing is the writing for the horns of the Czech Philharmonic, the orchestra who commissioned the piece."

The Viktor Kalabis and Zuzana Růžičková Foundation has the following list of musical compositions. 

Ballets



Symphonies



Symphonic music



Instrumental concertos



Compositions for chamber orchestra



String quartets



Piano quartet



Nonets



Compositions for wind instruments



Duos with piano



Duos with harpsichord



Duos for other instrumentation



Piano



Harpsichord



Violoncello



Flute



French horn



Guitar



Organ



Vocal Compositions



Songs with orchestral accompaniment



Mixed choirs

Children choirs





