

The Citrus industry in the Caribbean is a major one in the Caribbean. Citrus fruits consists of oranges, pineapples, grapefruit, tangerines, limes, &amp; lemons. The Caribbean countries which export citrus fruit are Belize, Jamaica, Puerto Rico, Guadeloupe, Dominica, Martinique &amp; Trinidad &amp; Tobago.



The industry is an important one is it provides foreign revenue. In Belize, citrus fruit formed 14.1% of the exports in 1998 &amp; brought in BZD$43.16 million dollars. The Caribbean exports citrus fruits in various forms such as in its normal form or processed into canned juices, canned segments, canned fruit and essential oils. Citrus products are exported to the United Kingdom, Canada, United States and other countries. 

Citrus production, along with sugar and bananas are the main agricultural exports. The main producing areas are the Pomona Valley and the Stann Creek Valley in the Stann Creek District. The 1999 output included 170,000 tons of oranges and 41,000 tons of grapefruit. About 40 square kilometres are under cultivation in the Stann Creek Valley with grapefruit occupying 25% of this area. Citrus is canned in the Stann Creek Valley where there are two processing plants. The harvesting season extends from August until the early part of the following year.

Citrus production in Jamaica isn't a large industry like bauxite or sugar but it is enough for local consumption and for exporting. The main producing areas are the weathered limestone soil in the parishes of Clarendon, St.Catherine, St.Mary, St. Ann Manchester &amp; Westmoreland, growing between elevations of 1,000 feet (300 m) to 2,500 feet (760 m). Processing plants are located at Bog Walk, May Pen &amp; Kingston. The harvesting season extends from November to April.

Citrus production in Dominica is a major export, also with bananas and coconuts. The main producing areas are in the Layou River Valley and on the southwest coast. In 1999, 21,000 tons of grapefruit, 1,000 tons of lemons and limes and  8,000 tons of oranges were produced.











