

"Homer's Barbershop Quartet" is the first episode of The Simpsons' fifth season. It features the Be-Sharps, a fictional barbershop quartet founded by Homer, whose story roughly parallels that of The Beatles. The episode was written by Jeff Martin, directed by Mark Kirkland, while George Harrison and David Crosby guest starred as themselves, and The Dapper Dans as the singing voices of "The Be-Sharps".

At the Springfield Swap Meet, Bart and Lisa notice Homer's face on an album cover. Homer explains that he, Principal Skinner, Barney, and Apu recorded a barbershop quartet album in 1985, which catapulted them to national fame. 

This development came after an agent, Nigel, offered to be their representative on the condition they expel original member Chief Wiggum, who was "too Village People."  After rejecting many auditions for a fourth member, the barbershop trio returned downheartedly to Moe's Tavern, where they recruited Barney after hearing him sing in a beautiful Irish tenor voice. The group considered "Handsome Homer Simpson Plus Three" (suggested by Nigel), finally calling themselves "The Be Sharps."  They had decided their name should be initially witty, yet become less funny each time you heard it.

Back in modern times, Homer brags that he sold a spare tire at the swap meet; unfortunately, on the way home their tire blows out. While Marge begins her long walk to a gas station, Homer continues the story. He tells Bart and Lisa that after Marge bought a "Baby On Board" sign, Homer wrote a song inspired by the fad. "Baby on Board" appeared on their first album, Meet the Be Sharps, and became a hit. The group performed the song at the Statue of Liberty's centennial in 1986. The Be Sharps also won a Grammy for "Outstanding Soul, Spoken Word, or Barbershop Album of the Year", and Homer met George Harrison. Meanwhile, Wiggum's singing career (now dead) was being mocked by numerous talk show hosts.

At home, Homer explains that the Be Sharps were on merchandise (similar to the Beatlemania craze) - such as lunch boxes, mugs, posters, etc. When Lisa pulls out a bottle of Be Sharps Funny Foam, Homer says that it was pulled off the market when it was discovered to be poisonous. The name of their second album was Bigger than Jesus. While the Be Sharps were becoming popular, Marge was having problems raising the children, and the Be Sharps also had their own issues. Creative disputes arose when Barney began dating a  Japanese conceptual artist, and Barney left the group in all but name. The two recorded a song in which his girlfriend repeatedly says "Number 8" over tape loops of Barney's belches (a nod to the Beatles song "Revolution 9"). Ultimately, the group realizes they had lost their popularity and were no longer hot, according to the latest issue of Us Weekly's What's Hot and What's Not, and splits up.  Principal Skinner returns to Springfield Elementary School, and Homer returns to the Springfield Nuclear Power Plant.

At the end of the episode, the group reunites to perform a concert on Moe's roof singing their number one hit "Baby on Board". Many passers-by stop to hear them sing their comeback concert, including George Harrison who remarks, "It's been done."

The following can be seen on the Season 5 DVD set:











