"Eurovision 2009" redirects here. For the Dance Contest, see Eurovision Dance Contest 2009. 



The Eurovision Song Contest 2009 will be the 54th Eurovision Song Contest, scheduled to take place between the 12 May and 16 May 2009. It will be held in Russia with the host venue confirmed as the Olympic Indoor Arena within Moscow. Changes in the voting procedure will occur with the re-introduction of a national jury alongside televoting. Thirty one countries have confirmed their participation in the 2009 contest, including Slovakia, which will return to the contest after 11 years. Georgia has announced that it is withdrawing from the contest, and seven further countries are undecided on if they will participate.

The contest will be held in Russia following its victory in the 2008 contest in Belgrade, Serbia with Dima Bilan's "". Vladimir Putin, Prime Minister of Russia, has stated that the contest will be held in Moscow and it was proposed by the host broadcaster, Channel One, that the contest be held in the Olympic Indoor Arena within Moscow. The Director-General of the venue, Vladimir Churilin refuted rumors of emergency reconstruction of building, saying: "It will not be required for the Eurovision Song Contest. We now can take up to 25 thousands of spectators. According to preliminary projections, for the Eurovision we will have around 12 to 15 thousands of spectators in the hall. There will be about 2.5 thousand of participants, and together with the organizers and the press we're expecting up to 8 thousands guests". . This proposal was evaluated by the European Broadcasting Union (EBU) and confirmed on 13 September 2008.

Discussion on the format of the 2009 Eurovision Song Contest took place at a EBU meeting in Athens, Greece in June 2008. A proposal was made that could have resulted in the "Big Four" countries (France, Germany, Spain and the United Kingdom) losing their automatic place in the final of the contest. However, it has been confirmed that the "Big Four" countries will continue to automatically qualify for the final at the 2009 contest.

In response to some broadcasters' continued complaints about politically charged, neighbourly and diaspora voting, the EBU evaluated the voting procedure used in the contest, with the possibility of a change in the voting system for 2009.  Contest organisers sent a questionnaire regarding the voting system to participating broadcasters, and a reference group incorporated the responses into their suggestions for next year's format. Telewizja Polska (TVP), the Polish broadcaster, suggested that an international jury similar to the one used in the 2008 Eurovision Dance Contest be introduced in the Eurovision Song Contest to lessen the impact of neighbourly voting and place more emphasis on the artistic value of the song. It has since been confirmed that for the contest final, each country's votes will be decided by a combination of televoting results and a national jury, though the exact mix of each component has yet to be confirmed. The method of selecting the semi-final qualifiers will remain the same, however, with nine countries in each semi-final qualifying based on televoting results and the tenth coming from the juries. Details on the jury method will be released after another Reference Group meeting in December. National juries were originally phased out of the contest beginning in 1997, and televoting became mandatory for nearly all participants beginning in 2003.

Edgar Böhm, director of entertainment for Austria's public broadcaster Österreichischer Rundfunk (ORF), has stated that the 2008 format with two semi-finals "still incorporates a mix of countries who will be politically favoured in the voting process," and "that, unless a clear guideline as to how the semifinals are organised is made by the EBU, Austria will not be taking part in Moscow 2009." Despite the inclusion of jury voting in the final, Austria will not return to the contest in 2009, but will broadcast the final on ORF as it did in 2008.

















