

"The Bart Wants What it Wants" is the eleventh episode of The Simpsons' thirteenth season. The episode aired on February 17, 2002. 

The episode opens with a car/helicopter chase. The Simpsons are fleeing olympic officials after Homer has stolen the Olympic torch. After being talked to by Marge, she snatches it from Homer, then throws it out the window. The torch is then grabbed by the helicopter guys, and they admire the beautiful flame, forgetting to steer, causing it to crash (extinguising the flame in the process). After the whole ordeal, the family visits a private school-held carnival. A girl, Greta (Rainier Wolfcastle's daughter), is being bullied, and Bart saves her. She likes Bart so much that she invites him to the Wolfcastle family house. Later, the Wolfcastles come to the Simpson house. Bart comes with Milhouse to visit Greta, who invites Bart to her school dance. However, Bart is very much looking forward to seeing Principal Skinner perform stand-up comedy, à la Jerry Seinfeld at a local club. Since the events occur on the same night, Bart chooses to go to the club. Bart is impressed that Skinner's "comedy" act is a bomb.

Later, Bart breaks up with Greta after he thinks that women are easy to deal with. After Bart attempts to apologize to Greta, she dates Milhouse as revenge. Bart is shocked. It only gets worse when she says she and Milhouse will join her dad in Toronto to shoot a movie. Bart asks the family to join him in going to Toronto. Bart finds Greta at a movie studio named Paramountie Studios (a parody of Paramount Pictures), but after Bart and Milhouse get in a big fight that ends up interrupting a curling match, Greta declares she has no interest whatsoever in either Bart or Milhouse. The boys then reconcile and become part of Canada's basketball team.

Although the episode was written by John Frink and Don Payne, the idea was pitched by Joel H. Cohen and Tim Long, both of whom are Canadian.



The episode received a mediocre review in the Toronto Star. Reviewer Hannah Sung said it "wasn't entirely bad, but the payoff didn't match the hype" (In Canada, the episode had been hyped for weeks, if not months). She said that the third act in the city of Toronto was a disappointment and "really just a sloppy amalgamation of every Canadian joke we've ever been told by Americans that lose their punch after the millionth time."





