Coordinates: 37°40′16.3″N 106°20′49″W﻿ / ﻿37.671194, -106.34694

Patriot Bible University, formerly known as Patriot University, is an unaccredited fundamentalist Christian correspondence school located in Del Norte, Colorado. Critics charge it is a diploma mill, lacking sufficient academic standards to award degrees.

Patriot is not accredited by any recognized accreditation body.  As such, its degrees may not be acceptable to employers or other institutions, and use of degree titles may be restricted or illegal in some jurisdictions.{|Cat:}

It was established in 1979 as Patriot University in Dallas, Texas at the home of school founder Lonnie Skinner. Then in 1985 it became affiliated with Hilltop Baptist Church in Colorado Springs.  

Beginning in March 1988 the school was authorized by the State of Colorado Higher Education Commission to issue "religious degrees". In July 2004, the school changed its name to Patriot Bible University and moved out of College Heights Baptist Church and into a building in the small town of 1,700 people in Del Norte, Colorado. Currently, Skinner remains a director and instructor at Patriot in addition to being a Baptist pastor.



In 1997 Patriot's street address was also listed as the residential address of Lonnie Skinner. As of 2007, Patriot's address is listed by Zabasearch.com as the residence of Lonnie Skinner and the Skinner family (Lonnie, Toni, and possibly Rachael). Also as of 2007 it has a total of four employees.

According to Patriot's website it issues approximately 50 to 100 Christian religious degrees (Bachelor's, Master's and Doctorates) per year, and has about 400 active distance learning based students.



Steve Levicoff's Name It and Frame It? New Opportunities in Adult Education and How to Avoid Being Ripped Off by 'Christian' Degree Mills (4th ed., 1995) listed Patriot Bible University as a degree mill. The college has varied its policies over the years, but it has been criticized for awarding students degrees based on questionable standards such as "life experience" or "ministry evaluation" that lack academic rigour and merit. 

The university is not accredited by any recognized accreditation associations of higher learning. It is recognized by the American Accrediting Association of Theological Institutions, which has no recognition from the United States Department of Education or any other government educational organization. The AAATI is itself considered an accreditation mill. The group provides approval to schools for a $100 charge.



Critics have charged that Patriot Bible University is a diploma mill as it has unreasonably low graduation requirements, lack of sufficient faculty or educational standards, and a suspicious tuition scheme, among other issues. The college itself has claimed that it simply does not "choose" to be accredited by standard associations. The school's current policies allow students to attain bachelor's degrees, master's degrees and even "Doctor of Ministry" degrees in months, rather than years, for as little as $25 per month plus books. The university offers a monthly fee, unlike most universities, which only charge per-credit fees. The school's catalog contains course descriptions but no listing of the school's faculty or their credentials. 

Much of the criticism of Patriot is leveled at the controversial creationist evangelist Kent Hovind, who received M.A. and Ph.D. degrees at Patriot in 1989 and 1991 respectively, both in Christian Education.  Hovind's use of the title "Doctor" in particular has provoked extensive scrutiny of his education credentials and his dissertation.

Doctoral dissertations from reputable institutions are published by the awarding institution and generally lodged with university libraries, as well as being made available to other scholars conducting research in similar areas. However, Patriot will not supply copies of Hovind's doctoral dissertation except with his permission. Although one copy of the dissertation is on file at the National Center for Science Education (NCSE) the organization is not able to provide it on request because of copyright and distribution restrictions.

Various criticisms have been made of Hovind's dissertation, including charges of incompleteness, low academic quality, poor writing, poor spelling, and ungrammatical style. The lack of quality was described, in part, by the fact that "the pages are not numbered; there is no title; of sixteen or so chapters in the index only the first four are finished; misspellings are rampant ("Immerged" for emerged and "epic" for epoch are two examples); and the single illustration was apparently cut out of a science book with scissors and fastened to the thesis with glue or tape."

Hovind's testimonial appears on Patriot Bible's website.





