For a complete overview of all Taurus models, see Ford Taurus.

The Second-generation Ford Taurus is an automobile produced by the Ford Motor Company from 1992 to 1995, which served as the second out of six generations of the Ford Taurus.

The second-generation Taurus shared all of its mechanical parts with the First-generation Ford Taurus, yet its exterior and interior was nearly completely redesigned. However, its exterior strongly resembled that of the first-generation Taurus, leading many to falsely believe that the second-generation was simply a face-lift of the first-generation Taurus.  This is partially true, however, as the wagon model from the B-pillar back was a carryover from the first-generation. This generation of Taurus proved to be very popular, selling 410,000 units in its first year, becoming the best selling car in the United States. It would hold this title until 1995, when it was discontinued and replaced with the Third-generation Ford Taurus. 

The exterior of this generation was completely redesigned from the previous one. Its length was increased by a few inches, and was a couple of hundred pounds heavier than the previous generation. Every body panel, save for the doors, was redesigned. However, many of the redesigned components closely resembled that of the previous generation, leading many to falsely believe that this generation is just a face-lift of the previous generation.

The front nose was redesigned with slimmer headlights, while retaining the first generation's "bottom breather" nose, albeit in a more aerodynamically efficient design that flowed into the front bumper.  In the rear, it received new taillights that closely resembled those of the previous generation, as well as an entirely new rear clip. The trunk was also redesigned, with a spoiler being integrated into the trunk lid's design to make the car more aerodynamically efficient. Also with this generation, each model of Taurus received different exterior trim. The lowest level Taurus L had light grey plastic mirrors and window trim, while the bumpers and side trim were also light grey. The GL, the mid priced model, got chrome window trim and body color mirrors, while still retaining the grey bumpers and side trim. The top-of-the-line LX model had its bumpers color keyed, as well as having the grey side trim replaced with color keyed body cladding. 1992 L and GL models (and the Mercury Sable GS) could also be ordered with a two-tone paint job, in which instead of being grey, the bumpers and side trim were painted a slightly darker shade of the vehicle's body color.  To cut costs, this was discontinued for the 1993 model year, as all models received color-matched trim and bumpers from that year onward.

The interior was also completely redesigned for 1992. The Taurus received a new dashboard that, like the previous generation, was designed to be user friendly.  Like the previous generation, it had all of the vehicle's main controls located near the left side of the dash, to be within the easy reach of the driver. Also like the previous generation, all of the controls were designed to be recognizable by touch, and to be operated by the driver without taking their eyes off the road.  The new dash also contained three buttons by the gauge cluster that allowed the driver to operate the radio without taking their eyes off the road. The radio was also redesigned, while the rest of the lower dash was carried over from the previous generation, as was the steering wheel. The new dash was also designed to contain a passenger's side airbag, a first of its kind.  It was optional in 1992, and became standard in 1994, making the Taurus the first car of its kind to have standard dual front airbags.

The seats and door panels were also redesigned. The new door panels contained integrated armrests, with the controls for the power windows and locks mounted flat on its frontal part, allowing the driver to operate them without moving their arm. These switches, along with all of the main controls, would become illuminated when toe headlights were turned on, allowing the driver to easily see them at night. 

Unlike the previous generation, the interior was not as customizable in this generation, and many options that were previously available were cut for 1992. This generation now only used a single seat design shared upon all models (The first generation LX got its own unique seat design), and was only available in two configurations; with a front bench seat and a column mounted shifter, or with front bucket seats and a center console with a floor mounted shifter. The console was a carryover from the previous generation, although it was redesigned for 1993.

Main article: List of Ford Taurus models#Second generationFor 1992, the Taurus was available in three models; L, GL, and LX. Just like the first generation, the L was the most basic model, the GL was the mid priced value model, and the LX was the most luxurious model. Due to poor sales, the L was dropped after 1992, leaving the GL as the entry level model. For the 1995 model year, a new SE model was added, intended to be a budget version of the SHO. It was a step above the entry level GL, a step below the top of the line LX, and came standard with front bucket seats and a center console with a floor mounted shifter, as well as a rear spoiler borrowed from the SHO. The SE was never available as a wagon.

The second generation also came in a modified Police version. A police Taurus was a GL trim with the 3.8 litre Essex V6 engine that was slightly different than the regular Essex engine. Output of the police Essex version was 15 bhp greater than the standard due to the addition of a dual exhaust muffler system, similar to that standard on the SHO; a Y-pipe was added after the resonator which allowed for the split to both sides of the rear of the vehicle. Other changes included a larger fuel tank, stainless steel brake lines, standard 4-wheel disc brakes with ABS, a modified front grille fascia that had a slit in it to allow for increased airflow to the radiator, and a certified calibration 140 mph speedometer. The Taurus police package didn't prove to be very popular, and it was often strongly outsold by Ford's own Crown Victoria.

With the 2.5 litre HSC four-cylinder was being dropped in early 1991, along with the 3-speed ATX automatic transmission, all Taurus models came standard with the 140 horsepower (104 kW) 3.0 litre Vulcan V6, except for the LX wagon that came with a 3.8 litre Essex V6. The Essex was optional on all other Taurus models. Every engine in this generation used the four speed AXOD-E transmission, until 1993, when it was replaced by the four speed AX4S transmission, which was used for the rest of this generation's production run in most models. (Some 1994-1995 3.0 litre came with the AX4N transaxle.)

Main article: Mercury SableThe second-generation of the Mercury Sable went on sale in 1992, along with the Taurus. Just like the first-generation, the second-generation Mercury Sable shared mechanical parts with the Taurus, but contained mostly unique cosmetic parts. This generation of Sable also carried over many design features from the first-generation, such as the wrap around rear windows and the front full length "lightbar". This generation of Sable was also offered as both a sedan and wagon, although it too was aimed at a more upscale market than the Taurus. This generation of Sable was sold until 1995, when it was replaced with a third-generation of Mercury Sable.

Main article: Ford Taurus SHOThe second-generation Ford Taurus SHO was launched in 1992, along with the Taurus. Unlike the first generation, this SHO contained less aggressive body cladding, as well as a unique front end using parts largely borrowed from the Mercury Sable.  Like the Taurus and Sable, the SHO's drivetrain was carried over from the first-generation. The only major change came in 1993, when an automatic transmission became optional.  Automatic equipped cars got a slightly bigger engine with more horsepower and torque. 









