

"Chevrolet Captiva" redirects here. For the car sold in Mexico, see Opel Antara.

The Daewoo Winstorm is a crossover SUV developed by General Motors's GM Daewoo design center in Bupyeong, South Korea. The Winstorm, which is given the model designation C100 is based on the GM Theta platform, and is derived from the S3X concept car. The Theta platform is also used to underpin Opel Antara, the Winstorm's mechanical derivative also built by Daewoo. Winstorm nameplate is only used within South Korea. In Europe, the Middle East and Southeast Asia, the Winstorm is known as the Chevrolet Captiva with the Holden Captiva name used in Australia and New Zealand.

The first generation C100, known as the CG in Holden's teminology was launched in 2006, with its styling inspired by the 2004 Chevrolet S3X concept car. Available in either five- or seven-seat configurations, the Winstorm is powered by the Australian-built Alloytec 3.2 litre V6 engine, which is mated to a five-speed automatic transmission, featuring Active Select. This engine is also shared by the Winstorm's Opel Antara derivative which utilises a different design, but shares the same underpinnings and powertrain components. A four-cylinder RA 420 SOHC turbodiesel engine, co-developed with VM Motori was later introduced into the range.

Standard safety features include: anti-lock brakes, electronic stability control (ESC), front seatbelt pre-tensioners and force limiters, and driver and front passenger airbags. Side curtain airbags are standard on higher luxury level variants in some markets. In crash safety tests conducted by Euro NCAP, the Winstorm was given a four out of five start crash rating. The results from the test were helped by the use of high-strength steel used in the body shell which was designed to spread crash forces over distinct load channels, therefore ensuring the safety of the occupants within the safety cell. The vehicle's optional active all-wheel drive system is fully incorporated with the ESC and anti-lock braking systems, consequently increasing car handling and control. When the driving conditions determine the need for improved traction, the vehicle’s all-wheel drive system instigates. In ordinary driving situations, only the vehicle's front wheels are employed.





