



Ludmila Yurina (born January 16, 1962) is a Ukrainian pianist and composer.

Born  on 16 January 1962 in Uzin’, Kiev region, Ukraine . Graduated from Kiev Music College as a pianist (1981) and from Kiev State P.I.Tchaikovsky Conservatoire as a composer (1990, Prof.E.Stankovych), where later she completed her post-graduate studies (1998) with Prof. E.Stankovych.

She attended master-courses with eminent musicians P-H.Dittrich, I.Arditti, H.Zapf, G.Stäbler, J.Durand (Rheinsberg, Germany) as well as with H.Lachenmann and W.Rihm (Dresden, Germany).

In 1990—1992 she was the Music Director of the theatre studios «Kolo» and «ARS» (Kiev). Since 1993 she has been a member and a coordinator of the Organising Committee of the International Youth Music Forum (Kiev, Ukraine). In 1997 she was the Artistic Director of the «Meta-Art» Ukrainian Contemporary Art Festival (Kiev, Ukraine).

Since 1995 she have works as associate Professor of Department of composition at the National Music Academy of Ukraine (composition and orchestration) . She was an invited composer at the flute master-course at the Rheinsberg Music Academy (Germany, 1999).

She had got creative residences: in Künstlerhof Schreyahn, Germany, 1998; at the Experimental Electronic Music Studio of Südwestrundfunk (by the Heinrich-Strobel-Stiftung, Freiburg, Germany, 1999) Baden-Württemberg Ministry of Research, Science and Art (Baden-Baden, Germany, 2001); International Center for composers aka VICC (Gotland,Sweden, 2005,2006).

In 1999 her name was included in the reference book «Life of famous persons» (Delawar, USA).

She participated in numerous international festivals; her works have been performed in Ukraine, Germany, Finland, Italy, Moldova, Mongolia, Poland, etc. She has actively collaborated with such known German performers as pianist S.Eder, cellist M.Lorenz, Ensemble timbre actuel etc.

Recordings of her music were produced on the CD «Two Days and Two Nights of New Music: Festivals 1998—2000» and by the Radio «Deutsche Welle» (Germany), Canadian broadcasting (Edmonton) and the Ukrainian National TV and Radio Company. Her works were published by «Muzychna Ukrajina» Publishing House (Ukraine) and "Frederic Harris Music Publishing " (Canada).

She is a Founder and Chairman of Association "Women in music" Ukraine ( since 2002), Chairman of Kiev section ISCM ( since 2006),member of the Ukrainian Composers’ Union.

2008 "EXISTENZA…" for electronic, video and modern dance : 29`

2007 "Perseus-Betha-Algol" for e-guitar with processor and electronic : 8` 40

2007 "Pulsar" for Violino  : 8`

2005 "Initiation ",cantata for baritono, mixed choir and orchestra : 19` 30

2005 "Crystal"for symphony orchestra :9`

2003\04 "Incoming" for symphony orchestra : 9`

2004 "Visions of John Baptist" for string quartet : 8`

2004 "Angel of white day" for Piano  : 5`

2002 "Shadows of deep sleep" for Fl,Ob, Piano and Cello : 11`20

2001 "Topos Uranios" for Harpsichord and live electronics: 8`

2001 "Kashmir", version of "Led Zeppelin"’s song for symphony orchestra and rock instruments: 5`

2001 "Waterdreams" for trombone, percussion, improvising saxophone and pantomime: 11`

2000 "Irrlicht" for solo cello: 6'

2000 "Klangillusion" for flute, piano, cello: 8'

1999 "Quad", electronic music to S.Becket’s piece: 16'

1999 "Shadows and Ghosts" for piano: 5'

1999 "Gemma" for solo flute: 6'

1998 "Funny Death" on A.Ginsberg’s text for soprano, 2 microphones, tam-tam: 5'

1998 "Funny Death "on A.Ginsberg’s text for 2 sopranos, 2 altos, 2 tenors, 2 baritones: 4`

1998 "Glass-Elegy" for piano: 8'

1998 "Xing" for trombone, percussion, piano, double bass: 10'

1997 "Streams" , film music: 8'

1997 "As soon as possible…" («Jaknajskorish…») for solo oboe: 6'

1997 "…end-Less…" for symphony orchestra: 8'

1996 "Ein kleiner Marsch mit grossem Wecker" for children’s percussion ensemble: 6'

1996 "Distanzierung" for 2 cellos: 8'

1995 S-re Beresciolo, chamber symphony (restoration and edition) for 2 oboes, chamber orchestra

1995 "Ritornelli" for piano: 5'

1995 "The End of the Game or Provocations" for clarinet, piano, violin, cello: 7'

1993 "Geometricum " for flute, oboe, clarinet, bassoon, horn: 14'

1993 "Ekagrata" for 4 groups of percussion: 15'

1993 "Ran-Nan" for 19 strings: 11'

1992 "The Garden of the Shadows ", film music: 12'

1992 "Disintegrations" for solo trombone: 8'

1991 "Rao Noala" for soprano, flute, vibraphone, piano, violin: 11'

1987—1991 "Jazz Fiesta", children’s piano album: 30'

1989 Concerto for solo trombone and symphony orchestra 17'

1987 "Two Jazz Etudes for Children" for piano: 2'

1984—1987 "Ukrainian Echo", five pieces for piano: 6'

1985 "Town and Country", three pieces for piano: 5'