David Osborne Hagger, born in 1939 in London, England, is a retired British government executive who was employed as Head of Abridged Licensing and Co-ordinator of the Executive support business of the Medicines Division of the Department of Health at Market Towers in London.

On July 5, 1999 David Osborne Hagger appeared by Statement 476 before the BSE Inquiry. He testified regarding the actions of civil servants and scientists under his administration concerning animal byproducts used during the licensed manufacture of medicines and vaccines in the United Kingdom. Of particular concern was the possibility of a health risk to thousands of British children who had received innocuations of vaccine that potentionally could have been contaminated by BSE during their licensed manufacture. No individual records had been kept as a central registry to identify specific children inoculated with these vaccines and consequently it became necessary to question every government official with regards to their own actions in the licensing of medicines and vaccines.

Since his retirement from the Department of Health, David Osborne Hagger has served as Chairman of the Board of Governors of Rosebery School, Epsom, Surrey, England. He is the first cousin of metaphysical author Nicholas Osborne Hagger.

On July 5, 1999 David Hagger appeared by Statement 476 before the inquiry into Bovine spongiform encephalopathy (mad cow disease BSE Inquiry), concerning the use of animal byproducts in use during the licensed manufacture of medicines in the United Kingdom.  He stated that in a previous enquiry the Agency had been asked to:"... identify relevant manufacturers and obtain information about the bovine material contained in children’s vaccines, the stocks of these vaccines and how long it would take to switch to other products."

It was further reported that the:"... use of bovine insulin in a small group of mainly elderly patients was noted and it was recognised that alternative products for this group were not considered satisfactory."

A medicines licensing committee report that same year recommended that: "... no licensing action is required at present in regard to products produced from bovine material or using prepared bovine brain in nutrient media and sourced from outside the United Kingdom, the Channel Isles and the Republic of Ireland provided that the country of origin is known to be free of BSE, has competent veterinary advisers and is known to practise good animal husbandry."

In 1990 the British Diabetic Association became concerned regarding the safety of bovine insulin and the government licensing agency assured them that:"... there was no insulin sourced from cattle in the UK or Ireland and that the situation in other countries was being monitored."

In 1991 a European Community Commission:"... expressed concerns about the possible transmission of the BSE/scrapie agent to man through use of certain cosmetic treatments."

Sources in France reported to the British Medicines Control Agency:"... that there were some licensed surgical sutures derived from French bovine material."  Concerns were also raised: "... regarding a possible risk of transmission of the BSE agent in gelatin products."