

The Hyundai Santa Fe is a compact/mid-size crossover SUV based on the Hyundai Sonata platform. It was introduced for the 2001 model year as Hyundai's first SUV, released at the same time as the Ford Escape/Mazda Tribute and Pontiac Aztek.  The car was a milestone in the company's restructuring program of the late 1990s because, despite receiving criticism from journalists for its obscure looks, the car was a hit with the American buyers.  The car was so popular that at times, Hyundai had trouble supplying the demand.  The Santa Fe quickly became Hyundai's best seller and contributed to Hyundai's success in the United States.  As of 2007, the Santa Fe falls between the Tucson and the related Veracruz (which was preceded by the Terracan). Hyundai Santa Fe awarded 2008 Consumer Reports "top pick". Hyundai Santa Fe was among the top 10 vehicles for 2008 unveiled in the magazine's issue. The magazine's annual ratings, based on road tests and predicted safety and reliability are considered highly influential among consumers.http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/23390986/

In its first year in production, the Santa Fe was offered with one of two engine and transmission combinations. In North America, a fuel-efficient although underpowered 2.4 L four cylinder engine was standard equipment and could be mated with either a 5-speed manual or a 4-speed automatic. A 2.7 L Delta V6 offered more power than the four-cylinder but was only available with the automatic. Front wheel drive was standard (with traction control optional with the V6) and 4WD was optional. A 2.0 L Common Rail Turbo Diesel (CRTD) was offered outside the United States.  Australian Santa Fes went on sale in November 2000 with only one engine/transmission choice - a 2.7L V6 mated to a four-speed semi-automatic transmission. 4WD was standard. A cheaper 2.4L four cylinder joined the range several months later in 2001, but was only available with a manual transmission.

The Santa Fe entered its second year without any changes. Demand for the Santa Fe continued to be up but owners had several suggested changes for Hyundai. 

Mid-2002

In a rare mid-year model change, Hyundai increased the size of the fuel tank from 17 to 19 U.S. gallons and reorganized the location of the badges on the tailgate. The  interior layout of the console and the position of the clock were also changed.

In 2003, Hyundai responded to some of the customer complaints and suggestions such as the fact that the hood used a prop and not gas struts, there was no light in the glove compartment, and the car itself did not have enough power.  In 2003, Hyundai introduced the 3.5 liter V6 in addition to the other two gas engines in North America. The bigger engine came with a computer-controlled four-wheel drive system.  Automatic transmission models were given a chrome shift gate surround as opposed to the matte silver plastic style used in the 2001 and 2002 models. A Monsoon high-performance sound system came standard on the mid-level GLS model and came with a 6-disc CD changer on the top-tier LX. Rounding out the changes in the 2003 model was the discontinuation of the highly unpopular Pine Green which in some owner circles has gained the nickname 'Yucky Green'.  In Australia, the four cylinder Santa Fe was dropped in 2003, due to slow sales, leaving the 2.7L V6 automatic as the only model.

Hyundai continued to post sales records with the Santa Fe as it rolled into 2004 with very minor changes. The manual climate controls on the base GL and mid-line GLS were revised very slightly. The remote keyless entry system was given a confirmation 'chirp' when the 'LOCK' button on the remote was pressed twice. 

Mid-2004

Midway through the year the AM/FM antenna was moved from on the glass in the rear drivers side window to a three inch (76 mm)  rubber antenna in the center of the roof just above the tailgate.

The Santa Fe received its final face lift for 2005. Changes were made to the grill, taillights, rear bumper, interior instrument cluster.  The instrument cluster was redesigned with the speedometer now reading 140 mph (earlier models only indicated 130 mph) and a better-designed toll ticket slot in the driver's sun visor. Both sun visors also received extensions so the sun could be blocked out better when coming in from the side.  The base Santa Fe was discontinued that time, making way for the Tucson.

In Australia, all models received body-colored (painted) bumpers from 2005 on. The color 'Sandstone' was discontinued in favor of a slightly different color named 'Mocha Frost'. The GL trim was dropped as was the four-cylinder engine and its respective 5-speed manual transmission. The 2.7 L V6 took over duties as the base engine. A passenger airbag cutoff that prevents the airbag from deploying if the seat is unoccupied (or occupied by a small person) was also added. A 3-point seatbelt was added to the center rear seating position, as well. The calendar function, housed in the overhead console was removed and a compass took its place.

The last year of this Santa Fe saw few changes. Two colors were discontinued for 2006, Merlot and Canyon Red. A rare color, Dark Emerald Green, was introduced mid-year. It did not appear in any sales brochures and could have only be ordered by a dealership. The LX trim level was renamed 'Limited' and got a corresponding tailgate badge, a first for the Santa Fe of any trim level. Another first was the availability of a monochromatic paint scheme, a departure from the contrasting gray cladding previously standard. The monochromatic option was only available on the Limited in black. In total, these options ran $1900, pushing the Santa Fe's total asking price to nearly $30,000.

In Europe, the new Santa Fe model was launched in April, offering a new 2.2 litre diesel engine and updated 2.7 litre petrol V6.

The next-generation 2007 Santa Fe debuted at the 2006 North American International Auto Show. The first production Santa Fe rolled off Hyundai's Montgomery, Alabama assembly line on April 18, 2006. It shares this assembly line with the current generation Hyundai Sonata. The new generation sheds the old style's quirky design in favor of a more contemporary look.

In the United States, the new generation is offered in GLS, SE, and Limited versions. The new Santa Fe sees the return of a manual transmission but only when mated with the 2.7-liter V6. The 3.3 liter V6 (a retuned version of the same engine found in the Sonata) is standard on the SE and Limited and comes only with a 5-speed automatic. Body lean in turns, a problem with the previous generation, has been curbed in the new Santa Fe. Both road and wind noise have been hushed, as well.

Newly standard on the latest iteration of the Santa Fe are all the safety features the previous model lacked or charged as extra. Electronic Stability Control (ESC), side curtain airbags for all seating rows, a tire pressure monitor, active front head restraints and anti-lock brakes are all standard. A heated windshield wiper grid located in the front wipers' 'park' position helps to thaw ice buildup on the blades in colder climates. Some features like the tailgate flip glass and the lower body cladding were not integrated into the new model.

The interior has been upgraded as well with blue-lit dashboard controls, (unlike the green color used in other Hyundai models), a gated shifter pattern, illuminated cupholders, and higher quality leather on Limited models. The rear seat head restraints caused visibility problems in the previous model due to their size. The new style features 'shingled' head rests that when lowered completely, sit flush with the top of the seat, helping to maximize rear visibility. The middle rear seating position now comes with its own head restraint and a three-point seatbelt built in. LATCH child seat anchors are also standard.

Pricing remained competitive despite the upward move in size and feature content.

In Malaysia, Hyundai Santa Fe is available as a Complete knock down model rebadged as Inokom Santa Fe. The Inokom Santa Fe is only available in CRDi 2.2-liter Diesel and 2.7-liter V6.

For 2008, only minor changes have been applied to the Santa Fe. A navigation system made by LG is now available on the Limited trim level. The Infinity sound system and the power glass sunroof have been made standard on Limited models. The non-metallic white paint trim has been dropped, leaving only the pearl style as the only white color available on the Santa Fe. A minor problem of driver and passenger interior dome lighting was also fixed as well where it previously did not illuminate when the door was opened.

In 2007, Hyundai's midsize SUV Santa Fe earns 2007 TOP SAFETY PICK award by IIHS. http://www.iihs.org/news/rss/pr061107.html http://www.motortrend.com/features/auto_news/2007/112_0706_2007_hyundai_santa_fe_safety Also, received 5 star safety rating by NHTSA. http://www.nhtsa.dot.gov/ncap/cars/4235.html

There is a Hyundai Santa Fe FCEV fuel cell vehicle .

There is also a Hyundai Sante Fe Blue Hybrid that is powered by gasoline engine coupled to a 30Kw electric motor. The Santa Fe blue Hybrid uses a 270V lithium polymer battery .

Advertising Standards Bureau of Australia banned a Santa Fe TV commercial titled 'restless' or 'toddler'http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6GfdyIZcRH4, which ASB argued that it promotes illegal activity.http://www.automk.com/thread-49434-1-1.htmlhttp://www.news.com.au/story/0,23599,21270460-2,00.html The ad was produced by Kim Thorp and Howard Greive from Assignment Group NZ and directed by Tony Williams from Sydney Film Company, with post via Frame Set + Match, Sydney.http://campaignbrief.blogspot.com/2007/02/hyundai-toddler-commercial-banned-by.html The ad itself won the 2006 Fair Go Ad Awards in Best Ad Award category, and was also nominated in the top five in the Worst Ad category.http://tvnz.co.nz/view/page/488120/842896







