

The Demon Murder Trial is the first known case in the United States of a lawyer claiming his client was innocent due to demonic possession. It involved the conviction of Arne Cheyenne Johnson, a resident of Brookfield, Connecticut, for first-degree manslaughter of his landlord Alan Bono on November 24, 1981. In the year leading up to the attack on Bono, Johnson had been staying with his fiancee whose younger brother supposedly had been possessed by demons and whose family called in the famed demonologists Ed and Lorraine Warren. Johnson supposedly taunted and was possessed by demons from the boy, and several months later killed his landlord during a heated conversation. His defense lawyer tried to argue in court that he was possessed, but the judge ruled that no such defense existed, and Johnson served 5 years of a 10 to 20 year sentence. The trial attracted media attention from around the world.

On July 3, 1980, Arne Johnson's fiancee, Debbie Glatzel, claimed to have discovered that her youngest brother David woke sobbing, saying that he had a vision of an "awful beast", describing it as "a man with big black eyes, a thin face with animal features and jagged teeth, pointed ears, horns and hoofs", and saying it had warned him to "Beware". As his visions persisted, Debbie requested that Johnson come and stay at her family's home. A catholic priest came to their house and blessed it, but to seemingly no effect on David. Visions began to occur in the daytime soon afterwards, in the form of an old man with a white beard, wearing a flannel shirt and jeans. Twelve days after the first incident, the family called upon demonologists Ed and Lorraine Warren of Monroe, Connecticut to assist. Lorraine, who claims to be clairvoyant, stated that she saw a black, misty form next to David, indicating a malevolent presence, and that David complained of invisible hands choking him, and the feeling of being hit. She also claims that afterwards, there were red marks on his neck. David's condition caused him to start missing school, and David also gained 60 pounds over the next few months. He also began to growl, hiss, speak in strange voices, and suddenly recite passages from the Bible or Paradise Lost. Each night, the family says that a family member would remain awake with David through sometime 30 minute long rapid spasms and convulsions. The Warrens claim that three "lesser exorcisms" took place, the first with four priests in attendance, and that when asked how many demons where inside him, David listed 43 names. She also claims David had marks all over his body, levitated, and demonstrated the supernatural ability of precognition relating to the murder Johnson would later commit. In October 1980, the Warrens contacted Brookfield police to warn them that the situation was becoming dangerous.

While staying with Debbie's family, Johnson supposedly taunted the demons said to be within David to possess his own body while participating in David's exorcisms. "Take me on, take me on instead of him" Johnson is purported to have said. The Warrens claimed to have warned him not to do this, but Johnson refused to listen. As David's condition worsened, Debbie and Johnson moved out; Debbie was hired by Alan Bono, a new resident of the town, as a dog groomer at the Brookfield Pet Motel, and given an nearby apartment to stay at. It was then that Johnson's behavior supposedly began to change, and made Debbie fear that he had become possessed as well. According to Debbie, Johnson would go into a kind of trance, where he would growl, and say he saw a beast, but later have no memory of it.

On February 16, 1981, Johnson called in sick to his job at Wright Tree Service, claiming he had a sore throat. He joined his girlfriend Debbie at the animal clinic where she worked along with her sister and cousin. Alan Bono, the couples 40 year old landlord and Debbie's employer at the kennel,  bought the whole group lunch at a local bar, with Bono, Johnson, and Debbie all drinking wine, Bono more than the rest of the group. After lunch, the group returned to the dog kennels, where Johnson fixed Bono's stereo, which blared noisily. Debbie then took the girls to get pizza, but insisted they return quickly, saying "There's going to be trouble." When they returned, Bono invited everyone up to his apartment above the kennel, and when the television was turned on, it too was very loud, and Bono became agitated, punching his fist into his palm. Everyone left the room at Debbies urging, except Bono seized Debbie's nine year old cousin Mary and would not let go. Johnson, who had walked to the car, headed back to the apartment and told Bono to release Mary. Wanda Johnson, who recounted her story to the police, stated that "it just broke". Mary ran for the car, an Debbie stood between the two men. Wanda, who was holding on to Johnson, remembers he was "like stone", and couldn't be moved. Wanda heard Johnson growling like an animal, saw a flash through the air, and stated that "it just stopped". Johnson walked towards the woods, staring straight ahead, and Bono continued to punch his fist into his palm, before falling on his face. Bono had suffered "four or five tremendous wounds" according to Johnson's lawyer from a 5-inch (130 mm) pocket knife, mostly on his chest, and one that stretched from his stomach to the base of his heart. Bono died several hours later from his wounds. Johnson was discovered two miles (3 km) from the site of the murder and was held at the Bridgeport Correctional Center on bail of 125,000 USD. It was the first murder in the history of Brookfield, Connecticut.

Lorraine Warren called Brookfield police the day after the murder to tell them that Johnson was possessed. A "media blitz" began to surround the story, and the Warrens began to spread the story throughout the press, promising to lecture about it, write a book, and make a movie about it through their agents at William Morris. Martin Minella, Johnson's lawyer, said he received calls from all over the world about the case, and news spread to the point that Minella was recognized on the streets of London by passersby. Minella traveled to England to meet with lawyers who had been involved in two similar cases (though neither ever went to trial), planned to fly in exorcism specialists from Europe, and threatened to subpoena the priests involved if they would not cooperate.

The trial took place in Danbury, Connecticut Superior Court beginning on October 28, 1981. Minella entered the unprecedented plea of not guilty by virtue of possession by the devil, but the presiding judge, Robert Callahan, rejected Johnson's lawyer's attempt to show that Johnson was under the influence of a demon at the time of the murder. Callahan stated that there was no such defense, and it would be "irrelative and unscientific" to allow such testimony, forcing the defense attorney to argue instead that Johnson acted in self-defense. The jury thus never heard Minella's theory. The jury deliberated for 15 hours over three days before convicting Johnson on November 24, 1981, of first-degree manslaughter, and was sentenced to 10 to 20 years in prison, of which he served 5.

After he served his sentence, Johnson went on to marry his fiancee. The alleged incident led to the creation of a made for TV movie called The Demon Murder Case on NBC and a major motion picture which has stalled due to internal conflicts. In 1983, Gerald Brittle, with the assistance of Lorraine Warren, published a book about the incident entitled The Devil in Connecticut, which Lorraine Warren says the profits of which were shared with the family. Two-thousand dollars was paid by the book publisher to the family. Upon the books republication in 2006 by iUniverse Inc., Carl Glatzel Jr. and David Glatzel sued the authors and book publishers for violating their right to privacy, libel, and "intentional affliction of emotional distress"; further, he claims the book alleges he committed criminal and abusive acts against his family and others. Carl Glatzel Jr. has stated that the possession story was a hoax concocted by Ed and Lorraine Warren to exploit the family and his brothers mental illness, and that the book presents him as the villain because he disbelieved in the supernatural claims. He also asserts that the Warrens said that the story would make the family "millionaires", and would help get Johnson out of jail. He is currently writing a book titled Alone Through The Valley about his version of the events surrounding his brother. Further, the publicity generated by the alleged incident forced Carl to drop out of school, and lost friends and business opportunities. Lorraine Warren defends her work with the family, claiming that the six priests who were involved in the incident agreed at the time that the boy was possessed, and that the supernatural events she described were real. Gerald Brittle, the books author, says he wrote the book because "the family wanted the story told", that he possesses video of over 100 hours of his interviews with the family, and that they signed off on the book as accurate before it went to print. Glatzel's father, Carl Glatzel Senior, denies telling the author that his son was possessed. Johnson and his wife Debbie believe the account of demonic possession to be true, and that Glatzel is suing to make money.

