King's Field II is the second game in the King's Field RPG series. Like both its successors and predecessor, the game is played through first person view in a dark and mysterious, medieval fantasy setting.

The game was developed by the Japanese game development company From Software, and released July 21st, 1995 in Japan, and December 31, 1995 in the U.S.  Since the first King's Field game was never published outside Japan, King's Field II is commonly known simply as 'King's Field' in the U.S. It has only been released for the Playstation console.

The game takes place on the island of Melanat. You take the role of Prince Alexander, who has taken it upon himself, as one of the king of Verdite's closest friends, to retrieve the holy sword known as the Moonlight Sword, and return it to King Alfred of the kingdom of Verdite. Alexander is washed up on the coast of Melanat, as the sole survivor after the ship he came with sank into the ocean. To find the Moonlight Sword, Alexander must press ever forward and uncover the secrets the dark island of Melanat holds.

Not yet complete. This information has been taken directly from the game, including any grammatical errors. The information has been gathered through the Truth Mirror item in the game. If any information appears twice(sometimes with slight changes), it means that one NPC might be moving around to different areas.







































































































This information has been taken directly from the game, including any grammatical errors. The information has been gathered through the Truth Mirror item in the game. If any information appears twice(sometimes with slight changes), it means that there are more than one type of that enemy in the game, but with the same name or Truth Mirror information on it.

















































































Credits acquired from IMDB.com and the original U.S. release game manual. 



Agetec 'King's Field (U.S.)' listing

