

Milk and Honey is an album of music by John Lennon and Yoko Ono released in 1984.  It is notable for being Lennon's first posthumous release of music, having been recorded in the last months of his life during and following the sessions for Double Fantasy.

Milk and Honey was the duo's projected follow-up to Double Fantasy, though Lennon's death caused a temporary shelving of the project, until Ono was capable of returning to complete it. Ono's material largely comprises new recordings, which she undertook during the album's preparation in 1983, to give her songs a more commercial and contemporary edge.  Conversely, Lennon's material, being the rehearsal recordings, has a more casual feeling.

"Nobody Told Me", a song Lennon had intended for Ringo Starr's upcoming album Stop and Smell the Roses, became a worldwide Top 10 hit, and was followed by the minor successes "I'm Stepping Out" and "Borrowed Time".

Milk and Honey's title is a reference to John and Yoko's relationship, "milk and honey" being an expression for an Asian/Caucasian mixed-race couple. Its cover shot is a colour outtake from the same photo session that produced the front cover of Double Fantasy.

Predictably, the reaction to Milk and Honey was less fanatical than the one that greeted Double Fantasy, but it was still well-received, peaking at #3 in the UK and #11 in the U.S., where it went gold.

After a falling out with David Geffen, whose Geffen Records had initially released Double Fantasy, Ono moved future projects to Polydor Records, which initially released Milk and Honey.  EMI, home of Lennon's entire recorded output—including that with The Beatles—acquired Milk and Honey in the late 1990s.

Jack Douglas, who had co-produced Double Fantasy with Lennon and Ono, also had input into the initial sessions for Milk and Honey, though Ono declined to credit him after their professional relationship soured following Lennon's death.

In 2001, Yoko Ono supervised the remastering of Milk and Honey for its CD reissue, adding three bonus tracks, including a 22-minute excerpt from John Lennon's last interview in the late afternoon of 8 December 1980.

The songs "Let Me Count the Ways" and "Grow Old With Me" were written by John and Yoko to each other using inspiration from poems by Elizabeth Barrett Browning and Robert Browning.  They are presented in their demo form.





Album - Billboard (United States)

Singles - Billboard (United States)



