In Britain a unit of alcohol is defined as 10 millilitres (or approximately 8 grams) of ethanol (ethyl alcohol). It is used as a basis for guidelines on consumption of alcoholic beverages; the number of units contained in a typical drink is publicised and marked on bottles. 

The number of units of alcohol in a drink can be determined by multiplying the volume of the drink (in millilitres) by its percentage ABV, and dividing by 1000 (or litres &amp;times; % abv). Thus, one pint (568ml) of beer at 4% ABV contains:

\frac{568 \times 4}{1000} = 2.3\mbox{ units}

The formula uses the quantity in millilitres divided by 1000; this has the result of there being exactly one unit per percentage point per litre of any alcoholic beverage.

As the volume of alcoholic drinks is becoming increasingly shown in centilitres, discerning the number of units in a drink can be as simple as multiplying volume by percentage (converted into a fraction of 1). Thus, 75 centilitres of wine at 13 % ABV contains:

75 \times 0.13 = 9.75\mbox{ units}

It is often misleadingly stated that a unit is supplied by a small glass of wine,  half a pint of beer, or a single measure of spirits. Such statements are misleading because they do not reflect the large differences in strengths and measures of wines, beers and spirits. 









Since 1995 the UK government has advised that regular consumption of between three and four units a day for men and between two and three units a day for women would not pose significant health risks, but that consistently drinking four or more units a day (men) or three or more units a day (women) is not advisable. Previously (from 1992 until 1995) the advice was that men should drink no more than 21 units per week, and women no more than 14.  This was changed because a government study showed that many people were in effect "saving" up their units and "using" them at the end of the week, a phenomenon referred to as binge drinking.  The difference between sexes is given due to the (typically) lower weight and water-to-body-mass-ratio of women. 

It was claimed in October 2007 that these limits had been "plucked out of the air" and have no scientific basis.

An international study (Kanis, 2005) of almost 6,000 men and 11,000 women found that persons who reported that they drank more than 2 units of alcohol a day had an increased risk of fractures compared to non-drinkers.  For example, those who drank over 3 units a day had nearly twice the risk of a hip fracture.



