

The Coca-Cola formula is The Coca-Cola Company's secret recipe for Coca-Cola. As a publicity marketing strategy started by David W. Woodruff, the company presents the formula as a closely held trade secret known only to a few employees, mostly executives.

The formula ingredients are mixed into a syrup, a highly concentrated mixture of flavors, which is mixed only in select centers throughout the world. This is then distributed to local bottling companies to mix with carbonated water and other minor ingredients, ensuring tight control over the actual contents.

Published accounts say it contains (or once contained) sugar crystals, caramel, caffeine, phosphoric acid, coca leaf and kola nut extract, lime extract, flavoring mixture, vanilla and glycerin.  Merchandise 7X (Lemon, orange, lime, cassia (a type of cinnamon), nutmeg oils) is the "secret ingredient" in Coca-Cola. Alleged syrup recipes vary greatly, and Coca-Cola reluctantly admits the formula has changed over the decades. For example, the formula was changed in 1935 with the help of Rabbi Tobias Geffen of Atlanta to allow it to be certified kosher.

The basic “cola” taste from Coca-Cola and competing cola drinks comes mainly from vanilla and cinnamon; distinctive tastes among various brands are the result of trace flavorings such as orange, lime and lemon and spices such as nutmeg.

Amateur sleuths have tried to reverse-engineer the production process and ingredients. The secret formula is the subject of books, speculation and marketing lore.  Aided by modern analytical methods, food scientists can easily identify the composition of food products, including Coca-Cola. The company consistently claims that all published recipes are incorrect. 

The employees who know the full recipe must fly on separate planes when traveling, and cannot be left alone with strangers while they are together. To this day, Coca-Cola uses as an ingredient from coca leaf extract prepared by a Stepan Company plant in Maywood, New Jersey, using a process monitored by the Drug Enforcement Administration. Because cocaine is naturally present in coca leaves, today's Coca-Cola uses "spent", or treated, coca leaves, those that have been through a cocaine extraction process, to flavor the beverage. Some contend that this process cannot extract all of the cocaine alkaloids at a molecular level, and so the drink still contains trace amounts of the stimulant. The Coca-Cola Company currently refuses to comment on the continued presence of coca leaf in Coca-Cola. 

In an infamous corporate disaster, Coca-Cola introduced New Coke in 1985. After public outcry, the recipe was restored to the original "classic" formula, the only change being Coca-Cola bottlers in the United States replacing the traditional sucrose with cheaper corn syrup; Coca-Cola is still sweetened with cane sugar in most of the world.

The closest formula to the original that can be purchased is the 1935 kosher formula which is still produced (as of 2008) though it may be difficult to find outside of Passover, where it is sold in 2-Liter bottles with a yellow or white cap marked with a circle around the letter U followed by a P, indicating that the Orthodox Union certifies the soda as Kosher for Passover.  While the current American Coke formula is kosher, during Passover Ashkenazic Jews (who make up the majority of American Jews) do not consume corn products or their derivatives, which prevents them from consuming High fructose corn syrup.   Even sugar-based formulas would still require certification of both the local formula and the specific bottling plant, as the strictures of Kashrut on Passover are far higher and more complicated than usual kosher observance.

This recipe is attributed to a sheet of paper found in an old formulary book owned by Coca-Cola inventor, John S. Pemberton, just before his death (U.S. measures):

Directions:

This recipe does not specify when sugar, coca, caramel or the rest of the water are added, or the flavoring oil quantity units of measure.

Source: Mark Pendergrast. For God, Country, and Coca-Cola: The Definitive History of the Great American Soft Drink and the Company That Makes It. New York: Basic Books, 2000. ISBN 0-465-05468-4.

This recipe is attributed to pharmacist John Reed.



Recipe is from Food Flavorings: Composition, Manufacture and Use. Makes one U.S. gallon (3.8 L) of syrup. Yield (used to flavor carbonated water at 1 fl oz per bottle): 128 bottles, 6.5 fl oz (192 ml).









