

The Saturn Outlook is a premium full-size crossover SUV which debuted at the New York International Auto Show.  The Outlook is based on the new GM Lambda platform, which it shares with the Buick Enclave, Chevrolet Traverse and GMC Acadia.  The Outlook features the lowest sticker price among GM's Lambda crossover SUVs.

The Outlook is powered by the 3.6 L V6 DOHC 24-valve HFV6 engine with Variable Valve Timing, available in two versions:Both versions use the Hydra-Matic 6T75 six-speed automatic transmission, and are available with either front-wheel drive or all-wheel drive.





The Outlook can seat eight in a three-row setting.  The front row consists of two bucket seats, and the second row is available as either a 60/40 split-folding three-passenger bench seat or two individual "captain chairs."  The third row is a 60/40 split-folding three-passenger bench seat.

In the press release accompanying the Outlook's launch, GM emphasized the "industry first" SmartSlide second row.  In case of both bench seat or captain chairs, the seat cushion flips forward while the seat is being slid forward, which allows for "compression" of the space used by the seat in the foremost position.  If the third seat is folded, this allows for expansion of the cargo area. The system also allows for fore-aft adjustment of the middle seat to change the spacing between the second and third-row seats for more legroom.

The Outlook, along with the other Lambda-based vehicles, is built in the Delta Township Assembly plant near Lansing, Michigan.

The first pre-production Outlook rolled off the assembly line at the Delta Township plant on May 24, 2006.

In December 2006, all sales of the first batch of the Outlook (and the GMC Acadia) were temporarily stopped due to the engine mounts' not having holes drilled to release accumulated water, as well as an issue with potentially faulty rivets in the load floor just forward of the rear hatch.  The assembly process was quickly adjusted, and dealerships were told to fix the problems themselves before offering the Outlook for sale again.  Sales resumed within days of the notice.

National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA)

Frontal: 

Side: 

The 2007 Saturn Outlook large crossover sport-utility equipped with side-impact airbags received a 5-star rating for its performance in the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration's (NHTSA) front crash and side-impact crash tests; rear crash and rollover ratings have not yet been released.

For testing frontal collisions, crash-test dummies are placed in driver and front passenger seats and secured with the vehicle's seat belts. Vehicles are crashed into a fixed barrier at 35 miles per hour (56 km/h), which is equivalent to a head-on collision between two similar size vehicles each moving at 35 mph (56 km/h). Instruments measure the force of impact to each dummy's head, chest, and legs. The resulting information indicates a belted person's chances of incurring a serious injury in the event of a crash.

For side crash ratings, crash-rating dummies representing an average-sized adult are placed in the driver and rear passenger seats (driver's side) and secured with the vehicle's seat belts. The side crash rating represents an intersection-type collision with a 3,015 pound (1368 kg) barrier moving at 38.5 mph (62 km/h) into a standing vehicle. The moving barrier is covered with material that has "give" to replicate the front of a vehicle. Since all rated vehicles are impacted by the same size barrier, it is possible to compare all vehicles with each other when looking at side crash protection ratings. Instruments measure the force of impact to each dummy's head, neck, chest, and pelvis. Side-collision star ratings indicate the chance of a serious chest injury for the driver, front seat passenger, and the rear seat passenger (first and second row occupants). Head injury, although measured, is not currently included in the star rating. An excessive head injury score (HIC greater than 1,000) is reported separately as a safety concern. As with the frontal crash ratings, a serious injury is one requiring immediate hospitalization and may be life threatening.

A five-star rating in the frontal crash test indicates that there is a 10% or less chance of serious injury. In the side-impact tests, a five-start rating means a 5% or less chance of serious injury.

The Insurance Institute for Highway Safety (IIHS) have tested the Saturn Outlook and it got the IIHS Top Safety Pick award.





