

Princess Jasmine (Arabic: الأميرة ياسمين) is a fictional Arabian princess who originally appeared in the 1992 Disney film, Aladdin, followed with its two direct-to-video sequels, The Return of Jafar (1994) and Aladdin and the King of Thieves (1996) and the animated television series. Her singing voice was performed by Lea Salonga in the first movie and , and Liz Callaway in The Return of Jafar and Aladdin and the King of Thieves. She is also one of the Official Disney Princesses. She has also made various appearances in the Disney Channel series House of Mouse, and she appeared in . Her most recent appearance was in the direct-to-video film, .

Her animator Mark Henn states in the Aladdin Platinum Edition DVD that her design was based on his younger sister, Beth. She was originally supposed to be an arrogant and spoiled girl whose father had a hard time marrying off (because she was so annoying with her massive ego), but she would have changed when she met Aladdin. She is an adaptation of Princess Badroulbadour based on the story of Aladdin and the magic lamp from The Book of One Thousand and One Nights. The song "Call Me A Princess" was written to introduce her, but the character was soon changed and the song was cut.

With Aladdin, its two sequels, the Aladdin television series, House of Mouse, the three Kingdom Hearts games, and Disney Princess Enchanted Tales, Jasmine holds the record for appearing in more media than any of the other Disney princesses, as well as being the first Disney princess not of European descent, plus not to marry a prince.

 Jasmine is the daughter of the wealthy Sultan of Agrabah. She is shown to be brave, intelligent, strong, independent, fiery, and charitable.  She can also be quite cunning.  Unwilling to marry any of the princes her father suggests, she runs away from home, but having never been outside the palace before, she inadvertently gets into trouble. A street urchin named Aladdin saves her.  Aladdin is arrested by guards sent by the evil vizier and sorcerer, Jafar, and Jasmine confronts Jafar demanding why this happened.  Jafar pretends that he thought Aladdin kidnapped her and lies to Jasmine when he tells her Aladdin's been beheaded.  Jasmine is distraught, thinking she's resonsible for Aladdin's death.  After Aladdin's wish to become a prince is granted to him by The Genie, he visits Jasmine in the guise of 'Prince Ali Ababwa'.  She initially refuses even to speak to him, believing him to be just another "stuffed-shirt, overinflated, swaggering" suitor, but later accepts his proposal after falling in love with him on a magic carpet ride. During this time, Jasmine sees through Aladdin's disguise, but Aladdin convinces her that he sometimes dressed up as a commoner to "escape the pressures of palace life," which she relates to.  She is taken back to the palace and the two share a kiss.  However, upon announcing her decision to marry Aladdin, Jafar takes over Agrabah by stealing the lamp from Aladdin.  Jasmine is horrified as Jafar reveals Aladdin's true identity (Aladdin had resolved and intended to tell the truth to Jasmine, though under much different circumstances). After Jafar banishes Aladdin to the ends of the Earth, he then makes Jasmine his personal slave.  Jafar offers her a place at his side, as his queen, which she angrily refuses.  Jafar attemps to use his third wish to make Jasmine fall in love with him, but according to The Genie's rules, this is a wish that The Genie cannot grant him.  However, upon seeing Aladdin sneaking back into the Palace, Jasmine distracts Jafar by pretending that the wish has been granted.  She compliments Jafar, and even when Jafar asks "And the street rat?" as if to test her loyalty, she dismisses Aladdin by echoing Jafar "What street rat?"  But then, Abu accidentally knocks over a cup while trying to keep Iago, who has spotted Aladdin and is trying to alert Jafar, quiet.  The noise catching his attention, Jafar nearly discovers Aladdin, but Jasmine stops him by giving him and EXTREMELY passionate kiss with her soft, luscious rbu red lips. The plan is foiled, however, when they break apart, and Jafar sees Aladdin's reflection on Jasmine's crown.  Jafar attacks Aladdin, but when Jasmine tries to help by getting the Genie's lamp, the sorcerer imprisons her in a giant hourglass.  Aladdin frees her moments before she is suffocated by sand, and outwits Jafar by tricking him into wishing he is an all-powerful Genie, imprisoning Jafar in a lamp of his own.  With this, Aladdin has proven his worth, and the Sultan agrees to let his daughter marry whoever she wants.  She naturally chooses Aladdin and they wed.

In the first direct-to-video sequel, The Return of Jafar (1994), Jasmine later begins to question her choice in Aladdin, wondering if he was trustworthy enough after he defends Iago, Jafar's former pet parrot who had terrorized her father, but she quickly gets over these questions. Her part in the movie is relatively minor, though she does help to defeat Jafar for a final time. Finally, in the third direct-to-video/DVD movie, "Aladdin and the King of Thieves" (1996) she and Aladdin are finally wed.  The Return of Jafar and Aladdin and the King of Thieves together serve as bookends to the animated TV series as its prologue and epilogue, respectively.

In an early draft, when Aladdin first met Jasmine, he already knew that she was the Princess.  Eventually, it was decided that Aladdin wouldn't find out Jasmine was the princess until after he fell in love with her.  This gives the message that Aladdin married her because he loved her, and not because of her money or power.

Jasmine aids Aladdin, Abu, Iago, and the Genie in their adventures. Her role is more active than in the movies and she often dons a "warrior princess" motif to the point where she has been shown as skilled even compared to a race of women warriors and can easily take on the palace guards by herself. She balances out Aladdin's brash, ready-for-action personality with a kinder, more emotionally collected one, though several plots revolve around her getting too emotional and causing trouble for it.  

In the Hercules: the Animated Series episode "Hercules and the Arabian Night", Jasmine appears and responds to Philoctetes's advances with an assertion she is married.

Princess Jasmine wears many different outfits throughout the movies.  Her "normal" outfit, the one worn mostly during the first movie and series, is a blue bedlah outfit with long poofy bustle pants and a top which leaves her forearms and midriff bare, along with copper earrings and gold slipper-like shoes. She also has a blue headband with a sapphire. She slips out into Agrabah wearing a brown beggar's outfit with a hijab. For a formal announcement, she wears a long, lilac gown. When she is Jafar's slave, she is forced to wear a red and golden slave outfit, with midriff revealing top, red pants, golden earrings and, later on, a golden crown. At the end of the movie, she is wearing a very fancy version of her usual outfit, in a dark purple with blue cloth. In the sequel, she often wears a purple gown, as well as the usual blue outfit. In the third movie, she wears a white wedding dress. Her garb throughout the series changes, usually due to events of some sort or another. In one episode she became evil and wore a black version of her outfit with an added whip. In the Disney Store in 2007, there was a pink outfit with lace portrayed on the tag of Jasmine clothes.

In the special features of Winx Club: The Island of Crystal Skull DVD, Jasmine, Ariel, Belle, Aurora, Cinderella, Snow White, Mulan and Pocahontas will dance with Obi-Wan Kenobi, Anakin Skywalker, Yoda, Mace Windu, Plo Koon, Ki-Adi-Mundi, Saesee Tiin, Aayla Secura, Luminara Unduli, Kit Fisto, Shaak Ti,  Army of Clone Troopers in the Jungle and the song is called Pokemon Johto Theme; Much like the Dancing Flubber.



The game follows the plot of the movie. Jasmine appears in cutscenes and must be rescued from Jafar in the final level. At the end of the game, she and Aladdin fly by on the magic carpet. They kiss as the credits scroll.http://www.vgmuseum.com/end/genesis/a/aladdin.htm.

In the first Kingdom Hearts game, Princess Jasmine  (プリンセスーズーン,  Purinsesu Jazumin) is kidnapped by Jafar and Maleficent. Aladdin teams up with Sora to save her, but she was taken by Riku because she is one of the "Princesses of Heart". She appears again in Kingdom Hearts II, and explains the strange behavior of Aladdin to Sora, Donald and Goofy. The cause of Aladdin's behavior is his loneliness after Genie went to see the other worlds. When Genie comes back all is well again.  Linda Larkin reprises her role in the English version, while Jasmine's Japanese voice actress is Kaori Aso.

