

This article is about the company based in Hong Kong.  For the company based in the USA, see NextMedia Group.  Next Media Limited (Chinese: 壹傳媒有限公司 Pinyin: Yī Chuán Méi Yǒuxiàn Gōngsī ) SEHK: 0282, founded by serial entrepreneur Jimmy Lai, has more than 3,600 employees and is the largest-listed media company in Hong Kong. 

Lai has built a company culture of transparency and creativity without hierarchy. Employees are encouraged to tackle challenges through trial and error while assuming responsibility for their actions and sharing in profits from success.

Subdivisions include Next Media Interactive. The corporation is known for introducing tabloid-style journalist into Hong Kong and Taiwan that set trends in both markets. Apple Daily was the first newspaper to use the massive graphics, bold headlines and full colour pages now common to all best-selling papers in Hong Kong and Taiwan. 

Next Media publications are also known for highly academic articles which attract a wide range of readers, including critics. Next Media has often taken a clear and sometimes proactive support for democratic groups in Hong Kong. Some companies with ties to the government of China never advertise in any papers or magazines owned by Next Media.

The bold style of journalism seems to trigger constant troubles with the triads with incidents of criminal damages at the offices of Next Media. Apple Daily and its parent company Next Media are thought to be pioneer of paparazzi and yellow Journalism in Hong Kong. A recent notable incident happened last year when Gillian Chung, a member of singing group Twins (band), was shot changing clothes at the backstage by spy camera installed by a subsidy magazine of Next Media. The case triggered debated over paparazzi acts in Hong Kong and regulation of paparazzi was considered. 



Monday Book - A set of four magazines sold together for HK$12 on Monday mornings that are more thematically male and commerce focussed. 

Friday Book - A set of three magazines sold together for HK$12 on Friday mornings that are more thematically female and leisure focussed. 

The Atnext.com network is the #1 online Chinese new, information and current events portal from Hong Kong and reaches more than 2 million users per month, audited by Neilsen//Netratings.



Publication websites

Vertical/community portalsIn addition to original exclusive content and social networking tools, these sites aggregate content from all other sites. 



Publication websites

Vertical/community portals

The top management committee of the company is the Board. The Board is responsible for overseeing the successful of Next Media and devising the company’s future strategy. The Board delegates the running of Next Media’s day-to-day operations to carefully chosen Executive Directors and Senior Management. The Board looks to the Management to ensure it appraised of all significant developments that may affect the company and its operations. 

There are four committees established by the Board, granted for different kinds of duties. 







Apple Daily LimitedApple Daily Online LimitedApple Daily Printing LimitedCameron Printing Company LimitedDatabase Gateway LimitedEasy Finder LimitedEasy Finder Hong Kong Marketing LimitedEasy Media LimitedEat and Travel Weekly Company LimitedNext Magazine Advertising LimitedNext Magazine Publishing LimitedNext Media Group Management LimitedNext Media Hong Kong/Publication Publishing LimitedParamount Printing Company LimitedRainbow Graphic &amp; Printing Company LimitedSudden Weekly Limited





