"Considerable evidence suggests a connection between heavy alcohol consumption and increased risk for cancer, with an estimated 2 to 4 percent of all cancer cases thought to be caused either directly or indirectly by alcohol" indicates the NIAAA." 3.6% of all cancer cases worldwide are related to alcohol drinking, resulting in 3.5% of all cancer deaths."

The International Agency for Research on Cancer (Centre International de Recherche sur le Cancer) of the World Health Organization has classified alcohol as a Group 1 carcinogen. Its evaluation states, "There is sufficient evidence for the carcinogenicity of alcoholic beverages in humans.… Alcoholic beverages are carcinogenic to humans (Group 1)."

The U.S. National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA) reports that  "Although there is no evidence that alcohol itself is a carcinogen, alcohol may act as a cocarcinogen by enhancing the carcinogenic effects of other chemicals. For example, studies indicate that alcohol enhances tobacco's ability to stimulate tumor formation in rats.  In humans, the risk for mouth, tracheal, and esophageal cancer is 35 times greater for people who both smoke and drink than for people who neither smoke nor drink,  implying a cocarcinogenic interaction between alcohol and tobacco-related carcinogens."

The NIAAA states that "Although epidemiologic studies have found a clear association between alcohol consumption and development of certain types of cancer, study findings are often inconsistent and may vary by country and by type of cancer."

In a review, Pöschl and Seitz list some possible mechanisms of alcohol as a carcinogen:

Purohita et al propose an overlapping list: 

A study of the influence of alcohol intake on tumor growth of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) in patients with type C cirrhosis, found that alcohol influenced tumor volume doubling time (TVDT). "In conclusion we found that alcohol intake was closely related to the tumor growth of HCC in patients with type C cirrhosis."

A study of chick embryos suggests that alcohol stimulates their tumor growth by fueling the production of a growth factor that stimulates blood vessel development in tumors. A 2006 study in mice showed moderate drinking resulted in larger and more robust tumors.

A study where high amounts of alcohol were given to mice suggests that it accelerates their cancer growth by speeding up the loss of body fat and depressing immune activity - particularly that of 'killer t-cells'.

A study found that "the ADH1C*1 allele and genotype ADH1C*1/1 were significantly more frequent in patients with alcohol-related cancers…" A European study has found two gene variants which offer "significant" protection against mouth and throat cancers. Alcohol is a known porphyrinogenic chemical. Several studies in Europe published on Pubmed have linked the inherited hepatic porphyrias with  a predisposition to hepatocellular carcinoma. Typical risk factors for HCC need not be present with the acute hepatic porphyrias, specifically acute intermittent porphyria, variegate porphyria and hereditary coproporphyria.  Porphyria cutanea tarda is also associated with HCC, but with typical risk factors including evidence of hepatotropic viruses, hemochromatosis and alcoholic cirrhosis. Tyrosinemia Type I, an inherited disorder in tyrosine metabolism impacting the second enzyme in the heme metabolic pathway is associated with a high risk of developing HCC in younger populations, including children.

Head and neck cancers, as used in this article, mean cancers of the mouth, esophagus, pharynx and larynx. The U.S. National Cancer Institute states "Drinking alcohol increases the risk of cancers of the mouth, esophagus, pharynx, larynx, and liver in men and women, … In general, these risks increase after about one daily drink for women and two daily drinks for men. (A drink is defined as 12 ounces of regular beer, 5 ounces of wine, or 1.5 ounces of 80-proof liquor.) … Also, using alcohol with tobacco is riskier than using either one alone, because it further increases the chances of getting cancers of the mouth, throat, and esophagus."

A WCRF panel found the evidence "convincing" that alcohol can increase the risk of cancers of the mouth, esophagus, pharynx and larynx. The International Head and Neck Cancer Epidemiology (INHANCE) Consortium co-ordinates a meta-study on the issue. A study looking at laryngeal cancer and beverage type concluded, "This study thus indicates that in the Italian population characterized by frequent wine consumption, wine is the beverage most strongly related to the risk of laryngeal cancer."

The American Cancer Society estimates that in 2007, cancer of the oral cavity (including the mouth, tongue, pharynx and all other parts of the oral cavity) constituted 2.3 % of all new cancers and 1.0% of all cancer deaths in the U.S. Cancers of the esophagus were 1.0% of all new cancers and 2.4% of all cancer deaths, while those of the larynx were under one percent of both new cases and that year

A review of the epidemiological literature published from 1966 to 2006 concluded that:



Although they are also located in the head or neck, alcohol consumption is not a risk factor for brain cancer, eye cancer, pituitary gland cancer, thymus cancer, salivary gland cancer, thyroid cancer, nasal cavity and paranasal sinus cancer, or adenoid cancer (see below).



There's scientific medical consensus that alcohol is a risk factor for breast cancer.The American Cancer Society lists alcohol as one of over 40 risk factors for the disease. Based on their analyses of the research evidence, the National Cancer Institute  and other organizations including Cancer Research UK,  the American Society of Clinical Oncology  the Mayo Clinic  and the Susan G. Komen breast cancer foundation  have concluded that alcohol, especially at high levels of consumption, is a risk factor for breast cancer.

Alcohol increases the risk of breast cancer in women. A review concludes that "studies confirm previous observations that there appears to be an association between alcohol intake and increased risk of breast cancer in women. On balance, there was a weak association between the amount of alcohol consumed and the relative risk."

The National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA) concludes that "Chronic alcohol consumption has been associated with a small (averaging 10 percent) increase in a woman's risk of breast cancer.  According to these studies, the risk appears to increase as the quantity and duration of alcohol consumption increases. Other studies, however, have found no evidence of such a link. "  The nature and inconsistency of the evidence has called into question the existence of any causal link between moderate alcohol consumption and breast cancer The Committee on Carcinogenicity of Chemicals in Food, Consumer Products concludes, "The new research estimates that a woman drinking an average of two units of alcohol per day has a lifetime risk of developing breast cancer 8% higher than a woman who drinks an average of one unit of alcohol per day. The risk of breast cancer further increases with each additional drink consumed per day. … The research also concludes that approximately 6% (between 3.2% and 8.8%) of breast cancers reported in the UK each year could be prevented if drinking was reduced to a very low level (i.e. less than 1 unit/week)."

It has been reported that "Two drinks daily increase the risk of getting breast cancer by about 25 percent." (NCI) but the evidence is inconsistent. The Framingham study has tracked individuals since the 1940s. Data from that research found that drinking alcohol moderately did not increase breast cancer risk.  Similarly, research by the Danish National Institute for Public Health found that moderate drinking had virtually no effect on breast cancer risk.        Breast cancer constitutes about 7.3% of all cancers.  Among women, breast cancer comprises 60% of alcohol-attributable cancers. One study suggests that women who frequently drink red wine may have an increased risk of developing breast cancer.

Alcohol consumption has been shown to increase the rate of breast cancer in women.

A study of 17,647 nurses found that high drinking levels more than doubled risk of breast cancer. "The relative risk of breast cancer was 2.30 … for alcohol intake of 22–27 drinks per week, compared to 1–3 drinks per week. Among alcohol consumers, weekly alcohol intake increased the risk of breast cancer with 2% for each additional drink consumed. Weekend consumption increased the risk with 4% for each additional drink consumed Friday through Sunday." Binge drinking of 4–5 drinks on the last weekday increased risk by 55%.

"The findings from this prospective study suggest that moderate alcohol consumption increases breast cancer risk."

A study showed that one or two alcoholic drinks a day increases the risk of breast cancer by 10 per cent compared with light drinkers who drank less than one drink a day. Women who have three or more drinks a day increase their risk of breast cancer by 30 per cent. The type of drink was not a factor. "A typical 50-year-old woman has a five-year breast cancer risk of about 3 percent. If her risk jumps by 30 percent, her individual risk is still only about 4 percent."

One of the largest studies of its kind has found that alcohol is a substantial risk factor for development of the most common type of breast cancer - the 70% of tumors that are classified as positive for both the estrogen and progesterone receptors (ER+/PR+). Researchers report that even moderate alcohol consumption, defined as one or two drinks per day, increased risk of developing this kind of cancer, and the more a woman drank, the higher her risk. Compared to women who did not drink at all, women who had three or more glasses of alcohol daily had as much as a 51% increased risk of ER+/PR+ breast cancer.

"Folate intake counteracts breast cancer risk associated with alcohol consumption" and "women who drink alcohol and have a high folate intake are not at increased risk of breast cancer".  Those who have a high (200 micrograms or more per day) level of  folate (folic acid or Vitamin B9) in their diet are not at increased risk of breast cancer compared to those who abstain from alcohol.  A study of over 17,000 Australian women aged 40-69 over a period of about ten years found that those who consumed 40 grams of alcohol (about three to four drinks) per day have a higher risk of breast cancer than do women who abstain from alcohol. However, in women who take 200 micrograms of folate or folic acid (Vitamin B9) every day, the risk of breast cancer drops below that of alcohol abstainers.  See Folic acid for more.

A study on mice suggests that, when breast cancer is established, drinking as little as two alcoholic drinks a day increases the growth rate of tumors. Alcohol causes cancer cells' blood vessels to grow which in turn fuels the growth of the tumor, a process known as angiogenesis.

Studies suggest that drinking alcohol during pregnancy may affect the likelihood of breast cancer in daughters. "For women who are pregnant, ingestion of alcohol, even in moderation, may lead to elevated circulating oestradiol levels, either through a reduction of melatonin or some other mechanism. This may then affect the developing mammary tissue such that the lifetime risk of breast cancer is raised in their daughters."

Male breast cancer is uncommon and, in Western populations, the incidence is less than one case per 100,000 men. There is no evidence to suggest that the effect of alcohol varies between genders. 

"Heavy alcohol intake increases the risk of breast cancer in men." "If you drink heavy amounts of alcohol, you have a greater risk of breast cancer."

Cirrhosis is commonly listed as one of the risk factors for liver cancer.   Approximately 5 percent of people with cirrhosis develop the disease.  "Prolonged heavy drinking has been associated in many cases with primary liver cancer. However, it is liver cirrhosis, whether caused by alcohol or another factor, that is thouight to induce the cancer. 

Primary liver cancer can affect anyone, but it occurs most frequently in people with advanced liver diseases. In the United States, the risk is greattest for those with long standing hepatitis B, advanced hepatitis C and cirrhosis. Because hepatitis viruses are so widespread, liver cancer is the second most common cause of cancer death worldwide.  "The average age of onset is 60 to 70 years" in the U.S., where "approximately 30% to 40% of patients with liver cancer have no discernable risk factor for liver cancer." 

"The cancer is relatively rare in North America and Europe. By contrast, in certain African and East Asian countries, it is the most common of all types of cancer." It's been reported that "Chronic hepatitis B infections cause 80% of all primary liver cancer worldwide." 

The NIAAA reports that "Prolonged, heavy drinking has been associated in many cases with primary liver cancer." However, it is liver cirrhosis, whether caused by alcohol or another factor, that is thought to induce the cancer."  

"The chances of getting liver cancer increase markedly with five or more drinks per day" (NCI). (Drinking coffee may reduce the risk. "Coffee drinking was inversely associated with HCC regardless of its aetiology." "These data support the hypothesis that there is an ingredient in coffee that protects against cirrhosis, especially alcoholic cirrhosis.")

"There is compelling epidemiologic data confirming the increased risk of cancer associated with alcohol consumption, which is supported by animal experiments."

In areas of Africa and Asia, liver cancer afflicts 50 or more people per 100,000 per year, usually associated with cirrhosis caused by hepatitis viruses. In the United States, liver cancer is relatively uncommon, afflicting approximately 2 people per 100,000, but excessive alcohol consumption is linked to as many as 36% of these cases by some investigators "Mortality rates of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) are high in Italy compared with other Western countries. … Overall, 61% of HCC were attributable to HCV [hepatitis C virus], 13% to HBV [hepatitis B virus], and 18% to heavy alcohol drinking." A study in the province of Brescia, northern Italy concluded, "On the basis of population attributable risks (AR), heavy alcohol intake seems to be the single most relevant cause of HCC in this area (AR: 45%), followed by HCV (AR: 36%), and HBV (AR: 22%) infection."

There's a lack of medical consensus about whether or not alcohol consumption is a risk factor for colorectal cancer, which refers to cancers of the colon and rectum. Cancer Research, the National Cancer Institute,the National Institutes of Health, the National Library of Medicine, the American Society of Clinical Oncology, and the Memorial Slocan-Kettering Cancer Center have concluded that alcohol is not a risk factor.

Alternatively, the American Cancer Society, the Mayo Clinic,and the Colorectal Cancer Coalition suggest that "heavy use" or "heavy drinking" may increase the odds of the disease. The M.D. Anderson Cancer Clinic  believes that drinking may increase risk.

A WCRF panel report finds the evidence "convincing" that alcoholic drinks increase the risk of colorectal cancer in men at consumption levels above 30 grams of absolute alcohol daily.  The National Cancer Institute states, "Heavy alcohol use may also increase the risk of colorectal cancer" 

The NIAAA reports that, "Epidemiologic studies have found a small but consistent dose-dependent association between alcohol consumption and colorectal cancereven when controlling for fiber and other dietary factors.  Despite the large number of studies, however, causality cannot be determined from the available data."

"Heavy alcohol use may also increase the risk of colorectal cancer" (NCI). One study found that "People who drink more 30 grams of alcohol per day (and especially those who drink more than 45 grams per day) appear to have a slightly higher risk for colorectal cancer."  Another found that "The consumption of one or more alcoholic beverages a day at baseline was associated with approximately a 70% greater risk of colon cancer."

One study found that "While there was a more than twofold increased risk of significant colorectal neoplasia in people who drink spirits and beer, people who drank wine had a lower risk. In our sample, people who drank more than eight servings of beer or spirits per week had at least a one in five chance of having significant colorectal neoplasia detected by screening colonoscopy.". 

Other research suggests that "to minimize your risk of developing colorectal cancer, it's best to drink in moderation"

The EPIC study suggests that "people who drink 15 grams of alcohol a day - equivalent to about two units - have about a 10 percent increased risk of bowel cancer. Those who drank more than 30 grams of alcohol - equivalent to three to four units which is less than a couple of pints of strong lager - increased their bowel cancer risk by around 25 per cent."

A study found, "The proportion of patients with adenomas was 29.6% in abstainers, 22.1% in moderate drinkers, and 36.7% in heavy drinkers." It concluded "Consumption of less than seven alcohol drinks per week does not increase the risk of having a colorectal adenoma. We found evidence in this study that moderate alcohol consumption among long-term smokers may potentially decrease the risk of an adenoma compared to abstainers."

A Japanese study concluded, "One fourth of colorectal cancer cases in men were attributable to an alcohol intake of ≥23 g/day."

Drinking may be a cause of earlier onset of colorectal cancer.

Colorectal cancer constitutes about 9.7% of all cancers. 

This section lists cancers where alcohol is not thought to be a risk factor but where papers have been published.

 Alcohol isn't a risk factor for ALL according to the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society,  the National Cancer Institute , the American Society of Clinical Oncology  the American Cancer Society  and Cancer Research UK  

The relevant research includes a review of the literaturepublished by the National Cancer Institute that placed maternal alcohol consumption during pregnancy and ALL in the category of "suggestive" and asserted that it is "unlikely to be an important risk factor." 

Alcohol doesn't increase the risk of AML according to leading medical organizations sucha as the National Cancer Institute,  the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society Society  the American Society of ClinicalOncology, the American Cancer Society Cancer Research UK and the Mayo Clinic

Research includes of review of the literature published by the National Cancer Institute that placed maternal alcohol consumption during pregnancy and AML in the category of "suggestive" and a case-control study in Italy that a non-significant inverse association (i.e., as consumption went up, risk went down) but increased risks at higher levels of consumption for AML

After examining the totality of medical research evidence, the National Cancer Institute  and other medical bodies     have concluded that alcohol isn't a danger for bile duct cancer.

Among others, the research literature includes a study published in the journal Cancer that found alcohol not to be a risk factor for extrahepatic bile duct cancer ." and a study that examined alcoholic patients in Swenden that found "limited evidence" that alcoholism is a risk factor for intrahepatic, but not for extrahepatic, bile duct cancer. ."

The consensus of scientific medical opinion is that alcohol doesn't increase the risk for bladder cancer. The National Cancer Institute  and other medical organizations have determined that alcohool doesn't increase the chance of getting bladder cancer based on their analyses of the scientific data

The research evidence includes a study of over 120,000 subjects in the Netherlands that found no significant relationship between drinking and bladder cancer,  a study of high alcohol intake northern Italians tht found no association, even at high levels of consumption, a study in Massachusetts that fouind no association, except that beer significantly reduced bladder cancer risk ." and a study in Los Angeles County that found that "alcohol consumption was strongly associated with reduced risk of bladder cancer." 

Major medical groups  have concluded, based opn the research evidence, that alcohol is not a risk factor for cervical cancer. 

A study concluded "that alcoholic women are at high risk for in situ and invasive cervical cancer" but attributed this to indirect, lifestyle-related reasons.

 Alcohol is not listed as a risk factor for CLL. 

A study concluded, "In conclusion, even though our study did not show a clear association between alcohol intake and leukemia risk, some of the patterns of the risk estimates (a possible J-shaped dose-response curve between alcohol intake and ALL, AML, and CLL risks, and the positive association between alcohol and CML), may be suggestive."

Alcohol isn't a risk factor for CML according to Cancer Research UKhttp://www.cancerhelp.org.uk/help/default.asp?=4836 the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society,  the American Cancer Society,and the American Society of Clinical Oncology

A population-based case-control studuy in Italy found a non-significant positive association between drinking and CML 

Alcohol is not a risk factor for DCIS.  

Illustrative is a population-based, case-control study of women in Connecticut that found no relationship between alcohol consumption and the disease. 

There's scientific medical consensus that alcohol doesn't increase the chance for having endometrial cancer. The National Cancer Institute  and other authoritative scientific medical groups such as the American Academy of Famuily Physicians and the Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center do not consider alcohol a risk for endometrial cancer, based on the totality of available evidence. 

"Thirteen studies to date have reported on the relationship between endometrial cancer and alcohol consumption. Only two of these studies have reported that endometrial cancer incidence is associated with consumption of alcohol; all the others have reported either no definite association, or an inverse association." (Six studies showed an inverse association; that is, drinking was associated with a lower risk of endometrial cancer) "…if such an inverse association exists, it appears to be more pronounced in younger, or premenopausal, women." "Our results suggest that only alcohol consumption equivalent to 2 or more drinks per day increases risk of endometrial cancer in postmenopausal women."

"Considering total alcohol drinking, the relative risk for alcohol drinkers vs. nondrinkers was 1.3 … No relation emerged between duration of alcohol consumption and risk of endometrial cancer. These findings suggest a potential link between alcohol drinking and endometrial cancer risk and are, in any case, inconsistent with a protective role of alcohol in endometrial carcinogenesis."

Alcohol is not a risk factor for this cancer.  

A review of the  literature found that consumption of beer was associated with increased risk in one study  but not in another

Drinking isn't a risk for fallopian tube cancer. 

A review of the research found no evidence that drinking is associated with fallopian tube cancer. 

Alcohol isn't among the over one dozen risks for gallbladder cancer identified by the American Cancer Society and other medical groups    after their assessments of the available research findings. 

The evidence includes studies such as the following: "It is concluded that high intake of alcoholic beverages is associated with the development of liver and gall bladder cancers among workers.". A study of female gallbladder cancer patients in Kerala, India found that 10% consumed alcohol. Another study found no relationship between alcohol consumption and the disease."There was no clear association between alcohol consumption and the risk. … Drinking may pose an elevated risk among men, but that seems to be less true among women."

 Inflammatory is the most aggressive and lethal breast cancer  Alcohol is not a risk factor for this disease.   

Alcohol was not identified as a risk factor in two recent reviews of the research literature.   

Drinking isn't a risk factor for hairy cell leukemia Hairy cell leukemia. 

A case-control study in the U.S. found there was no association between alcohol consumption and hairy cell leukemia.

Alcohol isn't a risk factor for leukemia (British spelling leukaemia) according to the National Cancer Institute,  the American Cancer Society, the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society  the National Institutes of Health and the Mayo Clinic

For additional information, see acute lymphocytic leukemia (ALL), acute myleoid leukemia (AML), chronic lymphocytic lymphoma (CLL), chronic myeloid leukemia (CML), eolsino;hilic l;eukemia, B-cell leukemia, T-cell leukemia, and hairy cell leukemia.

A sample of research includes the following:“Results from the few studies that have examined the association between alcohol use during pregnancy and childhood leukemia are conflicting,” reported a study that found an association." A review published by the National Cancer Institute placed maternal alcohol consumption during pregnancy in the category of “suggestive” and  asserts that it is “unlikely to be an important risk factor.” 

Leukemia constitutes about 7.8% of all cancers.

Drinking isn't a risk for lung cancer according to the analyses of scientific research by medical groups that have analyzed the totality of medical evidence. The National Cancer Institute,  the American Cancer Society,  the American Society of Clinical Oncology, the National Institutes of Health  the Sloan-Kettering Medical Center  and the M. D. Anderson Cancer Center  have all concluded, on the basis of the research evidence, that alcohol doesn't increase the risk of lung cancer.

The National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism reports that “A few studies have linked chronic heavy drinking with cancers of the ...lungs. However, the association is consistently weak and the majority of studies have found no association.” 

Chronic heavy alcohol consumption possibly increases the risk of lung cancer, but the evidence is inadequate to date. Commenting on a study by Freudenheim et al R. Curtis Ellison MD writes, "This study, like others, suggests a weak, positive association between consuming larger amounts of alcohol (&amp;gt;2 drinks a day) and lung cancer risk."

"Globally, lung cancer is the most frequent malignancy in males, while it is the fifth most common cancer in females." http://64.233.161.104/search?q=cache:nYLpSqhqaGUJ:www.emedicine.com/med/topic1336.htm+oat+cell+cancer&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=1 It is a major cause of death, constituting about 28.8% of all cancers in the U.S.. The American Cancer Society reports that "about 87% of lung cancer deaths are caused directly by smoking, and some of the rest are caused by environmental exposure to tobacco smoke."  

Alcohol isn't among the risks for melanoma identified by the National Cancer Institute  and other medical organizations such as the National Institutes of Health   the Skin Cancer Foundation  the American Academy of Family Physicians  the American Academy of Dermatology  the American Soiciety of Clinical Oncology  and the Mayo Clinic their assessments of the published scientific evidence, such as the following.

"In interview data from the U.S.A.'s Third National Cancer Survey, alcohol ingestion was associated with a higher occurrence of cancers of the breast, thyroid, and malignant melanoma. Data from other studies support the first two associations." "High alcohol consumption was associated with an increased risk for melanoma, which remained after adjustment for confounders…".  Other studies suggest there is no association for melanoma. "The risk of malignant melanoma was not influenced by alcohol consumption or smoking habits." "There was no evidence that … alcohol or polyunsaturated fats were associated with an increased risk."

There is no association between alcohol and Nonmelanoma skin cancer.

 Drinking isn't a risk factor for multiple myleoma.    

An example of the research is a case-control study of Italians. It found that drinking alcohol was associated with a reduced risk of the disease that did not reach a level of statistical significance  

Alcohol isn't a risk factor for Nasopharyngeal cancer 

Illustrative is a study of over 61,000 Singapore Chinese reporting that alcohol was not a risk factor for the disease,as did a study in Taiwan  and another in the People's Republic of China 

Drinking isn't a risk factor for this cancer. 

An extensive review of the research found no evidence that alcohol is associated with oral malignant melanoma 

The consensus of scientific medical opinion is that alcohool isn't a risk for ovarian cancer. The National Cancer Institute and other major medical bodies including the National Institutes of Health the American Society of Clinical Oncology and others have concluded this after examining all the scientific literature.

A pooled analysis of ten (10) prospective cohort studies conducted in a number of countries and including 529,638 women fouind that neither total alcohol consumption nor  alcohol from drinking beer, wine or spirits was associated with ovarian cancer risk.." The results of a case-control study in the region of Milan, Italy, "suggests that relatively elevated alcohol intake (of the order of 40 g per day or more) may cause a modest increase of epithelial ovarian cancer risk" and a review of the literature reported that associations were fouind between alcohol and cancers of the ovary but only at heavy consumption levels of 50 g and 100 g per day."

The consensus of medical opinion is that drinking isn't a risk for pancreatic cancer. That's the medical judgment of the Pancreatic Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins Universityand other health groups such as the National Cancer Institutethe National Institute of Health   the american Society of Clinical Oncology the Mayo Clinic  and Cancer Research UK. This medical consensus is based on analyses of the available evidence, some of which is listed below, and considers the scientific strength of each research study.

"A few studies have linked chronic heavy drinking with cancers of the stomach, pancreas, and lungs. However, the association is consistently weak and the majority of studies have found no association", write the NIAAA,  citing the International Agency for Research on Cancer..  Alcohol has been reported as a possible risks in some (but not in most) studies.   Drinking alcohol excessively is a cause of acute pancreatitis and chronic pancreatitis. "About 7 out of 10 cases of chronic pancreatitis are due to long term heavy drinking. Chronic pancreatitis is a known risk factor for cancer of the pancreas. But chronic pancreatitis that is due to alcohol doesn't increase risk as much as other types of chronic pancreatitis. So if there is a link with alcohol and pancreatic cancer risk, it is only very slight."

"Chronic heavy alcohol consumption is a risk factor for pancreatitis, but evidence for an association with pancreatic cancer is inconsistent. Overall, research suggests an increased risk in heavy drinkers , but no increased risk for people consuming up to 30g of alcohol a day."

A study found, "An index of total alcohol consumption showed a greater than two-fold risk for pancreatic cancer for heavy alcohol consumption (four or more drinksper day), primarily due to heavy beer and hard liquor consumption.

"Our findings indicate that alcohol drinking at the levels typically consumed by the general population of the United States is probably not a risk factor for pancreatic cancer. Our data suggest, however, that heavy alcohol drinking may be related to pancreatic cancer risk."

The Iowa Women's Health Study found that, "Relative risks of pancreatic cancer increased with the amount of alcohol consumed (Ptrend = 0.11) after adjustment for age, smoking status, and pack-years of smoking."

"Cases [people with pancreatic cancer] drank significantly more beer than controls (p = 0.005) and there was evidence of a positive trend in risk with total alcohol consumption."

A Swedish study found "Alcoholics had only a modest 40% excess risk of pancreatic cancer … The excess risk for pancreatic cancer among alcoholics is small and could conceivably be attributed to confounding by smoking."

A British study stated, "It was shown that the relative risk of cancer of the pancreas increases with fat and alcohol intakes, … Alcohol may be not directly involved in the aetiology of cancer of the pancreas: its effect could be due to the contents of some alcoholic beverages."

A Dutch study found that, "When compared with data from non-drinkers, the cumulative lifetime consumption of all types of alcohol in grams of ethanol … beer, spirits, red wine and fortified wine was not related to risk. The consumption of white wine was inversely associated with risk …. The uniformly reduced risk estimates for the lifetime number of drinks of white wine were based on small numbers …."

A Polish study concluded, "The findings regarding alcoholic beverages were overall null, although the weakly positive trend in risk with spirits consumption (p = 0.71) may deserve further investigation in view of the special nature of the source of spirits (vodka) in Poland."

"For the most part, consumption of total alcohol, wine, liquor and beer was not associated with pancreatic cancer."

"Data from these two large cohorts do not support any overall association between coffee intake or alcohol intake and risk of pancreatic cancer."

 Alcohol is not a risk factor for penile cancer    

A recent review of the research found no evidence suggesting any link between drinking and this disease

The Prostate Cancer Foundation  and other research groups such as the American Society of Clinical Oncology the Mayo Clinic  and the national Cancer Institute have evaluated the medical research literature and concluded that alcohol isn't a risk for prostate cancer. This scientific conclusion is based on careful analyses of the entire research literature, giving careful considertion of the quality of each study, such as the following.

"A meta-analysis published in 2001 found a small but significant increased risk for men drinking more than 50 g/day of alcohol, with a slightly higher risk for men consuming more than 100 g/day. Since that analysis, cohort studies in America have found increased risks for men drinking moderate amounts of spirits, and for ‘binge drinkers, but moderate consumption of beer or wine has not been linked to an increased risk."

"Associations were also found between alcohol consumption and cancers of the ovary and prostate, but only for 50 g and 100 g a day." However, one study concludes, "In contrast to the majority of previous studies, we found a positive association between moderate alcohol consumption and the risk of prostate cancer. Liquor, but not wine or beer, consumption was positively associated with prostate cancer."

The Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center "found that men who consumed four or more glasses of red wine per week reduced their risk of prostate cancer by 50 percent". They "found no significant effects — positive nor negative — associated with the consumption of beer or hard liquor and no consistent risk reduction with white wine, which suggests that there must be a beneficial compound in red wine that other types of alcohol lack. That compound … may be an antioxidant called resveratrol, which is abundant in the skins of red grapes.".

Alcohol is not a risk factor for this genetic cancer. 

A review of the literature found no evidence that alcohol consumption is a risk factor for this disease 

Alcohol is not a risk factor for salivary gland cancer.  

Alcohol was found to be unrelated to salivary gland cancer in a case-control study in the U.S. 

There's medical consensus that alcohol isn't a risk factor for small intestine cancer. Major medical organizations have evaluated the research evidence and concluded that drinking doesn't increase the risk for cancers of the small intestine.        

A study of small intestine cancer patients reported that alcohol consumption was associated with adenocarcinomas and malignant carcinoid tumors.

"Heavy ethanol intake (&amp;gt;80 g a day) was also a risk factor in both men and women, with no increased risk associated with lower levels of ethanol intake, reported a study of patients in Los angeles County (US)."

"Alcohol and tobacco consumption did not increase the risk of adenocarcinoma of the small intestine. … While the present data are inconsistent with a major effect of tobacco or alcohol, a moderate association between these factors and small bowel cancer may have been obscured by the play of chance."

"Tobacco and alcohol consumption were unrelated to risk of small intestine cancer…"

Alcohol doesn't increase the risk of developing stomach cancer according to medical organizations that have analyzed the scientific research published to date.  

That research includes studies such as these:"While alcohol has been extensively studied as a cause of stomach cancer there is no conclusive evidence that it increases risk. However, results from at least three studies suggest that heavy alcohol consumption may increase the risk of stomach cancer in heavy smokers."

A Taiwanese study concluded, "… cigarette smoking may play the most harmful role in the initial development of gastric cancer, and that drinking alcohol may promote the process."

A Norwegian study found that, "No statistically significant associations between various degrees of exposure to alcohol and risk of gastric cancer was revealed, but combined high use of cigarettes (&amp;gt;20/day) and alcohol (&amp;gt;5 occasions/14 days) increased the risk of noncardia gastric cancer nearly 5-fold (HR = 4.90 [95% CI = 1.90-12.62]), compared to nonusers."

Alcohol consumption, even when chronic and heavy, probably does not affect the risk of stomach cancer.

Alcohol is not a risk factor for testicular cancer according to the American Society of Clinical Oncology the National Cancer Institute http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/Sites_Types/testicular  

A review concluded that "There is no firm evidence of a causal relation between behavior risks [tobacco, alcohol and diet] and testicular cancer."

Alcohol isn't considered a risk for thyroid cancer by the American Thyroid Association  and other medical organizations that have evaluated the existing research evidence, including the national Cancer Institute   the American Cancer Society and the American Socidty of Clinical Oncology 

"In interview data from the U.S.A.'s Third National Cancer Survey, alcohol ingestion was associated with a higher occurrence of cancers of the breast, thyroid, and malignant melanoma. Data from other studies support the first two associations." Another study suggests that drinking in moderation significantly reduces the risk of some malignant tumors such as thyroid cancer in women.  However, another study concludes, "A reduced risk associated with alcohol was eliminated after adjustment for smoking…".

Alcohol is not a risk factor for vaginal cancer.    

A Danish study found that "Abstinence from alcohol consumption was associated with low risk for both VV-SCCvagina and VV-SCCvulva in our study."

A study concluded that alcoholic women are at high risk for cancer of the vagina. In both studies, indirect, lifestyle-related reasons were cited.

The medical research evidence doesn't indicate that alcohol increases the risk of developing vulvar cancer, according to reviews of the existing research by the National Cancer Instituteand other major organizations

The reserch includes studies such as the following: A study that reported "No consistent association emerged between milk, meat, liver, alcohol and coffee consumption and risk of vulvar cancer." A Danish study that found that "Abstinence from alcohol consumption was associated with low risk for both VV-SCCvagina and VV-SCCvulva in our study." And a Swedish study that concluded concluded that alcoholic women are at no higher risk for cancer of the vulva.

A multi-center case-control study of subjects in Spain, Italy, Ireland, Germany, France, and the Czech Republic found results "consistent with previous studies, suggesting a protective effect of alcohol on HL." 

A population-based case-control study in Italy reported a protective effect of alcohol consumption on risk of HL among non-smokers. Analysis of data from a series of case-control studies in Northern Italy revealed a modest positive effect of alcohol on lowering risk of HL among both smokers and non-smokers.

 "Moderate alcohol consumption was associated with a lower risk of renal cell cancer among both women and men in this pooled analysis" of 12 prospective studies of 760,044 people. A pooled analysis of two case-control studies in Italy found "an inverse association between alcohol drinking and RCC. Risks continued to decrease even above eight drinks per day (i.e. &amp;gt;100 g/day) of alcohol intake, with no apparent levelling in risk."

A prospective cohort study of 59,237 women in Sweden found that alcohol was associated with a reduction in risk of RCC in general and especially for women age 55 and older. Among older women, light-to-moderate driniking reduced the risk of kidney cancer by 56%.Thus,"alcohol consumption may be associated with decreased risk of RCC." Researchers who conducted a study in Iowa reported that"In this population-based case-control investigation, we report further evidence that alcohol consumption decreases the risk of RCC among women but not among men. Our ability to show that the association remains after multivariate adjustment for several new confouonding factors Ii.e., diet, physical activity, and family history) strengthens support for a true association.

A small study in Italy reported finding no relationship between alcohol consumption and risk of kidney cancer among either men or women.

A study of a large cohort of Finnish male smokers found that risk of kidney cancer declined as total consumption of alcohol increased.  Data  from 88,759 women who were tracted for 20 years and from 47,828 men who were observed for 14 years suggest that alcohol reduces the risk of kidney cancer in both men and women.&amp;gt;ref&amp;gt;Jung Eun Lee et al. Total fluid intake and use of individual beverages and risk of renal cell cancer in two large cohorts. Cancer Epidemiology Biomarkers &amp; Prevention, 2006, 15, 1204-1211 Compared with nondrinkers, men who drank one or more drinks per day had a 31% lower risk of kidney cancer among 161,126 Hawaii-Los angeles Multiethnic Cohort participants.

Alcohol doesn't increase the risk of developing non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (NHL). That's the conclusion reached by the Lymphoma Research Foundation and other medical groups including the National Cancer Institute,Cancer Research UK,  the American Cancer Society,  the Mayo Clinic, Merck Manuals, and the Lymphoma Information Network  after evaluating the existing evedence. However, there's much evidence that alcohol may reduce the risk of developing NHL.

Many studies have found a protective effect on NHL from drinking. A pooled analysis of data from nine (9) case-control studies from the US, the UK, Sweden and Italy found that men and women who drank alcohol had a lower risk of NHL than did those who didn't drink, but the risk didn't decrease with increasing alcohol consumption. ." Similarly, a prospective study of over 473,000 men and women in the US founbd that alcohol consumers, compared to nondrinkers, had a lower risk for NHL both overall and for its main subtypes. A study of men and women in Los Angeles and Seattle also found that drinkers had a lower risk of NHL than those who didn't drink

Some studies have found a protective effect on NHL of drinkin gsome forms of alcoholic beverage or in some demographic groups. A study of men in the US found that consumption of wine, but not beer or spirits, was associated with a reduced NHL risk  and a large European  study found a protective effect of alcohol among men and in non-Mediterranean countries.." A study of older women in Iowa found alcohol to reduce the risk of NHL and the amount of alcohol  consumed, rather than the type of alcohollic beverages, appeared to be the main determinant in reducing risk. ."

Some studies have not found a protective effect from drinking. Research in England found no association between frequency of drinking and NHL  and research in Sweden found that total beerm wine , or liquor intake was not associated with any major subtype of NHL examined, apart from an association bwtween high wine consumption and increased risk of chronic lymphocytic leukemia.."

One study found alcohol to be a risk factor for NHL. A Uruguayan study found that drinking beer and "mate" were risk factors for NHL in that country.   Very high levels of carcinogenic polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) have been measured in mate, suggesting to researchers that its carcinogenicity may be related to its high PAH content.

Although it did not investigate alcohol as a possible risk factor, one study found that heavy smoking and heavy drinking, especially when combined, were associated with lower survival rates in NHL patients.."

This section lists cancers where alcohol is not thought to be a risk factor but where published papers have not yet been found.



Main article: Recommended maximum intake of alcoholic beveragesAs outlined above, there is no recommended alcohol intake with respect to cancer risk alone as it varies with each individual cancer. See Recommended maximum intake of alcoholic beverages for a list of governments' guidances on alcohol intake which, for a man, range from 140–280g per week.

One meta-analysis suggests that risks of cancers may start below the recommended levels. "Risk increased significantly for drinkers, compared with non-drinkers, beginning at an intake of 25 g ( 2 standard drinks) per day for the following: cancers of the oral cavity and pharynx (relative risk, RR, 1.9), esophagus (RR 1.4), larynx (RR 1.4), breast (RR 1.3), liver (RR 1.2), colon (RR 1.1), and rectum (RR 1.1)"











