

The Edge is a premium mid-size crossover SUV (CUV) manufactured by  Ford, based on the Ford CD3 platform — and marketed in slightly modified form as the Lincoln MKX.  The platform is shared with Mazda CX-9 crossover, the Ford Fusion, Mercury Milan, and the Lincoln MKZ sedans. The Edge is the smaller of Ford's present crossover lineup as follows:



The Edge made its public debut at the 2006 North American International Auto Show in January 2006, with production starting in the October 2006 as a 2007 model, with the first ones reaching dealerships just before December 25, 2006, because of a brief delay in production due to issues with the supplier . The Edge (codename U387) is built at Ford's Oakville Assembly Complex in Oakville, Ontario, Canada.

As a crossover vehicle, the Edge bridges the gap between minivans like the now discontinued Freestar, and truck-based sport utility vehicles such as the Explorer. The Edge officially slots below the Taurus X in Ford's crossover SUV lineup. The Edge implements Ford's front end design with a three bar chrome grille.

Although North America is the primary market for the vehicle, Ford also intends to market the Edge in 40 additional countries, including United Arab Emirates, Saudi Arabia, Jordan, and Panama. The Edge is also marketed in Israel.

Edge's U.S. sales have increased steadily since its launch, outselling all other mid- to large-sized crossover SUVs from January to June 2007 with over 58,000 units sold.  2007 sales totaled over 130,000 units. The Edge is now the best-selling mid-size SUV in the United States.

The Ford Edge and Lincoln MKX are among the first vehicles to use Ford's new 3.5 L Duratec 35 V6 engine. This new 213-cubic-inch engine produces 265 hp (197 kW) and 250 ft·lbf (186 N·m) and is mated to the new 6F six-speed automatic transmission, which was co-developed with General Motors. Fuel economy is rated at 15 (AWD) to 16 (FWD) mpg-US in the City and 22 (AWD) to 24 (FWD) mpg-US on the Highway.

The Edge is available with both front-wheel drive and all-wheel drive.

Initially introduced in 2007 with the three trim levels SE, SEL, and SEL Plus, the SEL Plus was superseded by the Limited trim in 2008.

Standard features on all trims include air conditioning; cruise control; driver's seat lumbar support; tilt and telescoping steering wheel; power windows, power door locks, and power mirrors; remote keyless entry; and P235/65R17 tires on alloy wheels.

Safety equipment is includes standard dual front airbags, front side-impact airbags, side curtain airbags, anti-lock brakes, traction control, electronic stability control, and a tire-pressure monitoring system.

National Highway Traffic Safety Administration (NHTSA) Crash Test Ratings

Frontal Driver: 

Frontal Passenger: 

Side Impact: 

Rollover: 

The Sport appearance package for the Ford Edge debuted at the 2008 Chicago Auto Show, with sales to begin as a 2009 model. It will come with standard all-body colored trim and 20-inch wheels. Massive 22-inch wheels are an optional factory upgrade.

Ford Canada announced in June 2007, that a gasoline-electric hybrid version of the Edge will debut in the 2010 model year. The model is expected to use a new hybrid system from Ford, pairing Electric motor to a V6 engine. 

Additionally, after public presentation in 2007, Ford has been carefully pointing on future production of its HySeries Edge.  This vehicle uses a Hydrogen Fuel Cell along with plug-in charging of its lithium-ion battery pack, for a combined range of over 200 miles (320 km). The HySeries system was first introduced in the Ford Airstream concept from the 2007 Detroit Auto Show. A concept of the Ford Edge with the HySeries Drive was unveiled in the 2007 Washington DC Auto Show. The HySeries system is related to General Motors E-Flex platform. The E-Flex Platform was introduced in the 2007 Detroit Auto Show as the power train of the Chevrolet Volt concept.

Ford Edge has received several honors:









