

The Saab 9-5 is an executive car produced by the Swedish automobile maker Saab. It was introduced in 1997 as the replacement to the Saab 9000. The 9-5 replaced the 9000 in the spring of 1997 for the 1998 model year. At the time, the car represented a great leap forward for Saab. In the US, the 9-5 was introduced in the spring of 1998, for the 1999 model year.

The 9-5 is available with sedan and station wagon body styles. Aerodynamically, the sedan's drag coefficient is 0.29, and the station wagon's is 0.31(U.S. version 0.33), which was introduced in 1999. It features such innovations as tracks to secure cargo down and a sliding load floor to make loading easier.

Badged as a 95, Saab consistently advertises it as the 9-5. The name is pronounced "nine five" rather than "ninety five". This model should not be confused with the Saab 95, produced from 1959 to 1978.

The 9-5 is powered by Saab's B205 and B235 straight-4 engines, and in Europe by Alfa Romeo's 1.9 JTD 16V diesel straight-4. A version of the GM 54° V6 powered by a unique asymmetrical low-pressure turbocharger was available from 1999 to 2003.  This engine was available only with an automatic transmission, and cars with this engine installed are distinguishable by their twin tailpipes. It was only available on Arc, SE, and Griffin models. In 2004, the V6 engine was replaced by a high pressure turbo straight-4 engine producing 220HP. By 2008 this engine was producing 260HP even in the non-Aero model (US model).

The B235-based 9-5 models have suffered an abnormally high rate of engine failures due to engine oil sludge.  This primarily affected the 1999-2002 models.  SAAB refined the engine's positive crankcase ventilation system (PCV) for the 2003 and later model years, virtually eliminating the problem.  Additionally, SAAB created update kits to retrofit to the 1999-2002 cars since they cannot be easily modified to accept the 2003 and later system. However, this fix was discontinued by Saab in 2005 after they received numerous complaints about increased oil consumption. Mounting complaints by 9-5 owners forced GM to offer an 8 year warranty on the engine in 4 cylinder models, provided the owner can produce proof that they followed the manufacturer's oil change intervals. Saab now also recommend the use of fully synthetic oil as a preventative measure.

The 9-5 was available with an Aisin Warner 4-speed automatic transmission from 1997-2001. A new Aisin Warner unit replaced the dated 4-speed automatic with a 5-speed automatic. A 5-speed manual transmission is fitted as standard to the base models and the Aero.

In 2005, an updated version of the 2.0 L turbocharged I4 was introduced in the European market together with the 2006 9-5. The engine is sold as 2.0t BioPower, and it is optimized to run on E85 producing 132 kW (180 hp) at 5500 r/min. There is also a 2.3t BioPower version sold from 2007. 

There is a Saab 9-5 E100 Concept, based on the turbo 2.0.

The Saab BioPower Hybrid concept/prototype is based on the Saab 9-5 E100, with three additional electric motors.

The 9-5 continued Saab's long-running tradition of offering class leading safety features and pioneered the availability of ventilated seats with Saab Active Head Restraints (SAHR), that moved up and forward to prevent whiplash when the car is struck from the rear. This feature won technology and safety awards, in Australia, Denmark and the United Kingdom. The Saab 9-5 also has been one of the first cars to have extensive side-crash protection. In the front seats are torso and head airbags on even the oldest of 9-5s, making it unique in that few other late 1990s vehicles provide the same feature. Even more important is the side structure, which includes a passenger cage and crumple zones. The design has been proven by the IIHS to protect occupants in side crashes, even without the addition of side airbags to the rear seats.

Another Saab feature is the "Night Panel", which permits dousing of the instrument panel lighting, except for essential information, for less distraction when night driving.

In the United States, OnStar is standard.

Earlier it was said that an all new 9-5 would be presented by the end of 2008, for the 2009 model year. Recent information however suggests that the current 9-5 will be replaced in 2009, for the 2010 model year. The new model will be based on GM's Epsilon 2 platform, shared with the next generation 9-3, and probably built in Ruesselsheim, Germany at the Opel plant.

Saab sells a performance oriented 9-5 called the Aero. The 9-5 Aero was first released in 2000 with a 230hp 2.3t B235R engine. The 9-5 Aero represents the flagship car and has a long list of standard features. The 9-5 Aero is also fitted with a sport tuned suspension and body side moldings. In 2002 a 250hp 2.3 turbo engine was made standard. The high-powered version of the 9-5 in the current form produces 260 hp ECE (194 kW) and 350 N·m (258 ft·lbf) of torque (370 N·m or 272 ft·lbf with its 20-second overboost function accessible on the manual transmission equipped version). Hirsch Performance, MapTun Performance, and Nordic Uhr and BSR AB, all tuners specializing in Saab models, can increase this to a maximum of approximately 300 hp ECE (220 kW). http://www.hirsch-performance.ch/Content.aspx?path=/Products/Leistung/E280008281

Currently, the 260hp B235R is the standard engine in the 9-5 in both the 2.3T and Aero trims. In addition, almost all standard features on the Aero are now standard on the 2.3T, the exceptions being sport-tuned chassis, two-tone leather upholstery, "anniversary" rims and brushed aluminum interior trim, all of which are standard on Aero and not available on the 2.3T.

The Aero's 2.3T engine accelerates the car from 80 to 120 km/h faster than a Porsche 911 Carrera 4s.

Additionally, companies like MapTun Performance have developed aftermarket BioPower conversion kits for the 9-5 Aero and other Saab models. Larger injectors and remapped software in the Engine Control Unit (ECU) allows impressive power levels from 285 hp/330 lb/ft in the Aero model on E85 Ethanol.









