



Prince Shōtoku (聖徳太子, Shōtoku Taishi, 573–621), also known as Prince Umayado  (厩戸皇子, Umayado no ōji), was a regent and a politician of the Asuka period in Japan. His existence, however, is disputed.

Prince Shōtoku looked to China for political and religious inspiration.

Shōtoku, inspired by Confucius' teachings, succeeded in establishing a centralized government during his reign. In 603, he established the twelve official ranks at court. He is credited with promulgating a Seventeen-article constitution, although contemporary scholars question the attribution based on its style. 

The Prince was a proponent of Buddhism and composed commentaries on the Lotus Sutra, the Vimalakirti Sutra, and the Sutra of Queen Srimala.  He also commissioned the Shitennō-ji Temple in Settsu province (present-day Osaka). Shōtoku's name has been linked with Hōryū-ji in Yamato province. Documentation at Hōryū-ji, in fact, claim Suiko and Shōtoku as founders during the year 607.  Archaeological excavations in 1939 have confirmed that Prince Shōtoku's palace, the Ikaruga-no-miya (斑鳩宮), occupied the eastern part of the current temple complex, where the Tō-in (東院) sits today.

Although Shōtoku admired China from afar, China seems to have taken the initiative in opening relations with Japan. Sui Emperor, Yangdi (kensui taishi) dispatched a message in 605 which said:

"The sovereign of Sui respectfully inquires about the sovereign of Wa."  Shōtoku responded by sponsoring a mission led by Ono no Imoko in 607. The Prince's own message contains the earliest written instance in which the Japanese archipelago is named "Nihon," literally, sun-origin. The salutation said:

"From the sovereign of the land of the rising sun (nihon/hi izuru) to the sovereign of the land of the setting sun."There are historians who have concluded that Prince Shōtoku was not a historical person at all. There are also historians who are against this claim.

Prince Shotoku laid the foundations for the rise of a stable political and economical systems through his prudent reign and reforms. His patronage of Buddhism brought in a flowering of Japanese art and culture. His legendary wisdom and far-sightedness, as well as peaceful foreign policy with Japan's neighbours has kept him in the public eyes in high esteem, even until today. In his honour, the 10,000 Yen banknote featured his image, the highest denomination. The 10,000 yen banknote with him was printed from the 1950s until the 1980s.

He is known by several titles, although his real name is Prince Umayado (厩戸皇子, Umayado no ōji, literally the prince of the stable door) since he was born in front of a stable. He is also known as Toyotomimi (豊聡耳, Toyotomimi) or Kamitsumiyaō (上宮王, Kamitsumiyaō). In the Kojiki, his name appears as Kamitsumiya no Umayado no Toyotomimi no Mikoto (上宮之厩戸豊聡耳命, Kamitsumiya no Umayado no Toyotomimi no Mikoto).  In the Nihon Shoki, in addition to Umayado no ōji, he is referred as 豊耳聡聖徳, 豊聡耳法大王, and  法主王.  The popular name Prince Shōtoku first appeared in Kaifūsō written in 751, more than a hundred years after his death.





