Lego Space theme featuring astronauts and spaceships. It was introduced in 1978. Space was one of the most expansive themes in Lego history, and contained over 200 individual sets. It was marketed under the Legoland banner until 1991. The name was changed to Lego System in 1992, but was dropped after 1999. 

The first Lego Space sets were a leap forward in Lego design. Classic space next to the castle and pirate lines is one of the most beloved and memerable of legos products.  Compared to the Lego Company's previous releases of spacecraft sets Space Rocket (year unknown, probably 1950s) Rocket Base (1973) and Moon Landing(1975) this new theme of sets boasted new parts and building techniques previously unseen. Although plenty of basic bricks were used, there were now parts with finer detail used in smoother-looking ships and multi-purpose vehicles.

Despite curiosities and oddities such as steering wheels used to direct spacecraft, and often no inflight pilot protection other than a spacesuit, simple new constructs sparked builders' imaginations. Starting with spaceships and basic wheeled vehicles, the theme developed, occasionally mirroring science fiction designs. As Lego Space expanded, the basic pattern of ground-buggies, walking robots, small and large spaceships, and bases emerged. 

Early Space sets had a simplistically modern yet colorful charm unrivaled by any other mass-produced science-fiction toy of the time. Many of the theme's more specialized pieces had yet to be developed, although when Space was first introduced, many parts were new, or were older parts made in new colors. Examples of these early simple sets include:Rocket Launcher (1978), Space Shuttle, and Mobile Tracking Station (both 1979).

Perfectly suited for utilitarian Lego Space, gray had finally become a major color for a Lego theme, especially as more plate-type parts were made in that color. Most often, gray Space sets were paired with green windows. The other predominant colors were blue with yellow windows. With the introduction of the Starfleet Voyager in 1981, classic spaceships began to appear in white, with blue canopies. 

Popular spaceships and vehicles from the Classic Space era include:Galaxy Explorer (1979), Starfleet Voyager (1980), Mobile Rocket Transport (1982), Galaxy Commander (1983), and Cosmic Fleet Voyager (1986).

The major surface bases were:Space Command Center (1978), Alpha-1 Rocket Base (1979), Beta-1 Command Base (1980), Intergalactic Command Base (1984), and Polaris-I Space Lab (1987).

Baseplates from this era:Space Landing Plates (1979), and Crater Plates (1979)



Value packs were released between 1983 and 1987 comprising of 3 separate sets and prove popular with classic space collectors. 



Other more obscure miscellaneous Classic Space sets include-



The first unified and truly themed Space sets, Blacktron took to the stars in black with yellow trim, and red and yellow transparent pieces. (The odd man out was the Meteor Monitor, which was white and black with red transparents.) Blacktron minifigures (or "minifigs" for short) wore black jumpsuits akin to today's military pilots, with white trim and opaque black visors. Stylish, sleek and intimidating, Blacktron was a major step up from the rather clunky design values of Classic Space. It featured a large spacecraft, the "Renegade," which set the tone for all future big ships by splitting into a number of smaller modules, including a storage bin for a small wheeled vehicle; these modules could be recombined not just with each other, but with modules from other vehicles in the set as well, specifically the "Invader" and "Battrax." This modular interchangeability has been a staple of Lego Space ever since.

Popular Blacktron vehicles include Renegade, Invader, Battrax (all 1987) and Alienator (1988). The base was Message Intercept Base (1988).

For clarification, Blacktron is often referred to as Blacktron I, as Lego released Blacktron II in 1991. Though Blacktron officially ended in 1988, the Meteor Monitor (1990) was released. Considering Blacktron II's slightly altered color scheme it could be viewed as being from between the "upgrade" era of Blacktron to Blacktron II.



Taking over from Classic Space and inheriting its white-and-blue color scheme, "Futuron" depicted an austere yet bustling settlement on the surface of a planetary body, probably Earth's moon. Its minifigures came in many colors (red, blue, yellow and black), but all shared the same uniform - a zipper crossing from hip to shoulder, with color on top and white below - as well as light-blue-tinted helmet visors. Instead of a big ship, the theme centered around the Monorail Transport System, which featured a battery-powered train system and some twenty linear feet of track.

Popular Futuron vehicles include Stardefender 200 (1987) and Monorail Transport System (1988). The base was Cosmic Laser Launcher (1987). (Although not officially a Futuron set, the aforementioned Polaris-I Space Lab is often considered a Futuron base as it was released at the same time, and shares Futuron colors and design and perhaps hinted at that the Classic race and the Futuron race where one and the same.



In 1989, Lego made a storyline decision. Blacktron, previously operating in a moral void, were now declared the "bad guys" of Lego Space; opposing them and defending Futuron from them were the Space Police, a series of brave individuals whose spacecraft were black and blue with red transparent elements. (This would be a continuing theme of space, having "bad guy" races, "good guy" races and "civilian" races between them.) Space Police re-introduced the idea of modular systems, on a smaller but also grander scale. The Space Police theme features three spaceships, two wheeled vehicles and a ground-based space station; all but the smallest buggy comes with a Space Police jail cell , supplied with a Blacktron occupant. These jail cells were identical from set to set and could be traded around between vehicles with no hassle whatsoever. This theme marks the beginning of Lego Space's greatest period of success, and is one of the most well-loved themes of the collection; complete models of the largest ship, the Mission Commander, have been known to sell for USD $90 via online vendors.

Popular Space Police vehicles include Spy-Trak I and Mission Commander (both 1989). The base was Space Lock-Up Isolation Base (1989).

Space Police is often referred to as Space Police I as Space Police II was released by Lego in 1992.



In an effort to increase interactivity, Lego introduced magnets in the next Space theme, M:Tron, who took over the "civilian" role of the Futuron race. Vehicles in this set, distinctive for their red hulls, gray trim and neon-green canopies, are devoted primarily to mining out precious ores. They often featured crane-like attachments with magnets for picking up small cargo and storage boxes. These boxes, unfortunately, were generally not interchangeable. The figures wore white pants, a red shirt with an "M" logo in the middle, and a black helmet with glowing green visor.

Popular M:Tron vehicles include Stellar Recon Voyager and Mega Core Magnetizer (both 1990).

M:Tron was the first major Space theme that did not include a base of any kind; all sets were vehicles. M:Tron was also the last space theme to carry the Legoland banner. Lego System was the name used starting in 1992.

Unlike previous themed Space series, the M:Tron sets did not look like they were made for fighting, either for good or evil. Note also that the British names for sets, while not as flashy and extreme sounding as their American equivalents, give a clear picture of vehicles meant for rescue and research.  * Actually, there are two versions of this set. The earlier one is on all boxes and the cover of the building instructions. There's a little difference with the rotor assembly, slightly different parts needed to build.



In 1991, Blacktron received a makeover: black with white trim, M:Tron's neon green canopies, as well as new uniforms. It also replaced the creative but haphazard interchangeability of Blacktron I with refined and mostly-uniform cockpit globes (best seen here), which could be switched unimpeded between those ships.  To the dismay of fans, however, only four sets of eleven featured them (the Alpha Centauri Outpost, Spectral Starguider, Aerial Intruder, and the Allied Avenger).  Some fans were also disappointed that, aside from a proliferation of small (50-element-or-less) vehicles, Blacktron II seemed to be mostly a rehash Blacktron I on a set-by-set basis.

Popular Blacktron II vehicles include Spectral Starguider and Aerial Intruder (both 1991). The base was Alpha Centauri Outpost (1991).



Space Police was the next theme to receive a makeover, remodeled into black and grey with green canopies and red trim. The standardized jail cells were retained, though only three vehicles could accept them; the theme also lacked a permanent installation like Space Police I's Space Lock-Up Isolation Base (1989). It was the first Space set to replace the Lego standard smiley face minifig head with a more complex graphic (in this case, the face augmented by a fringe of hair and an ear-mounted microphone). Finally, Space Police II ships were known for being under-armed; several vehicles sported no overt weapons (such as the Galactic Chief, whose epaulet-wearing pilot is armed with only a hand-held blaster that might actually be a bullhorn), and the others featured only two small cockpit-mounted weapons (including the theme's heavyweight multi-module spaceship, the Galactic Mediator).

Popular Space Police II vehicles include Rebel Hunter and Galactic Mediator (both 1992). Space Police II did not include any bases. 

Though Space Police II officially ended in 1993, Starion Patrol (1993) was re-released as Space Police Car in 1999.



Taking place in a time and location that should be fairly obvious, Ice Planet can be considered M:Tron's replacement as the "civilian" race. It featured new elements such as a distinct setting (an ice planet, dubbed "Krysto" on one of the boxes), skis (both on vehicles and personnel), bright neon cockpits (orange), and bright neon chainsaws (orange). As befitting an icebound theme, most of its vehicles were ground-based; many of its smaller vehicles also showcased satellite dishes. 

Popular Ice Planet vehicles include Ice-Sat V and their largest and only starship the Deep Freeze Defender (both 1993). The latter is often regarded as one of the best all-time Lego starships. The base was Ice Station Odyssey (1993). All three sets included Apollo type rockets.

Though Ice Planet officially ended in 1994, Snow Scooter (1994) was re-released as Space Diver in 1999.

In a bit of trivial information, the Ice Planet 2002 line has taken on a new pop-culture following on the /toy/ imageboard on popular website, 4chan. The bright neon chainsaws have become in-jokes on the board, as well as one of the minifigs, known in the line as "Commander Cold."



Taking over the "good guy" space race from the Space Police II was the Unitron, a more military themed group. Unitron also features elements from the classic Futuron line, as it revolved around a large monorail system powered by a 9V battery; it retained Lego interchangeability in the form of small, sleek cockpits which could dock on the front or top of its vehicles. Unfortunately, aside from a ground installation, a large buggy, an advanced looking spaceship, and aforementioned monorail, the theme was underdeveloped, a fact that is still lamented today.

The two Unitron vehicles were Crater Cruiser and their largest starcraft Star Hawk II (both 1995) (which was only half the size for most of the other space races' largest starships). The base was Space Station Zenon (1995). The monorail system was Monorail Transport Base (1994). This set was the last Lego monorail set released. 

Dark gray quietly made an appearance as a new Lego Space color in Unitron minifigure torsos. The color appears in no other parts in this theme but for a rock feature on the space station zenon.



Red and black, with blue cockpits, Spyrius homeworld appeared to be a craggy, desolate moon. The Spyrius took over the "bad guy" race space theme as a group of spies out to steal technology and valuable data. Official evidence of a Spyrius attack against Unitron is documented in this 1994 catalog picture. Commercial clips also featured a high scale attack of Spyrius against the monorail.

This nine-set theme was the first to feature robot minifigures. 

Popular Spyrius vehicles include Saucer Scout and their largest starcraft the Saucer Centurion (both 1994) (which, like the Unitron's Star Hawk II, is smaller than the largest starships of other space races). The base was Lunar Launch Site (1994). The theme also included two robot vehicles, Recon Robot and Robo-Guardian (both 1994).

Though Spyrius officially ended in 1996, Surveillance Scooter (1995) was re-released as Space Jet in 1999.



Returning to the clean white and transparent blue cockpits of Futuron (as well as their civilian role), Exploriens sets are known for their use of large, open (sometimes rickety) structures and special image elements (e.g., as foil-holograph stickers for viewscreens). The Exploriens were searching, evidently, for fossils, certain flat plates contained triple images: one in white, for the naked eye; one in blue, for viewing under transparent red scanners; and one in red, for viewing under transparent blue scanners. It was the second space theme to include a robot minifigure, and was also the second Space theme to include a female minifigure, a robot named Ann Droid. The Exploriens were much themed after the famous Star Trek series, being aliens who searched for new life in their "starships" along with their "droid"; even their insignia bears a remarkable resemblance. 

Popular Exploriens vehicles include Scorpion Detector and their largest starcraft the Explorien Starship (both 1996). The base was Android Base (1996). A mini-base was also included, Nebula Outpost (1996).



Taking the "good guy" role was another four-set theme, Roboforce featured various large robots in varying color schemes. Orange Class features a police-like patrol/rescue function in humanoid robos, equipped with buzz saws for extracting criminals or rescuing civilians. The "head" of each robot was also a small space ship that could be used as an escape pod or secondary vehicle. Green Class featured a more military theme with animal shaped robots. The Robo Raptor was the only set not to feature a space craft, while the Robo Master's small starcraft strongly resembled the Unitron Star Hawk II as a tribute to the fan favorite set. Roboforce "Robos" were powered by "secret" "robo disks" which were oddly enough rectangle-shaped power sources. By this time, the space theme was well and truly exhausted, and the remaining sets were a slow march to the theme's obscurity.

Orange Class: Small Variant Robo Raider (1997)Orange Class: Large Variant Robo Stalker (1997)Green Class: Small Variant Robo Raptor (1997)Green Class: Large Variant Robo Master (1997)



UFO was the first Lego race to look alien instead of human. All of UFO's minifigures were cybernetic in nature, and the race featured two wholly robot figures (the red one was said to be "Andy Droid" Ann Droid's brother stolen from the Explorians), and, as befitting its name, many of its spaceships used saucers or half-saucers as elements. It has the smallest proportion of wheeled ground vehicles to ships (two to nine) of any Lego Space theme before or since. UFO was the first theme to introduce what has since become a staple of Lego System sets in general: large pieces meant to provide effects (such as curvature) that would be difficult to achieve with traditional Lego pieces. 

Popular UFO Ships include Warp Wing Fighterand their largest starship the Interstellar Starfighter (both 1997). The UFO had no primary base however when the smaller saucer detached from the main hull of the Alien Avenger (1997) the bottom half was converted into a command center.



The second alien appearing race, the Insectoids were insectial humanoid cyborgs especially interested in "energy orbs" which included magnetic stickers so that magnets attached to cranes could lift them. Predictably the Insectoids utilized a number of pieces designed to look like insect components, particularly legs and wings. Its minifigures were primarily cybernetic, and the third Lego Space theme to have a female minifigure, Gypsy Moth, also known as Queen. It also featured droids, utilizing the old Spyrius droid helmet even.

The Insectoids were going to be enemies for the Rock Raiders at first, but the concept was dropped in the prototype stage. http://news.lugnet.com/underground/?n=129

Popular Insectoids vehicles include Bi-Wing Blaster and Celestial Stinger (both 1998). The base was the mobile and bizarre Arachnoid Star Base (1998).



This line focused on the Space Port trying to defend earth from an incoming meteor. It also made a special appearance in Lego Island 2 and was actually a sub-line of LEGO Town.

Life On Mars is one of two Space themes with both Humans and Aliens. The sets denote peaceful coexistence between the two species on the planet Mars, and were timed for release to the public around a time of much curiosity about the planet, and the life that could possibly exist there. Although set in the future, LOM is unique among the Space themes, as its conception was more inspired by and coincided with real space exploration activity than any other Space theme yet introduced. 

Incorporating the new "sand" colors, red, green, and purple, Life on Mars sets were not as colorfully bold as sets from other Space themes. Transparent brown (or trans-black/"smoke," as it is popularly known) made its debut as a primary window and canopy color for Space with this theme.

Life On Mars introduced organic-style printed parts into Space. Print patterns on parts such as tiles, slopes, and dishes had a characteristic non-mechanical design, atypical of Lego Space. The game Lego Racers 2 had five racecourses centred around this theme, and several of the sets could be seen, such as the space shuttle and both Martian mechs. 

The Martian base was 7317 Aero Tube Hangar, and the Human base was 7315 Solar Explorer, although it isn't actually much of a ground base, just a shuttle and a small ground pod. The Aero tube hanger was particularilly popular among fans as all the other Martain sets connected to it.

After the theme ended, Lego Space would not be seen again for six years, being replaced by the much more popular and profitable Lego Star Wars line of toys.



Mars Mission is the second Space theme to feature both Humans and Aliens and is a reboot of Life On Mars. Unlike Life on Mars, the aliens and humans were pitted against each other as children had been fond of doing with the original line. The logo used by the human explorers is very similar to the one in Classic Space, Futuron, Space Police I and Ice Planet, suggesting they are all the same space agency. The sets typically have more aliens than humans, although many aliens in the sets are captured ones. The alien ships also have more weapons than the humans, with some having more than 15 laser weapons. The largest human ship is the 7644 MX-81 Hypersonic Operations Aircraft,also called the MX-81 Hypersonic Spacecraft, and the largest alien ship without a doubt is the mothership. Popular human vehicles include 7692 MX-71 Recon Dropship and 7697 MT-51 Claw Tank Ambush. The human base is 7690 MB-01 Eagle Command Base (which uses a similar pump system to 7317 Aero Tube Hangar). The aliens have no normal base, but they do have a main starcraft, their mothership. The line was released in May 2007. There will be more space themed sets in years to come, although no specific dates or sets have been announced.



