

See also: Policing in the United States Police vehicles in the United States and Canada are made by several manufacturers and are available in three broad vehicle types:

Since the 1920s, the New York City Police Department has employed a fleet of Radio Motor Patrol vehicles to aid in its fight against crime in the city.

In the United States and Canada, police departments historically have used standard-size, low-price line sedans such as the Ford Model A or Chevrolet Bel Air.  Police switched to intermediates, such as the Plymouth Satellite, Ford Torino and AMC Matador, in the 1960s.  The Ford LTD and Chevrolet Caprice were re-adopted as standard when the models were downsized in the late 1970s.  Since the termination of the Chevrolet Caprice product, most police departments currently use the Ford Crown Victoria Police Interceptor as the standard patrol car.  New North American Crown Victoria Police Interceptors are optionally equipped with a fire suppression system to combat instances of vehicle fires subsequent to high speed rear impacts.

Some departments have adopted SUVs and front-wheel drive sedans for non-pursuit applications, but the rear wheel drive V8 configuration is favored for being consistent with pursuit driver training.  General Motors and Chrysler provide other types (front-wheel drive, smaller engine) police vehicles as well, and a few jurisdictions (primarily in Canada) use these vehicles.

There are many jurisdictions that use the Chevrolet Impala, which in its current configuration is a front wheel drive V6.  The Dodge Charger (LX) and Dodge Magnum are the most likely challengers to the Crown Victoria as a RWD V8 patrol car, though the Washington State Patrol and the North Carolina Highway Patrol are using the vehicle initially as an unmarked patrol car.  The former 44th Precinct in the Bronx NY, now home to a special police task force, has Hemi Dodge Chargers for testing.  The Charger has shown great promise as a police car, being faster, more modern, and more fuel efficient than the commonly used Ford Crown Victoria.[]  Some complaints about the Charger though are its limited rear visibility and smaller trunk than the Crown Victoria.  At the end of 2006, multiple Dodge Chargers have been put into the NYPD fleet for citywide testing.  In the summer of 2006, the Georgia State Patrol announced that it would begin using the Dodge Charger for high speed chases on Interstate highways due to its additional power and speed. As of 2007, the Alameda County (California) Sheriff's Office has plans as well to upgrade to the Dodge Charger.  Many police agencies in the metropolitan Detroit area have also adopted a fleet that includes a number of Dodge Chargers.

Some state highway patrols (such as California) adopted pony cars such as the Ford Mustang, Chevrolet Camaro or even AMC Javelin as high-speed pursuit vehicles.

North American police cars were once noted for being painted black and white, with the car doors and roof painted white, while the trunk, hood, front fenders and rear quarter panels were painted black.  The fleet vehicles that were used typically came painted in a single color, most commonly white or black, from the factory and were used as such.  The contrasting black or white color was added to make the vehicle stand out from civilian vehicles.  In 2007, the Ontario Provincial Police (OPP) began converting its fleet back to a black-and-white scheme after decades of using other colours.  

Beginning in the 1970s, police vehicle markings have become increasingly stylistic, with widespread use of computer-graphics and vinyl striping.  While black and white designs are still in use in many jurisdictions, cars may range from being all white to completely black. Blues and greens of various hues are also frequently used. Brown, beiges and tans are favored by rural police and sheriff's offices.

Official markings also vary by jurisdiction.  The side doors and sometimes the hood of a marked police car usually bear the agency's badge or the city seal, often in reflective finish.  Markings such as emergency telephone numbers, generic anti-drug or anti-crime messages, or even website URLs are also common.  Some agencies also have identification numbers printed on the roofs of patrol cars for tracking from aircraft, or to distinguish specialized units, such as K-9 units or supervisors.

Currently, in the United States, the paint scheme for each fleet is determined either by the individual agency or by uniform state legislation as in Minnesota http://www.revisor.leg.state.mn.us/bin/getpub.php?pubtype=STAT_CHAP_SEC&amp;year=2006&amp;section=169.98. Usually, state laws exist that establish standards for police vehicle markings, and proscribe civilian vehicles from using certain markings or paint schemes as is the case in California http://www.dmv.ca.gov/pubs/vctop/d12/vc27605.htm.

Today, most fleet markings on patrol vehicles are created from reflective vinyl with an adhesive backing that is applied in a peel-and-stick manner. Colors chosen to represent the departments identity are typically chosen by the individual department, although, as noted above, some states have specific guidelines for color schemes and markings. Vinyl used to produce fleet markings comes in large rolls that are fed through a plotter (cutter) or large-format printer/cutter. The designs are created in specialized computer software and sent to the machines via cable link for production. Once the design is cut into the vinyl, the excess vinyl on the sheet is removed in a process called "weeding". Finally, a paper pre-mask is applied to the top of the vinyl design to allow easy application of multiple letters and shapes at one time.











A few police departments use alternative police vehicles. http://www.drive.subaru.com/Win05_YourTurn.htm. 

A number of Drug Abuse Resistance Education (DARE) programs in local police departments have some notable vehicles marked as police cars to promote the program. The DARE cars appear at schools and in parades.  Typically these cars are high-end or performance cars that have been seized in a drug raid.  They are used to send the message that drug dealers forfeit all their glamorous trappings when they get caught.  Cars include the Chevrolet Corvette, Ford Mustang, and Humvee. 





