

Mario Golf (マリオゴルフ64, Mario Gorufu 64, Mario Golf 64) is a sports game developed by Camelot Software Planning and published by Nintendo for the Nintendo 64 in 1999. In the game, Mario, his friends, and his enemies play golf on a variety of Mario-themed courses. It is the second game in the Mario Golf series (though the first to carry that name). Its tagline was "Tee Up with Mario and his Friends". 

Mario Golf was re-released on the Virtual Console in Japan on September 30, 2008, and in North America on October 6, 2008.

Players can play as a variety of characters including Mario, Luigi, Princess Peach and Yoshi. The game also included new characters including Plum, Sonny, Harry, Maple, and Charlie. Players can then select from a number of courses which have features adapted to the Nintendo world. Mario Golf is also very easy to play (also known as a "pick up and play" game) as it makes golf very simple, because it does away with many of the complicated real-life aspects of the sport that are found in games like Tiger Woods PGA Tour 2006. Although the game is easy to play and simple in appearance, the game's engine is very deep and there are a multitude of variables that can affect a shot, such as wind strength and direction (indicated by a Boo), rain, characters individual attributes, spin on the ball, and relief of the land. There is a variety of gameplay modes, including speed golf, ring shot, mini golf and skins match. Every character in the game has recorded voice samples which can be used to comment on opponent's shots.

This game features Transfer Pak compatibility with the Game Boy Color version of Mario Golf. Players can upload characters and data found on the Game Boy version to the Nintendo 64 version. That way, you can play as these characters in full 3D. Additionally, data from the Nintendo 64 version is saved onto the Game Boy Color version of the game. However, the characters imported onto the Nintendo 64 version are not saved onto the cartridge; you must upload the characters again to play as them on the Nintendo 64. After playing a round with a GBC Character, that character will earn experience points. Transfer Pak functionality is not included in the Virtual Console version.

Main article: Mario Golf (series)#Playable charactersThere are 14 playable characters in the game and each of them differs in swing style size and strength. Note that three of these characters have to unlocked. 

GameSpot describes the game as easy to play, by having simple features and by "removing the guesswork for gamers who are not familiar with the subtle nuances of golf" that may put off many players.

Mario Golf (known as Mario Golf GB (マリオゴルフGB) in Japan) is the handheld version of this game for the Game Boy Color, also developed by Camelot Software Planning. Unlike the console version, it includes role-playing elements.

Mario Golf received highly positive reviews, and was considered a better game overall than the console version, averaging 89.6% compared to 87.6%. IGN gave Mario Golf a perfect score of 10 out of 10, calling it one of the few must-buy games for the Game Boy Color. They also praised it for exceeding the standards for audio quality in a Game Boy Color game. GameSpot did not enjoy it as much, giving it only a 7.2 of 10. They criticized it, saying that some of the mechanics could have used some work, such as putting. However, they feel it to be an excellent adaptation of the console version.

A sequel to this game, , was released for the Nintendo GameCube in 2003.





