In the Alien franchise's stories outside the films, numerous changes and additions have been made in various media and publications. 

Below is a list of non-canon castes from the Alien universe. For various reasons, the makers of various spin-offs to the Alien and Alien vs. Predator franchises would expand the variety of forms for the Xenomorph species.

A strong purple and black brood that uses powerful jump attacks.  They are assumed to be special variants of the Warrior and Stalker aliens created through experimentation, much like the Chrysalis and Razor Claws minibosses.  They are sometimes seen curled up on the ground as they wait for enemies. 



A mutated Alien variant incapable of maturing past its larval stage, the Bodyburster resembles a large black Chestburster. Hatched from a pink egg among an ordinary clutch, the Bodyburster's egg was smuggled to the pleasure planet Celeste, where the resulting hatchling, after escaping from a human host, caused havoc among the population with its diseased slime trail, which caused people to go delirious and detonate. 



A very large (around the same size as a Praetorian) Xenomorph with a greyish-green exoskeleton and a hard, tan carapace on its head, back, and forearms.  It sometimes moves/attacks by rolling itself along the ground in a ball. It gets its name from the chrysalis that it is seen gestating in when it first appears. The Chrysalis's head can actually extend a short distance from underneath the carapace over its head when biting its prey, in addition to the extension of the inner mouth. More Chrysalis are also seen defending the Queen during the final battle. These have a reddish or blue coloring. 

A variation of the Chrysalis appears in the second level of the Konami "Aliens" arcade game, but it looks considerably different and has a different attack pattern.



A bluish brood with an apparently hardened carapace on its arms and head that can defend itself against most projectiles and hand-to-hand attacks.



Eloise is a vat grown prototype Alien/humanoid android hybrid created using Queen DNA. She escapes captivity with a band of Alien warriors, with whom she settles on the planet LK176. She and her army successfully beat back both Predator and human forces, and gives the latter an ultimatum to leave her people alone, or be destroyed.



Flying aliens can be seen in Konami's Aliens, the arcade game  as a boss under the name Alien Dragon, in the Super Nintendo game Alien vs. Predator as an end-level boss (this one having gestated in a giant species of bat and taken on the arm-wings and overall appearance of a bat), as well as a Flying Queen in the Kenner toy line.

 

A Human implanted by a type of facehugger altered as a bioweapon.  Instead of being sedated, they are put in a zombie-like state, and move around the nesting area, attacking any intruders.  If the same type of facehugger implants a Predator, the Predator is instead driven into a beserk state, and will attack anything that moves. Similar zombie-like humans controlled by aliens are found in the  comic book.

 

In , a variation of the original xenomorphs are created by Dr. Samuel Kadinsky. This group is called "The K-Series". They are almost identical to normal xenomorphs in ability but have white and yellow pigmentations to their exoskeleton rather than the dark colors usually seen. They were eventually wiped out in a hive war to keep the species of xenomorphs "pure" (being that they weren't naturally created, but were instead clones).

 

A royal elite guard to the Queen, and in some cases, the ones who fertilize her. Praetorians are larger than typical adults, but still only about half the size of the queen herself. Praetorians appear in the graphic novel series (and the Millennium/Orion books based on the same), such as Rogue and Female War (originally serialised as Earth War). They are also a playable class in the computer game Aliens versus Predator 2, in which they cannot "wall-crawl" like the smaller aliens, but have a very thick bullet-resistant exoskeleton and a very high crouch jump. In the game, a background report on their biology reveals them to be a final phase for many drones in Aliens versus Predator 2, or alternatively a young queen in . 

The praetorians have been noted to possess a second pair of limbs protruding from the torso, much the same as a Queen. In the video game , they are hatched from "Praetorian Eggs" and can later molt to become a queen if the current queen is killed.  However, in Aliens versus Predator 2 they are described as being born differently.  According to AvP 2, a Praetorian is a full grown drone (or other 3rd stage xenomorph) that grows old and begins to emit different pheromones that cause the hive to react violently towards it.  If the molting Praetorian manages to escape the Hive, it can finish the molting process and return to the Hive to reassert its position. This makes it so only the strongest, most worthy drones can become a protector of the queen.

Praetorians are easily recognized by their crown shaped headcrest, which is very similar in appearance to the Queen's. Theoretically, praetorian face huggers are purebred, meaning they do not integrate their host's most valuable traits into their own DNA. 

Praetorians also appear in the Alien vs. Predator arcade game, where they are known as Royal Guard, and are typically encountered as minibosses as the player gets close to the Queen.  Royal Guard are capable of spitting acid, and will often spray it in all directions as a defensive tactic. They also use a distinctive "throw" attack if the player comes too close.

 

In , a Praetorian can evolve into two other forms of Xenomorph than just the Queen: the Carrier and the Ravager. The Carrier Xenomorph has the ability to carry 6 Facehuggers on spikes coming out of its back, and some can even carry 12. Their vulnerability is their weak armor and their fragility against fire, but their greatest advantages are the face-huggers they are carrying. After the carrier is dead the facehuggers riding will scatter everywhere. Some times Carriers will actually hurl the face huggers it is carrying at its foes.

Carriers are arguably the most valuable tool for expansion of the hive in the game as it allows face huggers to traverse great distances without them needing to consume their own organs to survive whilst they are attached to the Carrier.

The Ravager Xenomorph is possibly one the largest alien breeds ever created, it is familiar to the appearance of a normal alien except of their large armour-like shoulder bones and dark blue skin. This Xenomorph possesses huge, scythe-like claws have the ability to kill enemies with one swipe. They can slice through metal (although this is considered nothing particularly unusual in the broader Aliens Universe - most adult xenomorphs are capable of bending steel) and their powerful armor makes them impervious to all but the most intense assault. Ravagers can also heal themselves over short periods of time. It can be argued that Ravagers are bred to be more geared toward all-out warfare than most breeds of Xenomorphs, as their claws are more of a blade-like appearance rather than merely claws and the fact that Ravagers rely more upon brute force to overpower multiple enemies, whereas most Xenomorphs called upon stealth or numbers to overcome such obstacles. Even more important is the fact that Ravagers make no efforts in capturing hosts for breeding and will always kill or destroy potential hosts outright instead.

 

The "PredAlien" is the product of an Alien Facehugger impregnating a Predator or, in rare cases, an after-result of genetic experimentation. The PredAlien caste has appeared in comic books, video games, and on film, in that order. Appearance and abilities vary between media, with varying degrees of common traits to its host species. 

The AvP games have shown a creature more in touch with its Predator host: complete with large mandibles, a heavily-built physique, and dreadlocks - even going so far as to shorten the elongated head and apparently remove the inner set of jaws. In the games, this variant is also depicted light brown, much like the skin-color of the Predators. In reality, it shares more of a resemblance with its host than other xenomorphs. In the first game the PredAlien is not able to headbite, however, in  the predalien is capable of using its mandibles to instantly crush and consume the head of a foe.

In Aliens vs. Predator: Extinction a PredAlien Queen appears in the final Predator mission saying it's "impure" and "an abomination". The PredAlien Queen's head was cut off and set onto a shrine while the rest of the hive was slaughtered by the clan and an Ancient Nuke Carrier destroyed the cave where the hive made base to insure the PredAlien Queen's impure strain would not spread.

Also the predalien-Queen showed different pigmentation and also different features. She was brown and had a predator mouth, and predator hair. She was tougher than the regular alien queens and she didnt have acidic blood.

The beastery/ codex of the game does not say that a Predalien can impregnate hosts.

The Empress is essentially a larger version of the Queen, also capable of laying eggs. When there are multiple Queens in an area, they will fight for dominance, the winner becoming the ascendant ruler over the others, and thereby all other Aliens on the planet. 

 

Though not given a specific name in-game, the leech appeared in  and appeared to be a part of the Xenomorph life cycle. Like the game's facehuggers, they would leap at the screen and take damage slowly. Before doing so, they would hang from walls and ceiling until the player got near enough to perform the jump. They would be a product of scientific experimentation, though, as the whole complex is run by xenomorph-studying androids.



Queen Mothers are the supreme rulers of the Xenomorph species, and even Queens are subordinate to them. They appear in Dark Horse's extended universe, albeit only on the Hiveworld, where they are protected by enlarged, elite drones. Queen Mother's nests consist of six orbs arranged around a central orb in which they reside. These orbs are interconnected and contain the prized royal jelly which molts a drone or warrior into a new Queen Mother when one becomes absent. Queen Mothers have acute telepathic and empathic abilities, thus they are able to call to their hive over vast distances. In fact, the Queen Mother was capable melding to the minds of humans during the Earth infestation. What makes a Queen Mother similar to a Queen is that they are both capable of laying eggs. The first Queen Mother was kidnapped by Ripley in Steve and Stephanie Perry's novel The Female War, leading to anarchy and chaos on the Hiveworld. While a drone was morphing to take the previous Mother's place, several deviant, drones, designated as "red drones" by the humans, were born that rebelled against the primary hive, and a countering red hive, led by a red Queen Mother, was created. In Aliens: Genocide, massive warfare broke out between the two subspecies over the genetic abnormalities. A fleet of Colonial Marines were sent on a mission to retrive the Mother's royal jelly in order to synthesize a highly addictive drug called Xeno-Zip. The crew decided to decimate the red Mother's hive to distract the drones of the original nest while the jelly was being extracted. The remaining Queen Mother was shot after killing a scientist during the extraction.



Another large breed with a purple coloration and large, sharp claws on its fingers.  It is known for its great speed, making it hard to defeat or even keep up with.  It is fond of using that speed to make dashing attacks in which it uses its namesakes to cause massive damage and slice its victims in half.  The birth of the Razor Claws was a result of a genetic malfunction in the cocoon process.

 

In the comic Aliens: Rogue, a mad scientist engineered the Rogue Alien: a male alien designed as a weapon to rival the queen caste and thus help rid the Earth of its alien infestation (see Earth Hive, Nightmare Asylum, Female War, and Genocide). However, the Rogue escapes and wreaks havoc until it is torn apart by a Queen.

In the book of the same name, the Rogue, while believed to be more powerful than the Queen, the scientist is shocked to find the Queen is in fact the superior specimen. While the Rogue is larger and stronger, the Queen's superior speed and intellect enable her to easily dodge the Rogue's brutish attacks while she slowly wears it down and finally slaughters it. The scientist, Ernst Kleist, is subsequently killed when he uses a sound cannon on the Queen until it goes critical, destroying the asteroid base he is on. The Rogue is seemingly much more aggressive and mercilessly attacks the smaller castes of Aliens. This is Illustrated when Professor Kleist finds the crushed corpses of the elite Praetorian guard of the queen. Interestingly, the Rogue appears to have been engineered to ignore humans - when exposed to a human prisoner, the Rogue examined him closely at first, but did not attack and finally ignored him completely. This may be due to a rogue caste not having as strong a sense to use humans to breed as a queen caste. Or maybe its simply because the human prisoner was un-armed and restrained so posed no threat. The Rogue's recklessness is also shown when it destroys the barrier that separates the Alien sector and the Human sector, allowing alien drones to pour into the human sector.

 

A brown or green brood with an oversized head that attacks with a charging ram attack. It will usually shake it's head before charging.  

 

In the Aliens Colonial Marines story published by Dark Horse Comics, a group of marines ends up on a colony planet known as 'Bracken's World', a primarily oceanic planet that grows large amounts of sea kelp. Having become stranded on one of the kelp beds following an APC breakdown, the group is attacked from the water by large xenomorphs resembling queen aliens from the top half, and a more whale-like structure below the waist with a lateral tail fin and several trailing tentacles.

The hybrids are a race of Aliens created by a corrupted computer system called "Toy". The hybrids possess the traits of Aliens/Predators and humans. Like Aliens, they are a eusocial species with acid for blood (though it is less acidic than that of the ordinary strain) and like humans, they are capable of speech and can use firearms. They are lead by a hybrid king which generates facehuggers capable of impregnating ordinary  Aliens.



In the first Aliens versus Predator computer game, there is a special variation of the Xenomorph, a cybernetically modified and enhanced xenomorph called the Xenoborg. It is reminiscent of the Star Trek villains known as the Borg; their appearance consists of a mechanical and flesh covered body, a Borg-eqsue face, and can fire laser blasts. Their only weakness appears to be a flashing green light that, when hit, shuts the Xenoborg down. A similar organism appears in the book Alien vs. Predator: Hunters Planet, where a mad-man creates a planet for hunters and creates Xenoborgs intent on using them to conquer worlds.

There is also an Easter Egg xenoborg in one of the Marine missions of Aliens versus Predator 2, available through using no clipping mode. It is found while in the vents, as a scientist talks about what most presume is the PredAlien. But when no clipping is used to go down into the room he's in, there is a partially mechanical xenomorph with missing parts laying on a table he was saying acted with extreme aggression when exposed to pheromones. If killed, it is shown the scientist is an android.

Various action figures have been made depicting non-canon Xenomorphs, such as the Gorilla Alien, Snake Alien, Arachnid Alien, Flying Queen Alien, and Bull Alien action figures released by Kenner Toys to coincide with the release of the SNES Alien vs. Predator Game; the Gorilla, Snake, and Flying Queen Aliens appear as boss enemies in the game.  Several of these Kenner Aliens would later be repainted as KB Toys exclusives in three separate lines, including Aliens vs. Marines two-packs and the Hive Wars line incorporating previously unreleased figures.



