

Zapotec language(s) describes a group of closely-related indigenous Mesoamerican languages spoken by the Zapotec people from Mexico's southwestern-central highlands region. Present-day numbers of native speakers are estimated at over half a million, with the majority inhabiting the state of Oaxaca. Zapotec-speaking communities are also found in the neighbouring states of Puebla, and Guerrero. Emigration has also resulted in a number of native Zapotec-speakers residing in the United States, particularly in the state of California.

The name of the language in Zapotec itself varies according to the geographical variant. In Juchitán (Isthmus) it is Diidxazá [didʒazá] and in Santa Catarina Quioquitani it is Tiits Së [tiˤts sæ], for example. The first part of these expressions is the word meaning 'word'.

See also: List of Zapotec languagesZapotec and the related language Chatino together form the Zapotecan subgroup of the Oto-Manguean language family.

There is no one Zapotec language:  in fact there are probably over 60 varieties of Zapotec.  Given that the dialectal divergence observed between Zapotec-speaking communities is an extensive one (many variants of Zapotec are mutually  unintelligible with one other), it is also recognised as forming a "dialect continuum".

Zapotec languages and dialects fall into four broad divisions: Zapoteco de la Sierra Norte (Northern Zapotec), Valley Zapotec, Zapoteco de la Sierra Sur [Southern Zapotec], and Isthmus Zapotec.  Northern Zapotec languages are spoken in the mountainous region of Oaxaca, in the Northern Sierra Madre mountain ranges; Southern Zapotec languages and are spoken in the mountainous region of Oaxaca, in the Southern Sierra Madre mountain ranges; Valley Zapotec languages are spoken in the Valley of Oaxaca, and Isthmus Zapotec languages are spoken in the Isthmus of Tehuantepec.

Phonologically, characteristics common to many Zapotec languages include: six or seven vowels; a plethora of fricatives; tone systems (present in all Zapotec variants); and a  fortis / lenis distinction in consonants. 

In Zapotec languages, fortis typically corresponds to voicelessness in stops and fricatives and long in sonorants. Lenis corresponds to voiced in stops and fricatives and short in sonorants. The valence alternations shown in the Grammar section below show fortis consonants at the beginning of many transitive verbs and corresponding lenis consonants at the beginning of many intransitive verbs.

Zapotec languages differ in the number of contrasting tones they have.  One example is Texmelucan Zapotec, which has four contrasting tones: three contour tones and one level tone, as shown in the figure. 

In a number of Zapotec languages there are phonation type differences in vowels.  San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec, for example, has phonation contrasts between modal, breathy, creaky, and checked vowels (Munro and Lopez, et al. 1999).

Zapotec languages form part of the Mesoamerican Linguistic Area, an area of linguistic convergence developed throughout millennia of interaction between the peoples of Mesoamerica.

Zapotec languages vary considerably. Some characteristics of Zapotec grammar common to the language family (though not necessarily present in all members) are: an extensive 3rd person pronoun system based on noun classes such as divinity, babies, animals, objects (inanimate), etc; a distinction in the first person plural ("we") as to inclusive (including the hearer(s)) and exclusive (not including the hearer(s)); a frequent underspecificity of singular/plural distinctions. 

Zapotec languages are VSO, as in the following example from San Dionisio Ocotepec Zapotec (Broadwell 2001):

'Juan hit the dog.'

Though the most basic order has the verb at the beginning of the sentence, all Zapotec languages have a number of preverbal positions for topical, focal, negative, and/or interrogative elements.  The following example from Quiegolani Zapotec (Black 2001) shows a focused element and an adverb before the verb:

‘Rodolfo’s wife was already standing there.’

The preverbal position for interrogatives is shown in the following example, from San Dionisio Ocotepec Zapotec (Broadwell 2001).  This is an example of wh-movement:

'Who hit the dog?'

Zapotec languages also show the phenomenon known as pied-piping with inversion.

Most Zapotec languages do not have a passive, but generally show morphological relationships between pairs of verbs which differ in valence.  In one typical pattern, an intransitive stative verb begins with a lenis consonant while the corresponding transitive active verb begins with the corresponding fortis consonant.  Consider the following examples from Mitla Zapotec (Stubblefield and Stubblefield  1991):



Verbs in Zapotec languages inflect with prefixes to show grammatical aspect.  

The following example from San Dionisio Zapotec (Broadwell 2001) shows the use of the completive aspect:

'Juan hit the dog.'

San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec (Munro and Lopez, et al. 1999) has seven aspect markers: habitual, perfective, irrealis, progressive, definite, subjunctive, and neutral.

Many linguists working on Zapotec languages use different terminology for describing what appear to be related or similar phenomenon, such as grammatical aspect markers.  The following table shows some correspondences:

The following abbreviations are used in glossing the examples above.

POSS possessed PROG progressive aspect

Franciscan and/or Dominican friars published a vocabulary and grammar of Zapotec in the 16th century [Córdova 1578a, 1578b].  In the past century there have been ongoing efforts to produce Zapotec alphabets and to write in Zapotec.  The Isthmus Zapotec alphabet in use today was founded in the 1950s, drawing from works going back as far as the 1920s.  Until recently the Zapotec language were only sparsely studied and documented but in recent years Zapotec language has begun to receive serious attention by descriptive linguists (see bibliography).

The viability of Zapotec languages also varies tremendously.  Loxicha Zapotec, for example, has over 70,000 speakers.  San Felipe Tejalapan Zapotec might have ten, all elderly. San Agustin Mixtepec Zapotec reportedly has just one remaining speaker.  Historically, government teachers discouraged the use of the language, which has contributed to its diminution in many places.  Other areas however, such as the Isthmus, proudly maintain their mother tongue.

Zapotec-language programming is carried by the CDI's radio stations XEGLO, based in Guelatao de Juárez, Oaxaca, and XEQIN-AM, based in San Quintín, Baja California.



















