

The United States twenty-dollar bill ($20) is a denomination of United States currency.  U.S. President Andrew Jackson is currently featured on the front side of the bill, which is why the twenty-dollar bill is often called a "Jackson," while the White House is featured on the reverse side.

The twenty-dollar bill in the past was referred to as a "double-sawbuck" because it is twice the value of a ten-dollar bill, which was nicknamed a "sawbuck" due to the resemblance the Roman numeral for ten (X) bears to the legs of a sawbuck, although this usage is far less common today than it was in the early 20th century. The twenty dollar gold coin was known as a "double eagle". Rather than a nickname, this nomenclature was specified by an act of congress.

The twenty-dollar bill is the primary banknote (and in most cases, the only banknote, as it would increase costs to make ATMs compatible with other bills) dispensed by ATMs in the United States as well as the primary bill used for withdrawals or cashing checks. It is, therefore, the highest denomination note most commonly used by Americans on an everyday basis.

The Bureau of Engraving and Printing says the "average circulation life" of a $20 bill is 25 months (2 years) before it is replaced due to wear.  Approximately 22% of all notes printed today are $20 bills. Twenty-dollar bills are delivered by Federal Reserve Banks in violet straps.







Jackson first appeared on the twenty dollar bill in 1928. It is not clear the reason the bill was switched from Grover Cleveland to Andrew Jackson. According to the U.S. Treasury, "Treasury Department records do not reveal the reason that portraits of these particular statesmen were chosen in preference to those of other persons of equal importance and prominence." The placement of Jackson on the $20 bill may be a historical irony;  as president, he vehemently opposed both the National Bank and paper money and made the goal of his administration the destruction of the National Bank. In his farewell address to the nation, he cautioned the public about paper money. 

Several unmade twenty-dollar bills are known.  Most are similar in design to the ones described above, with the only difference being certain obligations.  For example, a silver-certificate variety of the 1928 style Federal Reserve Note is known in the proof stage, with blue serial numbers.  More interesting examples include a 1923 Federal Reserve Note, with Grover Cleveland as on the Series of 1914, but different border elements, an 1873 National Bank note whose design is unknown, and also an 1896 Silver Certificate.

Andrew Jackson's actions towards the Native Americans as a general, as well as during his Presidency, have led some historians to question the suitability of Jackson's depiction on the twenty-dollar bill. Howard Zinn, for instance, identifies Jackson as a leading "exterminator of Indians," and notes how the public commemoration of Jackson obscures this part of American history. 

Some critics[] of the current design have proposed replacing Jackson's image with that of Martin Luther King, Jr.







