The Music School of Bitola or Muzicko Uciliste Bitola is a state school that is located in Bitola, Republic of Macedonia. Home to a population of over 1500 students, it is one of the most popular schools for Music Education in former Yugoslavia and Balkans. It provides a full education which includes solfege, music theory, and music history, Every year produces some of the best musicians such as Tose Proeski, Marijan Stojanovski, Lambe Alabakoski, Karolina Goceva, Dimitar Andonovski and Hristijan Spirovski. 

This school was founded in 1947 and was located in the Radio Bitola building.There was lots of interest about this school during that time.There were three music degrees in the school:piano,theoretical and strings. The school was then called "Nizo Muzicko Uciliste-Bitola" or "Primary School for Music Education." In the school at that time, Kire Kostov and Slave Dimitrov were students. In 1980 the school name was changed to today's name and the location is near Marshall Tito Street in the centre of the city. The school carries approximately 1800 students, all from South Macedonia. A proportion of the school's enrolment comes from a further field; either to participate in special programs like theory degree, instrument degree or solo singer degree. Each of these degrees have many teachers and examiners at the end of every year. For example if you are in the piano degree then you will study Piano, Chamber Music, Sight reading, Solfege, Theory and English. If you are a solo singer, the preference is to learn the Italian Language and Solfege respectively. The school received a donation from the American government and constructed all buildings, especially at the Primary school for music.

The school is constructed to educate students from YEAR 1 to YEAR 4. Each year the students have different teachers and subjects. It has 4 class coordinators, a director and a pedagogue.

The is school is one of the best in terms of admission. Students are of both genders and any sexuality, ethnicity, socio-economic status, age, geographic location or ability. This Centre selects the students in this way:It really doesn't matter where do you live, unless you attend all classes. The music talent which includes singing, or playing some instrument is really appreciated.





