



Operation Meghdoot was the name given to the attack launched by the Indian Military to capture the Siachen Glacier in the disputed Kashmir region, precipitating the Siachen Conflict. Launched on April 13, 1984, this military operation was unique as the first assault launched in the world's highest battlefield. The military action resulted in Indian troops managing to gain the entire Siachen Glacier and most of the disputed region. 

The Siachen Glacier became a bone of contention following a vague demarcation of territory as per the Simla Accord of 1972 which did not specifically specify who had authority over the Siachen Glacier area. As a result of this, both nations lay claim to the barren land. In the 1970s and early 80s, Pakistan permitted several mountaineering expeditions to climb the peaks in the Siachen region. This served to reinforce their claim on the area as these expeditions arrived on the glacier with a permit obtained from the Government of Pakistan. Indian sources claim that in many cases a liaison officer from the Pakistan army accompanied the teams. In 1978 the Indian Army began closely monitoring the situation in the region and concurrently India also allowed mountaineering expeditions to the glacier, approaching from its side. The most notable one was the one launched by Colonel N. Kumar of the Indian Army, who mounted an Army expedition to Teram Kangri peaks as a counter-exercise.

When Pakistan gave permission to a Japanese expedition to scale an important peak (Rimo Peak) in 1984, it further prompted Indians.  The peak, located east of the Siachen Glacier, also overlooks the northwestern areas of the Aksai Chin area which is occupied by China but claimed by India. The Indian military believed that such an expedition could further a link for a trade route from the southwestern (Pakistani) to the northeastern (Chinese) side of the Karakoram Range and eventually provide a strategic, if not tactical, advantage to the Pakistan Military.

The Indian Military decided to take action to stop future expeditions from the Pakistani side and eventually to prevent Pakistan from staking its claim on the glacier. Accordingly, the Indian military brought to the glacier area troops from Northern Ladakh region as well as some paramilitary forces.  Most of the troops had already been acclimatized to the extremities of the glacier after having been sent on a training expedition to Antarctica in 1982. Pakistan, meanwhile, felt that the Indians were planning to capture key ridges and passes near the glacier after the Indian Army's mountaineering expedition and accordingly decided to send its own troops to the glacier. However, according to one retired Pakistani colonel, Islamabad committed an intelligence blunder, ordering Arctic-weather gear from the same London suppliers from whom the Indians too sourced their outfits. The Indians were soon informed about this development and immediately put their plan into action, providing them the all-important head start.

On April 13, 1984, the Indian Army made its move onto the glacier to defend the territory and the peaks and passes around it when it launched "Operation Meghdoot". The operation was launched under the command of Lieutenant General P N Hoon, the then army commander of the Indian Army's Northern Command based at Udhampur in Jammu &amp; Kashmir state of India. The operation was also based on intelligence inputs that Pakistan was also preparing for an action in these areas. Reportedly the operation pre empted Pakistani Army by about 4 days, as intelligence reported that Pakistan was to launch an operation on 17 April 1984. Named after the divine cloud messenger (Meghaduuta) in a Sanskrit play, the operation involved the airlifting of Indian Army soldiers by the Indian Air Force (IAF) and dropping them in the glacial area. The IAF used planes such as the Il-76, An-12 and An-32 to transport stores and troops as well to airdrop supplies to high altitude airfields. Helicopters like Mi-17, Mi-8, Chetak and Cheetah carried provisions and personnel to areas near hitherto unscaled peaks. Approximately 300 troops were soon up on the important peaks and passes of the glacier. By the time Pakistan troops managed to get into the immediate area, they found that the Indian troops had occupied the major mountain passes west of Siachen Glacier. Handicapped by the altitude and the limited time, Pakistan could only manage to control the Saltoro Ridge's western slopes and foothills despite the fact that Pakistan possessed more accessible routes to the area, unlike Indian access to the Siachen which was largely reliant on air drops.

In , current Pakistani president, General Pervez Musharraf states that Pakistan lost almost 2,331 km² (900 mi²) of territory. TIME states that the Indian advance captured nearly 1,000 sq mi (2,600 km2). of territory claimed by Pakistan. Camps were soon converted to permanent posts by both countries. The number of casualties on both sides during this particular operation is not known.

The Operation was seen as a futile attempt to capture a non-strategic piece of land further antagonizing relations with neighbooring Pakistan though many nationalistic Indians refer to it as a "daring" success by the Indian Military at the time and ensured that the Indian military held its tactical high ground on the Saltoro Ridge just west of the glacier, albeit at a high cost. The operation and the continued cost of maintaining logistics to the area is a major drain on the indian military and has cost the indian army a disproportionately higher number of casualities then their Pakistani counterparts.  Pakistan tried to launch an all out assault in 1987 and later in 1989 to capture the ridge and passes held by India. The first attempt was headed by Pervez Musharraf (later President of Pakistan) and initially managed to capture a few high points before being beaten back. Later the same year, Pakistan ended up losing at least one major Pakistani post, the "Quaid", which came under Indian control as Bana Post, in recognition of Bana Singh who launched a daring daylight attack, codenamed "Operation Rajiv". The only Param Vir Chakra (PVC) — the highest gallantry award of India — in the ongoing battle was awarded to then Naib Subedar Bana Singh who was instrumental in capturing the post. Bana Post is the highest battlefield post in the world today at a height of 22,143 feet (6,749 m) above sea level.http://in.rediff.com/news/2001/jan/25hope.htmhttp://www.bharat-rakshak.com/LAND-FORCES/Army/History/1984/Siachen.html The second attempt, in 1989 too came to nothing as the ground positions did not change. The loss of most of the Siachen area and the subsequent unsuccessful military forays prompted Benazir Bhutto to taunt Zia ul Haq that he should wear a burqa as he had lost his manliness.

Operation Meghdoot was seen by some as the blueprint behind the Kargil War in 1999 when Pakistan backed guerillas and paramilitary forces covertly occupied the Kargil region. It is said that Operation Meghdoot was the inspiration for this abortive operation in Kargil launched by Pakistan later in 1999. Despite this, some obvious similarities do exist between Siachen and Kargil, including their preemptive nature and the tactical advantage held by the entity who holds the heights. But while Operation Meghdoot was launched on an area that provided scope for some amount of ambiguity, the Line of Control in the Kargil region was clearly marked and therefore India received more international sympathy during the Kargil episode. 

India: UnknownPakistan: Unknown











