"The Boyfriend" is a two part episode of the sitcom Seinfeld. The episode was the 35th and 36th episode for the show, and 18th and 19th episode for the show's third season. It aired on February 19, 1992. 

Jerry meets Keith Hernandez and wants to make a good impression. Meanwhile, George is out of time on his unemployment and he works harder than ever on his scheme to get a 13-week extension. He tells the unemployment office he was close to a job with Vandelay Industries, a company that makes latex products and whose main office is Jerry's apartment. Kramer and Newman take Hernandez back to a time when they were allegedly spit on by him; however, Jerry supports the "second-spitter theory" that Hernandez was not involved. Keith asks Jerry about Elaine's status. Keith makes a date with her and breaks a date with Jerry.

George tries two more approaches with the unemployment officer. Jerry gets Kramer to accompany him to see a former neighbors' new baby, "you got to see the baby." Though he's gone out with Keith once, does that mean he must help him move? Elaine and Keith are hitting it off until he pulls out a cigarette. George wants to sleep with a really tall woman. Keith supports the "second spitter theory." Jerry and Elaine both break up with Keith and George might get his wish.



Kramer: I hate Keith Hernandez. Hate him. Newman: I despise him. Elaine: Why?Newman: Why? I'll tell you why?Kramer and Newman who should talk then decides they both tell their sides of the story. Newman: June 14, 1987, Mets Phillies. We're enjoying a beautiful afternoon in the right field stands when a crucial Hernandez error opens the door to a five run Phillies ninth. Cost the Mets the game. Kramer: Our day was ruined. There was a lot of people, you know they were waiting by the player's parking lot. Now we're coming down the ramp ... (cuts to a flashback filmed in the same style as the Zapruder film) ... Newman was in front of me. Hernandez was coming toward us, as he passes Newman turns and says, "Nice game pretty boy." Keith continued past us up the ramp. Newman: Then a second later, something happened that changed us in a deep and profound way from that day forward. Elaine: What was it?Kramer: He spit on us... and I screamed out, "I'm hit!"Newman: Then I turned and the spit ricochet off him and it hit me. Elaine: Wow, what a story. Jerry: Unfortunately the immutable laws of physics contradict the whole premise of your account. Allow me to reconstruct this if I may for Miss Benes as I've heard this story a number of times. Newman, Kramer, if you'll indulge me.  According to your story Hernandez passes you and starts walking up the ramp. Then you say you were struck on the right temple. The spit then proceeds to ricochet off the temple striking Newman between the third and fourth rib. The spit then came off the rib made a right turn hitting Newman in the right wrist causing him to drop his baseball cap. The spit then splashed off the wrist, Pauses in mid air mind you... Makes a left turn, and lands on Newman's left thigh. That is one magic loogie.



