





"Love" is a ballad by John Lennon, originally released in 1970 on his John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band album.

The song first came out on Lennon's 1970 album John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band. "Love" later appeared on the 1982 compilation The John Lennon Collection, and was released as a promotional tie-in single for the collection. The single version is a remix of the original track, which most notably differs in having the piano intro and outro (played by Phil Spector) mixed at the same volume as the rest of the song; on the original album version, these parts begin much quieter and increase in volume. 

An alternate take of the song appears on the John Lennon Anthology box set.

The picture on the sleeve for 1982 release of "Love" was taken by famed photographer Annie Leibovitz in December 1980 - within days of Lennon's murder. 

Like 1982 UK issue, original version of the song was released as a single again in October 1998 for the Japanese market only with the Japanese edition of another compilation , and gained moderate success on the Japan's Oricon chart.

The musicians who performed on the original recording were as follows:

The Dream Academy covered this song in their 1990 album A Different Kind of Weather, and also released as a single (Cd, cassette, and vinyl formats are available). The single featured a strong Indian theme throughout (evident in the Music video). The song sampled the Funky drummer drum break. Like the album it was released on, A Different Kind of Weather it received mixed reviews. Many critics and fans felt that they over-stretched it . The Cd single included six different mixes of the song along with Mordechai Vanunu, which was written for Mordechai Vanunu. A second b-side, called "The Demonstration" can be found on the UK Cd single version. There are also exclusive remixes found on the cassette and 12" single. As it turned out, this was the band's penultimate single and has an accompanying video that was shot in India.

The Lettermen recorded the song for a 1971 single. This single became top-20 hit on the Japanese Oricon singles chart, and hit number-42 on the US Billboard Hot 100 chart, becoming the only charting version of the song in the US, and the last charting single of the group's career. In the same year, Barbra Streisand also covered the song on her eponymous album, along with another Lennon composition "Mother".

The song was later covered by Vicky Leandros, Kenny Loggins, Asha Puthli and The Cure.  Jimmy Nail's version featured on his album Big River was also released as a single on December 8, 1995 (the 15th anniversary of Lennon's death), and peaked at number-33 in the UK charts.



















