

The Princess and the Frog will be a 2009 upcoming American musical feature film produced by Walt Disney Animation Studios and based upon the classic fairy tale The Frog Prince. It will be the first traditional animated feature since 2004's Home on the Range. When finished, it will take its place as the 48th animated film by Walt Disney Animation Studios. It is being directed by John Musker and Ron Clements, directors of The Little Mermaid and Aladdin, with songs and score composed by Randy Newman and starring the voice talents of Anika Noni Rose (as Princess Tiana), Oprah Winfrey , Keith David, John Goodman, Jenifer Lewis, Bruno Campos and Peter Bartlett. 

The film, which began production under the working title The Frog Princess, will be an American fairy tale musical set in New Orleans during the 1920s Jazz Age, and will feature the first African American Disney Princess.

Disney had once announced that Home on the Range would be the studio's last 2D animated film entry to their animated features canon, but after the company's acquisition of Pixar in early 2006, it was reported that Ed Catmull and John Lasseter, new leaders of the animation department, were interested in going back to the Disney tradition of 2D animation.  Ron Clements and John Musker, directors of successful 2D Disney films The Little Mermaid and  Aladdin will be writing and directing.  About a month later, at the Comic-Con, Disney animator Eric Goldberg confirmed the news and also mentioned that Oscar-winning composer Alan Menken would be in charge of the music.  

The film promises to return to the Broadway-style musical in the style of the successful Disney films like Walt's classics, and the musical renaissance of the late-1980s and all of the 1990s.   Rhett Wickham also reported that John Lasseter had personally asked Ron Clements and John Musker to direct and write the film, and had let them choose what form of (both traditional animation or CGI) they wanted the film to be in.  New and updated software will be used in the digital processing of the film, as the old Computer Animation Production System from Disney is now outdated. 

On November 13 2006, it was revealed that Randy Newman, who was responsible for the music of many Pixar films, would be in charge of the music in the film instead of Alan Menken and his new lyricist Glenn Slater.  This change was due to John Lasseter not wanting the public to feel Disney being repetitive, as Menken was also working on another Disney fairy tale film, Enchanted.

On December 1, 2006, a detailed casting call was announced for the film at the Manhattan Theatre Source forum.  The casting call states the film as being an American fairy tale musical set in New Orleans during the 1920s Jazz Age, and provides a detailed list of the film's major characters, including the leading character, who at that point was to be called Maddy. Disney later officially confirmed this.

In February 2007, it was reported that Jennifer Hudson and Anika Noni Rose were top contenders for the voice of the film's title character, and that Alicia Keys directly contacted Disney's studio chief Dick Cook, telling him that she wanted the role very much.  It was later revealed that Tyra Banks was considered for the role as well. 

During the Walt Disney Company's annual shareholder meeting in March 2007, Randy Newman and the Dirty Dozen Brass Band performed a song from the film called "Down in New Orleans", while slides of pre-production art from the film played on a screen.

On April 19, 2007, it was confirmed that Anika Noni Rose would be voicing Tiana.

On July 5, 2007, it was reported that Keith David would be doing the voice of Dr. Facilier, the villain of the film.

On July 29, 2008, the official website was launched with the first teaser trailer of the movie.

On August 8, 2008, Rhett Wickham, writing for LaughingPlace.com confirmed and clarified the names of the ten supervising animators at the helm of the ten principal characters.

There was some controversy when the name of the heroine of the movie (the first Black American Disney Princess) was announced as "Maddy".  The character's name was perceived by some to be a stereotypically lower-class "black name", and the character was also a chambermaid, an occupation some felt not in keeping with the image of a Disney Princess.

On April 20, 2007, E! reported that the title of the film could possibly be changed from The Frog Princess to The Princess and the Frog, and that the lead character Maddy may be getting a name change as well. 

On May 4, 2007, USA Today published an article regarding the film in which they referred to it under the aforementioned title, The Princess and the Frog, and referred to the lead character as "Tiana" rather than Maddy, supporting the earlier reported name change possibilities.

On May 8, 2007, BET and other online sites reported that Disney spokeswoman Heidi Trotta stated that some of the original release information was incorrect, and confirmed the USA Today names "Princess Tiana" and The Princess and the Frog to be correct. Tiana will no longer be a "chamber maid." Trotta stated "Princess Tiana will be a heroine in the great tradition of Disney’s rich animated fairy tale legacy, and all other characters and aspects of the story will be treated with the greatest respect and sensitivity."

This is a list of the film's major characters, all of them are now officialy revealed on the official website. 











