

Double Fantasy is the comeback album by John Lennon and Yoko Ono, released in 1980 initially on the newly-formed Geffen Records, and then from 1989 onwards through EMI. It is notable for being John Lennon's last authorised release, released only three weeks before his murder. The album won the 1982 Grammy Award for Album of the Year.

With the birth of his son Sean in 1975, Lennon put his career on hold to raise the boy.  In the summer of 1980, both Lennon and Ono felt ready to resume work and began composing.

After five years of little musical activity aside from recording the occasional demo in his apartment at The Dakota, Lennon was absolutely bursting with creativity. He had fulfilled a lifelong ambition of learning how to sail in early 1980 and had been given fresh creative impetus in June of that year following his life-affirming experiences sailing a 43-foot sloop to Bermuda, accompanied by a small crew. Once in Bermuda, he started writing songs for a new album, sometimes writing about new experiences and occasionally reworking the half finished demos that he had recorded in the Dakota building.

He was also, he claimed, the most content he had ever felt in all his years, even writing a song called "Life Begins at 40" to commemorate that milestone in his life.  His assuredness and love for his family came through on the retro "(Just Like) Starting Over", as well as "Beautiful Boy (Darling Boy)" and "Woman".

Yoko Ono approached producer Jack Douglas, with whom both Lennon and Ono had worked before, giving him John's demos to listen to. “My immediate impressions were that I was going to have a hard time making it better than the demos because there was such intimacy in the demos,” Douglas told Uncut's Chris Hunt in 2005.

Lennon, Ono and Douglas produced dozens of songs beginning that August, enough to fill Double Fantasy and beyond.  A projected second album, Milk and Honey, was well into the rehearsal phase when work was halted following Lennon's murder that December.

Ono was currently being regarded with fresh perspective after the onslaught of the late 1970's punk movement which bore similarities to her earlier work.  As such, with renewed confidence, she produced many songs. 

Lennon and Ono made the decision to release their impending songs together on the same album, the first time they had done so since 1972's controversial Some Time in New York City.  Subtitled "A Heart Play", Double Fantasy would be a collection of songs whereby John and Yoko would be singing to each other.

Signed by David Geffen, alongside Elton John and Donna Summer, for his new label, Geffen, Double Fantasy was preceded by Lennon's "(Just Like) Starting Over", which finally became a US and UK #1 hit in the aftermath of John's murder.  The album itself was received with much interest, coming after such an extended break. However, sales were not so generous. The album debuted at #27 in the UK and the following week reached #14, but then it fell down very quickly to #25 and then #46, making the #14 its peak position. In the US, the situation was different. There, the album debuted at #25 and then rose to #12 and then #11. Although Double Fantasy was mildly criticized upon release for being slick, and Ono's songs were overlooked, the musical community was glad to have Lennon back.

On the evening 8 December 1980, Mark David Chapman shot John Lennon four times as he was walking into The Dakota with Ono; Lennon died approximately twenty minutes later.  “The last time I saw John he had this incredible smile on his face,” Jack Douglas later told journalist Chris Hunt. “It was the evening we finished ‘Walking On Thin Ice’. He was just thrilled, and so was Yoko, because we all knew we had accomplished what John set out to do with that track. I walked him to the elevator and said goodnight. About 40 minutes later my girlfriend came to the studio, all white. ‘It’s just been on the radio,’ she said. ‘John was shot’.”

With worldwide grief for Lennon's death on an almost unparalleled scale, Double Fantasy rose to #1 in most countries making a #11 to #1 move in the US and rising from #46 to #2 in the UK, spending there an impressive 7 weeks and then finally peaked at #1 for 2 weeks. "(Just Like) Starting Over" also immediately rose to #1 worldwide, selling several million copies, with many of Lennon's past solo and Beatles releases re-charting as well. Subsequent singles, "Woman" and "Watching the Wheels" were also very successful.

Only hours before his death, Lennon signed a copy of the album for his assassin.  In 2003 this autographed LP was sold for $525,000, making it the most valuable record ever.





Double Fantasy was released as an 8-track with a reordered track listing due to the technical limitations of the 8-track format.



























