

The Alien film series is a science fiction  horror film franchise, focusing on Lieutenant Ellen Ripley (played by Sigourney Weaver) and her battle with an extraterrestrial lifeform. Produced by 20th Century Fox, the series started with the 1979 film Alien, which led to three sequels, books, comics and video game spinoffs.

In addition to the franchise are the "Alien vs. Predator" films ( and ), based on the related franchise which combine the titular Aliens with the Predator beings from the Predator film series.

After completing the film Dark Star (1974), Dan O'Bannon wanted to take some of the ideas (such as where an alien hunts a crew through a ship) and make them into a science-fiction horror film, at that time provisionally called Memory. Screenwriter Ronald Shusett decided to collaborate with him in the project, adding elements from another O'Bannon script, Gremlins, which featured gremlins getting loose aboard a World War II bomber and wreaking havoc with the crew. The duo later finished the script, initially entitled Star Beast, until casting around for a better name, O'Bannon noticed the number of times the word "alien" occurred in the script, and so he adopted this for the film's title. The writers imagined a low-budget film, but ' success made Fox invest $8 million on production. 

In the original script, the ship has an all-male crew, including the Ripley character (though the script's 'Cast of Characters' section explicitly states that "The crew is unisex and all parts are interchangeable for men or women"), which would be played by actor Tom Skerritt, but later, character re-casting made Ripley a woman, because producer Alan Ladd, Jr., and script-doctors Walter Hill and David Giler had heard rumors of Fox working on other titles with strong female leads.  Skerritt became Captain Dallas, and Sigourney Weaver was cast as Ripley. 

Swiss painter and sculptor H. R. Giger designed the alien creature's adult form and the derelict ship, while Moebius created visual for the spacesuits  and Ron Cobb provided most of the on-set design.

The film was successful, but Fox wasn't very interested in a sequel until 1983, when James Cameron expressed his interest in continuing the Alien story to producer David Giler. After Cameron's The Terminator became a box office hit, Cameron and partner Gale Anne Hurd were given approval to direct and produce the sequel to Alien, scheduled for a 1986 release.  

Due to studio changes to Aliens, Sigourney Weaver wasn't much interested in returning to the series, so she didn't argue when producers David Giler and Walter Hill told her, in early 1990, that they were commissioning a third Alien film without Ripley, coming back with her in a fourth installment. But Fox's president Joe Roth didn't agree with Ripley's removal, and Weaver was called in for the movie. Alien³, released in 1992, had a troubled shooting, without even a finished script and having already spent $7 million when David Fincher, the third director considered for the film, was hired to lead the project.  After the film was ready, the studio reworked it without Fincher's consensus.

While fans and critics didn't receive Alien³ well, the $103 million in international box office kept Fox interested in continuing the franchise. In 1996, production on the fourth Alien film, , begun. Ripley wasn't in the script's first draft, and Sigourney Weaver wasn't much interested, but decided to join the project after meeting director Jean-Pierre Jeunet.  The film, released in 1997, had a long production and was described by screenwriter Joss Whedon as having done "everything wrong" with his script.

Following is a plot summary for the entire Alien series. For additional plot details, see the movies' specific pages or The Alien Universe Timeline.

The Nostromo, a towing vessel hauling an enormous ore refinery and 20 million tons of raw ore, with a crew of seven (including Captain Dallas and Warrant Officer Ripley) has set out from the mining colony Solomons on its return to Earth in the year 2122. During the return voyage, the ship’s computer "Mother" intercepts a non-human transmission from the moon LV-426. Mother, according to Weyland-Yutani (“the Company”) protocol, alters course and wakes the crew from hypersleep in order to investigate the transmission.

Upon investigation of the transmission source, a derelict alien ship, Executive Officer Kane becomes infected with an alien parasite. On orders of Captain Dallas, Kane is brought back on board and treated by Science Officer Ash, who is, unknown to the others, an android. The crew members return to the Nostromo from LV-426, hoping to return to Earth as soon as possible. After a brief period, an alien emerges from Kane and proceeds to kill all human crew members except Ripley. Ash, the android, was terminated by the other crew members after his attempted murder of Ripley, an action he took in defense of the alien species.

Ripley activates Nostromo's auto-destruct sequence and escapes in the shuttle. The Nostromo and its cargo are destroyed in a series of explosions, but Ripley soon discovers that the alien had also entered the shuttle. Half-dressed and nervously singing "Lucky Star", Ripley kills the alien by blasting it out of the shuttle's airlock and burning it with the shuttle’s jets. Ripley sets the shuttle's course for Earth and returns to hypersleep.

Director Ridley Scott has stated that he did not really think that Alien required this tweaking, and that the term "Director's Cut" was used for marketing reasons only (and inconsistently as well). In the Alien Quadrilogy materials, he goes out of his way to state his preference for the original: "rest easy, the original 1979 theatrical version isn't going anywhere". He recut the film himself, only after viewing the studio's attempt to do so; a version that he felt was "too long" and ruined the film's pacing. 

A brief rundown of the restored footage or cut scenes, in the order that the scenes appear:

The Director's Cut also deleted brief snippets of footage: 

Found in the year 2179 after 57 years drifting in space, Ellen Ripley returns to human civilization. Upon recounting the events of the Nostromo and LV-426, she learns that a group of settlers has recently moved to LV-426 and set up Hadley's Hope, a space-colony. After dismissing Ripley’s claims as ridiculous, the Company (specifically Carter Burke) sends colonists to the derelict ship to investigate Ripley’s report of an alien species. Shortly thereafter contact with the colony ceases. In response, the Company sends Ripley, a group of Colonial Marines, and Carter Burke to investigate LV-426 aboard the vessel Sulaco.

Arriving at LV-426, Ripley and her companions soon discover that aliens have overrun the colony and that all settlers have died, except for a young girl, Rebecca Jordan, nicknamed Newt. The rescue team becomes trapped in the settlement, where hundreds of aliens hunt them. Their mission is further complicated by Ripley's discovery that Burke intends to bring one of the aliens back for the Company's bio-weapons division.

Eventually, the aliens kill all those barricaded at Hadley's Hope except for those who eventually retreat to the Sulaco: Ripley, Newt, Corporal Hicks, and the android, Bishop. After a brief confrontation with the Alien Queen aboard the "Sulaco", Ripley sets a course for Earth and the crew enters hypersleep.

The Aliens Special Edition added approximately 17 minutes to this film. Several small additions to the plot were presented, including:

The movie begins with one alien facehugger emerging during the crew's hypersleep on the Sulaco. It proceeds to impregnate Ripley with an alien queen-embryo. The cover of Ripley's hypersleep-chamber cuts the facehugger, and the release of its acidic blood causes a fire on board, which leads to the Sulaco jettisoning an escape shuttle towards a penal-colony planet, Fiorina 161, inhabited only by a small number of extremely violent and dangerous offenders. The rescuers who recover the escape shuttle discover that only Ripley has survived the crash. Meanwhile, prisoner Murphy's dog Spike becomes impregnated with a second alien embryo by the same facehugger. (A first in the series, as facehuggers have been depicted as only being able to impregnate a single being prior to this.)Ripley is nursed back to health by Dr. Clemens, who she develops a relationship with. After carrying out an autopsy on Newt, to make sure there is no "cholera" infection in her chest, the bodies are thrown into the prison's gigantic furnace. At the same time, Spike goes into convulsions and the alien is born. This alien is different from the previous kind, having lost the spikes on its back and now walks on all fours. A more dangerous alien has arrived. 

Upon learning about the alien on the planet, the Weyland-Yutani corporation sends a rescue ship to Fiorina 161. However, it quickly becomes clear that they only care about capturing the Alien specimen, not Ripley or the inmates. In these circumstances, Ripley convinces the inmates to kill the Aliens (including the one inside her) before the company's ship arrives. After an elaborate set-up, which required the inmates to run up and down tunnels and corridors to confuse the creature, Ripley, Dillon and Morse are chased into the furnace, where the destruction of the alien takes place. After pouring several hundred gallons of moulten lead onto the Alien, it still chases Ripley up to the ceiling via an extensive pipe system. Ripley activates the overhead sprinklers, which cover the alien in cold water; it then explodes from the immense temperature changes. 

Using a lead smelter, Ripley sacrifices herself to prevent the company from harvesting the queen embryo from her body, saving countless human lives in doing so. Every single prisoner on Fiorina 161 is dead, except Morse, who is seen being taken by the company to an unknown location for unknown purposes. 

The Special Edition added approximately 35 minutes of new or alternate footage to the film. Several changes to the plot ensued, including:

Two hundred years later, around the year 2379, several United Systems Military (USM) scientists have cloned Ripley eight times by using blood samples from Fiorina 161 rediscovered in the year 2356. Upon successfully cloning Ripley, the 8th clone, whose DNA had combined with the alien species her body had hosted, the experiment successfully develops an intact alien and extracts it from her chest. In the year 2381, a small ship called the Betty, manned by smugglers, brings several kidnapped space-travelers, still in hypersleep, to a secret USM research vessel called the USM Auriga. The smugglers do not realize the reason for the kidnappings, but they later discover that the USM scientists will impregnate the travelers with alien embryos. The experiment quickly runs awry when the aliens break loose by killing one of their own to melt a way out with its acidic blood. They then begin killing everyone on the ship. While chaos ensues, an android named Call (passing itself off as a regular human female) changes the course of the ship (previously heading to Earth as per default emergency procedures) to crash-land in an attempt at destroying the aliens on board in the process. 

While the ship is on course to crash, the crew race for their last ship after the escape pods have been ejected from the military presence. While rushing to the ship, Ripley falls into the alien nest only to confront the queen in pain from birth, who was given a human's reproductive system from the DNA combination. The Queen gives birth to "Newborn", which is half Alien half Human (more alien), which kills the Queen and accepts Ripley as its mother. Ripley runs for the ship as the Newborn chases after. She barely makes it aboard but brings the Newborn with her without knowing. The ship escapes with almost no time to spare as Ripley quickly realizes that the Newborn is aboard from Call's missing presence on the deck. Ripley, with quick thinking, cuts herself as the Newborn is "hugging" her and flicks her blood (acidic from the DNA combination) at a close viewing window, causing it to eat through the glass. As the window shatters, air rushes from the room, pinning the Newborn in the broken window's frame. The powerful pressure differential between the room's atmosphere and the dead vacuum of space outside quickly crushes the Newborn's body and its collapsed remains are violently blown from the ship.

The Auriga crashes into Africa and explodes, presumably killing all aliens on board. The clone Ripley, Call, and the remaining crew of the Betty (Johner and Vriess) manage to escape the Auriga before it explodes, violently. As the Betty descends towards Earth, Ripley and Call contemplate their next move.

Sigourney Weaver and director Ridley Scott are considering another Alien movie with Fox's approval.







IGN listed Alien as the 13th best film franchise of all time. Alien was nominated for two Academy Awards, winning for Best Visual Effects. Aliens got seven nominations, including a Best Actress for Sigourney Weaver, winning Best Visual Effects and Best Sound Effects. Alien³ was nominated for Best Visual Effects.

There have been a number of spin-offs in other media including a large number of crossovers within the Alien fictional universe. These include:

Main articles: Aliens (novel series) and Aliens vs. Predator (novel series)As well the novelizations based on the various films (including Alan Dean Foster's) there are a number of novel series.

Numerous comic appearances include:



See also: Alien vs. Predator video gamesThe first game based on the franchise was  Alien (1982) for the , a game heavily based on Pac-Man. A strategy game based on the first movie was released in 1984.

Aliens was adapted into four different videogames, a shoot 'em up arcade by Konami,  by Activision,  by Software Studios, and a MSX platformer by Squaresoft.

Acclaim released three different games based on Alien 3, two different run and gun platformers (one for various platforms in 1992, another for the SNES an year later) and a Game Boy adventure game in 1993. Sega also released a light gun arcade,  in 1993.

The last game based on an Alien film was 2000's , a  first-person shooter.

Other Alien games include Mindscape's adventure game  (1995), Acclaim's  first-person shooter Alien Trilogy  (1996), the FPS Aliens Online (1998), the Game Boy Color action game  (2001), and the mobile phone game  (2003). The latest game released was the arcade game , in 2006.

There is also a First person shooter videogame for PC called Aliens versus Predator (computer game) in which one can play as a Marine, Predator and Alien. This was followed by Aliens versus Predator 2 and the expansion pack 

In December 2006, Sega struck a deal with Fox Licensing to release two games based on the Alien franchise on seventh generation consoles.  Obsidian Entertainment will develop an Alien role-playing game,  and Gearbox Software will develop a first-person shooter. 









