

The Mercedes-Benz GLK (code name X204) is a compact crossover competing with the Infiniti EX, Acura RDX, BMW X3 and Land Rover LR2/Freelander, as well as the upcoming Audi Q5, Volvo XC60, Saab 9-4X, and Cadillac BRX. The model sits below the M-Class in the lineup. It is set for release in the United States at early 2010 and as informed by magazines, it should be wearing a price tag around $37,000, which is very close to one of its rivals, the BMW X3.

The GLK-Class was launched in 2008 and is built in Bremen (Germany), the first Mercedes SUV to be built there, however after 2008 most will be built in Mexico and Brazil. Its design is heavily influenced by the GL-Class. 

On 2008-01-12, actress Kim Cattrall appeared at a special unveiling ceremony at the North American International Auto Show in Detroit, confirming that her Sex and the City character (Samantha Jones) would drive the SUV in the movie version of the popular TV show.

The GLK was presented for the first time in 2008 in Detroit under the form of the Mercedes-Benz Vision GLK Freeside concept.

The GLK-Class shares the C-Class (W204) platform, and production plans continued after the demise of the similar Smart Formore.

 Comprehensive restraint system for the best possible occupant protection

In combination with the front and rear deformation zones, the high-strength passenger cell of the GLK-Class provides a highly efficient foundation for the occupant protection systems. The intricate restraint system is capable of offering the greatest possible protection potential. As many as nine airbags are fitted, which are deployed selectively depending on the type of collision and its severity to reduce the forces exerted on the occupants eMercedesBenz said - The all-encompassing approach taken to achieving a high standard of safety evinces itself particularly clearly in the Integral Safety concept, that Mercedes-Benz has once again implemented in the new GLK.



At launch in Germany, the car was offered in all-wheel drive only, though there has been media speculation of a possible rear-wheel drive only version.

The range at launch comprised:





