For other uses, see Android (disambiguation).



An android is a robot designed to resemble a human, usually both in appearance and behavior. The word derives from ανδρός, the genitive of the Greek ανήρ anēr, meaning "man", and the suffix -eides, used to mean "of the species; alike" (from eidos, "species"). Though the word derives from a gender-specific root, its usage in English is usually gender neutral; the female counterpart, gynoid, is generally used only when the  female gender is a distinguishing trait of the robot. The term was first mentioned by St. Albertus Magnus in 1270 and was popularized by the French writer Villiers in his 1886 novel L'Ève future, although the term "android" appears in US patents as early as 1863 in reference to miniature humanlike toy automations.

Thus far, androids have largely remained within the domain of science fiction, frequently seen in film and television. However, some humanoid robots now exist. 

As of August 2007, a handful of android projects have been successfully completed. 

Project Aiko of Canada has created an android portrait of a female person. Using the B.R.A.I.N.S. software (Biometric Robot Artificial Intelligence Neural System), they have created one of the most unusual androids. The android is called "Aiko", which has a silicon body. Aiko is the first android to mimic pain and the ability to learn and avoid pain. In addition, Aiko has speech, voice, face, and object recognition. It can also solve math problems displayed to her visually. It is also capable of learning new information from the environment. It is hoped that Aiko can walk in the near future.

The world's first Android DER 01 was developed by Japanese research group. The Intelligent Robotics Lab, directed by Hiroshi Ishiguro at Osaka University, and Kokoro Co., Ltd. have demonstrated the Actroid at Expo 2005 in Aichi Prefecture, Japan. In 2006, Kokoro Co. developed a new DER 2 android. The height of the human body part of DER2 is 165 cm. There are 47 mobile points. DER2 can not only change its expression but also move its hands and feet and twist its body. The "air servosystem" which Kokoro Co. developed originally is used for the actuator. As a result of having an actuator controlled precisely with air pressure via a servosystem, the movement is very fluent and there is very little noise. DER2 realized a slimmer body than that of the former version by using a smaller cylinder. Outwardly DER2 has a more beautiful proportion. Compared to the previous model, DER2 has thinner arms and a wider repertoire of expressions. The smoothness of her movement has also been improved, making it now even more likely for the uninitiated to confuse her with an actual human being. Once programmed, she is able to choreograph her motions and gestures with her voice. 

The Intelligent Mechatronics Lab, directed by Kobayashi[] at the Science University of Tokyo, has developed an android head called Saya, which was exhibited at Robodex 2002 in Yokohama, Japan. There are several other initiatives around the world involving humanoid research and development at this time, which will hopefully introduce a broader spectrum of realized technology in the near future. Now Saya is working at the Science University of Tokyo as a guide.

The Waseda University (Japan) and NTT Docomo's manufacturers have succeeded in creating a shape-shifting robot WD-2. It is capable of changing its face. At first, the creators decided the position of the necessary points to express the outline, eyes, nose, and so on of a certain person. The robot expresses his/her face by moving all points to the decided positions, they say. The first version of the robot was first developed back in 2003. After that, a year later, they did a couple of major improvements in the design. The robot features an elastic mask made from the average head dummy. It uses a driving system with a 3DOF unit. The WD-2 robot can change its facial features by activating specific facial points on a mask, with each point possessing three degrees of freedom. This one has 17 facial points, for a total of 56 degrees of freedom. As for the materials they used, the WD-2's mask is fabricated with a highly elastic material called Septom, with bits of steel wool mixed in for added strength. Other technical features reveal a shaft driven behind the mask at the desired facial point, driven by a DC motor with a simple pulley and a slide screw. Apparently, the researchers can also modify the shape of the mask based on actual human faces. To "copy" a face, they need only a 3D scanner to determine the locations of an individual's 17 facial points. After that, they are then driven into position using a laptop and 56 motor control boards. In addition, the researchers also mention that the shifting robot can even display an individual's hair style and skin color if a photo of their face is projected onto the 3D mask.

KITECH researched &amp; developed EveR-1, an android interpersonal communications model capable of emulating human emotional expression via facial "musculature" and capable of rudimentary conversation, having a vocabulary of around 400 words. She is 160 cm tall and weighs 50 kg, matching the average figure of Korean women in their twenties. EveR-1's name derives from the Biblical Eve, plus the letter r for robot. EveR-1's advanced computing processing power enables speech recognition and vocal synthesis, at the same time processing lip synchronization and visual recoginition by 90-degree micro-CCD cameras with face recognition technology. An independent microchip inside her artificial brain handles gesture expression, body coordination, and emotion expression. Her whole body is made of highly advanced synthetic jelly silicon and with 60 artificial joints in her face, neck, and lower body; she is able to demonstrate realistic facial expressions and sing while simultaneously dancing. In South Korea, the Ministry of Information and Communication hopes to put a robot in every home by as early as 2013, strictly for the purpose of clean, decorous, nonvulgar entertainment.

Hanson Robotics, Inc. of Texas and KAIST produced an android portrait of Albert Einstein, using Hanson's facial android technology mounted on KAIST's life-size walking bipedal robot body. This Einstein android, also called "Albert Hubo", thus represents the first full-body walking android in history (see video at ). Hanson Robotics, the FedEx Institute of Technology, and the University of Texas at Arlington also developed the android portrait of sci-fi author Philip K. Dick (creator of Blade Runner), with full conversational capabilities that incorporated thousands of pages of the author's works. In 2005, the PKD android won a first place Artificial intelligence award from AAAI.

Unlike the terms robot (a "mechanical" being) and cyborg (a being that is partly organic and partly mechanical), the word android has been used in literature and other media to denote several different kinds of artificially constructed beings:



Although human morphology is not necessarily the ideal form for working robots, the fascination in developing robots that can mimic it can be found historically in the assimilation of two concepts: simulacra (devices that exhibit likeness) and automata (devices that have independence).

The term android was popularized by the French author Auguste Villiers de l'Isle-Adam (1838–1889) in his work Tomorrow's Eve, featuring an artificial humanlike robot named Hadaly. As said by the officer in the story, "In this age of Realien advancement, who knows what goes on in the mind of those responsible for these mechanical dolls."

Although Karel Čapek's robots in R.U.R. (Rossum's Universal Robots) (1921)—the play that introduced the word robot to the world—were organic artificial humans, the word robot has come to primarily refer to mechanical humans, animals, and other beings. The term android can mean either one of these, while a cyborg ("cybernetic organism" or "bionic man") would be a creature that is a combination of organic and mechanical parts.

The word android is a combination of Ancient Greek andros and the suffix -oid, which literally means "in the form of a man."  This could be contrasted with the more general term anthropoid, which means humanlike.

Historically, science fiction authors have used android in a greater diversity of ways than the terms robot and cyborg. In some fiction works, the primary difference between a robot and android is only skin deep, with androids being made to look almost exactly like humans on the outside but with internal mechanics exactly the same as that of robots. In other stories, authors have defined android to indicate a wholly organic, yet artificial, creation. Other definitions of android fall somewhere in between.

The character Data, from the television series , is described as an android. Data became intoxicated in an early episode ("The Naked Now") and is later referred to having "bioplast sheeting" for skin ("The Most Toys"), perhaps suggesting that he was initially intended by the writers to be at least partially organic. Otherwise, Data was shown to be mechanical throughout and this often became a central plot theme.

In the show The Saint, Tyler is an android, or a robot with a human intellect. Tyler spends most of the series in fights with Mary, a normal human, and eventually they team up to fight against the dark evil Vincent.

The character Rock/Mega Man, from the game series of the same name, is called a humanoid in the instructions of the first game and a robot thereafter. He is a member of a class of robots called Robot Masters, which have a certain degree of autonomy. At the end of Mega Man 7, he states that he is "more than just a robot." Mega Man's successor, Mega Man X, is specifically identified to be fully autonomous.

The Replicants from the movie Blade Runner were bioengineered organic beings. While they were not referred to as either robots or androids in the movie, the screenplay was originally based on a novel by Philip K. Dick called Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep? In this novel, the beings in question are specifically referred to as "androids" or, more familiarly, "andys." They were created to serve as slaves for humans in the aftermath of a nuclear war. The feature that most obviously distinguishes them from humans is their lack of empathy—otherwise, they are virtually indistinguishable from their organic counterparts (indeed, at one point a character observes that a psychotic human could be confused with an android).

In the video game Beneath a Steel Sky, genetically engineered androids similar to Blade Runner's Replicants are a central plot theme. However, despite their organic makeup, their behavior is programmed by computer.

The robots of Karel Čapek's R.U.R. were organic in nature. Today, an author writing a similar story might very well be inclined to call them androids.

The character Ash in the movie Alien, another artificial organic being, is often referred to as an android (though not in the dialogue of the movie itself). Similarly, the character Bishop in Aliens and Alien 3 is a more advanced android commonly called a Synthetic, but prefers to be called an "artificial person". Much later in the series timeline, the character Call in Alien Resurrection is ashamed of being an android. Interesting to note is that the internal workings of the androids in the Alien universe seem almost human like. They have a white liquid, analogous for blood, probably for hydraulic movement. They also seem to have "guts" as seen in Aliens.

In the Star Wars movies, C-3PO, R2-D2, and other robots are referred to as "droids." While C-3PO could reasonably be called an android because he is humanoid in appearance, the squat cylinder R2-D2 is at most only humanoid in behavior.

In the movie A.I., the robotic characters are called mechas, but the film is loosely based on a short story written by Brian Aldiss called "Supertoys Last All Summer Long", in which the central character David is called an android (by which Aldiss seemed to be referring to an organic creation).

In the anime/manga Chobits, Androids are known as "persocoms", essentially computers in a man-made body. The series does not go into their internal composition, but it is assumed to be artificial with a very realistic outside. One of the key points of this series was a special type of persocom named "Chobit", a persocom that had free will and the ability to fall in love and have emotions.

The android BEJ (Bio Electric Jerk) is a character in the comic series Jack O Lantern Productions. Unlike many androids who usually talk politely, he has an eccentric attitude and refers to humans as "stupid apes."

The Cylon race in the re-imagined Battlestar Galactica series includes twelve android models that are virtually indistinguishable from human beings down to the cellular level. However subcellularly (molecularly) they are different in many ways; as such have superhuman capacities but lack the ability to functionally reproduce with each other.

The character Kryten from the television show Red Dwarf is described as being a "mechanoid" as well as an android. This is a melding of the words mechanical and humanoid. According to the episode "DNA", his brain is partly organic, and his DNA can therefore be altered. He is also capable of breaking his programming and obtaining emotions, though this proves to be difficult as displayed in the episode "Camille."



In fiction, one prominent android variation is the Bio android, which is constructed of protein based components as opposed to electronic and mechanical parts. Bio androids are all composed of synthetic flesh, though their exact composition varies from work to work. Biorobotics or synthetic biology are among the terms used to describe how they are made. Many more examples may be found in this list of fictional robots.











