



 The DataHand keyboard was introduced in 1995 by DataHand Systems, Inc.  Before that it was produced by Industrial Innovations as early as 1992.  The keyboard consists of two completely separate "keyboards", one for the left hand and one for the right, that are molded to rest your hands in.  This allows you to place each hand wherever it is most comfortable to you. Each finger activates five buttons, the four compass directions as well as down.  The thumbs also have five buttons as well, one inside and two outside as well as up and down. The button modules in which the fingers rest are adjustable to best fit the user's hands - each side can be independently moved up and down, towards the palm or further away.

This ergonomic layout allows for all typing to occur without any wrist motion, as well as without any finger extension.  The keyboard layout is initially similar to a QWERTY keyboard, but the middle two columns of keys (i.e. H,Y,G...) have been delegated to sideways finger movements, and all of the keys outside of the main three rows are accessed through two additional modes, including a mode for mousing.  There are three different modes all together: number and symbols, ten-key, and function and mouse mode.  Some practice is required. However eventual typing speedups are possible. Some people say they weren't able to type as fast as they used to. Others say they regained their typing speed. Even others say they could type significantly faster.

Also of note is the button design - instead of being spring loaded, the buttons are held in place with magnets and are activated using optical sensors.  This was done in order to reduce pressure required for typing.

This unconventional keyboard was seen in the Jodie Foster 1997 movie Contact as the pilot's controls for the futuristic space ship.  The Industrial Innovations version was featured on the television series Mighty Morphin Power Rangers.

After the initial prototype was released in 1995, DataHand has released the Professional and Professional II with new bodies.  The Professional II also has extended programming capabilities over the Professional, being able to record macros of keystrokes for convenient use.

Due to supplier issues, DataHand Systems, Inc. has recently announced on its web site that it will not sell the DataHand keyboard "until a new manufacturer can be identified."







