

Meg Masters is a fictional character on The CW Television Network's Supernatural'' portrayed by Nicki Aycox and serves as the host body to the demonic daughter of Azazel. In the second season, the demon temporarily takes possession of Sam Winchester, played by Jared Padalecki.

The demon is introduced meeting up with Sam for the first time in “Scarecrow” when she is on the roadside heading for California to get away from her family, or so she tells him. The two meet up again not too long later at a bus station and wait together for the bus to Sacramento to arrive. Sam tells Meg about Dean and how he seems to treat him like dirt. After Sam leaves to help Dean, Meg kills a man in a van and "makes a call" by slitting the man’s throat and draining his blood into a silver bowl. She refers to the person she speaks with in the bowl as her father.

Meg returns in the episode "Shadow", where she is in Chicago at a bar. She tells Sam that California was not all it was made up to be, and they decide to meet up later. Meg gives Sam her phone number, 312-555-0143, and her last name, Masters. Sam later follows her to a warehouse where he finds her talking with something. Sam returns to Dean and tells him what he saw, and they arrive at the conclusion that she was the one who summoned the Daeva (the evil of that episode) and that she might have been talking with Azazel. Meg captures the brothers and reveals that their capture was a trap for their father. However, the brothers manage to break free and destroy Meg's altar, thereby freeing the Daevas, which throw Meg out of a seven-story window to her apparent death. To the Winchesters' surprise, she quickly recovers and uses an amulet to regain control of the Daevas, which she sends after them. However, they manage to escape the attack.

Meg resurfaces once again at a church where she speaks with Pastor Jim Murphy, showing signs of being possessed, before she kills him. She later calls Sam and asks to speak to John. While on the phone, she kills a friend of John's, Caleb, and tells him that if he does not deliver the Colt to her by midnight in a warehouse in Lincoln, on the corner of Wabash and Lake, she would kill more of his friends. John agrees to the deal, despite how long it will take to get there. John makes it on time but gives her and her demonic brother, Tom, a fake gun. Tom shoots Meg and reveals that it is a fake. Meg then takes John hostage.

Meg, both furious and anxious to obtain the Colt, comes to a hunter and friend of the Winchesters', Bobby Singer's, auto shop where she confronts Dean, Sam, and Bobby. After presumably killing Bobby's dog, Meg breaks the door down and begins to taunt Dean and Sam about their father. Dean attempts to pour holy water on her, but is thrown backwards as Meg approaches Sam and Bobby. She unknowingly walks right into the center of a Key of Solomon, a magical circle which incapacitates any demons who enter. Dean then asks Sam to assist him with performing an exorcism on her while he tries to get information about their dad. They are able to get information on where their father is after Meg is seemingly in an abundance of pain from the exorcism. Breathless, she asks them to let her go, but to her surprise Dean does not free her from the trap. Dean then forces Sam to finish the exorcism on Meg, releasing her from the hold of the demon that was controlling her. Upon the completion of the exorcism, the demon flies out in a cloud of black smoke through her mouth and into the Devil's Trap where it is sent to Hell.

The demon that had possessed Meg reappears in "Born Under a Bad Sign" sporting Sam's body. Not caring any longer about the grand war, she is looking for revenge for the world of pain and suffering she was put through after Dean and Sam sent her to Hell. After locking herself to Sam's body with a  "binding mark" carved into Sam's arm, she taunts Jo about her feelings for Dean, tries to kill Bobby, and successfully kills another hunter. Once again, the demon is trapped inside of the Key of Solomon symbol at Bobby's house. With her trapped inside, both Bobby and Dean attempt another exorcism. However, this time she has her own tricks and begins to chant in Latin during the exorcism, showing no signs of internal pain as she suffered before. As she recites this spell, the fire in the fireplace crackles ferociously and the ground shakes violently. Shockingly, she manages to break the Key of Solomon which kept her bound and trapped. Released from captivity, she throws Bobby against the wall and supposedly knocks him unconscious before attacking Dean without mercy. The demon reveals that she saw John in Hell and that he says "Howdy." Just in time, Bobby burns off the mark and the demon is expelled from Sam's body, escaping through the fireplace. As of now, her current whereabouts are unknown.

Meg was born in Andover, Massachusetts, and she attended a local high school. Walking alone one night, she was taken over by the demon. After it is exorcised from her, the true Meg reveals before she dies that the demon had possessed her for a year and that she was awake through some of it, referring to it as a nightmare. She then feels all of the pain that her body went through when the demon was possessing her, including the broken bones from her seven story fall and the gunshot wound to her abdomen. Slowly dying, she reveals to Sam and Dean where their father is in a cryptic message. Her last word was "sunrise", directing the brothers to the Sunrise apartments, where their father was held captive by demons.

The ghost of the real Meg appears in "Are You There, God? It's Me, Dean Winchester" as one of the Witnesses raised by Lilith's spell to attack the hunters who failed to save them. She reveals to Dean that she had a younger sister who killed herself after her dead body was found, and denounces Sam for working with Ruby, a demon who possesses helpless victims just like Meg herself. The ghost is enraged that the brothers didn't figure out sooner that she was a host and exorcize the demon before her body had sustained lethal damage.

While possessed by the demon, she is granted many demonic abilities, such as enhanced strength and inhuman durability. She also exhibits telekinesis, knowledge of certain spells and incantations, and the ability to commune with other demons, mainly the demon's father, Azazel. She is also seen to be immune to hallowed ground, as seen in "Salvation", due to the demon possessing her being beyond the "minor leagues." However, she is still vulnerable to holy water. 

In "Born Under a Bad Sign", the demon who originally possessed her is able to break free from the bounds of a Key of Solomon. Its ability to escape is probably associated with the fact that it "picked up a few tricks" and mastered some sort of spell, allowing it to damage the Key of Solomon, rendering it ineffective.







