



Waitati is a small seaside settlement in Otago, New Zealand, within the city limits of Dunedin. It is located close to the tidal mudflats of Blueskin Bay, 19 kilometres north of the Dunedin city centre. The small Waitati River flows through the Bay to the sea.

State Highway 1 skirts the western edge of the settlement, which marks the northern limit of the stretch known as the Dunedin Northern Motorway. 3 km to the north of here the highway ascends the notorious Kilmog hill. The Main South Line railway curves from east to north through Waitati and a tourist train, the Seasider, travels through here between Dunedin and Palmerston once or twice a week. The old station yard remains as a train crossing loop and parts of the old station building are used by rail maintenance workers.

Waitati is the site of a school, a branch of the Dunedin Public Libraries, a garden centre, a cafe and a general store. There are several holiday homes.

For many years the settlement has been known for its appeal to alternative lifestylers. The Waitati Militia, a pacifist warfare group, was founded here, and the village featured in the history of the Values Party, Mushroom magazine and anti Vietnam war and Aramoana aluminium smelter protests, as well as the development in New Zealand of Environmental education.

Waitati has no sewerage system, and has become a centre in New Zealand for the development of composting toilets and other alternative sewage disposal systems. Some villagers are edible garden and alternative energy enthusiasts.

Waitati has become an arrival point for German immigrants to New Zealand and has a high proportion of Germans and German-Kiwis.

Doctors Point Beach, a beautiful sandy southern beach that often has little blue penguins nesting there, amongst other wildlife that can be seen.  Sometimes seals come up to sleep on the beach.

Waitati Film Society screens films every second Tuesday night during most of the year (every Tuesday night in the middle of winter).

The Orokonui Ecosanctuary wildlife project is under construction in an area of native bush here.

Waitati is part of the Transition Towns Aotearoa  initiative, using some Transition Towns techniques and patterns for energy descent.



Coordinates: 45°45′S 170°34′E﻿ / ﻿-45.75, 170.567