David Woozley (born December 6, 1979) is an English former professional footballer. As of August 2007, Woozley worked in the Fire Service. 

Woozley was born in Berkshire and began his career as a trainee with Crystal Palace, turning professional in August 1997. He made his Palace debut on March 28, 1999 in a 1-0 win at home to Bradford City and kept his place in the side for the remainder of the season. He played 22 times in the league and six times in cup games the following season, but at the start of the 2000-2001 season found himself out of favour and was allowed to join Bournemouth on loan.

He returned to Palace, but couldn't find a way back into the first team. At the start of the following season he had a successful loan spell with Torquay United, but returned to Palace. He finally joined Torquay in March 2002 on a free transfer and quickly re-established himself in Torquay's defence, playing alongside either Steve Woods or his former Palace teammate Sean Hankin.

He was again a regular the following season, but lost his place after the signing of Craig Taylor and played just ten league games as Torquay won promotion, However, he did play in the crucial 2-1 win at Southend United on the last day of the season, coming on as a last minute substitute for David Graham as Torquay held on to clinch promotion. 

He was released shortly after the Southend game and in July 2004 signed for Oxford United, but struggled to establish himself and joined Yeovil Town on loan in March 2005. He was released by Oxford at the end the season and joined Crawley Town in August 2005.

In October 2006 Woozley became joint manager of Crawley Town with Ben Judge after manager John Hollins and his assistant Alan Lewer were sacked from the club. In January 2007 it was announced that Woozley and Judge would remain in charge until the end of the season.

On August 28, 2007, Woozley announced that he was to leave Crawley Town and to retire from professional football, aged 27, to take up a job with the Fire Service and signed for semi-professional team Farnborough FC.









