A list of henchmen from the 1999 James Bond film The World Is Not Enough from the List of James Bond henchmen



Giulietta da Vinci or the Cigar Girl is a fictional character from the opening sequence to the 1999 James Bond film The World Is Not Enough, played by Maria Grazia Cucinotta. In the film the name is given by association only but in the novelisation of the film the character is called Giulietta da Vinci.

The Cigar Girl first appears in the Swiss banker's office in Bilbao where Bond was investigating the murder of 0012. She offers him a cigar and her Mediterranean physical allure captures the attention of James Bond [In fact Bond alludes to her physical beauty in one of the most famous [[puns]] uttered by him. When the Swiss banker asks her to show Bond papers depicting the money being returned to him, she asks Bond, "Would you like to check my figures?" Bond replies with considerable elan, "No, I am sure, they are perfectly rounded!"]. On Bond's attempt to force the banker to relay information about the death of 0012, The Cigar Girl escapes after throwing a knife in the banker's back as he is about to give away information.



Later in the opening sequence, after Sir Robert King was blown up with explosive money,the Cigar Girl was waiting in a speedboat on the River Thames with a scoped rifle taking a shot at Bond for good measure and then attempting to escape. 007 went after her and the two eventually ended up in a hot air balloon. By then MI6, via helicopters, cornered her. Rather than face Renard's persecution, the Cigar Girl chose suicide by firing into the gas tanks forcing Bond to jump and land on the roof of the Millennium Dome.

Last Conversation 

Bond : "I can protect you!"

Cigar Girl : "Not from him!"



Gabor is a henchman in the James Bond film The World Is Not Enough. He was portrayed by John Seru.

He is Elektra King's bodyguard, and is usually seen accompanying her. It is unknown whether he is really an employee of Renard, but nevertheless, as Elektra's and Renard's goals are the same, he assists both. He helped Elektra capture M after shooting her guards. He is shot dead by Bond after the agent escapes from Elektra's grasp and wastes no time in gunning Gabor down during the Maiden's Tower assault.



Bullion is a supporting villain in the James Bond film The World Is Not Enough, portrayed by Drum and Bass artist Goldie.

Bond first encounters him while on his way to speak to Valentin Zukovsky, but had to apply a little force to get through Bullion to speak to his boss.  A seemingly loyal servant to Valentin Zukovsky, Bullion ultimately double-crosses his boss by working for Elektra King. After tipping her off to Bond's location at the Caviare Factory and the failed assassination attempt, Bullion resorts to leaving his gold case behind in the KGB Headquarters. The bomb explodes but fails to kill Bond, Christmas Jones and Zukovsky, who ultimately gets his revenge by gunning him down during the Maiden's Tower assault. True to his name, Bullion is easily recognizable by the sheer amount of gold jewellery he sports, including gold-capped teeth. His real name is Maurice Womasa from Somalia. Apparently, according to Valentin, he does not trust banks.

Last Words - "Boss! You're alive... So glad to see you!" - Zukovsky: "Me too," [shoots him]



Sasha Davidov is a villain in the James Bond film The World Is Not Enough. He was portrayed by Ulrich Thomsen.

Davidov is in effect Elektra King's right-hand-man, as he is in charge of her personal security and also meets with Renard regularly. After Dr. Arkov is killed, he takes over the job of infiltrating the nuclear decommissioning site but only makes it as far as the airport. After having his devotion to the cause tested by Renard and his scalding rocks, Bond discovers Davidov's affiliation and shoots him twice before dropping him into a dumpster. It is later revealed that Elektra's men recovered Davidov's body at the airstrip when she contacts M on Bond's disappearance. 



Lachaise is a villain in the James Bond film The World Is Not Enough. He was portrayed by Patrick Malahide. A Swiss banker, he handed over Sir Robert King's recovered money to 007, and had information about the murder of an MI6 agent. Much to Bond's dismay, Lachaise said "I'm just the middleman. Take the money." Lachaise did know who was the person whom killed the MI6 agent. Renard's employee, the Cigar Girl, killed him with a throwing knife before he could tell James Bond who had the money stolen from.



Dr. Mikhail Arkov is a villain in the James Bond film The World Is Not Enough. He was portrayed by Jeff Nuttall.

Arkov is a nuclear physicist stationed in Kazakhstan. He is Renard's contact within the Kazakhstan facility, and plans to supply Renard with the atomic bomb that he needs to blow up Istanbul. However, after Arkov shows himself to be afraid of Bond and orders the plan be abandoned, Renard orders an unnamed henchman to shoot him, and orders Davidov to impersonate him to get the bomb.

During his pursuit of Davidov, Bond finds Arkov's body in Davidov's car. After he kills Davidov, Bond takes Arkov's ID card to continue the ruse in an attempt to stop Renard.

