"Angels of Death" redirects here. You may be looking for Space Marines (Warhammer 40,000)This is a list of henchmen in the novel and film On Her Majesty's Secret Service. 



Irma Bunt is the main henchwoman in the James Bond novel and film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  She is portrayed by German actress Ilse Steppat. The role was Steppat's only English speaking part.

Irma Bunt resides at the mountain-top clinic of Piz Gloria with Ernst Stavro Blofeld. Bunt is first introduced at a train station taking Bond up to the clinic by sleigh and helicopter while he is disguised as Sir Hilary Bray. She ostensibly looks after the girls who are suffering allergies – and secretly being brainwashed into 'angels of death' – and has dinner with them and 'Sir Hilary'. A red-haired disciplinarian in the mold of Rosa Klebb, Bunt is determined to keep any fraternizing between 'Sir Hilary' and the girls kept to a minimum. Bond himself subtly insults her by telling her that her name comes from a nautical word for the baggy, swollen part of a sail.

When Bond escapes from Piz Gloria after his cover as Sir Hilary Bray was blown, Bunt helps some of the men pursue him in the village at the bottom of the mountain with a Mercedes-Benz W111. She fails in this and was seemingly killed when she was caught in an explosion at a stock car rally. She is not seen again until right at the end of the film after 007's wedding (a scene deleted from the film had Bunt trailing Bond and Tracy when they were purchasing a wedding ring from a jewelry store). Bunt showed up, alive and well, in a car driven by Blofeld. As they passed the newlyweded couple, Bunt leaned out of the window and sprayed bullets at Bond with a machine gun. Bond was unharmed, but Tracy was killed.

Unusual for a Bond film villain, Bunt seems to have escaped punishment and retribution from 007: she did not appear in the following film, Diamonds Are Forever, where Bond avenges Tracy's death by relentlessly tracking down and killing Blofeld. Other villains, such as Jaws, survive because they switched allegiances. This is probably because Ilse Steppat passed away shortly after OHMSS was released. Playboy.  In this sequel to the book You Only Live Twice; after almost being killed by James Bond, she takes revenge upon the secret agent.



Grunther is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by Yuri Borienko. 

Grunther is a henchman to Ernst Stavro Blofeld. He appears from Piz Gloria onwards. In the film, he is first seen with Irma Bunt. Later, he is seen denying Shaun Campbell access to the Piz Gloria base and later holds him prisoner. He leads the first group on the downhill ski to catch the escaping Bond. He crashes into a tree and ends up with Blofeld's second group. His final appearance is during the Battle of Piz Gloria, in which he fights with Tracy Bond and is killed when she impales him on a wall of spikes.



Braun is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by George Lane Cooper. 

Braun's most distinguishing features are his large sideburns. He is one of two SPECTRE henchmen who accompany Irma Bunt in her pursuit of Bond through a small town in the Alps. He and Felsen fight with Bond in a shed and are defeated by him, but Bunt recalls them to her car and they chase Bond and Tracy through a racecourse. Braun sits on the left side front seat of the car, next to the driver, and manges to get a few potshots off at Bond's car before he is forced to abandon his car before it blows up.

Braun is not to be confused with another henchman called Braun, who featured in the later Bond film Licence to Kill.



Felsen is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by Les Crawford. 

Felsen is a thin SPECTRE henchman who accompanies Irma Bunt and Braun in their pursuit of Bond. He and Braun are knocked out by Bond, but are woken up by Bunt in order to chase Bond and Tracy in their car. Felsen sat in the back seat with Bunt and tried to shoot at Bond's car on the highway, but his car veered off the road before he could fire. He abandoned the car before it blew up at the racetrack.



SPECTRE Driver is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by Reg Harding. 

This man drives Bunt, Felsen, and Braun after Bond during his second escape from Piz Gloria Allergy Clinic. He strafes a phone booth in the Alpine town Bond flees to, allowing Braun and Felsen to fill it with bullets. Beyond that, he does little more than get orders barked at him by Bunt. He abandons the car when it blows up at the racetrack.



Josef is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by Joseph Vasa, credited as "Piz Gloria receptionist". 

Josef is the receptionist at Blofeld's sham clinic, Piz Gloria. Josef meets Bond at the entrance to the clinic an shedules an appointment for Bond, as "Sir Hilary," to see the doctor. Josef is often seen skulking around in the background during the first half of the film, including putting in a phone call to Blofeld that Bond's ally Campbell is scaling the mountain. Shortly after this, he is seen on the phone again, presumably ordering Campbell's execution.

Bond later encounters Josef again during his escape from Piz Gloria. Josef, now dressed in full SPECTRE gear, attacks Bond, who knocks him out after a short fight. Bond stashes Josef's unconscious body in a locker full of skiing equipment.



Gumbold is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by James Bree. 

Gumbold is a Swiss attorney who is in the employ of SPECTRE. His role is to help Blofeld be recognized as Balthzar de Bleuchamp, Count of Bleuville. His role in the film is minimal, although Bond finds documents from the College of Arms in his office that help lead him to Blofeld.



SPECTRE Skier is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by George Leech. 

There are several SPECTRE skiers, with this man being the only one with a significant part. He comes after Bond during his escape from Piz Gloria, after hearing the scream of another skier whom Bond threw over a cliff. Bond knocks out this skier, intent on stealing his skis to replace the ones he lost dealing with the first skier. This skier wakes up and attacks Bond, so Bond strangles him into submission with his own skis and then tosses him off a nearby cliff.

The Angels of Death are several beautiful women from all over the world (though in the novel, only ten from the UK) being brainwashed by Blofeld under the guise of allergy treatment. Their mission is to help Blofeld contaminate and ultimately sterilize the world's food supply. Blofeld claimed he will rescind this threat if all his past crimes are pardoned and he is recognized as the current Count de Bleauchamp. In the novel, Ruby's last name is "Windsor".





Raphael is a henchman in the James Bond film On Her Majesty's Secret Service.  He is portrayed by Terry Mountain. 

Raphael, along with his unnamed subordinate, are foes of bond in the pre-credits sequence. They menace Bond and Tracy after he saves her from the ocean, in a vain attempt to restrain them. Bond and Tracy escape, and Raphael is not seen again.

