

This article is about the princess from the Mario series. For the video game starring her, see Super Princess Peach. Princess Peach (ピーチ姫, Pīchi-hime) is a character in Nintendo's Mario series of video games. She is the princess of the fictitious Mushroom Kingdom, and often plays the "damsel in distress" role in the adventure series. She was known as "Princess Toadstool" outside Japan until late 1996, when the name "Peach" was added in Super Mario 64, later solely becoming "Princess Peach". In 2008, Princess Peach landed on Forbes Wealthiest Fictional People list, with a fortune upwards of $1 billion. []

Peach is portrayed as the princess of the Mushroom Kingdom. King And Queen Toadstool, her mother and father, rule the kingdom. In , the princess's grandmother is shown (she has a grandmother), and the Mushroom Kingdom government is ruled by a chancellor and the mushroom retainers.

Peach first appeared in Super Mario Bros. and has been kidnapped several times by the series' main antagonist, Bowser.

In Super Mario Bros. 2, players could go through the game as Princess Toadstool. Toadstool, along with Mario, Luigi and Toad, were called by the Subcon to save their dream land from the evil Wart. Toadstool's main ability was that she could hover for a limited time after jumping left or right. This makes her a popular choice amongst players, since her jumping skills allow her to easily make jumps over larger areas than other characters.  

In Super Mario Bros. 3, Bowser made a new attempt on capturing the princess. Hearing of it, Princess Toadstool asked Mario and Luigi to rescue the Mushroom Kings, sending them items while they were on their quest and providing them with power-ups after completing each level.

In Super Mario World, Mario, Luigi and Toadstool were having a vacation in Dinosaur Land when Bowser once again kidnapped her. This time, she was held captive in Bowser's Castle in the Valley of Bowser. Bowser had brought her inside his Koopa Clown Car for the final battle against the brothers. Toadstool was helping Mario in the final battle by throwing mushrooms at him right before Bowser retreated after being hit three times. In the end, Toadstool was rescued by Mario, and she gave him a kiss.

In Super Mario RPG: Legend of the Seven Stars, Toadstool was one of Mario's party members, along with Mallow, Geno and Bowser. Toadstool possesses healing/resurrection powers similar to Mallow. 

In Super Mario 64, Peach invited Mario to her castle for a cake, but before Mario arrived at the castle-side, Bowser came and took control over the Power Stars. He sealed Peach in the fresco over the entrance of the castle.

In Super Mario Sunshine, Mario, Peach, and Toadsworth went to Isle Delfino on Peach's private plane. However, Bowser Jr., in the disguise of Shadow Mario, had filled the island with graffiti. The crimes were blamed on Mario, and he was sentenced to clean the entire island with FLUDD. Eventually, Bowser Jr. kidnapped Peach while Mario was away, and took her to Pinna Park, where he revealed his true identity. Bowser Jr. claimed that Peach was his mother and that the evil Mario had kidnapped her. After Mario destroyed Bowser Jr.'s Mecha-Bowser, in which the princess was held captive, Bowser Jr. used a balloon to take the still intact head of the Bowser robot to Corona Mountain, with Peach still inside. Later, Mario made his way to the top of the active volcano and found Peach forced to battle with Bowser and Bowser Jr. in a pool of green acid. This was described by Bowser as a "family vacation". Mario managed to rescue Peach, and later they were able to enjoy their vacation together with FLUDD. 

Princess Peach was kidnapped once again in New Super Mario Bros. However, as in Super Mario Sunshine, the culprit was not Bowser but his son, Bowser Jr.

Super Princess Peach marked the second time that Princess Peach was cast as the main hero in a video game, as Princess Peach had to save Mario and Luigi from King Bowser.

In Super Mario Galaxy, Peach's castle was lifted into space by Bowser, who wanted Peach to rule the universe by his side. She was brought into Outer Space, along with some Toads, and Mario had to go through different galaxies to save her. 

Princess Peach has appeared in nearly all of the Mario spin-off titles.

Since the first Mario Party, Peach has appeared in every single installment, including Mario Party Advance. However, like all Mario Party games, she has nothing outside appearance and voice to set her apart from other characters. An exception to this is Mario Party 7, in which both Peach and Daisy can use the Flower Orb as their special orb (that is, no other characters can receive it at orb spaces or shops).

In the Mario Kart series, she is in with the medium category characters with the fastest acceleration, the lowest top speed, and the best off-road ability to take the shortcuts on each course.

In , her special move involves flying hearts surrounding her kart, and any item that hits them becoming hers to use. She shares her special with Princess Daisy who is supposedly her cousin as stated in the Mario Kart Wii official guide, but nonetheless, she is still her best friend, and appears in a few games in the Mario series, including Mario and Sonic at the Olympic Games.

  In the Mario Tennis'' and Mario Golf'' series, she is labeled as a "Technique" character and has one of the lightest hits. She is a captain in the game Mario Superstar Baseball and specializes in pitching. She is also a playable character in Super Mario Strikers and its sequel, Mario Strikers Charged. Peach is fast, agile, and has good passing skills. Finally, she also appears in the first Mario basketball game, Mario Hoops 3-on-3, for the Nintendo DS, and is a technical type (good at shooting). She appears in the Sonic the Hedgehog and Mario crossover sports game, Mario &amp; Sonic at the Olympic Games, where she is a skill type character. Her crown appears as the "Unspeakable Wonder" in Pikmin 2.

In the Super Smash Bros.'' series, Peach first appears in Super Smash Bros. Melee, the second game of the series. She has the unique ability to float for a number of seconds, much as she can in Super Mario Bros. 2, an advantage which is balanced by the fact that she is one of the lighter fighters. Peach is also a playable character in Super Smash Bros. Brawl. Some of her attacks include the Peach Bomber, her parasol, her back throw using Toad as a human shield, her aerial back attack using golf clubs and frying pan as mêlée weapons, and pulling vegetables from the ground.

In The Super Mario Bros. Super Show!, Peach has red hair instead of her now-standard blonde (although this may have been due to the original NES games depicting her with red hair, due to technological limitations).

Peach has made cameo appearances in several non-Mario games. She is a playable guest character in the GameCube ports of the Electronic Arts games NBA Street V3 and SSX On Tour. Peach also made a minor appearance in , in a painting in Hyrule Castle. A Princess Peach kart toy appears and can be driven in the Labrador and Friends version of Nintendogs. Peach also made a cameo in , appearing in a picture sent to Mr. Write from the goat in the animal village. The photo is of Peach with the name "Christine" written underneath the picture.

Princess Peach has long yellow hair, sparkling azure eyes, fair pink skin, rosy pink cheeks, and a statuesque figure. She wears a pink princess gown, pink princess shoes, white princess gloves, a sapphire pendant, sapphire earrings, and a gold tiara with sapphires and rubies. She owns a lot of princess gowns, princess shoes, princess gloves, pendants, earrings, and tiaras. Peach always wears pink princess panties as an undergarment. She owns a lot of princess panties. In sports games, Peach wears a pink skirt or pink shorts with a pink top, white bobby socks, and pink tennis shoes. She wore various dresses, skirts, and tops in Mario Party 2. In Super Mario Sunshine, Peach wore a pink summer gown, pink summer shoes, and lots of jewelry. She also carries a white parasol decorated with pink lace. In Paper Mario - The Thousand Year Door, when she is possessed by the Shadow Queen, Peach wears a black dress, black dress shoes, long black gloves, a black cape, a ruby pendant, ruby earrings, and a pointed gold tiara with rubies. She wore a pink soccer uniform in Super Mario Strikers. In Mario Strikers Charged, Peach wears pink battle armor. In Mario Kart Wii, when riding a bike, Peach wears white trousers with pink lining, a white jacket with pink lining, pink boots, a pink scarf, pink gloves, and a pink belt with a white buckle.

In her first voiced appearance in the 1986 Japanese anime  (Super Mario Bros.: The Great Mission To Rescue Princess Peach) Peach was voiced by Mami Yamase, a pop singer. On the cartoon segments on The Super Mario Bros. Super Show!, Peach was usually voiced by Jeannie Elias, and on The Adventures of Super Mario Bros. 3 and Super Mario World cartoons, she was voiced by Tracey Moore.

In the CD-i game Hotel Mario, Peach was voiced by Jocelyn Benford.

In Super Mario 64 and the English version of Mario Kart 64, Peach was voiced by Leslie Swan, a localization manager for Nintendo of America. Swan voiced Peach again for the release of Super Mario 64 DS in 2004.

In Mario Party, Mario Party 2 and the Japanese version of Mario Kart 64, Peach was voiced by Asako Kozuki.

Starting with Mario Golf'' on the Nintendo 64, Peach has been voiced by Jen Taylor.

In 2005, Nintendo used a new voice for Princess Peach. Although Super Princess Peach and Mario Hoops 3-on-3 still used Taylor's voice, other games, such as  and Super Mario Strikers have a new Peach voice, Nicole Mills. The infant form of Princess Peach that appears in Mario and Luigi: Partners in Time, Yoshi's Island DS and Mario Kart Wii, known as Baby Peach, is also voiced by Mills. However, in Super Paper Mario, Peach is once again voiced by Swan. Additionally, Peach was voiced by Samantha Kelly in games such as Super Mario Galaxy, Mario Party 8, Mario Strikers Charged, and Super Smash Bros. Brawl. In Mario &amp; Sonic at the Olympic Games, Peach is again voiced by Taylor, although much is from sound clips recycled from previous Mario games. Likewise, if a player selects Peach in Brawl using a Wii remote or classic controller, Peach's taunt from Melee (also then voiced by Taylor) will sound over the Wii Remote's speaker.



