There are four genus' of geckos that indigenous to Madagascar, the Geckolepis genus, the Paroedura genus, the Phelsuma genus, and the Uroplatus genus, with the latter two more commonly known as the day geckos and the leaf-tailed geckos respectively. 

Geckolepis maculata often shelter on Pandanus plants of the Paleotropics http://72.14.253.104/search?q=cache:21eCmFLKFP0J:www.wooster.edu/biology/rlehtinen/Lehtinen%25202002a.pdf+Geckolepis+maculata+habitat&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=4. 

The Paroedura genus consists of several species of ground-dwelling geckos that live in most, if not all, of the habitats in Madagascar, ranging from dry-deciduous forestshttp://www.tropical-biology.org/admin/documents/pdf_files/Madagascar%20abstracts/Madagascar_Other%20animals.pdf to spiny bushhttp://vesmir.msu.cas.cz/Pavel/ekokonference_EN.htmland deserts, to rainforests.http://www.bio.sdsu.edu/pub/tod/students/yang/webpageA terrestrial and diurnal gecko that grows to approximately 6 inches in length. It lives in a dry forest habitat and typically shelters under wooden debri or trees. http://www.hoch-rep.com/html/seiten/tiere.phtml?nav=4&amp;lang=en&amp;parentID=193&amp;tier=59Paroedura bastardi is terrestrial gecko approximately 15cm in length that lives in dry forests, and thornbush steppes. It requires a humidity between 60% and 80%, a daytime temperature between 25 and 28 degrees Celsius, and a nighttime temperature between 20 and 22 degrees Celsius to survive. http://www.hoch-rep.com/html/seiten/tiere.phtml?nav=4&amp;lang=en&amp;parentID=196&amp;tier=59Paroedura gracilis is both terrestrial and somewhat arboreal, and lives in the rainforest that spans the eastern coast of Madagascar http://www.naturalia.org/zoo/RETTILI/e_125.html. Paroedura maingoka survives in the dry-deciduous forest ecosystem of Madagascar.http://www.worldwildlife.org/wildworld/profiles/terrestrial/at/at0202_full.htmlParoedura masobe is an arboreal gecko http://www.gex-anon.00page.com/caredoc/Pictus%20Care.html that lives in the lowland forest habitat of Madagascar http://www.worldwildlife.org/wildworld/profiles/terrestrial/at/at0117_full.html. Paroedura picta are a terrestrial species that typically grow between 5 and 6 inches in length. They live in forests, savannahs, and a variety of semi-arid ecosystems with a temperature between 82 and 85 degrees Fahrenheit during the day, and 75 to 78 degrees Fahrenheit at night. http://www.geckosunlimited.com/care_p.picta.htmParoedura stumpffi is an arboreal gecko http://www.gex-anon.00page.com/caredoc/Pictus%20Care.html. Paroedura tanjaka geckos make their home in the dry deciduos forests of Madagascar. http://www.worldwildlife.org/wildworld/profiles/terrestrial/at/at0202_full.htmlParoedura vazimba survives only in the Zambitse-Vohibasia National Park of Madagascar. http://www.worldwildlife.org/wildworld/profiles/terrestrial/at/at1312_full.html

The Phelsuma genus contains the day geckos. The name is a misnomer as they sometimes hunt at night, feeding on fruits, nectar, insects, invertebrates and sometimes small vertebrates. Most day geckos require a humidity between 50% and 85% to survive and a mean temperature of 65 degrees Fahrenheit. The typical coloration consists of an olive, chartreuse, or turquoise with red spots.http://animal.discovery.com/fansites/jeffcorwin/carnival/lizard/dgecko.html Phelsuma abbotti chekei grows to a maximum length of 6 inches. They live on the fringes of large forests, as well as mangrove forests, and seasonal dry forests. In an urbanized setting, they can live around residential sections. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_abbotti_chekei_1.htmlPhelsuma antanosy grow to approximately 4 inches. These critically endangered geckos only live in three small, coastal forests on the southeastern portion of Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_antanosy_1.htmlPhelsuma is a highly terrestrial species of gecko that lives above the tree line in the Ankaratra and Andingitra mountains. This habitat’s temperature can range from below freezing to 86 degrees Fahrenheit. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_barbouri_1.htmlPhelsuma lives in a coastal forest habitat where the humidity can easily rise to 100%. They live on the Ravanela madagascariensis plant where they retreat into the hollow leaves when they feel threatened. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_berghofi_1.htmlPhelsuma breviceps survives in the dry deserts of Southwestern Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_breviceps_1.htmlPhelsuma dubia grow to 6 inches in length and inhabit the West coast of Madagascar in a wide variety of ecosystems. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_dubia_1.htmlPhelsuma flavigularis lives in the Andisabe region at altitudes ranging from 900 and 1100 meters. The temperature in the region can vary from the upper 50’s to 70 degrees on the Fahrenheit scale with a humidity of approximately 95%. The Speckled day gecko is an arboreal species of gecko that lives in the rainforests of Madagascar. They reach a length of approximately 5 inches. Phelsuma kely is an arboreal gecko that reaches a length of approximately 2.7 inches. Phelsuma klemmeri inhabit the bamboo forests of Northwestern Madagascar and reach a length of approximately 3.5 inches. http://www.phelsumaweb.com/eng/klemmeri_care.htmlPhelsuma laticauda angularis is an arboreal gecko species that inhabits Northwestern Madagascar in the Antsohihi region. An arboreal species of gecko that typically lives on banana trees, palms, and bamboo at the Northern portion of Madagascar. They can grow to approximately 5 inches in length. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_laticauda_laticauda_1.htmlPhelsuma lineata bombetokensis grows to approximately 4 inches in length. This subspecies inhabits newly planted vegetation such as palms in Northern Madagascar due to complete destruction of its habitat. Phelsuma lineata dorsivittata grows to approximately 5 inches in length. This subspecies lives in Northern Madagascar on broadleaf trees and on homes. Phelsuma lineata elanthana inhabits the Central-Eastern portion of Madagascar. http://www.xs4all.nl/~phelsuma/Species/lineataelanthana.htmPhelsuma lineata lineata inhabits the east coast of Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_lineata_lineata_1.htmlPhelsuma lineata punctulata inhabit the mountain ecosystems in Northern Madagascar. They can grow to a length of approximately 5 inches. This arboreal species inhabits the rainforests of Eastern Madagascar. This species can grow to about 8.5 inches in length. http://www.fact-index.com/b/bo/boehme_s_giant_day_geckko.htmlThe Madagascar giant day gecko is an arboreal species that lives primarily on trees in high humidity environments. This species grows to approximately 11 inches in length. Koch’s giant day gecko is an arboreal species of Northwest and Western Madagascar. This species can comfortably live in a dry climate where the temperature can reach 104 degrees Fahrenheit. The Madagascar day gecko is an arboreal species that is endemic to the rainforests of East Madagascar. This species can grow to about 8.5 inches in length. Phelsuma malamakibo is a terrestrial species that inhabits the evergreen rainforests, montane grassland, and heathland of Southern Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_malamakibo_1.htmlPhelsuma masohoala inhabits Eastern and Northeastern Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_masohoala_1.htmlPhelsuma modesta inhabit Southern and Western Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_modesta_1.htmlPhelsuma mutabilis inhabit Southern and Eastern Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_mutabilis_1.htmlPhelsuma pronki is an arboreal species of gecko that inhabits the rainforests of Central Madagascar. Phelsuma pusilla hallmanni is an arboreal species that inhabits Eastern Madagascar. Phelsuma pusilla pusilla is an arboreal gecko that inhabits Eastern Madagascar. It grows to approximately 3 inches. Phelsuma quadriocellata bimaculata is an arboreal species of gecko that inhabits Eastern Madagascar and grows to 4.5 inches. Phelsuma quadriocellata lepida is a species of gecko that lives in the rainforests of Northeastern Madagascar up to a maximum elevation of 1200 meters. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_quadriocellata_lepida_1.htmlPhelsuma quadriocellata parva is an arboreal species of gecko that inhabits the Northeastern region of Madagascar. They can grow to a length of 3.5 inches and commonly live in coconut palms, banana plants, and residential areas. The Four Spot Day Gecko inhabits the inland rainforests along the eastern side of Madagascar. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_quadriocellata_quadriocellata_1.htmlSeipp’s day gecko is an arboreal species that inhabits the rainforests of North Madagascar. It has the peculiar habit for a reptile of avoiding sunlight. The Flat-tailed day gecko is an arboreal species that inhabits the rainforests of Eastern Madagascar. The males can grow to a maximum length of 6 inches. Phelsuma standingi is an arboreal species that inhabits the dry thorn forests of Southwestern Madagascar. They can grow to a maximum length of 1 foot, however, individuals ranging between 8 and 10.5 inches are more common. http://www.gekkota.com/html/phelsuma_standingi.htmlPhelsuma vanheygeni only inhabits the bamboo forest on the Ampasindava peninsula of Madagascar and often rests on the stalks of the bamboo. This species grows to approximately 3 inches in length. http://www.phelsumania.com/public/systematics/species/phelsuma_vanheygeni_1.html

Uroplatus is genus of geckos ranging in size from 4” to 12”. These geckos are camouflaged by coloration, patterns, as well as structures on their bodies in order to resemble their habitat and camouflage themselves almost completely. Uroplatus geckos require an approximate humidity of 80% and an average temperature between 70 and 80 degrees Fahrenheit. Many Uroplatus species are arboreal, however Uroplatus ebenaui and Uroplatus phantasticus live in the foliage near the ground.http://www.gherp.com/gherp/pages/uroplatus.htmThe Spearpoint leaf-tailed gecko’s specific camouflage is designed to mimic a dried leaf. They occur in the Eastern rainforest belt of Madagascar http://www.naturalia.org/zoo/RETTILI/e_128.html and must have a habitat with a temperature of 60-70 degrees Fahrenheit and 80%-100% humidity. http://www.amphibiancare.com/frogs/caresheets/spearpointleaftailedgecko.htmlThis nocturnal species of gecko lives along the entire east-coast of Madagascar. It requires regions with a humidity between 70% and 100%, a temperature of at least 22 degrees Celsius and up to 30 degrees Celsius. Uroplatus guentheri is an arboreal species that occurs in Northwestern and Western Madagascar and can grow to 6 inches. This species inhabits the humid rainforests of Northern Madagascar. http://whozoo.org/Intro2001/rolabote/RB_gecko.htm They typically grow to a length between 10 and 12 inches. http://www.scz.org/animals/g/henkel.htmlUroplatus lineatus inhabits the bamboo forests of Northeast Madagascar and typically grow to 10 inches in length. http://www.faunaimportuk.com/caresheets/csleaftail.htmUroplatus malahelo was discovered in the Malahelo forest of Southeastern Madagascar in 1992, however, it may be extinct due to only 2 specimens being discovered. http://www.unusualdestinations.com/madagascar/articles/news-articles/article/1256/madagascars.htmlhttp://www.endangeredspecieshandbook.org/madagascar_biological_reptiles3.phpUroplatus malama was discovered in a low-montane forest, however only one specimen is known to exist and this species may be extinct. http://www.unusualdestinations.com/madagascar/articles/news-articles/article/1256/madagascars.htmlUroplatus phantasticus occurs in Eastern Madagascar [www.cites.org/eng/cop/13/prop/E13-P27.pdf]and typically grows from 5 to 6 inches in length. In order to survive, their habitat must be between 65 and 80 degrees Fahrenheit at the extremes, but an average temperature between 70 and 75 degrees must also be present as well as a humidity between 75% and 90%, although a humidity between 80% and 90% is more inhabitable. http://www.gekkota.com/html/u_phantasticus.htmlUroplatus sikorae is an arboreal gecko that occurs in the rainforest belt of Eastern Madagascar. http://www.naturalia.org/ZOO/RETTILI/e_129.html This species can grow to approximately 7 inches in length and has the feature of flaps on the underside of its head in order to blur its outline when pressed against a tree to hide from predators more effectively. http://info.bio.sunysb.edu/rano.biodiv/Reptiles/Uroplatus-sikorae/http://www.wildmadagascar.org/wildlife/geckos.html