

Skopje Fest (Macedonian: Скопје Фест) or Festival na zabavni melodii Skopje (Фестивал на забавни мелодии Скопје) is one of the main musical events in the Republic of Macedonia. 

SkopjeFest began in 1968 in the Universal Hall in Skopje, and continued until 1980. After Macedonia gained its independence peacefully from Yugoslavia in 1991, SkopjeFest was revived, and has since taken over from Makfest as Macedonia's premier music festival. 

It has also been used as the Macedonian national selections for the Eurovision Song Contest, in the appropriate years. The show involves some of Macedonia's finest performers, singing original tracks submitted to MRT (Makedonska Radio Televizija). The first Macedonian representative in Eurovision, was Macedonian singer Vlado Janevski who won SkopjeFest 1998 with the song "Ne Zori Zoro", for the Eurovision Song Contest 1998. This was Macedonia's first participation in the Eurovision Song Contest. Ever since, SkopjeFest has been shadowed by many controversial debates regarding the strategies behind the song selections and the lack of transparence concerning the winner. Such allegations are not new to this contest, however they intensified as the Eurovision participation became a factor. After the decision to make SkopjeFest the National Pre-Selection round for Macedonia's representative to Eurovision, the traditional point award ceremony was eliminated and replaced by the announcement of only the Top 3 places. Neither the points of the jury nor the televoting results are made public.

Up until 2002, SkopjeFest used to be the biggest musical activity in the country, however it faced financial problems. In 2003, the festival wasn't held in order to save money for the next year when Macedonia was going to particate in the Eurovision Song Contest. In the meantime, MRT made new criteria for the national selection for the Eurovision Song Contest, the festival returned in 2004 only to celebrate the 60th aniversary of MRT. After that, financial problems increased and it wasn't organised until 2008, again as a ESC national final.

A selection of winners and participants in SkopjeFest:





MKRTV choose 6 singers to compete in the National Final Skopjefest. Then they reduced for 2 singers. The top 5 singers that were nominated were:



The top 2 however were Martin Vučić and Aleksandra Pileva. In the first round the best song of each singer was chosen before the winner was chosen in the second round. Aleksandra won the televote in both rounds, while Martin won the "expert" jury &amp; audience votes.









