France-China relations, also known as Sino-French relations or Franco-Chinese relations, refers to the interstate relations between China and France (Kingdom or later).

Note that the meaning of both "China" and "France" as entities has changed throughout history; this article will discuss what was commonly considered 'France' and 'China' at the time of the relationships in question.  There have been many political, cultural and economic relationships between China and France.

Main article: Jesuit China missionsNumerous French Jesuits were active in China during the 17th and 18th century: Nicolas Trigault (1577-1629), Alexander de Rhodes (1591-1660, active in Vietnam), Jean-Baptiste Régis (1663-1738), Jean Denis Attiret (1702-1768), Michel Benoist (1715-1774), Joseph-Marie Amiot (1718-1793).

French Jesuits pressured the French king to send them to China with the aims of counterbalancing the influence of Ottoman Empire in Europe. The Jesuits sent by Louis XIV were: Jean de Fontaney (1643-1710), Joachim Bouvet(1656-1730), Jean-François Gerbillon (1654-1707), Louis Le Comte (1655-1728) and Claude de Visdelou (1656-1737)). Returning to France, they noticed the similarity between Louis XIV of France and the Emperor Kangxi. Both were said to be the God servitor, and to control their respective area: France being the strongest country of Europe, and China being the strongest power in East Asia. Other biographical factors lead commentators to proclaim that Louis XIV and Kangxi were protected by the same Angel. (In childhood, they overcame the same illness; both reigned for a long time, with many conquests.)

Under Louis XIV's reign, the work of these French researchers sent by the King had a notable influence on Chinese sciences, but continued to be mere intellectual games, and not tools to improve the power of man on nature. Conversely, China was fashionable in France, examplified by the Chinoiserie fashion, and Louis XIV had the Trianon de Porcelaine built in Chinese style in 1670.

In the same time, the first ever know Chinese people came to the French Kingdom. Michel Sin went to Versaille in 1684 before continuing to England. More notable is Arcadio Huang, who cross the Kingdom in 1702, spend some time in Rome (for the Rites dispute), and came back to Paris in 1704, where he was the "Chinese interprete of the King", and died in 1716.  He started the first ever Chinese-French dictionary, and a Chinese grammar to help French and European researchers to understand and study Chinese, but died before finishing his work.

In the 18th century, the French Jesuit Michel Benoist, together with Giuseppe Castiglione, helped the Qianlong Emperor build a European-style area in Old Summer Palace (often associated with the European-style palaces (Xi Yang Lou) built of stone), to satisfy his taste for exotic buildings and objects. Jean Denis Attiret became "Painter to the Emperor" Qianlong. Joseph-Marie Amiot (1718-1793) also won the confidence of the Qianlong Emperor and spent the remainder of his life at Beijing. He was official translator of Western languages for Emperor Qianlong, and the spiritual leader of the French mission in Peking.

In 1844, China and France concluded its first modern treaty, the Treaty of Whampoa.

In 1860, the Summer Palace was ransacked by French units. Many precious objects nowaday in French museums come from this looting.

Second Opium War,Sino-French War, and French Indochina, Eight-Nation Alliance.

France and the PRC had established ambassadorial level diplomatic relations by 1964, before either Great Britain and Germany did so with China.  This was precipitated by Charles de Gaulle's official recognition of the People's Republic of China. Deng Xiaoping completed his studies in Paris prior to ascending to power in China.

This state of relations would not last, however. During the 1990's, France and the PRC repeatedly clashed as a result of the PRC's One China Policy. France sold weapons to Taiwan, angering the Beijing government. This resulted in the temporary closure of the French Consulate-General in Guangzhou. France eventually agreed to prohibit local companies from selling arms to Taiwan, and diplomatic relations resumed in 1994.

Since then, the two countries have exchanged a number of state visits. Today, Sino-French relations are primarily economic. Bilateral trade reached new high levels in 2000. Cultural ties between the two countries are less well represented, though France is making an effort to improve this disparity.

In 2008, Sino-French relations entered a brief period of uncertainty after widespread pro-human rights and pro-Tibet protests in Paris during the Olympic torch's relay through the French capital. Chinese media reported on the protests, provoking an angry, anti-French response by people in China. The Chinese government hinted that Sino-French friendship could be affected. A call to boycott French hypermart Carrefour from 1 May began spreading through mobile text messaging and online chat rooms amongst the Chinese over the weekend from 12 April, accusing the company's major shareholder, the LVMH Group, of donating funds to the Dalai Lama. There were also calls to extend the boycott to include French luxury goods and cosmetic products. Chinese protesters organized boycotts of the French-owned retail chain Carrefour in major Chinese cities including Kunming, Hefei and Wuhan, accusing the French nation of pro-secessionist conspiracy and anti-Chinese racism. Some burned the French flag and spread short online messages calling for large protests in front of French consulates and embassy. Some shoppers who insisted on entering one of the Carrefour stores in Kunming were blocked by boycotters wielding large Chinese flags and hit by water bottles. Hundreds of people joined anti-French rallies in Beijing, Wuhan, Hefei, Kunming and Qingdao, which quickly spread to other cities like Xian, Harbin and Jinan.

In response to the demonstrations, the Chinese government attempted to calm the situation. State media and commentaries began to call for calm, such as an editorial in the People's Daily which urged Chinese people to "express [their] patriotic enthusiasm calmly and rationally, and express patriotic aspiration in an orderly and legal manner". The government also began to patrol and censor the internet forums such as Sohu.com, with comments related to the Carrefour boycott removed. In the days prior to the planned boycott, evidence of efforts by Chinese authorities to choke the mass boycott's efforts online became even more evident, including barring searches of words related to the French protests, but protests broke out nonetheless in front of Carrefour's stores at Beijing, Changsha, Fuzhou and Shenyang on 1 May. The French authorities also attempted to secure good relations with China in response to the incidents. French President Nicolas Sarkozy wrote a letter of support and sympathy to Jin Jing, a Chinese athlete who had carried the Olympic torch in Paris; the letter was delivered in person by the President of the French Senate, Christian Poncelet. The Chinese State media agency Xinhua reported that Jin had received the letter by saying she "hope[d] to contribute her own efforts to cementing the Sino-France friendship". Chinese President Hu Jintao sent a special envoy to France to help strengthen relations and declared that "China was attached to a policy of Franco-Chinese friendship". Interviewed on French television, the Chinese ambassador to France re-iterated that China and France were "friends".

According to survey from Sina.com, nearly 90% of Chinese surveyee claim that Sarkozy is not welcomed at Beijing Olympics.http://www.news.com.au/heraldsun/story/0,21985,23957742-5005961,00.html



The China Quarterly  (2002), 169: 33-44 Cambridge University PressCopyright © The China Quarterly, 2002doi:10.1017/S0009443902000049Published online by Cambridge University Press 25Apr2002





