

This is a list of various fictional and recurring characters who appear in the Mario series of video games created by Nintendo, as well as spin-off media, such as books, comics, and animated series. 

__TOC__

Main article: MarioMario is a fictional character created by game designer Shigeru Miyamoto. Serving as Nintendo's mascot, Mario is arguably the most recognizable video game character of all time, and he has appeared in over 200 video games since his creation. Though originally only appearing in platforming games (starting with Donkey Kong), currently Mario appears in many game genres, such as racing games (i.e., Mario Kart), puzzle games, role-playing games, fighting games (Super Smash Bros.), sports games (Mario Superstar Baseball), and many others.

Mario is depicted as a short, pudgy, Italian plumber who lives in the Mushroom Kingdom, where he is regarded as a hero; he often must thwart the evil King Bowser's plans to kidnap Princess Peach and subjugate the Mushroom Kingdom.  

Main article: LuigiLuigi (ルイージ, Ruīji?) is a video game character created by Nintendo game designer Shigeru Miyamoto. He is portrayed as the younger brother of Nintendo's official mascot, Mario. Luigi first appeared in the arcade game Mario Bros., where he was featured as a main character alongside Mario. Since his debut, Luigi has appeared in many games in the Mario series, often accompanying Mario as the central protagonist, but has starred as the main character of his own game, Luigi's Mansion. In most games of the main series, Luigi is playable, occasionally as a secret revealed in-game or an unlockable character.

Main article: Princess PeachPrincess Peach is a video game character in Nintendo's Mario video games series, often playing the "damsel in distress" role in the adventure series. Peach is the beautiful human princess of the fictitious Mushroom Kingdom, and was formerly known as Princess Toadstool in the West until the Nintendo 64 era. She is the oldest female video game character still in use.. In Super Paper Mario, she has an alter ego called Shadow Queen.

Princess Daisy (デイジー姫, Deijī-hime) is the princess of Sarasaland. Daisy's debut appearance was in 1989 in Super Mario Land, where she was kidnapped by the tyrannical alien Tatanga, who planned to marry her and rule over her kingdom. Daisy appeared later in NES Open Tournament Golf as Luigi's caddy. After a long hiatus, Daisy made her return in the game Mario Tennis, after which she began making recurring appearances in Mario sports and party games. Daisy is best friends with Princess Peach, and is also rumored (among the characters of the Mario universe) to be in a romantic relationship with Luigi. As of Mario Kart Wii, this relationship seems to have been made canon, with statues on the Daisy Circuit course depicting the two characters dancing with each other. She also appears in both Mario Kart DS and Mario Kart Wii as an unlockable character. The infant version of herself, Baby Daisy, debuted in Mario Kart Wii and appears in Mario Super Sluggers.

Daisy's first voice actress was Kate Fleming in Mario Tennis for the Nintendo 64. Daisy's next voice actress was Jen Taylor, who provided her voice in Mario Party 3, Mario Party 4, and Mario Party 5. In every other game, Daisy has been and is currently voiced by Deanna Mustard. Outside of the video games, Daisy appears as one of the main characters in the Super Mario Bros. 1993 film, played by Samantha Mathis.  She also appears in the comic books.

Main article: Donkey Kong (character)Donkey Kong is a fictional ape who first appeared in Nintendo's popular 1981 video game Donkey Kong. Donkey Kong, along with two other characters, was created by game designer Shigeru Miyamoto, as an original property of Nintendo once their licensing of Popeye fell through. The three characters were supposed to mirror the love triangle that exists in the Popeye comics. Donkey Kong was cast as the antagonist, with the creator explaining that a gorilla is not "too evil or repulsive". Miyamoto believed "donkey" meant "stupid" in English, and assumed the name Donkey Kong would convey the sense "stupid ape" to an American audience. When he suggested this name to Nintendo of America, he was laughed at, but the name stuck.

Donkey Kong Jr. is the son of Donkey Kong.  He was introduced in Donkey Kong Jr., in which he was the protagonist and had to save his father from Mario. Donkey Kong Jr. also appeared in Donkey Kong 2, Donkey Kong Jr. Math, and Donkey Kong Classics as the main character. In Donkey Kong '94, Donkey Kong Jr. appears as an obstacle throughout the game, attempting to impede Mario in his progress by pulling levers and throwing poison mushrooms at him. Donkey Kong Jr. also appears in Super Mario Kart and as an unlockable character in Mario Tennis.  Shortly after the release of Donkey Kong 64, a representative from Rare stated that the current Donkey Kong is a grown version of Junior,  while the Donkey Kong Sr. of previous games appears in more recent games as the elderly Cranky Kong. Nintendo has never given an official stance on Donkey Kong's heritage.

Donkey Kong Jr. is also featured as a major character in the 1982 cartoon series Saturday Supercade, which has him searching for his runaway father, who was being chased by Mario and Pauline.

Professor Elvin Gadd (Professor Oya Mā (オヤ・マー博士, Oya Mā Hakase) in Japan), more commonly known as E. Gadd, is a scientist who, with his various inventions, helps Mario and his friends. In Japan, he is named after Nintendo game designer Yoshiyuki Oyama. He first appears in Luigi's Mansion, in which he investigates the mansion that mysteriously appeared by his house. To help him study the ghosts in the mansion, he uses the "Poltergust 3000," an invention that can capture ghosts, and the "Game Boy Horror," an invention for tracking and detecting objects. He lends it to Luigi, and helps him on his quest. Other major inventions include his FLUDD--a Flash Liquidizer Ultra Dousing Device--and Magic Brush used in Super Mario Sunshine. In Mario Party 6, E. Gadd is featured on a party board called E. Gadd's Garage. He later appears in  where he creates a time-traveling machine. He also makes brief appearances in  with various inventions as rewards for making bean coffees at the Starbean Cafe.

Pauline (ポリーン, Porīn) is the woman whom Mario must rescue from Donkey Kong in the original Donkey Kong. In the same way Mario was originally called "Jumpman," Pauline was simply referred to as Lady (レディ, Redi) in Japan. It was during the game's distribution in North America that she was given the name Pauline after Polly James, the wife of Nintendo of America's warehouse manager, Don James. Pauline later appeared in Family Basic and in Pinball for the Nintendo Entertainment System. Princess Peach, who was introduced in Super Mario Bros., took Pauline's place as damsel-in-distress in that game, eventually becoming Mario's primary romantic interest in most of the subsequent games in the series.

Pauline did not appear in another game until the 1994 Game Boy version of Donkey Kong, where she was once again taken captive by Donkey Kong and his son. Whereas the original arcade game's cabinet depicts Pauline with blond hair, the Game Boy remake features a redesigned modern Pauline as a brunette, distinguishing her from the blond-haired Peach, wearing a red dress with a torn skirt. This version of Pauline makes an appearance in  for the Nintendo DS, where she appears as the guest of honor in the opening of the Super Mini-Mario World theme park.

 Poochy is a dog-like creature that first appears in , where he could be found in few levels and could be ridden by Yoshi over spikes and into enemies, who are instantly destroyed upon touching Poochy. In Tetris Attack, Poochy is among the denizens of Yoshi's Island who are brainwashed by Bowser and Kamek; Yoshi must defeat Poochy in battle to free him from this brainwashing. In Yoshi's Story, Poochy appears in some levels, but is smaller and can not be ridden, and can only be used to sniff for buried treasures.

Rosalina (Rosetta (ロゼッタ, Rosetta) in Japan) is the enigmatic princess who first appeared in Super Mario Galaxy. She runs the spaceship called the Comet Observatory, where she lives with star-like beings called Lumas. She agrees to help Mario find Princess Peach who was kidnapped by Bowser. Her first appearance outside of Super Mario Galaxy was in Mario Kart Wii as a secret racer in the Heavy class. In both titles, she is voiced by Mercedes Rose.

Main article: Toad (Nintendo)Toad (Kinopio in Japan), is a humanoid mushroom that is both a single character and the collective name of the "Mushroom People" found in the Mushroom Kingdom. The Toad species first appeared in Super Mario Bros. as seven guards that serve Princess Peach, called Mushroom Retainers. Toad's voice is first heard in Mario Kart 64, in which he is voiced by Isaac Marshall. Jen Taylor provided the voice of Toad until 2005, when Kelsey Hutchison took over for games such as Super Mario Strikers. Recently, Nicole Mills voiced him in Mario Party 8. 

Toad first appeared as a single character in Super Mario Bros. 2 as one of the four playable characters. He is stated to be the chief guard of the "Mushroom Retainers." The character then went on to star in Wario's Woods, and he appears in the Mario Kart series and various sports games. In other games, he acts as an instructor, such as in the earlier Mario Party games, and he helps guide characters in other games. As with the games, Toad plays a major supporting character in other forms of media starring Mario. He usually tags along with Mario in the various cartoons and comics as a sidekick. In Super Smash Bros. Melee and Super Smash Bros. Brawl, Princess Peach uses Toad as a shield. Toad had been best friends with Mario and Luigi for a long time. In Mario Party games before Mario Party 5, Toad was the host of the parties.

Toadette (キノピコ, Kinopiko) is a female Toad who appears as a playable character in various Mario spin-off games. She first appeared as Toad's partner in  as a hidden character, and later appeared in  as an instructor when Mario received upgraded boots and hammers. Since Mario Party 6 she has made regular appearances in the Mario Party series as a playable character, with the exception of the handheld games, where she acts as a NPC. The official Mario Kart Wii guide suggests that she is Toad's sister.

Other playable appearances include Mario Superstar Baseball and Mario Kart Wii; in both titles, she must be unlocked. She is voiced by Jen Taylor in most of her appearances, however in Mario Party 8, she is voiced by Nicole Mills. She appeared in  as the owner of a hotel Mario and Toad must rebuild, she is voiced by Jennifer Hale in this game. She also made a cameo appearance in the beginning of Super Mario Galaxy.

Toadsworth (キノじい, Kinojii), voiced by Charles Martinet, is an elderly Toad steward of Princess Peach who has taken care of Peach since she was a toddler. He first appears in Super Mario Sunshine, where he travels to Isle Delfino with Mario, Princess Peach and an entourage of Toads. He has a very minor appearance in . He plays similar supporting roles in , , and Mario Party 7. He makes his first appearance as a playable character in Mario Superstar Baseball, and returned in Mario Super Sluggers. Toadsworth was the host of Mario Party 7.

Main article: YoshiYoshi (ヨッシー, Yosshī?, sometimes romanized Yossy in earlier Japanese language materials) is a fictional dinosaur-like creature. His debut was in Super Mario World on the Super Nintendo Entertainment System. He later had his own series with several platform and puzzle games, including . He has also appeared in many of the spin-off Mario games, such as the Mario Party, the Mario Kart series as well as in other various Mario sports titles.

Main article: List of Mario series enemies=== Birdo ===Birdo, known in Japan as Catherine (キャサリン, Kyasarin), is an enemy to Mario  and playable character in various games. Birdo first appeared in the Japanese game  and the remade Super Mario Bros. 2 as a recurring boss. Birdo later appeared in Wario's Woods as an ally of Toad,  as a boss character, and in Mario &amp; Luigi: Superstar Saga, as a boss paired with the thief Popple. Birdo made its first playable appearance in the Nintendo 64 installment of Mario Tennis, as Yoshi's partner. Since then, Birdo appears as a playable character in several Mario sports titles and in the Mario Party and Mario Kart series. 

Birdo's gender has changed throughout various American game versions, but has always been male in Japan. In the original manual for Super Mario Bros. 2, Birdo is referred to as male that believes he is female, and would liked to be called Birdetta. Most later American-localized games, such as the Mario sports titles, which have featured Birdo with a diamond ring, have usually listed Birdo as a female. Recent localizations have avoided the use of any gender pronouns when describing Birdo. In Super Smash Bros. Brawl, it is said that Birdo is of "indeterminate gender" in its trophy.

In addition, the trailer for the Wii game Captain Rainbow is narrated by Birdo using a distinctly male voice. However, reviews have stated that part of the plot surrounding the Birdo character is gender related and involves proving its womanhood.

King Boo (キングテレサ, Kingu Teresa, King Teresa) first appears as the final boss of Luigi's Mansion and plays minor roles in various other Mario games, including the Mario Kart and Mario Party series. King Boo is a member of the Boo species, though he is larger than the average Boo and dons a crown, with a large ruby in Luigi's Mansion, and a regular crown in subsequent appearances, on his head. It is well distinguished by its green eyes, blue tongue and unique evil laugh. As well as appearing as the main antagonist of Luigi's Mansion, King Boo also appears as a boss in Super Mario Sunshine, Mario Kart DS, and Super Princess Peach.

Main article: Bowser (Nintendo)Bowser, also known as King Koopa, is a video game character and the primary antagonist of Nintendo's Mario series. In Japan, he is called Koopa (クッパ, Kuppa).

Bowser is Mario's archnemesis. He is the leader and most powerful of the turtle-like Koopa race. Although Bowser has joined forces with Mario in a few games, he is considered an antagonist due to his ambition to kidnap Princess Peach and conquer the Mushroom Kingdom.

Bowser Jr. (クッパJr., Kuppa Junia, Koopa Jr.) is the eighth and youngest child of Bowser. He debuted in Super Mario Sunshine.  He acts as the main antagonist of both Super Mario Sunshine and New Super Mario Bros., with his father only playing a minor role in each. In Super Mario Sunshine, he uses a magic paintbrush, invented by Professor E. Gadd, and a special kerchief to transform into a translucent blue doppelgänger of Mario, Shadow Mario, who vandalizes Isle Delfino with graffiti, tricking the native people into believing that Mario himself is to blame. In New Super Mario Bros, he kidnaps Princess Peach, dragging her off to a new castle each time his old one is defeated. Additionally, he appears in Super Mario Galaxy, acting as his father's right hand and challenging Mario at several points of the game to impede him. He also has been appearing in Mario sports games as a playable character ever since Super Mario Sunshine.

Bowser Jr. shares many physical similarities with his father.  Unlike his father, though, he is about the same size as Mario, and has small black beady eyes, a more rounded snout, and a single sharp tooth visible in his mouth. He wears a kerchief that shows a set of sharp teeth.

Clawgrip, known as Chokkī (チョッキー, Chokkī) in Japan, is an enemy boss character that appears in Super Mario Bros. 2. He is a giant crab monster that throws large rocks. It lives in a giant tree awaiting the arrival of Mario and his friends. In Super Mario Advance, he is voiced by Charles Martinet. Clawgrip made a few appearances in The Super Mario Bros. Super Show!, while several Clawgrips also appeared in the comics published by Nintendo Comics System.  In the NES and SNES versions of Super Mario Bros. 2, his name is misspelled "Clawglip"; however, he is correctly called "Clawgrip" in the Game Boy Advance version.

A reincarnation of Bowser first appearing in New Super Mario Bros. where he played as one of the two final bosses in World 8.  He is shown with the likeness of a Dry Bones, being a complete skeleton, but also has red hair and a black and red shell with spikes on top.  Dry Bowser throws parts of his own body as weapons.  He later appears in Mario Kart Wii as a playable character after receiving at least one star on each of the 150cc "Wii Cups". Dry Bowser has a voice in the Mario Kart game, using a more fearsome roar than Bowser along with bone cracking noises.

Foreman Spike, known as Blackey (ブラッキー, Burakkī) in Japan, is the main antagonist of the game Wrecking Crew during both regular gameplay and bonus levels and Wrecking Crew '98 after being hired by Bowser to build him a new castle. Foreman Spike also appears as an unlockable character in Mobile Golf. He depicted as an obese, bearded and corrupt construction worker, whose face is obscured by his sunglasses.

Fryguy, known as Hībōbō (ヒーボーボー, Hībōbō) in Japan, is an enemy character that appears in Super Mario Bros. 2. Fryguy is essentially a giant living fireball, given life by Wart, that spews smaller fireballs when it is angry. He, along with Mouser, Tryclyde, and Clawgrip, is one of the boss characters that appear at the end of each world in Super Mario Bros. 2.

Gooper Blooper is a giant variation of the Blooper. It has appeared as a boss in Super Mario Sunshine and Super Princess Peach. It has also appeared in Mario Power Tennis, Mario Hoops 3-on-3, and Mario Super Sluggers. It can commonly be seen with a cork in its tube-like snout; it has eight tentacles with large bulges, similar to suction cups; and it has a large arrow-shaped head with white skin and blue spots.

Kamek (カメック, Kamekku) is a Magikoopa who acts as Bowser's caretaker during Bowser's childhood and one of his high-ranking minions afterwards. Kamek can perform various feats of magic, such as self-duplication, teleportation, shooting magical blasts and changing the size of other creatures. He first appears as the main antagonist of , which has him trying to abduct Baby Mario and Baby Luigi, who he foresees as causing trouble for the Koopas in the future. Succeeding in only capturing Baby Luigi, Kamek and his minions, the Toadies, try to steal Baby Mario from the Yoshis throughout the game; before every boss battle, Kamek will appear and change an enemy creature into a giant, or perform some magical feat, and make them fight a Yoshi.

After his appearance in Super Mario World 2: Yoshi's Island, Kamek appears in several other games, such as Tetris Attack, which features him as the penultimate boss and the one who brainwashed the inhabitants of Yoshi's Island; Super Princess Peach as a boss character;  as Baby Bowser's sidekick.Yoshi Touch and Go, where he kidnaps the babies once again; and as a main antagonist in Yoshi's Island DS. Kamek also appears throughout the Mario Party series, most commonly as an orb summon and or a boss.

Koopa Kids (Mini-Bowsers in PAL regions) are minions of Bowser that appear in the Mario Party series. They do his general bidding, interrupting the players as they traverse the game boards. In Mario Party 5 and Mario Party 6, the main one became a playable character, although they do not appear in Mario Party 8 or Mario Party DS.

Mario Party 5 introduced three differently-colored Koopa Kids: Red Koopa Kid, Green Koopa Kid, and Blue Koopa Kid. They have been around in the Mario Party series ever since. While these three can compete with the player in mini-games in Mario Party 6, only the original Koopa Kid has ever been playable. The coloured Koopa Kids continue to make appearances in Bowser mini-games in Mario Party 7 and Mario Party Advance.

Koopaling (コクッパ, Ko Kuppa) is the generic title given to the seven children of King Bowser who help him in various games. They first appeared in Super Mario Bros. 3. Each Koopaling was a boss at the end of one of the game’s seven kingdoms. The Koopalings are also world bosses in Super Mario World, Mario is Missing!, Yoshi's Safari, and Hotel Mario. In , however, they are mini-bosses in Bowser's Castle. They are made up of Larry Koopa, Morton Koopa Jr., Wendy O. Koopa, Iggy Koopa, Roy Koopa, Lemmy Koopa , and Ludwig von Koopa, from youngest to oldest.. Most of the Koopalings have wild punk hairstyles and are named after musicians. It is said that each Koopaling was personally designed by a different member of the production staff of Super Mario Bros. 3, which Shigeru Miyamoto explains is a way to honor the creators of the games personally.  

In the Mario cartoons by DiC, the original seven Koopalings are given different names based on their given personalities. They are called Cheatsy Koopa, Big Mouth Koopa, Kootie Pie Koopa, Hop Koopa, Bully Koopa, Hip Koopa, and Kooky von Koopa. Aside from their names and personalities, they look slightly different and serve Bowser differently, compared to their video game counterparts. Instead of acting as minions, they act directly as his children, and do things such as seek his attention, and even plot against him. They also appear in the Mario anime, Nintendo Adventure Books, and comic books.

Mouser, Don Churuge (ドン・チュルゲ, Don Churuge) in Japan, is one of Wart's generals featured as in Super Mario Bros. 2 and . His strategy is to throw bombs at his opponents. Mouser is also a major character in The Super Mario Bros. Super Show!, which casts him as King Koopa's second-in-command and a member of the Koopa Pack. John Stocker provided the voice for Mouser, who spoke with a German accent in the series. He also appears in the Super Mario Bros. comic books as a king corrupted by Bowser, whose now-leaderless subjects now steal vegetables for food. He is voiced by Charles Martinet in Super Mario Advance.

Petey Piranha, known as Boss Packun (ボスパックン, Bosu Pakkun) in Japan, first appears as the primary boss of Bianco Hills in Super Mario Sunshine. He has appeared as a boss in later games as well such as in Super Princess Peach, , New Super Mario Bros., and Super Smash Bros. Brawl. He also acts as a playable character in spin-off Mario games like Mario sports games and in Mario Kart Double Dash!!. A dinosaur-like version of him also appears as the first episode boss in Super Mario Galaxy.

Petey is a larger, much more powerful version of a Piranha Plant, which is the result of mutation. Whereas normal Piranha Plants usually grow from pipes, Petey's leaves and roots have grown into foot-like and arm-like appendages. He can also use his leaves to fly around in the air. Furthermore, Petey sports a pair of white-spotted red briefs. Although Petey does not speak, he does make some growling, drooling and licking noises, which translate into actual speech. Petey frequently vomits out mud-like Earth Goop, a substance similar to that of Shadow Mario's Paintbrush, which can make the ground slippery and sometimes generate more goop-based monsters.

Raphael the Raven, also known as Raphael Raven, is large version of the Raven species of enemies in the Yoshi series. He first appears in  as the boss character, who is a regular Raven enlarged by Kamek. He also appears in Tetris Attack as a boss that must be rescued from Kamek's spell, and Paper Mario as a leader of tribe of Ravens on Lavalava island.

Tryclyde, Gabucho (ガブチョ, Gabucho) in Japan, is an enemy character that appears in Super Mario Bros. 2. Tryclyde is a large red or green serpent with three heads and the ability to breathe fire. Tryclyde serves as Wart's lackey, and was apparently an outsider before Wart took him in due to his cunning and evil nature. He was also a semi-regularly recurring villain in the animated series The Super Mario Bros. Super Show and a member of the semi-competent Koopa Pack. He was voiced by Harvey Atkin in the television show and by Charles Martinet in Super Mario Advance.

Tatanga the Mysterious Spaceman (宇宙怪人タタンガ, Uchū Kaijin Tatanga) appears as the final boss in Super Mario Land, where he kidnaps Princess Daisy of Sarasaland. He fights in a war robot called Pagosu (パゴス, Pagosu) while Mario attempts to shoot him down from his Sky Pop airplane. Tatanga also appears in  as the guardian of the Space Zone coin. Since then, Tatanga has remained largely obscure. Tatanga also appeared in the Game Boy comic books, published by Valiant as part of the Nintendo Comics System in 1990. There, in addition to an obvious change in his appearance, he had taken control of an estranged human from New Jersey by the name of Herman Smirch.

Waluigi (ワルイージ, Waruīji) was created by Fumihide Aoki and is voiced by Charles Martinet.  He has so far only appeared in spin-off titles, sport games and party games, as opposed to the main platformer titles, but his costume is wearable in one of the Paper Mario games.  He is the same age as  Luigi and is a rival to Luigi. He is presumably the brother of Wario, Mario's nemesis. Waluigi has a hat and gloves with an inverted L ( Γ ), which is similar to Wario's "W", an inverted "M". Waluigi's name is a portmanteau of the Japanese word warui (悪い), meaning "bad," and the name Luigi, so that his name literally means "bad Luigi". His name could be Waluigi simply because there isn't a letter 'Γ' in the alphabet.

Waluigi's first appearance was in the Mario Tennis games for the Game Boy Color and Nintendo 64, as Wario's doubles partner. Later, along with Princess Daisy, he joined the Mario Party series's roster in Mario Party 3 where he plays an important role, in which he owns an island full of hearts. He has been a playable character in many entries in the series since, as well as various Mario sports and Kart games. He acts as an antagonist in , in which he wreaks havoc in the Mushroom Kingdom by stealing special objects called the Music Keys in order to hypnotize the world with his dancing, thus enabling him to conquer it. In Super Smash Bros. Brawl, Waluigi is one of the characters who can be summoned using the Assist Trophy item and as an alternate costume for Luigi(However, this is only Luigi in Waluigi's palette). When summoned, Waluigi attacks opponents by striking them with a tennis racket and by angrily stomping on them until they become temporarily stuck in the ground.

Main article: WarioWario (ワリオ, Wario?) is a fictional Nintendo video game character created by Gunpei Yokoi.[1] Wario was designed as another antagonist to Mario (besides Bowser), and first appeared in the 1992 handheld video game Super Mario Land 2:6 Golden Coins as the main villain and final boss. Since that time, Wario has developed into the protagonist and antihero of the Wario series, spanning both handheld and console markets, in addition to his numerous appearances in spin-offs of the Mario series. He is voiced by Charles Martinet, who also voices Mario, Luigi, and Waluigi.

Wart (Mamu (マムー, Mamū) in Japan) plays the role of final boss in Super Mario Bros. 2, and , the game that it is derived from. Wart is a fat, toad-like creature, with a crown on his head and a robe that can scarcely conceal his big belly. He is voiced by Charles Martinet in Super Mario Advance. Wart appears in the comics "Cloud Nine" and "Tanooki Suits Me" published for the Nintendo Comics System, his character design resembling an alligator rather than a frog in the former story. Wart also appeared in book six of the Nintendo Adventure Books, titled Doors to Doom. There, though, he appeared as a skateboarder who ended up helping the Mario Bros. during their current plight. Under the name "Mamu", Wart also appeared in  to teach Link the third Ocarina song. Wart is also alluded to in Super Paper Mario.







