Penge is a place in the London Borough of Bromley. It is a suburban development situated 7.1 miles (11.4 km) south east of Charing Cross. 

Penge was once a small town, which was recorded under the name Penceat in a Saxon deed dating from 957. Most historians believe the name of the town is derived from the Celtic word "Penceat" which means "edge of wood" and refers to the fact that the surrounding area was once covered in a dense forest. The original Celtic words of which the name was composed referred to "pen", "head", as in the Welsh "pen" (used in Penarth) and "ceat", "wood", similar to the Welsh "coed" (used in Llangoedmor).

Penge formed a part of the parish of Battersea, with the historic county boundary between Kent and Surrey forming its eastern boundary. In 1855 both parts of the parish were included in the area of the Metropolitan Board of Works, with Penge Hamlet Vestry electing six members to the Lewisham District Board of Works. The Local Government Act 1888 abolished the Metropolitan Board, with its area becoming the County of London. However the London Government Act 1899 subsequently made provision for Penge to be removed from the County of London and annexed to either Surrey or Kent. Accordingly, an order in council transferred the hamlet to Kent in 1900, constituting it as Penge Urban District. The urban district was abolished in 1965 by the London Government Act 1963, and its former area merged with that of other districts to form the London Borough of Bromley.  With the creation of the Penge Urban District, Penge New Road (formerly the part of Beckenham Road north of Kent House Road) was renamed Penge High Street.

From 1885 the Hamlet of Penge was a ward of the Dulwich (UK Parliament constituency)(then in Surrey) and remained in that electorate until 1918 when it was transferred to the new Bromley (UK Parliament constituency). In future elections Penge will become part of Lewisham West and Penge (UK Parliament constituency)

In the Victorian era Penge developed into a fashionable suburb because of its proximity to the relocated Crystal Palace.  By 1862 Stanford's map of Londonhttp://www.mappalondon.com/london/south-east/map-london.htm shows large homes had been constructed along Penge New Road (now Crystal Palace Park Road and Penge High Street), Thick Wood (now Thicket) Road and Anerley Road.  This all came to an end with the notorious Penge Murders of 1877http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/postcodes/places/SE20/stories/CAT122.html



Penge was an inconspicuous area with few residents before the arrival of the railways. A traveller passing through Penge would have noticed the large green with a small inn on its boundary. Penge appears as Pensgreene on Kip's 1607 map. The green was bounded to the north by Penge Lane, the west by Beckenham Road and the southeast by the Crooked Billet. On a modern map that area is very small but the modern day Penge Lane and Crooked Billet are not in their original locations and Beckenham Road would have been little more than a cart track following the property line on the west side of Penge High Street. The original Penge Lane from Penge to Sydenham is now named St John's Road and Newlands Park Road. After the LC&amp;D railway was built, Penge Lane crossed the line by level crossing. When this crossing was closed Penge Lane was realigned to the east of the tracks until it passed under the railway to the present day Penge Lane.

The 1868 Ordnance Survey map shows the Old Crooked Billet located to the southeast of the current location. This earlier location was on the eastward side of Penge Green, which disappeared as a result of The Penge Enclosure Act, 1827 which enclosed the whole Green. This left the Crooked Billet with no frontage to Beckenham Road, so new premises were constructed on the present site.

The Crooked Billet is by far the oldest and arguably the most famous public house in Penge particularly for lending its name as a bus route terminus since 1914. General Omnibus routes 109 and 609 both operated between Bromley Market and the Crooked Billet following different routes. The 109 was renumbered 227 by London Transport and continued to terminate at the Crooked Billet. (Route 609 was shortened terminating in Beckenham ). At various times the 227 operated from the Crooked Billet to Chislehurst, Eltham and Welling. Around 1950 some services were extended past the Crooked Billet to the Crystal Palace. Eventually alternate buses travelled the extended route until the present service arose at the time London Transport was privatised. The 354 buses now use the terminus, as do so short running buses on route 194 which carry the destination 'Penge High Street'.

William Hone wrote about a visit to the Crooked Billet in 1827. 

After the Crystal Palace was moved to Penge, a fashionable day out was to visit the Crystal Palace during the day and to take the tram down the hill to one of the 'twenty-five pubs to the square mile'or two Music Halls - The King's Hall and the Empire Theatre (later the Essoldo cinema) http://www.ideal-homes.org.uk/bromley/penge/empire-theatre.htmhttp://viewfinder.english-heritage.org.uk/search/reference.asp?index=565&amp;main_query=&amp;theme=&amp;period=&amp;county=&amp;district=&amp;place_name=London&amp;imageUID=77020&amp;=&amp;JS=True.  Music Hall comedians were in the habit of making fun of the locale in which they appeared and consequently Penge became the butt of many jokes. Playing on the idea that the word penge seems to be an inherently funny word, and its apparent shabby-genteel image, the place has been lightly parodied by:

Seagoon:  I didn't know you had a deaf ear. Bloodnok:  Yes, I found it on the floor of a barber's shop in PengeA small Post Office in east Penge was the location for Part 2 of The Stolen    Policeman (series 8, ep.11) and Series 8 episode 13 opens:

Greenslade:This is the BBC light program. We present the all leather Goon Show. For the benefit of listeners who are listening we present 'The Plastercine Man'. The curtain rises on a window revealing the waiting room of the East Penge labour exchange. On a crude wooden bench sit two crude wooden men.







Penge is served by London buses routes N3, 75, 157, 176, 194, 197, 227, 249, 354, 356. and 358. The bus station at Crystal Palace lays within the area historically occupied by Penge.  This adds a large number of routes that technically serve Penge but are of little practical use to the residents of Penge.

Two A roads, the A213 and A234 pass through the area, intersecting at the Pawleyne Arms.

Southern trains to London Bridge and East Croydon or West Croydon run from Penge West railway station (originally named Penge but renamed Penge West because of the change of name of Penge East railway station).  Southeastern services between London Victoria and Orpington via Bromley South operate from Penge East railway station (originally named Penge Lane but renamed after the portion of Penge Lane in proximity to the station was itself renamed.).  The other nearest stations are:



Transport for London has begun work on the southern extension of the East London Line,  to be rebranded as  the London Overground East London Railway. This will bring services to the Docklands and Shoreditch through Penge West to connect with the North London Line, opening in 2011. In the 1860s, Penge was also a terminus for the short-lived Crystal Palace pneumatic railway.











