Benjamin-Gunnar Cohrs (born 21 September 1965 in Hameln) is a German conductor, scholar, and publicist on music. 

Benjamin-Gunnar Cohrs gave his early conducting debut 1984 with the orchestra of the Youth Music School in Hameln, where he received his early musical education since 1972 (Flute, Theory, Aural Training, Piano). In the same year he founded the Youth String Orchestra of Hameln, which performed with him numerous works of the string- and chamber orchestra repertoire until 1992. From 1986 to 1989 he studied conducting privately with the noted Italian composer and conductor Nicola Samale (Rome), and from 1989 to 1994 concert conducting (Hans-Joachim Kauffmann), voice (Hidenori Komatsu) and flute (Susanne Meier) at the Conservatory of Arts, Bremen He also attended to rehearsals and projects of numerous well-known conductors, and performed himself with several choirs and orchestras. His concert examination in 1994 included compositions by Felix Mendelssohn Bartholdy, Jean Sibelius and Frank Martin as well as the first Bremen performance of Ralph Vaughan Williams’ Fifth Symphony, recorded and broadcasted by Radio Bremen. In 1996 he finished a Postgraduate Diploma in Musicology at the University of Adelaide for which he was granted a full scholarship of the DAAD. Deutschen Akademischen Austauschdienstes Since then, he has developed a career as a freelance concert conductor, editor, scholar and publicist on music.

Ben Cohrs made his international conducting debut in November 2000 in the Moscow Bolshoi Hall, when he introduced historically informed performing practice to the Russian National Orchestra. In March 2001 he participated in the farewell-concert of the famous Philharmonia Hungarica, which was closed by the German Government and the Orchestral Union for political reasons. He appeared with orchestras such as the Royal Flanders Philharmonic (September 2001, Sumida Triphony Hall, Tokyo), Sarajevo Symphony Orchestra, and the Janacek Philharmonic; with the latter he gave the Austrian Premiére of Bruckner’s completed Ninth Symphony in Gmunden. In 2002 the New Queen’s Hall Orchestra appointed him as a Musical Advisor and Guest Conductor. 

Since 1996 Cohrs contributes to international music magazines, presents pre-concert-talks as well as own radio programmes (Radio Bremen, SWR, WDR, ORF), writes programme notes, booklet notes, reports on musicological conferences and is a successful editor of music. Since 1995 he is a co-editor of the Anton Bruckner Gesamtausgabe (Bruckner Complete Edition, Vienna). Today he is a well-known Bruckner-scholar, in particular due to his studies and editions on Bruckner’s Ninth Symphony. He was also part of the editorial team of Nicola Samale which prepared the Completed Performing Version of the unfinished Finale of Bruckner’s Ninth (1986–2006). For the Magazine Musik-Konzepte he compiled Vol. 120/121/122 on request of the earlier editors, Heinz-Klaus Metzger and Rainer Riehn (Bruckners Neunte im Fegefeuer der Rezeption, Munich 2003). He also edited new completed performing versions of Schubert’s Unfinished Symphony in b-minor and the C Minor Mass by Mozart, both based on original sources. 





