<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 16:54:32[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>General intelligence factor</title>
<id>374298</id>
<revision>
<id>242249276</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-01T14:08:21Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Minesweeper</username>
<id>7279</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Intelligence</category>
<category>Intelligence tests</category>
<category>Educational psychology</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

This article is about the general intelligence factor.&#32;&#32;For the magnetism-related <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../269/6095269.xml">
g-factor</link>, see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../679/1228679.xml">
gyromagnetic ratio</link>.&#32;&#32;<p>

The <b>general intelligence factor</b>  (abbreviated <b><it>g</it></b>) is a controversial construct used in the field of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../921/22921.xml">
psychology</link> (<it>see also <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/24982.xml">
psychometrics</link></it>) to quantify what is common to the scores of all <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/14892.xml">
intelligence test</link>s.  </p>
<p>

<image location="right" width="200px" src="SpearmanFactors.svg" type="thumb">
<caption>

An illustration of Spearman's two-factor intelligence theory. Each small oval is a hypothetical mental test. The blue areas show the variance attributed to <it>s</it>, and the purple areas the variance attributed to <it>g</it>.
</caption>
</image>
</p>
<p>

<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<statistician wordnetid="110653238" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/1290799.xml">
Charles Spearman</link></research_worker>
</mathematician>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</statistician>
</associate>
</psychologist>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</colleague>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
,  early psychometrician, found that schoolchildren's grades across seemingly unrelated subjects were positively correlated, and proposed that these correlations reflected the influence of a dominant factor, which he termed <it>g</it> for "general" intelligence.  He developed a model where all variation in intelligence test scores can be explained by two factors. The first is the factor specific to an individual mental task: the individual abilities that would make a person more skilled at one cognitive task than another. The second is <it>g</it>, a general factor that governs performance on all cognitive tasks.</p>
<p>

The accumulation of cognitive testing data and improvements in analytical techniques have preserved <it>g</it>'s central role and led to the modern conception of <it>g</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref>  A hierarchy of factors with <it>g</it> at its apex and group factors at successively lower levels, is espoused to be the most widely accepted model of cognitive ability.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref>  Other models have also been proposed, and significant <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/519280.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Multiple_intelligences%22])">
controversy</link> attends <it>g</it> and its alternatives.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 Mental testing and <it>g</it> </st>
<p>

The abstraction of <it>g</it> stems from the observation that scores on all forms of cognitive tests <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../057/157057.xml">
correlate</link> positively with one another. <it>g</it> can be derived as the principal factor from cognitive test scores using the method of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../340/76340.xml">
principal components analysis</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../492/253492.xml">
factor analysis</link>.</p>
<p>

The relationship of <it>g</it> to intelligence tests may be more readily understood with an analogy. Irregular objects, such as the human body, are said to vary in "size". Yet no single measurement of a human body is obviously preferred to measure its "size" (excluding the volume, admittedly). Instead, many and various measurements, such as those taken by a tailor, may be made. All of these measurements will be positively correlated with each other, and if one were to "add up" or combine all of the measurements, the aggregate would give a better description of an individual's size than any single measurement. The method of factor analysis allows this. The process is intuitively similar to taking the average of a sample of measurements of a single variable, but instead "size" is a summary measure of a sample of variables. <it>g</it> is like size, in that it is abstracted from various measures (of cognitive ability). Of course, variation in "size" does not fully account for all variation in the measurements of a human body. Factor analysis techniques are not limited to producing single factors, and an analysis of human bodies might produce (for example) two major factors, such as height and girth. However, the scores of tests of cognitive ability do in fact produce a primary dominant factor, <it>g</it>. </p>
<p>

Tests of cognitive ability derive most of their validity from the extent to which they measure <it>g</it>. If quantifiable measures of the performance of a task correlate highly with <it>g</it>, it is said to be <it>g</it>-loaded. Creators of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/14892.xml">
IQ</link> tests, whose goals are generally to create highly <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../138/239138.xml">
reliable</link> and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../366/32366.xml">
valid</link> tests, have thus made their tests as <it>g</it>-loaded as possible. Historically, this has meant dampening the influence of group factors by testing as wide a range of mental tasks as possible. However, tests such as <process wordnetid="105701363" confidence="0.8">
<inquiry wordnetid="105797597" confidence="0.8">
<thinking wordnetid="105770926" confidence="0.8">
<problem_solving wordnetid="105796750" confidence="0.8">
<experiment wordnetid="105798043" confidence="0.8">
<trial wordnetid="105799212" confidence="0.8">
<higher_cognitive_process wordnetid="105770664" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../210/2389210.xml">
Raven's Progressive Matrices</link></higher_cognitive_process>
</trial>
</experiment>
</problem_solving>
</thinking>
</inquiry>
</process>
 are considered to be the most <it>g</it>-loaded in existence, even though Raven's is quite homogeneous in the types of tasks comprising it.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref></p>
<p>

Elementary cognitive tasks (ECTs) also correlate strongly with <it>g</it>. ECTs are, as the name suggests, simple tasks that apparently require very little intelligence, but still correlate strongly with more exhaustive intelligence tests. Determining whether a light is red or blue and determining whether there are four or five squares drawn on a computer screen are two examples of ECTs. The answers to such questions are usually provided by quickly pressing buttons. Often, in addition to buttons for the two options provided, a third button is held down from the start of the test. When the stimulus is given to the subject, he removes his hand from the starting button to the button of the correct answer. This allows the examiner to determine how much time was spent thinking about the answer to the question (reaction time, usually measured in small fractions of second), and how much time was spent on physical hand movement to the correct button (movement time).  Reaction time correlates strongly with <it>g</it>, while movement time correlates less strongly.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref>
ECT testing has allowed quantitative examination of hypotheses concerning test bias, subject motivation, and group differences.  By virtue of their simplicity, ECTs provide a link between classical IQ testing and biological inquiries such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../725/226725.xml">
fMRI</link> studies.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Biological and genetic correlates of <it>g</it> </st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>Main article: <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../935/4868935.xml">
Heritability of IQ</link></it>
</indent>

<it>g</it> has a large number of biological correlates. Strong correlates include mass of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../220/469220.xml">
prefrontal lobe</link>, overall brain mass, and glucose metabolization rate within the brain. <it>g</it> correlates less strongly, but significantly, with overall body size. There is conflicting evidence regarding the correlation between <it>g</it> and peripheral nerve conduction velocity, with some reports of significant positive correlations, and others of no or even negative correlations.</p>
<p>

Current research suggests that the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/155624.xml">
heritability</link> of <it>g</it> is approximately .85 - even higher than that for IQ itself - so the heritability of most test performance is thus attributable to <it>g</it>.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></p>
<p>

Brain size has long been known to be correlated with <it>g</it> <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref>.  Recently, an <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../450/19450.xml">
MRI</link> study on twins <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref> showed that frontal gray matter volume was highly significantly correlated with <it>g</it> and highly heritable.  A related study has reported that the correlation between brain size (reported to have a heritability of 0.85) and <it>g</it> is 0.4, and that correlation is mediated entirely by genetic factors <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%228%22])">8</ref>. <it>g</it> has been observed in mice as well as humans <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%229%22])">9</ref>.</p>
<p>

Lehrl and Fischer (1990)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> have claimed that <it>g</it> is limited by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../204/231204.xml">
channel capacity</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../944/28944.xml">
short-term memory</link>. Mental power, or the capacity C of short-term memory (measured in bits of information), is the product of the individual mental speed Ck of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../578/315578.xml">
information processing</link> (in bit/s) (see the external link below to the paper by Lehrl and Fischer),<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2210%22])">10</ref> and the duration time D (in s) of information in short-term <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/33912.xml">
working memory</link>, meaning the duration of memory span. Hence:</p>
<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>C</it> (bit) = <it>Ck</it>(bit/s) &amp;times; <it>D</it> (s).
</indent>

This theory has been tested and found wanting by Roberts et al. (1992).<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2211%22])">11</ref> There is much evidence that <it>g</it> is closely related to measures of the capacity of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../912/33912.xml">
working memory</link> (<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2212%22])">12</ref>; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2213%22])">13</ref>; <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2214%22])">14</ref>), but this capacity can not be measured in bits of information <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2215%22])">15</ref>.</p>
<p>

However recent studies attempting to find regions in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../888/42888.xml">
genome</link> relating to intelligence have had little success. A recent study used several hundred people in two groups, one with a very high IQ, average 160, and a control group with an average IQ of 102.  The study used 1,842 DNA markers and put them through a five step inspection process to eliminate false positives. By the fifth step the study could not find a single gene that was related to intelligence.  Critics of these studies say the failure to find a specific gene associated with intelligence is indicative of the complex nature of intelligence. They contend that intelligence is probably under the influence of several genes. Some estimate that as much as 40% of the genome may contribute to intelligence.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2216%22])">16</ref></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Social correlates of <it>g</it> </st>

<p>

Most measures of <it>g</it> positively correlate with conventional measures of success (income, academic achievement, job performance, career prestige) and negatively correlate with what are generally seen as undesirable life outcomes (school dropout, unplanned childbearing, poverty)<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2217%22])">17</ref>. IQ tests that measure a wide range of abilities do not predict much better than <it>g</it>. Scientific publishings of findings of differences in <it>g</it> between ethnic groups (see <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/26494.xml">
race and intelligence</link>) have sparked public controversy.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 The Flynn effect and <it>g</it> </st>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../773/11773.xml">
Flynn effect</link> describes a rise in IQ scores over time. There is no strong consensus as to whether rising IQ scores also reflect increases in <it>g</it>. In addition, there is recent evidence that the tendency for intelligence scores to rise has ended in some <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../353/160353.xml">
first world</link> countries.  <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2218%22])">18</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2219%22])">19</ref>
<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2220%22])">20</ref>
Statistical analyses of IQ subtest scores suggest a <it>g</it>-independent input to the Flynn effect <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2221%22])">21</ref>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 Challenges to <it>g</it> </st>

<p>

In 1981, the late <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../875/27875.xml">
Stephen Jay Gould</link></scientist>
</person>
, a paleontologist, voiced his objections to the concept of <it>g</it>, as well as intelligence testing in general, in his <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../897/1746897.xml">
controversial book</link> <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../283/31283.xml">
The Mismeasure of Man</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it>. In 1985, the British philosopher <academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../927/2672927.xml">
Philip Kitcher</link></academician>
 wrote that "Many scientists are now convinced that there is no single measure of intellectual ability" and that "it is useful to continue to expose the myth of "general intelligence". Some researchers in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../164/1164.xml">
artificial intelligence</link> have argued that the science of mental ability can be thought of as "computationalism" and is "either silly or pointless," noting, "Mental ability tests measure differences in tasks that will soon be performed for all of us by computational agents."<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2222%22])">22</ref> And intelligence theorist <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../771/524771.xml">
Howard Gardner</link></scientist>
 also has written that he does not believe "that there is a single general talent, whether it be called intelligence, creativity or 'g'."
In 2005, Wendy Johnson and Thomas Bouchard investigated the structure of mental ability by administering 42 diverse tests of mental ability to 436 adults. The tests included "different uses" (generation of novel uses for specified objects), "object assembly" (reassembly of cut-up figures), "verbal—proverbs" (interpretation of proverbs) and "mechanical ability" (identification of mechanical principles and tools); factor analysis found a clear single higher order factor, <it>g</it>. In their report, published in the journal <it>Intelligence</it>, the study authors conclude:</p>
<p>

In combination with our earlier findings regarding the consistency of general intelligence factors across test batteries, our results point unequivocally to the existence of a general intelligence factor contributing substantively to all aspects of intelligence.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2223%22])">23</ref>
</p>
<ss1>
<st>
Savant syndrome</st>

<p>

<indent level="1">

<it>See also: <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<initiate wordnetid="110206887" confidence="0.8">
<intellectual wordnetid="109621545" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<scholar wordnetid="110557854" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/370785.xml">
Savant syndrome</link></scholar>
</causal_agent>
</intellectual>
</initiate>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</it>
</indent>
Howard Gardner has contends that the rare condition of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../785/370785.xml">
savant syndrome</link> argues against a single generalized intelligence. People with savant syndrome may have general IQs in the mentally retarded range but may possess certain mental abilities that are remarkable compared to the average person. These abilities include superior memory, lightening fast arithmetic calculation, advanced musical ability, rapid language learning and exceptional artistic ability. Standardized IQ tests fail to predict the abilities of those with Savant syndrome. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%2224%22])">24</ref></p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<peer wordnetid="109626238" confidence="0.8">
<physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<colleague wordnetid="109935990" confidence="0.8">
<scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<professional wordnetid="110480253" confidence="0.8">
<educator wordnetid="110045713" confidence="0.8">
<psychologist wordnetid="110488865" confidence="0.8">
<associate wordnetid="109816771" confidence="0.8">
<statistician wordnetid="110653238" confidence="0.8">
<academician wordnetid="109759069" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<mathematician wordnetid="110301261" confidence="0.8">
<research_worker wordnetid="110523076" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../799/1290799.xml">
Charles Spearman</link></research_worker>
</mathematician>
</causal_agent>
</academician>
</statistician>
</associate>
</psychologist>
</educator>
</professional>
</adult>
</scientist>
</colleague>
</person>
</physical_entity>
</peer>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../107/850107.xml">
Fluid and crystallized intelligence</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/519280.xml">
Intelligence</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/14892.xml">
Intelligence quotient</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../494/26494.xml">
Race and intelligence</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Notes</st>

<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
(Carroll 1993)</entry>
<entry id="2">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.lrainc.com/swtaboo/taboos/apa_01.html">
Stalking the Wild Taboo -APA Statement on The Bell Curve - Intelligence: Knowns and Unknowns</weblink></entry>
<entry id="3">
Jensen, 1998, p 38</entry>
<entry id="4">
Jensen, 1998, p 213</entry>
<entry id="5">
(Jensen, 1998)</entry>
<entry id="6">
(Jensen, 1998)</entry>
<entry id="7">
(Thompson <it>et al.</it>, 2001)</entry>
<entry id="8">
(Posthuma <it>et al.</it>, 2002)</entry>
<entry id="9">
(Matzel <it>et al.</it>, 2003)</entry>
<entry id="10">
Lehrl and Fischer (1990)</entry>
<entry id="11">
Roberts et al. (1992)</entry>
<entry id="12">
Ackerman et al., 2005</entry>
<entry id="13">
Kane et al., 2005</entry>
<entry id="14">
Oberauer et al., 2005</entry>
<entry id="15">
(Miller, 1956)</entry>
<entry id="17">
Geary, D.C. (2005). The Origin of Mind: Evolution of Brain Cognition and General Intelligence. Washington, D.C.: American Psychological Association. ISBN 1-59147-181-8</entry>
<entry id="16">
<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.meb.ki.se/education/epi/descriptions/gen_mol_epi/cognitive_paper.pdf">
A Genome-Wide Scan of 1842 DNA Markers for Allelic Associations With General Cognitive Ability: A Five-Stage Design Using DNA Pooling and Extreme Selected Groups</weblink></entry>
<entry id="19">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://72.14.205.104/search?q=cache:RDb9nvlTcr4J:www.missouri.edu/~aab2b3/LFE_GNXP/T%26O_PAID.pdf+%2B%22Thomas+W.+Teasdale%22+%2BIQ&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=5">
A long-term rise and recent decline in intelligence test performance: The Flynn Effect in reverse.</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="18">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://72.14.207.104/search?q=cache:sLUpdtOiKmoJ:www.missouri.edu/~aab2b3/LFE_GNXP/sdarticle.pdf+%2B%22Jon+Martin+Sundet%22+%2BIQ&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=9">
The end of the Flynn Effect.  A study of secular trends in mean intelligence scores of Norwegian conscripts during half a century.</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="21">
(Wicherts et al. 2004)</entry>
<entry id="20">
"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://education.guardian.co.uk/schools/story/0,,1693061,00.html">
Children are less able than they used to be</weblink>".</entry>
<entry id="23">
Johnson, Wendy and Bouchard, Thomas J. Jr. (2005). "The structure of human intelligence: It is verbal, perceptual, and image rotation (VPR), not fluid and crystallized." <it>Intelligence, 33 393–416.</it></entry>
<entry id="22">
(Bringsjord, 2000)</entry>
<entry id="24">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Heaton, Pamela.&#32;"<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.sedsu.org/Pdf/Heaton_04.pdf">
Annotation:The savant syndrome</weblink>". <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111%2Fj.1469-7610.2004.t01-1-00284.x">
10.1111/j.1469-7610.2004.t01-1-00284.x</weblink>.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>

<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Ackerman, P. L., Beier, M. E., &amp; Boyle, M. O. (2005). Working memory and intelligence: The same or different constructs? <it>Psychological Bulletin, 131</it>, 30&ndash;60.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Brand, C. (1996). <it>.</it> (depublished) [originally Wiley]. ISBN 0-471-96070-5</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Bringsjord, S. (2000). In light of artificial intelligence, the science of mental ability is either silly or pointless: Review of Jensen's <it>The </it>g<it> Factor</it>. <it>Psycoloquy,  11</it>(44). <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://psycprints.ecs.soton.ac.uk/archive/00000044/">
http://psycprints.ecs.soton.ac.uk/archive/00000044/</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Carroll, J.B. (1993). <it>Human Cognitive Abilities</it>.  Cambridge University Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gardner, H. (1993). The relationship between early giftedness and later achievement.  In Ciba Foundation.  The origins and development of high ability. <it>Ciba Foundation Symposium</it> (pp. 175&ndash;186). Chichester, England: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Jensen, A.R. (1998). <it>The </it>g<it> factor: The science of mental ability</it>. Westport, CT: Praeger. ISBN 0-275-96103-6</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kane, M. J., Hambrick, D. Z., &amp; Conway, A. R. A. (2005). Working memory capacity and fluid intelligence are strongly related constructs: Comment on Ackerman, Beier, and Boyle (2004). <it>Psychological Bulletin, 131</it>, 66&ndash;71.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Kitcher, P. (1985). <it>Vaulting ambition: Sociobiology and the quest for human nature.</it> Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Matzel, L.D., Han, Y.R., Grossman, H., Karnik, M.S., Patel, D., Scott, N., Specht, S.M., &amp; Gandhi, C.C. (2003). Individual differences in the expression of a "general" learning ability in mice. <it>Journal of Neuroscience, 23</it>(16), 6423&ndash;6433.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Miller, G. A. (1956). The magical number seven, plus or minus two: Some limits on our capacity for processing information. <it>Psychological Review, 63</it>, 81&ndash;97.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Oberauer, K., Schulze, R., Wilhelm, O., &amp; Süß, H.-M. (2005). Working memory and intelligence - their correlation and their relation: A comment on Ackerman, Beier, and Boyle (2005). <it>Psychological Bulletin, 131</it>, 61&ndash;65.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Posthuma, D., De Geus, E.J., Baare, W.F., Hulshoff Pol, H.E., Kahn, R.S., Boomsma, D.I. (2002). The association between brain volume and intelligence is of genetic origin. <it>Nature Neuroscience, 5</it>(2), 83&ndash;84.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Rindermann, Heiner (2007). The g-factor of international cognitive ability comparisons: the homogeneity of results in PISA, TIMSS, PIRLS and IQ-tests across nations. <it>European Journal of Personality, 21</it>, 667-706 <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://groups.uni-paderborn.de/rindermann/materialien/PublikationsPDFs/07EJP.pdf">
http://groups.uni-paderborn.de/rindermann/materialien/PublikationsPDFs/07EJP.pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Roberts, R. D., Pallier, G., &amp; Stankov, L. (1996). The Basic Information Processing (BIP) unit, mental speed and human cognitive abilities: Should the BIP R.I.P.? <it>Intelligence, 23</it>, 133&ndash;155.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Thompson, P.M., Cannon T.D., Narr, K.L., Erp, T. van, Poutanen, V.-P., Huttunen, M., et al. (2001). Genetic influences on brain structure. <it>Nature Neuroscience, 4</it>(12), 1253&ndash;1258.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Wicherts, J.M., Dolan, C.V., Hessen, D.J., Oosterveld, P., Baal, G.C.M. van, Boomsma, D.I., &amp; Span, M.M. (2004). Are intelligence tests measurement invariant over time? Investigating the nature of the Flynn effect. <it>Intelligence, 32</it>, 509&ndash;537. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://users.fmg.uva.nl/jwicherts/wicherts2004.pdf">
http://users.fmg.uva.nl/jwicherts/wicherts2004.pdf</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Geary, D.C. (2005). The Origin of Mind: Evolution of Brain Cognition and General Intelligence. Washington, D.C.: American Psychological Association. ISBN 1-59147-181-8</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

See: 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../480/2177480.xml">
The g Factor</link> - Jensen's book</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
External links</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.psych.utoronto.ca/~reingold/courses/intelligence/cache/1198gottfred.html">
The General Intelligence Factor</weblink> <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.udel.edu/educ/gottfredson/reprints/1998generalintelligencefactor.pdf">
PDF</weblink> - Good article for laymen</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.volkmar-weiss.de/lehrl.html">
The Basic Period of Individual Mental Speed, Underlying IQ</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

[https://genepi.qimr.edu.au/staff/nick_pdf/CV411.pdf A Genomewide Scan for Genes Underlying General Cognitive Ability]</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.iapsych.com/carolmod.htm">
Carroll model</weblink>.</entry>
</list>
</p>


</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
