<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 22:57:37[mciao0828] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<system  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="104377057">
<entity  confidence="0.9511911446218017" wordnetid="100001740">
<header>
<title>Sex determination and differentiation (human)</title>
<id>7860110</id>
<revision>
<id>227425347</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-23T15:06:00Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>Ndenison</username>
<id>5126184</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Sex-determination systems</category>
<category>Physiology</category>
<category>Reproduction</category>
<category>Development</category>
<category>Epigenetics</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<image width="200px" src="YChromShowingSRY2.png" type="thumb">
<caption>

The Human Y Chromosome showing the SRY gene which codes for a protein regulating sexual differentiation.
</caption>
</image>

<b>Human sex determination</b> refers to the processes by which an individual becomes either a male or female during development.
<sec>
<st>
The Jost Paradigm</st>
<p>

Under typical circumstances, the sex of an individual will be determined and expressed through the following mechanisms:
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Chromosomal Sex (genetic): Presence or absence of Y chromosome</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Gonadal Sex (Primary Sex Determination): Controlled by presence or absence of testis determining factor (TDF)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Phenotypic Sex (Secondary Sex Differentiation): Determined by the hormonal products produced by the gonads.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sex determination</st>

<ss1>
<st>
Sex determination at the chromosome level</st>
<p>

For the majority of individuals, sex determination is as simple as the presence or absence of a Y chromosome. Those individuals with a Y chromosome (including XXY, XXXY, etc.) will develop into males, and those without one will become female. Some individuals, however, will undergo what is referred to as primary sex reversal, whereby the X and Y chromosomes [cross over] and exchange genetic material. This relatively rare occurrence (approximately 1 in 20000 births) can lead to males with two X chromosomes and females with a Y chromosome.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Testis determining gene</st>
<p>

During the late 1980s and early 1990s, coinciding with the mapping of the human genome, researchers began to look for the specific gene on the Y chromosome that, up until then, had been known as the testis determining factor (TDF). Through the study of individuals that underwent primary sex reversal (that is, XX males and XY females), researchers determined that the TDF must lie on the Y chromosome in a location that would permit its exchange to the X chromosome during cross over. In 1985, Dr. David C. Page published an article in Nature boldly stating that the TDF was the ZFY gene on the Y chromosome.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%221%22])">1</ref> However, Dr. MS Palmer later discovered a ZFY analogue on the X chromosome, providing evidence that ZFY was in fact not the TDF.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%222%22])">2</ref> Eventually, Dr. Peter Koopman was able to prove that the SRY gene is the TDF from studies on XX males..<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%223%22])">3</ref> The fact that SRY supports the following evidence further supports this claim:but if an s chromosome is there it means the child has hipotoraliop
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SRY is Y specific, and there is no analogue on the X chromosome.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SRY is deleted or mutated in XY females</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

It undergoes expression within the testis at the time of testis differentiation.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Its sequence suggests that its protein has a DNA binding motif because it has high homology to an 80 amino acid long DNA binding region (HMG box).</entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
SRY a repressor?</st>
<p>

Recently, it has been suggested by some that the SRY gene acts as a repressor or inhibitor of another gene, “Z”, that is involved in female development. Previously, it was stated that the SRY sequence suggests the presence of a DNA binding motif. Also, the idea that SRY is a repressor is further supported by the fact that a small percentage of sex reversal cases cannot be explained by the absence of SRY and could be due to a mutation in some gene “Z” that prevents the binding of SRY and its subsequent antagonist action.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Other sex determination genes</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

DAX1: Exerts its effects early on in development. There is some debate over what its role is in the development of testis. It is a candidate for gene “Z”.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%224%22])">4</ref></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

SOX9: mutations in this gene cause severe dwarfism, and a bone disorder called campomelic dysplasia, which occurs in many sex reversed males. <ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%225%22])">5</ref></entry>
</list>
</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Sex differentiation</st>

<p>

Sex differentiation refers to the expression of phenotypic attributes specific to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/26805.xml">
sex</link> of an individual. While gonad development is a result of the presence or absence of the sex determination gene SRY on the Y chromosome, sex differentiation is determined by the hormonal products produced by the gonads.</p>

<ss1>
<st>
Testosterone</st>

<p>

In the 1930s, Alfred Jost determined that the presence of testosterone was required for <embryology wordnetid="106071426" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../273/414273.xml">
Wolffian duct</link></embryology>
 development in the female rabbit.<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%226%22])">6</ref></p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
Müllerian inhibiting substance</st>
<p>

Jost also observed that while testosterone was required for Wolffian duct development, the regression of the <link>
Müllerian duct</link> was due to another substance. This was later determined to be Müllerian inhibiting substance (MIS), a 140 kD dimeric glycoprotein that is produced by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../956/608956.xml">
sertoli cells</link>. MIS blocks the development of <link>
Müllerian ducts</link>, promoting their regression.</p>

</ss1>
<ss1>
<st>
5-alpha dihydrotestosterone (DHT)</st>
<p>

Testosterone is converted to the more potent <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/591638.xml">
DHT</link> by 5-alpha reductase. DHT is necessary to exert <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../666/236666.xml">
androgenic</link> effects farther from the site of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../983/30983.xml">
testosterone</link> production, where the concentrations of testosterone are too low to have any potency. A 5-alpha reductase deficiency results in an androgen disorder characterized by female phenotype or severely undervirilized male phenotype with development of the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/410991.xml">
epididymis</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../999/410999.xml">
vas deferens</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../594/355594.xml">
seminal vesicle</link>, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../005/411005.xml">
ejaculatory duct</link>, but also a <link>
pseudovagina</link>.</p>

</ss1>
</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Pathologies</st>
<p>

The following disorders are caused by a malfunction in the sex determination and differentiation process:<ref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="#xpointer(//reflist/entry[@id=%227%22])">7</ref>
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Congenital Adrenal Hyperplasia - Inability of adrenal to produce sufficient cortisol, leading to increased production of testosterone resulting in severe masculinization of 46 XX females.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Persistent Müllerian Duct Syndrome - A rare type of pseudohermaphrititism that occurs in 46 XY males, caused by either a mutation in the Müllerian inhibiting substance (MIS) gene, on 19p13, or its type II receptor, 12q13. Results in a retention of Müllerian ducts and unilateral or bilateral undescended testes.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

Male Pseudohermaphroditism - Failure of androgen production or inadequate androgen response, which can cause incomplete masculinization in XY males. Varies from mild failure of masculinization with undescended testes to complete sex reversal and female phenotype.</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<reflist>
<entry id="1">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Page DC, de la Chapelle A, Weissenbach J&#32;(May 16-22 1985).&#32;"Chromosome Y-specific DNA in related human XX males.". <it>Nature</it>&#32;<b>315</b>&#32;(6016): 224–6. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038%2F315224a0">
10.1038/315224a0</weblink>. PMID 2987697.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="2">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Palmer MS&#32;(1989).&#32;"Sex determining genes.". <it>Science Progress</it>&#32;<b>73</b>: 245–61. PMID 2678463.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="3">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Koopman, P&#32;(1995).&#32;"The molecular biology of SRY and its role in sex determination in mammals.". <it>Reproduction, Fertility, and Development</it>&#32;<b>7</b>&#32;(4): 713–22. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071%2FRD9950713">
10.1071/RD9950713</weblink>. PMID 8711208.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="4">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Koopman P&#32;(June 1999).&#32;"Sry and Sox9: mammalian testis-determining genes". <it>Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences</it>&#32;<b>55</b>&#32;(6-7): 839–56. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2FPL00013200">
10.1007/PL00013200</weblink>. PMID 10412367.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="5">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">Pop R, Zaragoza MV, Gaudette M, Dohrmann U, Scherer G&#32;(June 2005).&#32;"A homozygous nonsense mutation in SOX9 in the dominant disorder campomelic dysplasia: a case of mitotic gene conversion.". <it>Human Genetics</it>&#32;<b>117</b>&#32;(1): 43–53. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs00439-005-1295-y">
10.1007/s00439-005-1295-y</weblink>. PMID 15806394.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
<entry id="6">
A. Jost, D. Price, R. G. Edwards (1970). "Hormonal Factors in the Sex Differentiation of the Mammalian Foetus [and Discussion]". Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological Sciences 259(828): 119-131. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0080-4622(19700806)259%3A828%3C119%3AHFITSD%3E2.0.CO%3B2-5#abstract">
link to article abstract</weblink></entry>
<entry id="7">
 <cite style="font-style:normal">MacLaughlin and Donahoe N&#32;(2004).&#32;"Mechanisms of Disease: Sex Determination and Differentiation". <it>New England Journal of Medicine</it>&#32;<b>350</b>: 367–378. <document wordnetid="106470073" confidence="0.8">
<written_communication wordnetid="106349220" confidence="0.8">
<writing wordnetid="106362953" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/422994.xml">
doi</link></writing>
</written_communication>
</document>
:<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1056%2FNEJMra022784">
10.1056/NEJMra022784</weblink>. PMID 14736929.</cite>&nbsp;</entry>
</reflist>





</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
</entity>
</system>
</article>
