<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 21:31:03[mciao0825] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<attempt  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100786195">
<test  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100791078">
<event  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100029378">
<act  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100030358">
<psychological_feature  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100023100">
<activity  confidence="0.8" wordnetid="100407535">
<header>
<title>Loudun possessions</title>
<id>5036540</id>
<revision>
<id>243378819</id>
<timestamp>2008-10-06T07:26:58Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>AlleborgoBot</username>
<id>3813685</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Articles lacking in-text citations</category>
<category>17th century in France</category>
<category>Inquisition</category>
<category>Witchcraft</category>
<category>1634 in law</category>
<category>Witch trials</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<table class="metadata plainlinks ambox ">
<row>
<col>

ambox-style" style=""</col>
</row>
<row>
<col class="mbox-image"><p>

<image width="50px" src="Text_document_with_red_question_mark.svg">
</image>
</p>
</col>
<col style="" class="mbox-text">
 This article or section includes a  or , but its sources remain unclear because it lacks <b>.</b>
You can  this article by introducing more precise citations . <it>(July 2006)''</it></col>
</row>
</table>


The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/35191.xml">
1634</link> case of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/246574.xml">
demonic possession</link> in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<commune wordnetid="108541609" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../502/200502.xml">
Loudun</link></district>
</commune>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, <country wordnetid="108544813" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../419/5843419.xml">
France</link></country>
, is arguably the most famous case of multiple or mass <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../574/246574.xml">
possession</link> in history. This case involved the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../265/1354265.xml">
Ursuline</link> nuns of Loudun who were allegedly inflicted by Father <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<priest wordnetid="110470779" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<clergyman wordnetid="109927451" confidence="0.8">
<occultist wordnetid="110370381" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_leader wordnetid="109505153" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<enchantress wordnetid="110055297" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/252680.xml">
Urbain Grandier</link></enchantress>
</causal_agent>
</spiritual_leader>
</leader>
</occultist>
</clergyman>
</person>
</priest>
</physical_entity>
, who was convicted of the crime of <power wordnetid="105190804" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/48489.xml">
sorcery</link></power>
, evil <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/48489.xml">
spells</link>, and the possessions visited upon the Ursuline nuns, based on the words of possessed demoniacs. Until the <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/5027523.xml">
Aix-en-Provence possessions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../992/34992.xml">
1611</link>, the words of the possessed nuns would have failed to become evidence. 
<sec>
<st>
Early trials and conspiracy</st>

<p>

<image width="240px" src="UrbainPact2.jpg" type="thumb">
<caption>

The pact allegedly signed between Urbain Grandier and the Devil, stolen from the Devil's cabinet of pacts by the demon Asmodeus. This page shows the signatures of all demons in possession of the Ursuline nuns at Loudun and the note added by Asmodeus. The other piece can be seen here: <image width="150px" src="UrbainPact.jpg">
<caption>

UrbainPact.jpg
</caption>
</image>

</caption>
</image>
Urbain Grandier was appointed <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../623/23623.xml">
parish</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../707/23707.xml">
priest</link> of St-Pierre-du-Marche in Loudun, a town in <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<commune wordnetid="108541609" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/51489.xml">
Poitiers</link></district>
</commune>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, France, in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../892/34892.xml">
1617</link>. Grandier was considered to be a very good-looking man, and was both wealthy and well-educated. The combination made the priest a target for the attention of girls in Loudun, one of whom was Philippa Trincant, the daughter of the King's solicitor in Loudun. It was believed by the people of Loudun that Grandier was the father of Trincant's child. In addition to Trincant, Grandier openly courted Madeleine de Brou, daughter of the King's councillor in Loudun. Most assumed that Madeleine was Grandier's mistress after he wrote a treatise against the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../035/6035.xml">
celibacy</link> of priests for her.</p>
<p>

Grandier was also a very well-connected man, high in political circles. When he was arrested and found guilty for immorality on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../855/15855.xml">
June 2</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/35078.xml">
1630</link>, it was these connections that restored him to full clerical duties within the same year. Presiding over the case was the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../092/4092.xml">
Bishop</link> of Poiters, a man who was known to dislike Grandier and admitted to wanting him out of the parish.</p>
<p>

Two stories exist about what happened next. Either the Bishop of Poiters approached Father Mignon, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../096/1206096.xml">
confessor</link> to the Ursuline nuns, and a plan was made to persuade a few of the sisters to feign possession and denounce Grandier, or Father Mignon was approached by the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../301/1301.xml">
Mother Superior</link> Jeanne des Anges (<it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/1665817.xml">
Joan of the Angels</link></movie>
</it>) for help. </p>
<p>

According to the first story, Father Mignon readily persuaded the Mother Superior, Jeanne des Anges, and another nun to comply. They would claim that Father Grandier had bewitched them, falling into fits and convulsions, often holding their breath and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../327/12327.xml">
speaking in tongues</link>. </p>
<p>

The second story claims that Jeanne had illicit dreams about Father Grandier, who appeared to her as a radiant angel. As an angel, he enticed her to sexual acts, causing her to rave loudly at night. Jeanne suffered <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../247/144247.xml">
flagellation</link> and did <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../480/217480.xml">
penance</link> for the night-time disturbances, but she was no less troubled and soon it was found that other nuns were being haunted by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../159/49159.xml">
hallucinations</link> and vulgar dreams. It was then, this version claims, that Mother Superior Jeanne des Anges called for Father Mignon to hear her confession and purge the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../315/1315.xml">
convent</link> of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../280/8280.xml">
demons</link>.</p>
<p>

However it came about, Father Mignon and his aide, Father Pierre Barre, saw in the activity an opportunity to remove Grandier.</p>
<p>

Fathers Mignon and Barre immediately proceeded to perform <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/3700127.xml">
exorcism</link>s on the possessed nuns. Several of the nuns, including Jeanne des Anges, suffered violent convulsions during the procedure, shrieking and making sexual motions toward the priests. Following the lead of Jean des Anges, many of the nuns reported illicit dreams. The accusers would suddenly bark, scream, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../469/90469.xml">
blaspheme</link>, and contort their bodies. During the exorcisms, Jeanne swore that she and the other nuns were possessed by two demons named <evil_spirit wordnetid="109541919" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<spirit wordnetid="109545324" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<devil wordnetid="109542339" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/250055.xml">
Asmodeus</link></devil>
</spiritual_being>
</spirit>
</belief>
</evil_spirit>
 and Zabulon. These demons were sent to the nuns when Father Grandier tossed a bouquet of roses over the convent walls.</p>
<p>

Nearby and realizing the danger he was in, Father Grandier pleaded with the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../689/220689.xml">
bailiff</link> of Loudun to isolate the nuns; the bailiff's orders were ignored, and the exorcisms and denouncements continued. Desperate, Grandier wrote to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../750/5284750.xml">
Archbishop of Bordeaux</link>, who sent his personal doctor to examine the nuns. No evidences of true possession were found, and the Archbishop ordered the exorcisms to cease on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../329/20329.xml">
March 21</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/35162.xml">
1633</link>. The nuns were sequestered in their cells.</p>
<p>

Having failed to remove Grandier, his contemporaries continued their efforts in earnest. One of these was Jean de Laubardemont, a relative of Jeanne des Anges' and favored by the powerful <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<priest wordnetid="110470779" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<clergyman wordnetid="109927451" confidence="0.8">
<bishop wordnetid="109857200" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_leader wordnetid="109505153" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../221/6221.xml">
Cardinal</link></causal_agent>
</spiritual_leader>
</leader>
</bishop>
</clergyman>
</person>
</priest>
</physical_entity>
 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../254/85254.xml">
Richelieu</link>. Laubardemont and a <order wordnetid="107168623" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<command wordnetid="107168131" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<speech_act wordnetid="107160883" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../369/101369.xml">
Capuchin</link></speech_act>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</command>
</event>
</order>
 monk, Tranquille, visited the Cardinal with news of the unsuccessful exorcisms and added further evidence against Grandier by providing a copy of a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../661/28661.xml">
libel</link>ous <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../791/26791.xml">
satire</link> Grandier had written about Richelieu. Aware that a relative of his, Sister Claire, was in the Loudun convent, Richelieu asserted his power and organized the Royal Commission to arrest and investigate Grandier as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../959/33959.xml">
witch</link>. Laubardemont was appointed head of the commission.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Public exorcisms at Loudun</st>

<p>

When exorcisms resumed at Loudun, they were led by the expert <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../127/3700127.xml">
exorcists</link> Capuchin Father Tranquille, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../176/64176.xml">
Franciscan</link> Father Lactance, and <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../083/16083.xml">
Jesuit</link> Father <exorcist wordnetid="110072187" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../994/11441994.xml">
Jean-Joseph Surin</link></exorcist>
, and they were held publicly; up to 7,000 spectators attended. The priests employed dramatic commands, threats, and rituals to both direct and encourage the nuns in their accusations against Grandier.</p>
<p>

Adding to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../000/184000.xml">
hysteria</link> prompted by the public exorcisms were the stories told by both nuns and Father Grandier's former lovers. As in both the <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/5033818.xml">
Louviers possessions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 and the <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/5027523.xml">
Aix-en-Provence possessions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
, the claims made against Grandier were overtly sexual and showed visible physical responses. Because they were public and dramatic, the citizens of Loudun and surrounding areas were set against Grandier.</p>
<p>

In addition to the dreams that Jeanne des Anges and other nuns had related, Jeanne added a third demon to the array of possessors afflicting the nuns: Isacarron, the devil of debauchery. After admitting to this third demon possessor, Jeanne went through a psychosomatic pregnancy. In all, Jeanne and the other nuns claimed to be possessed by a multitude of demons: <evil_spirit wordnetid="109541919" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<spirit wordnetid="109545324" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<devil wordnetid="109542339" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../055/250055.xml">
Asmodeus</link></devil>
</spiritual_being>
</spirit>
</belief>
</evil_spirit>
, Zabulon, Isacaaron, <evil_spirit wordnetid="109541919" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<spirit wordnetid="109545324" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<devil wordnetid="109542339" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../081/242081.xml">
Astaroth</link></devil>
</spiritual_being>
</spirit>
</belief>
</evil_spirit>
, Gresil, Amand, Leviatom, Behemot, Beherie, Easas, Celsus, Acaos, Cedon, Alex, Naphthalim, Cham, Ureil, and Achas.</p>
<p>

In an effort to clear his name, Father Grandier performed an exorcism on the nuns himself. He spoke to them in <language wordnetid="106282651" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../887/11887.xml">
Greek</link></language>
, testing their knowledge of languages previously unknown to the nuns (a sure sign of possession). The nuns had been coached, and responded that they had been ordered in their <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../547/2145547.xml">
pact</link> to never use Greek. </p>
<p>

In another exorcism, performed by Father Gault, the priest obtained a promise from the demon Asmodeus to leave one of the nuns he was possessing. Later, a devil's pact allegedly written between the Devil and Grandier was presented to the court. In this pact, stolen from <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../309/18309.xml">
Lucifer</link>'s cabinet of pacts by Asmodeus himself, was signed in blood by Grandier and various demons. Asmodeus had apparently written out the same promise he'd given to Father Gault on this pact:</p>
<p>

"I promise that when leaving this creature, I will make a slit below her heart as long as a pin, that this slit will pierce her shirt, bodice and cloth which will be bloody. And tomorrow, on the twentieth of May at five in the afternoon of Saturday, I promise that the demons Gresil and Amand will make their opening in the same way, but a little smaller - and I approve the promises made by Leviatam, Behemot, Beherie with their companions to sign, when leaving, the register of the church of St. Croix! Given the nineteenth of May, 1629."</p>
<p>

Later historians would prove that this note is written in Jeanne des Anges' hand. <it>Please see the top of this article for an image of the pact.</it></p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Torture at Loudun</st>

<p>

On <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../577/21577.xml">
November 30</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../162/35162.xml">
1633</link>, Father Grandier was put in prison at the Castle of Angiers. His body was shaved and a successful search for <evil_spirit wordnetid="109541919" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<spirit wordnetid="109545324" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<devil wordnetid="109542339" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../298/492298.xml">
devil's marks</link></devil>
</spiritual_being>
</spirit>
</belief>
</evil_spirit>
 was made by <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../512/213512.xml">
inquisitor</link>s. Protests by the Dr. Fourneau, the physician who prepared Grandier for torture, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../598/1274598.xml">
apothecary</link> from <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<commune wordnetid="108541609" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../489/51489.xml">
Poitiers</link></district>
</commune>
</location>
</administrative_district>
</region>
 were ignored. These protests claimed the inspection a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../239/52239.xml">
hoax</link>, and stated that no such marks had been found.</p>
<p>

Nicholas Aubin's 1693 <it>The Cheats and Illusions of Romish Priest and Exorcists Discovered in the History of the Devils of Loudun</it> describes what happened next:</p>
<p>

"They sent for Mannouri the surgeon, one of [Grandier's] enemies, and the most unmerciful of them all; when he [came] into the chamber, they stripped Grandier stark naked, blinded his eyes, shaved him every where, and Mannouri began to search him. When he would persuade them that the parts of his body which had been marked by the Devil were insensible, he turned that end of the probe which was round, and he guided it in such a manner, that not being able to enter into the flesh, nor to make much impression, it was pushed back into the palm of his hand; the patient did not then cry out, because he felt no pain; but when the barbarous surgeon would make them see that the other parts of his body were very sensible, he turned the probe at the other end, which was very sharp pointed, and thrust it to the very bone; and then the abundance of people [outside] heard complaints so bitter, and cries so piercing, that they [were] moved...to the heart"</p>
<p>

Other people spoke in Grandier's defense, even some of the possessed nuns proclaimed his innocence. Laubardemont, fulfilling his duty to convict Grandier, explained that the nuns' reactions were a ploy by <angel wordnetid="109538915" confidence="0.8">
<evil_spirit wordnetid="109541919" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<spirit wordnetid="109545324" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<devil wordnetid="109542339" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../694/27694.xml">
Satan</link></devil>
</spiritual_being>
</spirit>
</belief>
</evil_spirit>
</angel>
 to save Grandier. Jeanne des Anges appeared in court with a noose tied around her neck, violently stating that she would hang herself if she could not recant her earlier lies. All defenses were ignored, and some defense witnesses were pressured to keep silent. Publicly, Laubardemont announced that any citizens who testified in favour of Grandier would be arrested as traitors to the King and have their possessions confiscated. Many of these witnesses fled France.</p>
<p>

While the defense witnesses were forced to flee, 72 witnesses swore evidence against Grandier, who was denied the normal procedure of trial by a secular court. Had he been tried by secular court, Grandier could have appealed to the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/766191.xml">
Parliament of Paris</link>. Instead, Richelieu's committee took charge of the legal proceedings.</p>
<p>

Torture was a commonplace effort to extract confessions from accused witches during the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../569/34569.xml">
seventeenth century</link>, clearly recommended in the <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/20561.xml">
Malleus Maleficarum</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it>. Most accused witches immediately confessed, telling their torturers exactly what they wanted to hear. Father Grandier never confessed, maintaining his innocence even under the most severe forms of <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../702/47702.xml">
torture</link>. He refused to name any accomplices, which drove Father Tranquille to break both Grandier's legs. </p>
<p>

Nearly a year later, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../496/1496.xml">
August 18</link>, <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/35191.xml">
1634</link>, the Royal Commission found Grandier guilty of all counts against him and passed sentence - Grandier would be <know-how wordnetid="105616786" confidence="0.8">
<method wordnetid="105660268" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../645/97645.xml">
burned alive at the stake</link></method>
</know-how>
:</p>
<p>

"We have ordered and do order the said Urbain Grandier duly tried and convicted of the crime of magic, maleficia, and of causing demoniacal possession of several Ursuline nuns of this town of Loudun, as well as of other secular women, together with other charges and crimes resulting therefrom. For atonement of which, we have condemned and do condemn the said Grandier to make amende honorable, his head bare, a rope round his neck, holding in his hand a burning taper weighing two pounds, before the principle door of the church of St. Pierre-du-Marché, and before that of St. Ursual of this town. There on his knees, to ask pardon of God, the King, and the law; this done, he is to be taken to the public square of St. Croix, and fastened to a stake on a scaffold, which shall be erected on the said place for this purpose, and there to be burned alive...and his ashes scattered to the wind. We have ordered and so do order that each and every article of his moveable property be acquired and confiscated by the King; the sum of 500 livres first being taken for buying a bronze plaque on which will be engraved the abstract of this present trial, to be set up in a prominent spot in the said church of the Ursulines, to remain there for all eternity. And before proceeding to the execution of the present sentence, we order the said Grandier to be submitted to the first and last degrees of torture, concerning his accomplices."</p>
<p>

All details of the sentence were carried out.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Burning at Loudun</st>

<p>

Father Grandier was promised that he could have the chance to speak before he was executed, making a last statement, and that he would be <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../019/155019.xml">
hanged</link> before the burning, an act of mercy. Instead, the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../753/312753.xml">
friar</link>s who carried Grandier's crippled body to the stake had drenched him with large quantities <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../357/847357.xml">
holy water</link> so that his last words could not be heard, and the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../078/972078.xml">
garotte</link> used for hanging had no slip knot; it couldn't tighten. Grandier was left to burn alive. </p>
<p>

Witnesses to the execution reported that a large fly buzzed around Grandier's head, symbolizing that <evil_spirit wordnetid="109541919" confidence="0.8">
<belief wordnetid="105941423" confidence="0.8">
<spirit wordnetid="109545324" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_being wordnetid="109504135" confidence="0.8">
<devil wordnetid="109542339" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../124/19010124.xml">
Beelzebub</link></devil>
</spiritual_being>
</spirit>
</belief>
</evil_spirit>
, lord of the flies, had come to take Grandier's soul to hell. </p>
<p>

Before Grandier perished, he did have the last word. Struggling, Grandier declared that Father Lactance, present, would die in 30 days. To the day, Lactance did die, reportedly crying out, "Grandier, I was not responsible for your death." Within the next five years, both Father Tranquille and Dr. Mannouri, the inquisitor, died in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../529/157529.xml">
delirium</link>. Father Surin became haunted by the exorcisms, eventually unable to eat, dress himself, walk, read, or write. He could not <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../227/196227.xml">
pray</link>, instead seeing visions of demons and black wings. He tried to kill himself in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../607/38607.xml">
1645</link> and only recovered after the new head of the Jesuit College, Father Bastide, cared for Surin in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../685/34685.xml">
1648</link>. Surin would not walk again until <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../962/34962.xml">
1657</link>, 8 years before he died.</p>
<p>

The possessions failed to stop after Father Grandier's execution. The exorcisms had been so appreciated by the public of Loudun that they became a type of tourist attraction at the convent. Nuns would lift their skirts and beg for sexual attention, beat their heads, walk on their hands, and use obscene language. Public exorcisms would follow. These displays continued until <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../193/35193.xml">
1637</link>, when the duchess d'Aiguillon, niece to Cardinal Richelieu, reported the fraud to her uncle. Having achieved his original goal, Richelieu cut off the performers' salaries and ended the shows. </p>
<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../191/35191.xml">
1634</link>, Des Niau wrote the following description in his <it>The History of the Devils of Loudun</it>:</p>
<p>

"[The nuns] struck their chests and backs with their heads, as if they had their necks broken, and with inconceivable rapidity; They twisted their arms at the joints of the shoulder, the elbow, or the wrist, two or three times around. Lying on their stomachs, they joined the palms of their hands to the soles of their feet; their faces became so frightful one could not bear to look at them; their eyes remained open without winking. Their tongues issued suddenly from their mouths, horribly swollen, black, hard, and covered with pimples, and yet while in this state they spoke distinctly. They threw themselves back till their heads touched their feet, and walked in this position with wonderful rapidity, and for a long time. They uttered cries so horrible and so loud that nothing like it was ever heard before. They made use of expressions so indecent as to shame the most debauched of men, while their acts, both in exposing themselves and inviting lewd behavior from those present would have astonished the inmates of the lowest brothels in the country."</p>
<p>

Some claim that it was actually Jeanne des Anges who had the public exorcisms stopped. Jeanne allegedly had a vision that she would be freed from the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../539/8539.xml">
Devil</link> if she made a pilgrimage to the tomb of <person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<saint wordnetid="110546850" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../638/11638.xml">
St François of Assise</link></saint>
</person>
. She went to <region wordnetid="108630985" confidence="0.8">
<administrative_district wordnetid="108491826" confidence="0.8">
<prefecture wordnetid="108626947" confidence="0.8">
<location wordnetid="100027167" confidence="0.8">
<commune wordnetid="108541609" confidence="0.8">
<district wordnetid="108552138" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../527/508527.xml">
Annecy</link></district>
</commune>
</location>
</prefecture>
</administrative_district>
</region>
, then visited Richelieu and King <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../062/77062.xml">
Louis XIII</link> in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../146/35146.xml">
1638</link>. The demons were gone.</p>
<p>

Jeanne des Anges remained convinced of her <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../436/28436.xml">
saint</link>liness until she died in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../095/35095.xml">
1665</link>.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
Modern notes</st>

<p>

In <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../667/34667.xml">
1866</link>, <scientist wordnetid="110560637" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../831/932831.xml">
Jean-Martin Charcot</link></scientist>
 analyzed the case of the Loudun Possessions. His belief was that the nuns were victims of hystero-demonopathy; sexually frustrated, they had turned their erotic desires into dreams of demonic possession by Grandier, a handsome, charismatic man who was known as a seducer of women.</p>
<p>

As an opponent to Cardinal Richelieu, Grandier had made an enemy of the man when he wrote the libelous satire in <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../909/34909.xml">
1618</link>, but further actions by Grandier may have played a major role in gathering the cardinal's anger. While in Loudun, Jean de Laubardemont was to oversee the demolition of the town's fortifications, including the Castle of Loudun. Part of Richelieu's program to eliminate <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<traveler wordnetid="109629752" confidence="0.8">
<exile wordnetid="110071332" confidence="0.8">
<refugee wordnetid="110516016" confidence="0.8">
<absentee wordnetid="109757653" confidence="0.8">
<war wordnetid="100973077" confidence="0.8">
<group_action wordnetid="101080366" confidence="0.8">
<military_action wordnetid="100952963" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../899/75899.xml">
Huguenot</link></psychological_feature>
</act>
</causal_agent>
</event>
</military_action>
</group_action>
</war>
</absentee>
</refugee>
</exile>
</traveler>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 strongholds by destroying local fortifications, and the success of his mission would have helped cement the cardinal's power both within the church and within France.</p>
<p>

Protestant (Huguenot) and Catholic residents of Loudun were both against the removal of their battlements, which would leave them unprotected against <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../374/73374.xml">
mercenary</link> armies. Grandier cited the King's promise that Loudun's walls would not be destroyed and prevented Laubardemont from demolishing the fortifications. Laubardemont promptly reported back to Richelieu with the tale of failed exorcisms, the libelous satire, and Grandier's recent hindering of Richelieu's plans.</p>
<p>

Finally, another aim was achieved by the Loudun Possessions: conversion to <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../718/4559718.xml">
Catholicism</link>. Many of the protestant townspeople converted to Catholicism as a result of the public exorcisms, further eroding any Huguenot sentiment in the region.</p>
<p>

Historians today believe that the purpose of the injustice committed at Loudun was a mixture of political ambition, the need for attention, and a basic desire to dispose of political opponents.</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
See also</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/5027523.xml">
Aix-en-Provence possessions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/5033818.xml">
Louviers possessions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/20561.xml">
Malleus Maleficarum</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<priest wordnetid="110470779" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<clergyman wordnetid="109927451" confidence="0.8">
<occultist wordnetid="110370381" confidence="0.8">
<leader wordnetid="109623038" confidence="0.8">
<spiritual_leader wordnetid="109505153" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<enchantress wordnetid="110055297" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../680/252680.xml">
Urbain Grandier</link></enchantress>
</causal_agent>
</spiritual_leader>
</leader>
</occultist>
</clergyman>
</person>
</priest>
</physical_entity>
</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../586/459586.xml">
<it>The Devils''</it></link></movie>
 (film)</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <it><movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../817/1665817.xml">
Mother Joan of the Angels</link></movie>
</it> (film)</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
References</st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Huxley, Aldous. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.portifex.com/ReadingMatter/DevilsLoudun.htm">
The Devils of Loudun</weblink>. New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1952.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Sidky, H. <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0361-0160(199922)30%3A2%3C563%3AWLDADA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-Z">
Witchcraft, Lycanthropy, Drugs, and Disease: An Anthropological Study of the European Witch-Hunts</weblink>. New York: Peter Lang Publishing, Inc. 1997.</entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Bodin, Jean. <it>The Witches and the Law.</it> <it>Witchcraft in Europe 1100-1700: A Documentary History</it>. Ed. Alan C. Kors &amp; Edward Peters. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press. 1991. </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 Dumas, Alexander. <it>Urbain Grandier, Celebrated Crimes</it> - Available on </entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 de Certeau, Michel. <it>The Possession at Loudun</it>. University of Chicago Press. 2000. ISBN 0226100340, ISBN 9780226100340.</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>

----</p>
<p>

<table style=";" class="navbox" cellspacing="0">
<row>
<col style="padding:2px;">
<table style="width:100%;background:transparent;color:inherit;;" class="nowraplinks collapsible autocollapse " cellspacing="0">
<row>
<header colspan="2" style=";" class="navbox-title">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../929/58929.xml">
Witch-hunt</link></header>
</row>
<row style="height:2px;">

</row>
<row>
<col colspan="2" style="width:100%;padding:0px;;;" class="navbox-list navbox-odd">
<attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../663/16830663.xml">
Valais witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1428–1447) &nbsp;· <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../038/4384038.xml">
Formicarius</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> (1475)&nbsp;·  <it><work wordnetid="104599396" confidence="0.8">
<product wordnetid="104007894" confidence="0.8">
<creation wordnetid="103129123" confidence="0.8">
<artifact wordnetid="100021939" confidence="0.8">
<book wordnetid="106410904" confidence="0.8">
<publication wordnetid="106589574" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../561/20561.xml">
Malleus Maleficarum</link></publication>
</book>
</artifact>
</creation>
</product>
</work>
</it> (1486)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../153/18092153.xml">
Val Camonica witch trials</link> (1505, 1518) &nbsp;·  <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../296/16402296.xml">
Trier witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1581–1593)&nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<occultist wordnetid="110370381" confidence="0.8">
<female wordnetid="109619168" confidence="0.8">
<woman wordnetid="110787470" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<enchantress wordnetid="110055297" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../918/11730918.xml">
Witches of Warboys</link></enchantress>
</adult>
</causal_agent>
</woman>
</female>
</occultist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 (1589–1593) &nbsp;·  <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../641/1978641.xml">
North Berwick witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1590)&nbsp;·  <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../864/16400864.xml">
Fulda witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1603–1606)&nbsp;·  <link>
Køge Huskors</link> (1608–1615)&nbsp;·  <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../180/12072180.xml">
Basque witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1609)&nbsp;·  <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../523/5027523.xml">
Aix-en-Provence possessions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1611)&nbsp;· <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../991/19269991.xml">
Pendle witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1612)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../723/18092723.xml">
Roermond witch trial</link> (1613) &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../772/19086772.xml">
Spa witch trial</link> (1616) &nbsp;·  <link>
Finspång witch trial</link> (1617) &nbsp;·  <physical_entity wordnetid="100001930" confidence="0.8">
<person wordnetid="100007846" confidence="0.8">
<occultist wordnetid="110370381" confidence="0.8">
<female wordnetid="109619168" confidence="0.8">
<woman wordnetid="110787470" confidence="0.8">
<causal_agent wordnetid="100007347" confidence="0.8">
<adult wordnetid="109605289" confidence="0.8">
<enchantress wordnetid="110055297" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../672/8955672.xml">
Witches of Belvoir</link></enchantress>
</adult>
</causal_agent>
</woman>
</female>
</occultist>
</person>
</physical_entity>
 (1619) &nbsp;·  <link>
Würzburg witch trial</link> (1626–1631)&nbsp;·  <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../624/11355624.xml">
Ramsele witch trial</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1634)&nbsp;·  <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../540/5036540.xml">
Loudun possessions</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1634) &nbsp;· <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../423/13216423.xml">
Bury St. Edmunds witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1645, 1662, 1655 &amp; 1694)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../818/5033818.xml">
Louviers Possessions</link> (1647) &nbsp;· <link>
Kirkjuból witch trial</link> (1656) &nbsp;·  <link>
Vardø Witch Trials</link> (1662–1663)&nbsp;·  <link>
Torsåker witch trials</link> (1675)&nbsp;· <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../982/18463982.xml">
Salzburg witch trials</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1675–1681) &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../416/18692416.xml">
Jesenice witch trials</link> (1678) &nbsp;· <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../452/2142452.xml">
Poison affair</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1679) &nbsp;· <attempt wordnetid="100786195" confidence="0.8">
<test wordnetid="100791078" confidence="0.8">
<event wordnetid="100029378" confidence="0.8">
<act wordnetid="100030358" confidence="0.8">
<psychological_feature wordnetid="100023100" confidence="0.8">
<activity wordnetid="100407535" confidence="0.8">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../656/8662656.xml">
Bideford witch trial</link></activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
 (1684)&nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/205246.xml">
Salem witch trials</link>  (1692–1693) &nbsp;·  <link>
Paisley witch trials</link> (1696)&nbsp;·  <link>
Islandmagee witch trial‎</link> (1711) &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../867/17792867.xml">
Szeged witch trials</link> (1728–1729) &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../077/17792077.xml">
Doruchowo witch trial</link> (1775)<it> &nbsp;·  <movie wordnetid="106613686" confidence="0.9508927676800064">
<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../128/1816128.xml">
The Burning Times</link></movie>
</it>  &nbsp;·  <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../805/43805.xml">
McCarthyism</link></col>
</row>
</table>
</col>
</row>
</table>
</p>




</sec>
</bdy>
</activity>
</psychological_feature>
</act>
</event>
</test>
</attempt>
</article>
