<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- generated by CLiX/Wiki2XML [MPI-Inf, MMCI@UdS] $LastChangedRevision: 92 $ on 16.04.2009 17:15:36[mciao0826] -->
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../article.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<header>
<title>Crash incompatibility</title>
<id>535476</id>
<revision>
<id>224220491</id>
<timestamp>2008-07-07T21:28:24Z</timestamp>
<contributor>
<username>SmackBot</username>
<id>433328</id>
</contributor>
</revision>
<categories>
<category>Car safety</category>
<category>Road transport</category>
</categories>
</header>
<bdy>

<b>Crash incompatibility</b>, <b>crash compatibility</b>, <b>vehicle incompatibility</b>, and <b>vehicle compatibility</b> are terms in the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../345/13673345.xml">
automobile</link> <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../322/286322.xml">
crash test</link>ing industry.  They refer to the tendency of some vehicles to inflict more damage on another vehicle (the "crash partner vehicle") in two-car crashes.  Vehicle <it>incompatibility</it> is said to lead to more dangerous, fatal crashes, while <it>compatibility</it> can prevent injury in otherwise comparable crashes.  <p>

The most obvious source of crash incompatibility is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../048/19048.xml">
mass</link>; a high mass vehicle such as a <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../828/20828.xml">
large MPV</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../696/47696.xml">
SUV</link> will tend to cause much more serious damage in a crash with a lighter vehicle such as a typical <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../325/381325.xml">
sedan</link> or <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../474/588474.xml">
compact car</link>.  Incompatibility may also result from the specific shape, stiffness, or other design aspects of the impacting vehicles. For example, some SUVs and pickup trucks ride higher than cars and lack crumple zones to absorb impact energy. Another source of incompatibility is that heavier vehicles are required to have stronger front ends because of today's test requirements like the <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../173/564173.xml">
NCAP</link> test <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=16125334">
http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=16125334</weblink>.</p>
<p>

The <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../530/989530.xml">
National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</link> have done studies of the <it>aggressiveness</it> of vehicle designs.  The term 'aggressiveness' is used to denote the average injury risk a vehicle imposes on occupants of other vehicles during collisions.  A 2003 NHTSA study estimated that in vehicle to vehicle crashes, the design of minivans was 1.16 times as aggressive as cars, pickups were 1.39 times more aggressive, and SUVs were 1.71 times more aggressive than cars.  When weight was included in the analysis, light trucks (including SUVs) were estimated to be 3.3 times more aggressive than cars in head on crashes and perhaps more so in side impact crashes.</p>
<p>

These studies have been controversial as they affect public perception and policy decisions on <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../246/440246.xml">
CAFE</link> standards and light truck safety test standards as they exist today. Besides, the numbers above are difficult to translate into any meaningful steps because the NHTSA does not define a car or a light truck very well (the PT Cruiser is classified as a light truck whereas as Lexus LS430, a much heavier vehicle, is classified as a car). So, it would not make sense to say that eliminating all light trucks (which includes minivans, SUVs and pickups) will eliminate incompatibility because there would still be smaller vehicles crashing into larger vehicles. This is the case in Japan which has few light trucks but crash incompatibility is considered to be a major issue.</p>
<p>

There has been extensive research and testing done by NHTSA, other governments, research organizations as well as automobile manufacturers to find solutions that improve safety in the small cars when colliding with a larger vehicle. In the US, a group of experts proposed major steps to improve compatibility <weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.autoalliance.org/archives/archive.php?id=56&amp;cat=Press%20Releases">
http://www.autoalliance.org/archives/archive.php?id=56&amp;cat=Press%20Releases</weblink>and these have been accepted as a voluntary regulation by the US automotive manufacturers as well as by most other companies selling vehicles in the US. The Canadian Government has also accepted these recommendations. The recommendations require all manufacturers to put head protection airbags (<link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../023/60023.xml#xpointer(//*[./st=%22Curtain+air+bags%22])">
'curtain' airbags</link>) in their cars within a couple of years and also to design the front end of all light trucks to be less aggressive. </p>
<p>

Although much of the crash incompatibility debate in recent years has centered around SUVs, the concept has been around far longer.  When subcompact cars were introduced in the 1970s, there was a fear that incompatibilities of mass and design could lead to more serious injuries for drivers of these smaller, lighter vehicles.  Crash incompatibility remains an area of active study.</p>

<sec>
<st>
 See also</st>
<p>
 
<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../341/330341.xml">
Car safety</link></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

 <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="../285/1587285.xml">
Insurance Institute for Highway Safety</link></entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 References </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<it>Physics Today</it>, January 2006, "Vehicle Design and the Physics of Traffic Safety"</entry>
</list>
</p>
<p>


</p>

</sec>
<sec>
<st>
 External links </st>
<p>

<list>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nhtsa.dot.gov/cars/rules/regrev/evaluate/pdf/809662.pdf">
National Highway Traffic Safety Administration report on vehicle compatibility</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

<weblink xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.hwysafety.org/research/topics/compat.html">
Insurance Institute reports on vehicle compatibility (April 4, 2003)</weblink></entry>
<entry level="1" type="bullet">

http://www.autoalliance.org/archives/archive.php?id=56&amp;cat=Press%20Releases</entry>
</list>
</p>

</sec>
</bdy>
</article>
